Acts 2

2

^1And when the day of Pentecost was now come, they were all together in one place. ^2And suddenly there came from heaven a sound as of the rushing of a mighty wind, and it filled all the house where they were sitting. ^3And there appeared unto them tongues parting asunder, like as of fire; and it sat upon each one of them. ^4And they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and began to speak with other tongues, as the Spirit gave them utterance. ^5Now there were dwelling at Jerusalem Jews, devout men, from every nation under heaven. ^6And when this sound was heard, the multitude came together, and were confounded, because that every man heard them speaking in his own language. ^7And they were all amazed and marvelled, saying, Behold, are not all these that speak Galilaeans? ^8And how hear we, every man in our own language wherein we were born? ^9Parthians and Medes and Elamites, and the dwellers in Mesopotamia, in Judaea and Cappadocia, in Pontus and Asia, ^10in Phrygia and Pamphylia, in Egypt and the parts of Libya about Cyrene, and sojourners from Rome, both Jews and proselytes, ^11Cretans and Arabians, we hear them speaking in our tongues the mighty works of God. ^12And they were all amazed, and were perplexed, saying one to another, What meaneth this? ^13But others mocking said, They are filled with new wine. ^14But Peter, standing up with the eleven, lifted up his voice, and spake forth unto them, saying, Ye men of Judaea, and all ye that dwell at Jerusalem, be this known unto you, and give ear unto my words. ^15For these are not drunken, as ye suppose; seeing it is but the third hour of the day. ^16but this is that which hath been spoken through the prophet Joel:

^17And it shall be in the last days, saith God,

I will pour forth of my Spirit upon all flesh:

And your sons and your daughters shall prophesy,

And your young men shall see visions,

And your old men shall dream dreams:

^18Yea and on my servants and on my handmaidens in those days

Will I pour forth of my Spirit; and they shall prophesy.

^19And I will show wonders in the heaven above,

And signs on the earth beneath;

Blood, and fire, and vapor of smoke:

^20The sun shall be turned into darkness,

And the moon into blood,

Before the day of the Lord come,

That great and notable day.

^21And it shall be, that whosoever shall call on the name of the Lord shall be saved.

^22Ye men of Israel, hear these words: Jesus of Nazareth, a man approved of God unto you by mighty works and wonders and signs which God did by him in the midst of you, even as ye yourselves know; ^23him, being delivered up by the determinate counsel and foreknowledge of God, ye by the hand of lawless men did crucify and slay: ^24whom God raised up, having loosed the pangs of death: because it was not possible that he should be holden of it. ^25For David saith concerning him,

I beheld the Lord always before my face;

For he is on my right hand, that I should not be moved:

^26Therefore my heart was glad, and my tongue rejoiced;

Moreover my flesh also shall dwell in hope:

^27Because thou wilt not leave my soul unto Hades,

Neither wilt thou give thy Holy One to see corruption.

^28Thou madest known unto me the ways of life;

Thou shalt make me full of gladness with thy countenance.

^29Brethren, I may say unto you freely of the patriarch David, that he both died and was buried, and his tomb is with us unto this day. ^30Being therefore a prophet, and knowing that God had sworn with an oath to him, that of the fruit of his loins he would set one upon his throne; ^31he foreseeing this spake of the resurrection of the Christ, that neither was he left unto Hades, nor did his flesh see corruption. ^32This Jesus did God raise up, whereof we all are witnesses. ^33Being therefore by the right hand of God exalted, and having received of the Father the promise of the Holy Spirit, he hath poured forth this, which ye see and hear. ^34For David ascended not into the heavens: but he saith himself,

The Lord said unto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand,

^35Till I make thine enemies the footstool of thy feet.

^36Let all the house of Israel therefore know assuredly, that God hath made him both Lord and Christ, this Jesus whom ye crucified. ^37Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their heart, and said unto Peter and the rest of the apostles, Brethren, what shall we do? ^38And Peter said unto them, Repent ye, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus Christ unto the remission of your sins; and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Spirit. ^39For to you is the promise, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God shall call unto him. ^40And with many other words he testified, and exhorted them, saying, Save yourselves from this crooked generation. ^41They then that received his word were baptized: and there were added unto them in that day about three thousand souls. ^42And they continued stedfastly in the apostles' teaching and fellowship, in the breaking of bread and the prayers. ^43And fear came upon every soul: and many wonders and signs were done through the apostles. ^44And all that believed were together, and had all things common; ^45and they sold their possessions and goods, and parted them to all, according as any man had need. ^46And day by day, continuing stedfastly with one accord in the temple, and breaking bread at home, they took their food with gladness and singleness of heart, ^47praising God, and having favor with all the people. And the Lord added to them day by day those that were saved.

Acts 3

3

^1Now Peter and John were going up into the temple at the hour of prayer, being the ninth hour. ^2And a certain man that was lame from his mother's womb was carried, whom they laid daily at the door of the temple which is called Beautiful, to ask alms of them that entered into the temple; ^3who seeing Peter and John about to go into the temple, asked to receive an alms. ^4And Peter, fastening his eyes upon him, with John, said, Look on us. ^5And he gave heed unto them, expecting to receive something from them. ^6But Peter said, Silver and gold have I none; but what I have, that give I thee. In the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, walk. ^7And he took him by the right hand, and raised him up: and immediately his feet and his ankle-bones received strength. ^8And leaping up, he stood, and began to walk; and he entered with them into the temple, walking, and leaping, and praising God. ^9And all the people saw him walking and praising God: ^10and they took knowledge of him, that it was he that sat for alms at the Beautiful Gate of the temple; and they were filled with wonder and amazement at that which had happened unto him. ^11And as he held Peter and John, all the people ran together unto them in the porch that is called Solomon's, greatly wondering. ^12And when Peter saw it, he answered unto the people, Ye men of Israel, why marvel ye at this man? or why fasten ye your eyes on us, as though by our own power or godliness we had made him to walk? ^13The God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Jacob, the God of our fathers, hath glorified his Servant Jesus; whom ye delivered up, and denied before the face of Pilate, when he had determined to release him. ^14But ye denied the Holy and Righteous One, and asked for a murderer to be granted unto you, ^15and killed the Prince of life; whom God raised from the dead; whereof we are witnesses. ^16And by faith in his name hath his name made this man strong, whom ye behold and know: yea, the faith which is through him hath given him this perfect soundness in the presence of you all. ^17And now, brethren, I know that in ignorance ye did it, as did also your rulers. ^18But the things which God foreshowed by the mouth of all the prophets, that his Christ should suffer, he thus fulfilled. ^19Repent ye therefore, and turn again, that your sins may be blotted out, that so there may come seasons of refreshing from the presence of the Lord; ^20and that he may send the Christ who hath been appointed for you, even Jesus: ^21whom the heaven must receive until the times of restoration of all things, whereof God spake by the mouth of His holy prophets that have been from of old. ^22Moses indeed said, A prophet shall the Lord God raise up unto you from among your brethren, like unto me. To him shall ye hearken in all things whatsoever he shall speak unto you. ^23And it shall be, that every soul that shall not hearken to that prophet, shall be utterly destroyed from among the people. ^24Yea and all the prophets from Samuel and them that followed after, as many as have spoken, they also told of these days. ^25Ye are the sons of the prophets, and of the covenant which God made with your fathers, saying unto Abraham, And in thy seed shall all the families of the earth be blessed. ^26Unto you first God, having raised up his Servant, sent him to bless you, in turning away every one of you from your iniquities.

Acts 4

4

^1And as they spake unto the people, the priests and the captain of the temple and the Sadducees came upon them, ^2being sore troubled because they taught the people, and proclaimed in Jesus the resurrection from the dead. ^3And they laid hands on them, and put them in ward unto the morrow: for it was now eventide. ^4But many of them that heard the word believed; and the number of the men came to be about five thousand. ^5And it came to pass on the morrow, that their rulers and elders and scribes were gathered together in Jerusalem; ^6and Annas the high priest was there, and Caiaphas, and John, and Alexander, and as many as were of the kindred of the high priest. ^7And when they had set them in the midst, they inquired, By what power, or in what name, have ye done this? ^8Then Peter, filled with the Holy Spirit, said unto them, Ye rulers of the people, and elders, ^9if we this day are examined concerning a good deed done to an impotent man, by what means this man is made whole; ^10be it known unto you all, and to all the people of Israel, that in the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, whom ye crucified, whom God raised from the dead, even in him doth this man stand here before you whole. ^11He is the stone which was set at nought of you the builders, which was made the head of the corner. ^12And in none other is there salvation: for neither is there any other name under heaven, that is given among men, wherein we must be saved. ^13Now when they beheld the boldness of Peter and John, and had perceived that they were unlearned and ignorant men, they marvelled; and they took knowledge of them, that they had been with Jesus. ^14And seeing the man that was healed standing with them, they could say nothing against it. ^15But when they had commanded them to go aside out of the council, they conferred among themselves, ^16saying, What shall we do to these men? for that indeed a notable miracle hath been wrought through them, is manifest to all that dwell in Jerusalem; and we cannot deny it. ^17But that it spread no further among the people, let us threaten them, that they speak henceforth to no man in this name. ^18And they called them, and charged them not to speak at all nor teach in the name of Jesus. ^19But Peter and John answered and said unto them, Whether it is right in the sight of God to hearken unto you rather than unto God, judge ye: ^20for we cannot but speak the things which we saw and heard. ^21And they, when they had further threatened them, let them go, finding nothing how they might punish them, because of the people; for all men glorified God for that which was done. ^22For the man was more than forty years old, on whom this miracle of healing was wrought. ^23And being let go, they came to their own company, and reported all that the chief priests and the elders had said unto them. ^24And they, when they heard it, lifted up their voice to God with one accord, and said, O Lord, thou that didst make the heaven and the earth and the sea, and all that in them is: ^25who by the Holy Spirit, by the mouth of our father David thy servant, didst say,

Why did the Gentiles rage,

And the peoples imagine vain things?

^26The kings of the earth set themselves in array,

And the rulers were gathered together,

Against the Lord, and against his Anointed:

^27for of a truth in this city against thy holy Servant Jesus, whom thou didst anoint, both Herod and Pontius Pilate, with the Gentiles and the peoples of Israel, were gathered together, ^28to do whatsoever thy hand and thy council foreordained to come to pass. ^29And now, Lord, look upon their threatenings: and grant unto thy servants to speak thy word with all boldness, ^30while thy stretchest forth thy hand to heal; and that signs and wonders may be done through the name of thy holy Servant Jesus. ^31And when they had prayed, the place was shaken wherein they were gathered together; and they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and they spake the word of God with boldness. ^32And the multitude of them that believed were of one heart and soul: and not one of them said that aught of the things which he possessed was his own; but they had all things common. ^33And with great power gave the apostles their witness of the resurrection of the Lord Jesus: and great grace was upon them all. ^34For neither was there among them any that lacked: for as many as were possessors of lands or houses sold them, and brought the prices of the things that were sold, ^35and laid them at the apostles' feet: and distribution was made unto each, according as any one had need. ^36And Joseph, who by the apostles was surnamed Barnabas (which is, being interpreted, Son of exhortation), a Levite, a man of Cyprus by race, ^37having a field, sold it, and brought the money and laid it at the apostles' feet.

Acts 6

6

^1Now in these days, when the number of the disciples was multiplying, there arose a murmuring of the Grecian Jews against the Hebrews, because their widows were neglected in the daily ministration. ^2And the twelve called the multitude of the disciples unto them, and said, It is not fit that we should forsake the word of God, and serve tables. ^3Look ye out therefore, brethren, from among you seven men of good report, full of the Spirit and of wisdom, whom we may appoint over this business. ^4But we will continue stedfastly in prayer, and in the ministry of the word. ^5And the saying pleased the whole multitude: and they chose Stephen, a man full of faith and of the Holy Spirit, and Philip, and Prochorus, and Nicanor, and Timon, and Parmenas, and Nicolaus a proselyte of Antioch; ^6whom they set before the apostles: and when they had prayed, they laid their hands upon them. ^7And the word of God increased; and the number of the disciples multiplied in Jerusalem exceedingly; and a great company of the priests were obedient to the faith. ^8And Stephen, full of grace and power, wrought great wonders and signs among the people. ^9But there arose certain of them that were of the synagogue called the synagogue of the Libertines, and of the Cyrenians, and of the Alexandrians, and of them of Cilicia and Asia, disputing with Stephen. ^10And they were not able to withstand the wisdom and the Spirit by which he spake. ^11Then they suborned men, who said, We have heard him speak blasphemous words against Moses, and against God. ^12And they stirred up the people, and the elders, and the scribes, and came upon him, and seized him, and brought him into the council, ^13and set up false witnesses, who said, This man ceaseth not to speak words against this holy place, and the law: ^14for we have heard him say, that this Jesus of Nazareth shall destroy this place, and shall change the customs which Moses delivered unto us. ^15And all that sat in the council, fastening their eyes on him, saw his face as it had been the face of an angel.

Acts 7

7

^1And the high priest said, Are these things so? ^2And he said, Brethren and fathers, hearken: The God of glory appeared unto our father Abraham, when he was in Mesopotamia, before he dwelt in Haran, ^3and said unto him, Get thee out of thy land, and from thy kindred, and come into the land which I shall show thee. ^4Then came he out of the land of the Chaldaeans, and dwelt in Haran: and from thence, when his father was dead, God removed him into this land, wherein ye now dwell: ^5and he gave him none inheritance in it, no, not so much as to set his foot on: and he promised that he would give it to him in possession, and to his seed after him, when as yet he had no child. ^6And God spake on this wise, that his seed should sojourn in a strange land, and that they should bring them into bondage, and treat them ill, four hundred years. ^7And the nation to which they shall be in bondage will I judge, said God: and after that shall they come forth, and serve me in this place. ^8And he gave him the covenant of circumcision: and so Abraham begat Isaac, and circumcised him the eighth day; and Isaac begat Jacob, and Jacob the twelve patriarchs. ^9And the patriarchs, moved with jealousy against Joseph, sold him into Egypt: and God was with him, ^10and delivered him out of all his afflictions, and gave him favor and wisdom before Pharaoh king of Egypt; and he made him governor over Egypt and all his house. ^11Now there came a famine over all Egypt and Canaan, and great affliction: and our fathers found no sustenance. ^12But when Jacob heard that there was grain in Egypt, he sent forth our fathers the first time. ^13And at the second time Joseph was made known to his brethren; and Joseph's race became manifest unto Pharaoh. ^14And Joseph sent, and called to him Jacob his father, and all his kindred, threescore and fifteen souls. ^15And Jacob went down into Egypt; and he died, himself and our fathers; ^16and they were carried over unto Shechem, and laid in the tomb that Abraham bought for a price in silver of the sons of Hamor in Shechem. ^17But as the time of the promise drew nigh which God vouchsafed unto Abraham, the people grew and multiplied in Egypt, ^18till there arose another king over Egypt, who knew not Joseph. ^19The same dealt craftily with our race, and ill-treated our fathers, that they should cast out their babes to the end they might not live. ^20At which season Moses was born, and was exceeding fair; and he was nourished three months in his father's house. ^21and when he was cast out, Pharaoh's daughter took him up, and nourished him for her own son. ^22And Moses was instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians; and he was mighty in his words and works. ^23But when he was well-nigh forty years old, it came into his heart to visit his brethren the children of Israel. ^24And seeing one of them suffer wrong, he defended him, and avenged him that was oppressed, smiting the Egyptian: ^25and he supposed that his brethren understood that God by his hand was giving them deliverance; but they understood not. ^26And the day following he appeared unto them as they strove, and would have set them at one again, saying, Sirs, ye are brethren; why do ye wrong one to another? ^27But he that did his neighbor wrong thrust him away, saying, Who made thee a ruler and a judge over us? ^28Wouldest thou kill me, as thou killedst the Egyptian yesterday? ^29And Moses fled at this saying, and became a sojourner in the land of Midian, where he begat two sons. ^30And when forty years were fulfilled, an angel appeared to him in the wilderness of Mount Sinai, in a flame of fire in a bush. ^31And when Moses saw it, he wondered at the sight: and as he drew near to behold, there came a voice of the Lord, ^32I am the God of thy fathers, the God of Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Jacob. And Moses trembled, and durst not behold. ^33And the Lord said unto him, Loose the shoes from thy feet: for the place whereon thou standest is holy ground. ^34I have surely seen the affliction of my people that is in Egypt, and have heard their groaning, and I am come down to deliver them: and now come, I will send thee into Egypt. ^35This Moses whom they refused, saying, Who made thee a ruler and a judge? him hath God sent to be both a ruler and a deliverer with the hand of the angel that appeared to him in the bush. ^36This man led them forth, having wrought wonders and signs in Egypt, and in the Red Sea, and in the wilderness forty years. ^37This is that Moses, who said unto the children of Israel, A prophet shall God raise up unto you from among your brethren, like unto me. ^38This is he that was in the church in the wilderness with the angel that spake to him in the Mount Sinai, and with our fathers: who received living oracles to give unto us: ^39to whom our fathers would not be obedient, but thrust him from them, and turned back in their hearts unto Egypt, ^40saying unto Aaron, Make us gods that shall go before us: for as for this Moses, who led us forth out of the land of Egypt, we know not what is become of him. ^41And they made a calf in those days, and brought a sacrifice unto the idol, and rejoiced in the works of their hands. ^42But God turned, and gave them up to serve the host of heaven; as it is written in the book of the prophets,

Did ye offer unto me slain beasts and sacrifices

Forty years in the wilderness, O house of Israel?

^43And ye took up the tabernacle of Moloch,

And the star of the god Rephan,

The figures which ye made to worship them:

And I will carry you away beyond Babylon.

^44Our fathers had the tabernacle of the testimony in the wilderness, even as he appointed who spake unto Moses, that he should make it according to the figure that he had seen. ^45Which also our fathers, in their turn, brought in with Joshua when they entered on the possession of the nations, that God thrust out before the face of our fathers, unto the days of David; ^46who found favor in the sight of God, and asked to find a habitation for the God of Jacob. ^47But Solomon built him a house. ^48Howbeit the Most High dwelleth not in houses made with hands; as saith the prophet,

^49The heaven is my throne,

And the earth the footstool of my feet:

What manner of house will ye build me? saith the Lord:

Or what is the place of my rest?

^50Did not my hand make all these things?

^51Ye stiffnecked and uncircumcised in heart and ears, ye do always resist the Holy Spirit: as your fathers did, so do ye. ^52Which of the prophets did not your fathers persecute? and they killed them that showed before of the coming of the Righteous One; of whom ye have now become betrayers and murderers; ^53ye who received the law as it was ordained by angels, and kept it not. ^54Now when they heard these things, they were cut to the heart, and they gnashed on him with their teeth. ^55But he, being full of the Holy Spirit, looked up stedfastly into heaven, and saw the glory of God, and Jesus standing on the right hand of God, ^56and said, Behold, I see the heavens opened, and the Son of Man standing on the right hand of God. ^57But they cried out with a loud voice, and stopped their ears, and rushed upon him with one accord; ^58and they cast him out of the city, and stoned him: and the witnesses laid down their garments at the feet of a young man named Saul. ^59And they stoned Stephen, calling upon the Lord, and saying, Lord Jesus, receive my spirit. ^60And he kneeled down, and cried with a loud voice, Lord, lay not this sin to their charge. And when he had said this, he fell asleep.

Acts 8

8

^1And Saul was consenting unto his death. And there arose on that day a great persecution against the church which was in Jerusalem; and they were all scattered abroad throughout the regions of Judaea and Samaria, except the apostles. ^2And devout men buried Stephen, and made great lamentation over him. ^3But Saul laid waste the church, entering into every house, and dragging men and women committed them to prison. ^4They therefore that were scattered abroad, went about preaching the word. ^5And Philip went down to the city of Samaria, and proclaimed unto them the Christ. ^6And the multitudes gave heed with one accord unto the things that were spoken by Philip, when they heard, and saw the signs which he did. ^7For from many of those that had unclean spirits, they came out, crying with a loud voice: and many that were palsied, and that were lame, were healed. ^8And there was much joy in that city. ^9But there was a certain man, Simon by name, who beforetime in the city used sorcery, and amazed the people of Samaria, giving out that himself was some great one: ^10to whom they all gave heed, from the least to the greatest, saying, This man is that power of God which is called Great. ^11And they gave heed to him, because that of long time he had amazed them with his sorceries. ^12But when they believed Philip preaching good tidings concerning the kingdom of God and the name of Jesus Christ, they were baptized, both men and women. ^13And Simon also himself believed: and being baptized, he continued with Philip; and beholding signs and great miracles wrought, he was amazed. ^14Now when the apostles that were at Jerusalem heard that Samaria had received the word of God, they sent unto them Peter and John: ^15who, when they were come down, prayed for them, that they might receive the Holy Spirit: ^16for as yet it was fallen upon none of them: only they had been baptized into the name of the Lord Jesus. ^17Then laid they their hands on them, and they received the Holy Spirit. ^18Now when Simon saw that through the laying on of the apostles' hands the Holy Spirit was given, he offered them money, ^19saying, Give me also this power, that on whomsoever I lay my hands, he may receive the Holy Spirit. ^20But Peter said unto him, Thy silver perish with thee, because thou hast thought to obtain the gift of God with money. ^21Thou hast neither part nor lot in this matter: for thy heart is not right before God. ^22Repent therefore of this thy wickedness, and pray the Lord, if perhaps the thought of thy heart shall be forgiven thee. ^23For I see that thou art in the gall of bitterness and in the bond of iniquity. ^24And Simon answered and said, Pray ye for me to the Lord, that none of the things which ye have spoken come upon me. ^25They therefore, when they had testified and spoken the word of the Lord, returned to Jerusalem, and preached the gospel to many villages of the Samaritans. ^26But an angel of the Lord spake unto Philip, saying, Arise, and go toward the south unto the way that goeth down from Jerusalem unto Gaza: the same is desert. ^27And he arose and went: and behold, a man of Ethiopia, a eunuch of great authority under Candace, queen of the Ethiopians, who was over all her treasure, who had come to Jerusalem to worship; ^28and he was returning and sitting in his chariot, and was reading the prophet Isaiah. ^29And the Spirit said unto Philip, Go near, and join thyself to this chariot. ^30And Philip ran to him, and heard him reading Isaiah the prophet, and said, Understandest thou what thou readest? ^31And he said, How can I, except some one shall guide me? And he besought Philip to come up and sit with him. ^32Now the passage of the span which he was reading was this,

He was led as a sheep to the slaughter;

And as a lamb before his shearer is dumb,

So he openeth not his mouth:

^33In his humiliation his judgment was taken away:

His generation who shall declare?

For his life is taken from the earth.

^34And the eunuch answered Philip, and said, I pray thee, of whom speaketh the prophet this? of himself, or of some other? ^35And Philip opened his mouth, and beginning from this span, preached unto him Jesus. ^36And as they went on the way, they came unto a certain water; and the eunuch saith, Behold, here is water; what doth hinder me to be baptized? ^37And Philip said, If thou believest with all thy heart, thou mayest. And he answered and said, I believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God. ^38And he commanded the chariot to stand still: and they both went down into the water, both Philip and the eunuch, and he baptized him. ^39And when they came up out of the water, the Spirit of the Lord caught away Philip; and the eunuch saw him no more, for he went on his way rejoicing. ^40But Philip was found at Azotus: and passing through he preached the gospel to all the cities, till he came to Caesarea.

Acts 9

9

^1But Saul, yet breathing threatening and slaughter against the disciples of the Lord, went unto the high priest, ^2and asked of him letters to Damascus unto the synagogues, that if he found any that were of the Way, whether men or women, he might bring them bound to Jerusalem. ^3And as he journeyed, it came to pass that he drew nigh unto Damascus: and suddenly there shone round about him a light out of heaven: ^4and he fell upon the earth, and heard a voice saying unto him, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? ^5And he said, Who art thou, Lord? And he said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest: ^6but rise, and enter into the city, and it shall be told thee what thou must do. ^7And the men that journeyed with him stood speechless, hearing the voice, but beholding no man. ^8And Saul arose from the earth; and when his eyes were opened, he saw nothing; and they led him by the hand, and brought him into Damascus. ^9And he was three days without sight, and did neither eat nor drink. ^10Now there was a certain disciple at Damascus, named Ananias; and the Lord said unto him in a vision, Ananias. And he said, Behold, I am here, Lord. ^11And the Lord said unto him, Arise, and go to the street which is called Straight, and inquire in the house of Judas for one named Saul, a man of Tarsus: for behold, he prayeth; ^12and he hath seen a man named Ananias coming in, and laying his hands on him, that he might receive his sight. ^13But Ananias answered, Lord, I have heard from many of this man, how much evil he did to thy saints at Jerusalem: ^14and here he hath authority from the chief priests to bind all that call upon thy name. ^15But the Lord said unto him, Go thy way: for he is a chosen vessel unto me, to bear my name before the Gentiles and kings, and the children of Israel: ^16for I will show him how many things he must suffer for my name's sake. ^17And Ananias departed, and entered into the house; and laying his hands on him said, Brother Saul, the Lord, even Jesus, who appeared unto thee in the way which thou camest, hath sent me, that thou mayest receive thy sight, and be filled with the Holy Spirit. ^18And straightway there fell from his eyes as it were scales, and he received his sight; and he arose and was baptized; ^19and he took food and was strengthened. And he was certain days with the disciples that were at Damascus. ^20And straightway in the synagogues he proclaimed Jesus, that he is the Son of God. ^21And all that heard him were amazed, and said, Is not this he that in Jerusalem made havoc of them that called on this name? and he had come hither for this intent, that he might bring them bound before the chief priests. ^22But Saul increased the more in strength, and confounded the Jews that dwelt at Damascus, proving that this is the Christ. ^23And when many days were fulfilled, the Jews took counsel together to kill him: ^24but their plot became known to Saul. And they watched the gates also day and night that they might kill him: ^25but his disciples took him by night, and let him down through the wall, lowering him in a basket. ^26And when he was come to Jerusalem, he assayed to join himself to the disciples: and they were all afraid of him, not believing that he was a disciple. ^27But Barnabas took him, and brought him to the apostles, and declared unto them how he had seen the Lord in the way, and that he had spoken to him, and how at Damascus he had preached boldly in the name of Jesus. ^28And he was with them going in and going out at Jerusalem, ^29preaching boldly in the name of the Lord: and he spake and disputed against the Grecian Jews; but they were seeking to kill him. ^30And when the brethren knew it, they brought him down to Caesarea, and sent him forth to Tarsus. ^31So the church throughout all Judaea and Galilee and Samaria had peace, being edified; and, walking in the fear of the Lord and in the comfort of the Holy Spirit, was multiplied. ^32And it came to pass, as Peter went throughout all parts, he came down also to the saints that dwelt at Lydda. ^33And there he found a certain man named Aeneas, who had kept his bed eight years; for he was palsied. ^34And Peter said unto him, Aeneas, Jesus Christ healeth thee: arise and make thy bed. And straightway he arose. ^35And all that dwelt at Lydda and in Sharon saw him, and they turned to the Lord. ^36Now there was at Joppa a certain disciple named Tabitha, which by interpretation is called Dorcas: this woman was full of good works and almsdeeds which she did. ^37And it came to pass in those days, that she fell sick, and died: and when they had washed her, they laid her in an upper chamber. ^38And as Lydda was nigh unto Joppa, the disciples, hearing that Peter was there, sent two men unto him, entreating him, Delay not to come on unto us. ^39And Peter arose and went with them. And when he was come, they brought him into the upper chamber: and all the widows stood by him weeping, and showing the coats and garments which Dorcas made, while she was with them. ^40But Peter put them all forth, and kneeled down and prayed; and turning to the body, he said, Tabitha, arise. And she opened her eyes; and when she saw Peter, she sat up. ^41And he gave her his hand, and raised her up; and calling the saints and widows, he presented her alive. ^42And it became known throughout all Joppa: and many believed on the Lord. ^43And it came to pass, that he abode many days in Joppa with one Simon a tanner.

Acts 10

10

^1Now there was a certain man in Caesarea, Cornelius by name, a centurion of the band called the Italian band, ^2a devout man, and one that feared God with all his house, who gave much alms to the people, and prayed to God always. ^3He saw in a vision openly, as it were about the ninth hour of the day, an angel of God coming in unto him, and saying to him, Cornelius. ^4And he, fastening his eyes upon him, and being affrighted, said, What is it, Lord? And he said unto him, Thy prayers and thine alms are gone up for a memorial before God. ^5And now send men to Joppa, and fetch one Simon, who is surnamed Peter: ^6he lodgeth with one Simon a tanner, whose house is by the sea side. ^7And when the angel that spake unto him was departed, he called two of his household-servants, and a devout soldier of them that waited on him continually; ^8and having rehearsed all things unto them, he sent them to Joppa. ^9Now on the morrow, as they were on their journey, and drew nigh unto the city, Peter went up upon the housetop to pray, about the sixth hour: ^10and he became hungry, and desired to eat: but while they made ready, he fell into a trance; ^11and he beholdeth the heaven opened, and a certain vessel descending, as it were a great sheet, let down by four corners upon the earth: ^12wherein were all manner of fourfooted beasts and creeping things of the earth and birds of the heaven. ^13And there came a voice to him, Rise, Peter; kill and eat. ^14But Peter said, Not so, Lord; for I have never eaten anything that is common and unclean. ^15And a voice came unto him again the second time, What God hath cleansed, make not thou common. ^16And this was done thrice: and straightway the vessel was received up into heaven. ^17Now while Peter was much perplexed in himself what the vision which he had seen might mean, behold, the men that were sent by Cornelius, having made inquiry for Simon's house, stood before the gate, ^18and called and asked whether Simon, who was surnamed Peter, were lodging there. ^19And while Peter thought on the vision, the Spirit said unto him, Behold, three men seek thee. ^20But arise, and get thee down, and go with them, nothing doubting: for I have sent them. ^21And Peter went down to the men, and said, Behold, I am he whom ye seek: what is the cause wherefore ye are come? ^22And they said, Cornelius a centurion, a righteous man and one that feareth God, and well reported of by all the nation of the Jews, was warned of God by a holy angel to send for thee into his house, and to hear words from thee. ^23So he called them in and lodged them. And on the morrow he arose and went forth with them, and certain of the brethren from Joppa accompanied him. ^24And on the morrow they entered into Caesarea. And Cornelius was waiting for them, having called together his kinsmen and his near friends. ^25And when it came to pass that Peter entered, Cornelius met him, and fell down at his feet, and worshipped him. ^26But Peter raised him up, saying, Stand up; I myself also am a man. ^27And as he talked with him, he went in, and findeth many come together: ^28and he said unto them, Ye yourselves know how it is an unlawful thing for a man that is a Jew to join himself or come unto one of another nation; and yet unto me hath God showed that I should not call any man common or unclean: ^29wherefore also I came without gainsaying, when I was sent for. I ask therefore with what intent ye sent for me. ^30And Cornelius said, Four days ago, until this hour, I was keeping the ninth hour of prayer in my house; and behold, a man stood before me in bright apparel, ^31and saith, Cornelius, thy prayer is heard, and thine alms are had in remembrance in the sight of God. ^32Send therefore to Joppa, and call unto thee Simon, who is surnamed Peter; he lodgeth in the house of Simon a tanner, by the sea side. ^33Forthwith therefore I sent to thee; and thou hast well done that thou art come. Now therefore we are all here present in the sight of God, to hear all things that have been commanded thee of the Lord. ^34And Peter opened his mouth and said, Of a truth I perceive that God is no respecter of persons: ^35but in every nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteousness, is acceptable to him. ^36The word which he sent unto the children of Israel, preaching good tidings of peace by Jesus Christ (He is Lord of all.) -- ^37that saying ye yourselves know, which was published throughout all Judaea, beginning from Galilee, after the baptism which John preached; ^38even Jesus of Nazareth, how God anointed him with the Holy Spirit and with power: who went about doing good, and healing all that were oppressed of the devil; for God was with him. ^39And we are witnesses of all things which he did both in the country of the Jews, and in Jerusalem; whom also they slew, hanging him on a tree. ^40Him God raised up the third day, and gave him to be made manifest, ^41not to all the people, but unto witnesses that were chosen before of God, even to us, who ate and drank with him after he rose from the dead. ^42And he charged us to preach unto the people, and to testify that this is he who is ordained of God to be the Judge of the living and the dead. ^43To him bear all the prophets witness, that through his name every one that believeth on him shall receive remission of sins. ^44While Peter yet spake these words, the Holy Spirit fell on all them that heard the word. ^45And they of the circumcision that believed were amazed, as many as came with Peter, because that on the Gentiles also was poured out the gift of the Holy Spirit. ^46For they heard them speak with tongues, and magnify God. Then answered Peter, ^47Can any man forbid the water, that these should not be baptized, who have received the Holy Spirit as well as we? ^48And he commanded them to be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ. Then prayed they him to tarry certain days.

Acts 11

11

^1Now the apostles and the brethren that were in Judaea heard that the Gentiles also had received the word of God. ^2And when Peter was come up to Jerusalem, they that were of the circumcision contended with him, ^3saying, Thou wentest in to men uncircumcised, and didst eat with them. ^4But Peter began, and expounded the matter unto them in order, saying, ^5I was in the city of Joppa praying: and in a trance I saw a vision, a certain vessel descending, as it were a great sheet let down from heaven by four corners; and it came even unto me: ^6upon which when I had fastened mine eyes, I considered, and saw the fourfooted beasts of the earth and wild beasts and creeping things and birds of the heaven. ^7And I heard also a voice saying unto me, Rise, Peter; kill and eat. ^8But I said, Not so, Lord: for nothing common or unclean hath ever entered into my mouth. ^9But a voice answered the second time out of heaven, What God hath cleansed, make not thou common. ^10And this was done thrice: and all were drawn up again into heaven. ^11And behold, forthwith three men stood before the house in which we were, having been sent from Caesarea unto me. ^12And the Spirit bade me go with them, making no distinction. And these six brethren also accompanied me; and we entered into the man's house: ^13and he told us how he had seen the angel standing in his house, and saying, Send to Joppa, and fetch Simon, whose surname is Peter; ^14who shall speak unto thee words, whereby thou shalt be saved, thou and all thy house. ^15And as I began to speak, the Holy Spirit fell on them, even as on us at the beginning. ^16And I remembered the word of the Lord, how he said, John indeed baptized with water; but ye shall be baptized in the Holy Spirit. ^17If then God gave unto them the like gift as he did also unto us, when we believed on the Lord Jesus Christ, who was I, that I could withstand God? ^18And when they heard these things, they held their peace, and glorified God, saying, Then to the Gentiles also hath God granted repentance unto life. ^19They therefore that were scattered abroad upon the tribulation that arose about Stephen travelled as far as Phoenicia, and Cyprus, and Antioch, speaking the word to none save only to Jews. ^20But there were some of them, men of Cyprus and Cyrene, who, when they were come to Antioch, spake unto the Greeks also, preaching the Lord Jesus. ^21And the hand of the Lord was with them: and a great number that believed turned unto the Lord. ^22And the report concerning them came to the ears of the church which was in Jerusalem: and they sent forth Barnabas as far as Antioch: ^23who, when he was come, and had seen the grace of God, was glad; and he exhorted them all, that with purpose of heart they would cleave unto the Lord: ^24for he was a good man, and full of the Holy Spirit and of faith: and much people was added unto the Lord. ^25And he went forth to Tarsus to seek for Saul; ^26and when he had found him, he brought him unto Antioch. And it came to pass, that even for a whole year they were gathered together with the church, and taught much people, and that the disciples were called Christians first in Antioch. ^27Now in these days there came down prophets from Jerusalem unto Antioch. ^28And there stood up one of them named Agabus, and signified by the Spirit that there should be a great famine over all the world: which came to pass in the days of Claudius. ^29And the disciples, every man according to his ability, determined to send relief unto the brethren that dwelt in Judea: ^30which also they did, sending it to the elders by the hand of Barnabas and Saul.

Acts 12

12

^1Now about that time Herod the king put forth his hands to afflict certain of the church. ^2And he killed James the brother of John with the sword. ^3And when he saw that it pleased the Jews, he proceeded to seize Peter also. And those were the days of unleavened bread. ^4And when he had taken him, he put him in prison, and delivered him to four quaternions of soldiers to guard him; intending after the Passover to bring him forth to the people. ^5Peter therefore was kept in the prison: but prayer was made earnestly of the church unto God for him. ^6And when Herod was about to bring him forth, the same night Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, bound with two chains: and guards before the door kept the prison. ^7And behold, an angel of the Lord stood by him, and a light shined in the cell: and he smote Peter on the side, and awoke him, saying, Rise up quickly. And his chains fell off from his hands. ^8And the angel said unto him, Gird thyself, and bind on thy sandals. And he did so. And he saith unto him, Cast thy garment about thee, and follow me. ^9And he went out, and followed; and he knew not that it was true which was done by the angel, but thought he saw a vision. ^10And when they were past the first and the second guard, they came unto the iron gate that leadeth into the city; which opened to them of its own accord: and they went out, and passed on through one street; and straightway the angel departed from him. ^11And when Peter was come to himself, he said, Now I know of a truth, that the Lord hath sent forth his angel and delivered me out of the hand of Herod, and from all the expectation of the people of the Jews. ^12And when he had considered the thing, he came to the house of Mary the mother of John whose surname was Mark; where many were gathered together and were praying. ^13And when he knocked at the door of the gate, a maid came to answer, named Rhoda. ^14And when she knew Peter's voice, she opened not the gate for joy, but ran in, and told that Peter stood before the gate. ^15And they said unto her, Thou art mad. But she confidently affirmed that it was even so. And they said, It is his angel. ^16But Peter continued knocking: and when they had opened, they saw him, and were amazed. ^17But he, beckoning unto them with the hand to hold their peace, declared unto them how the Lord had brought him forth out of the prison. And he said, Tell these things unto James, and to the brethren. And he departed, and went to another place. ^18Now as soon as it was day, there was no small stir among the soldiers, what was become of Peter. ^19And when Herod had sought for him, and found him not, he examined the guards, and commanded that they should be put to death. And he went down from Judaea to Caesarea, and tarried there. ^20Now he was highly displeased with them of Tyre and Sidon: and they came with one accord to him, and, having made Blastus the king's chamberlain their friend, they asked for peace, because their country was fed from the king's country. ^21And upon a set day Herod arrayed himself in royal apparel, and sat on the throne, and made an oration unto them. ^22And the people shouted, saying, The voice of a god, and not of a man. ^23And immediately an angel of the Lord smote him, because he gave not God the glory: and he was eaten of worms, and gave up the ghost. ^24But the word of God grew and multiplied. ^25And Barnabas and Saul returned from Jerusalem, when they had fulfilled their ministration, taking with them John whose surname was Mark.

Acts 13

13

^1Now there were at Antioch, in the church that was there, prophets and teachers, Barnabas, and Symeon that was called Niger, and Lucius of Cyrene, and Manaen the foster-brother of Herod the tetrarch, and Saul. ^2And as they ministered to the Lord, and fasted, the Holy Spirit said, Separate me Barnabas and Saul for the work whereunto I have called them. ^3Then, when they had fasted and prayed and laid their hands on them, they sent them away. ^4So they, being sent forth by the Holy Spirit, went down to Seleucia; and from thence they sailed to Cyprus. ^5And when they were at Salamis, they proclaimed the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews: and they had also John as their attendant. ^6And when they had gone through the whole island unto Paphos, they found a certain sorcerer, a false prophet, a Jew, whose name was Bar-jesus; ^7who was with the proconsul, Sergius Paulus, a man of understanding. The same called unto him Barnabas and Saul, and sought to hear the word of God. ^8But Elymas the sorcerer (for so is his name by interpretation) withstood them, seeking to turn aside the proconsul from the faith. ^9But Saul, who is also called Paul, filled with the Holy Spirit, fastened his eyes on him, ^10and said, O full of all guile and all villany, thou son of the devil, thou enemy of all righteousness, wilt thou not cease to pervert the right ways of the Lord? ^11And now, behold, the hand of the Lord is upon thee, and thou shalt be blind, not seeing the sun for a season. And immediately there fell on him a mist and a darkness; and he went about seeking some to lead him by the hand. ^12Then the proconsul, when he saw what was done, believed, being astonished at the teaching of the Lord. ^13Now Paul and his company set sail from Paphos, and came to Perga in Pamphylia: and John departed from them and returned to Jerusalem. ^14But they, passing through from Perga, came to Antioch of Pisidia; and they went into the synagogue on the sabbath day, and sat down. ^15And after the reading of the law and the prophets the rulers of the synagogue sent unto them, saying, Brethren, if ye have any word of exhortation for the people, say on. ^16And Paul stood up, and beckoning with the hand said, Men of Israel, and ye that fear God, hearken: ^17The God of this people Israel chose our fathers, and exalted the people when they sojourned in the land of Egypt, and with a high arm led he them forth out of it. ^18And for about the time of forty years as a nursing-father bare he them in the wilderness. ^19And when he had destroyed seven nations in the land of Canaan, he gave them their land for an inheritance, for about four hundred and fifty years: ^20and after these things he gave them judges until Samuel the prophet. ^21And afterward they asked for a king: and God gave unto them Saul the son of Kish, a man of the tribe of Benjamin, for the space of forty years. ^22And when he had removed him, he raised up David to be their king; to whom also he bare witness and said, I have found David the son of Jesse, a man after My heart, who shall do all My will. ^23Of this man's seed hath God according to promise brought unto Israel a Saviour, Jesus; ^24when John had first preached before his coming the baptism of repentance to all the people of Israel. ^25And as John was fulfilling his course, he said, What suppose ye that I am? I am not he. But behold, there cometh one after me the shoes of whose feet I am not worthy to unloose. ^26Brethren, children of the stock of Abraham, and those among you that fear God, to us is the word of this salvation sent forth. ^27For they that dwell in Jerusalem, and their rulers, because they knew him not, nor the voices of the prophets which are read every sabbath, fulfilled them by condemning him. ^28And though they found no cause of death in him, yet asked they of Pilate that he should be slain. ^29And when they had fulfilled all things that were written of him, they took him down from the tree, and laid him in a tomb. ^30But God raised him from the dead: ^31and he was seen for many days of them that came up with him from Galilee to Jerusalem, who are now his witnesses unto the people. ^32And we bring you good tidings of the promise made unto the fathers, ^33that God hath fulfilled the same unto our children, in that he raised up Jesus; as also it is written in the second psalm, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee. ^34And as concerning that he raised him up from the dead, now no more to return to corruption, he hath spoken on this wise, I will give you the holy and sure blessings of David. ^35Because he saith also in another psalm, Thou wilt not give Thy Holy One to see corruption. ^36For David, after he had in his own generation served the counsel of God, fell asleep, and was laid unto his fathers, and saw corruption: ^37but he whom God raised up saw no corruption. ^38Be it known unto you therefore, brethren, that through this man is proclaimed unto you remission of sins: ^39and by him every one that believeth is justified from all things, from which ye could not be justified by the law of Moses. ^40Beware therefore, lest that come upon you which is spoken in the prophets:

^41Behold, ye despisers, and wonder, and perish;

For I work a work in your days,

A work which ye shall in no wise believe, if one declare it unto you.

^42And as they went out, they besought that these words might be spoken to them the next sabbath. ^43Now when the synagogue broke up, many of the Jews and of the devout proselytes followed Paul and Barnabas; who, speaking to them, urged them to continue in the grace of God. ^44And the next sabbath almost the whole city was gathered together to hear the word of God. ^45But when the Jews saw the multitudes, they were filled with jealousy, and contradicted the things which were spoken by Paul, and blasphemed. ^46And Paul and Barnabas spake out boldly, and said, It was necessary that the word of God should first be spoken to you. Seeing ye thrust it from you, and judge yourselves unworthy of eternal life, lo, we turn to the Gentiles. ^47For so hath the Lord commanded us, saying,

I have set thee for a light of the Gentiles,

That thou shouldest be for salvation unto the uttermost part of the earth.

^48And as the Gentiles heard this, they were glad, and glorified the word of God: and as many as were ordained to eternal life believed. ^49And the word of the Lord was spread abroad throughout all the region. ^50But the Jews urged on the devout women of honorable estate, and the chief men of the city, and stirred up a persecution against Paul and Barnabas, and cast them out of their borders. ^51But they shook off the dust of their feet against them, and came unto Iconium. ^52And the disciples were filled with joy with the Holy Spirit.

Acts 14

14

^1And it came to pass in Iconium that they entered together into the synagogue of the Jews, and so spake that a great multitude both of Jews and of Greeks believed. ^2But the Jews that were disobedient stirred up the souls of the Gentiles, and made them evil affected against the brethren. ^3Long time therefore they tarried there speaking boldly in the Lord, who bare witness unto the word of his grace, granting signs and wonders to be done by their hands. ^4But the multitude of the city was divided; and part held with the Jews, and part with the apostles. ^5And when there was made an onset both of the Gentiles and of the Jews with their rulers, to treat them shamefully and to stone them, ^6they became aware of it, and fled unto the cities of Lycaonia, Lystra and Derbe, and the region round about: ^7and there they preached the gospel. ^8And at Lystra there sat a certain man, impotent in his feet, a cripple from his mother's womb, who never had walked. ^9The same heard Paul speaking, who, fastening eyes upon him, and seeing that he had faith to be made whole, ^10said with a loud voice, Stand upright on thy feet. And he leaped up and walked. ^11And when the multitude saw what Paul had done, they lifted up their voice, saying in the speech of Lycaonia, The gods are come down to us in the likeness of men. ^12And they called Barnabas, Jupiter; and Paul, Mercury, because he was the chief speaker. ^13And the priest of Jupiter whose temple was before the city, brought oxen and garlands unto the gates, and would have done sacrifice with the multitudes. ^14But when the apostles, Barnabas and Paul, heard of it, they rent their garments, and sprang forth among the multitude, crying out ^15and saying, Sirs, why do ye these things? We also are men of like passions with you, and bring you good tidings, that ye should turn from these vain things unto a living God, who made the heaven and the earth and the sea, and all that in them is: ^16who in the generations gone by suffered all the nations to walk in their own ways. ^17And yet He left not himself without witness, in that he did good and gave you from heaven rains and fruitful seasons, filling your hearts with food and gladness. ^18And with these sayings scarce restrained they the multitudes from doing sacrifice unto them. ^19But there came Jews thither from Antioch and Iconium: and having persuaded the multitudes, they stoned Paul, and dragged him out of the city, supposing that he was dead. ^20But as the disciples stood round about him, he rose up, and entered into the city: and on the morrow he went forth with Barnabas to Derbe. ^21And when they had preached the gospel to that city, and had made many disciples, they returned to Lystra, and to Iconium, and to Antioch, ^22confirming the souls of the disciples, exhorting them to continue in the faith, and that through many tribulations we must enter into the kingdom of God. ^23And when they had appointed for them elders in every church, and had prayed with fasting, they commended them to the Lord, on whom they had believed. ^24And they passed through Pisidia, and came to Pamphylia. ^25And when they had spoken the word in Perga, they went down to Attalia; ^26and thence they sailed to Antioch, from whence they had been committed to the grace of God for the work which they had fulfilled. ^27And when they were come, and had gathered the church together, they rehearsed all things that God had done with them, and that he had opened a door of faith unto the Gentiles. ^28And they tarried no little time with the disciples.

Acts 15

15

^1And certain men came down from Judaea and taught the brethren, saying, Except ye be circumcised after the custom of Moses, ye cannot be saved. ^2And when Paul and Barnabas had no small dissension and questioning with them, the brethren appointed that Paul and Barnabas, and certain other of them, should go up to Jerusalem unto the apostles and elders about this question. ^3They therefore, being brought on their way by the church, passed through both Phoenicia and Samaria, declaring the conversion of the Gentiles: and they caused great joy unto all the brethren. ^4And when they were come to Jerusalem, they were received of the church and the apostles and the elders, and they rehearsed all things that God had done with them. ^5But there rose up certain of the sect of the Pharisees who believed, saying, It is needful to circumcise them, and to charge them to keep the law of Moses. ^6And the apostles and the elders were gathered together to consider of this matter. ^7And when there had been much questioning, Peter rose up, and said unto them, Brethren, ye know that a good while ago God made choice among you, that by my mouth the Gentiles should hear the word of the gospel, and believe. ^8And God, who knoweth the heart, bare them witness, giving them the Holy Spirit, even as he did unto us; ^9and he made no distinction between us and them, cleansing their hearts by faith. ^10Now therefore why make ye trial of God, that ye should put a yoke upon the neck of the disciples which neither our fathers nor we were able to bear? ^11But we believe that we shall be saved through the grace of the Lord Jesus, in like manner as they. ^12And all the multitude kept silence; and they hearkened unto Barnabas and Paul rehearsing what signs and wonders God had wrought among the Gentiles through them. ^13And after they had held their peace, James answered, saying, Brethren, hearken unto me: ^14Symeon hath rehearsed how first God visited the Gentiles, to take out of them a people for his name. ^15And to this agree the words of the prophets; as it is written,

^16After these things I will return,

And I will build again the tabernacle of David, which is fallen;

And I will build again the ruins thereof,

And I will set it up:

^17That the residue of men may seek after the Lord,

And all the Gentiles, upon whom my name is called,

^18Saith the Lord, who maketh these things known from of old.

^19Wherefore my judgment is, that we trouble not them that from among the Gentiles turn to God; ^20but that we write unto them, that they abstain from the pollutions of idols, and from fornication, and from what is strangled, and from blood. ^21For Moses from generations of old hath in every city them that preach him, being read in the synagogues every sabbath. ^22Then it seemed good to the apostles and the elders, with the whole church, to choose men out of their company, and send them to Antioch with Paul and Barnabas; namely, Judas called Barsabbas, and Silas, chief men among the brethren: ^23and they wrote thus by them, The apostles and the elders, brethren, unto the brethren who are of the Gentiles in Antioch and Syria and Cilicia, greeting: ^24Forasmuch as we have heard that certain who went out from us have troubled you with words, subverting your souls; to whom we gave no commandment; ^25it seemed good unto us, having come to one accord, to choose out men and send them unto you with our beloved Barnabas and Paul, ^26men that have hazarded their lives for the name of our Lord Jesus Christ. ^27We have sent therefore Judas and Silas, who themselves also shall tell you the same things by word of mouth. ^28For it seemed good to the Holy Spirit, and to us, to lay upon you no greater burden than these necessary things: ^29that ye abstain from things sacrificed to idols, and from blood, and from things strangled, and from fornication; from which if ye keep yourselves, it shall be well with you. Fare ye well. ^30So they, when they were dismissed, came down to Antioch; and having gathered the multitude together, they delivered the epistle. ^31And when they had read it, they rejoiced for the consolation. ^32And Judas and Silas, being themselves also prophets, exhorted the brethren with many words, and confirmed them. ^33And after they had spent some time there, they were dismissed in peace from the brethren unto those that had sent them forth. ^34But it seemed good unto Silas to abide there. ^35But Paul and Barnabas tarried in Antioch, teaching and preaching the word of the Lord, with many others also. ^36And after some days Paul said unto Barnabas, Let us return now and visit the brethren in every city wherein we proclaimed the word of the Lord, and see how they fare. ^37And Barnabas was minded to take with them John also, who was called Mark. ^38But Paul thought not good to take with them him who withdrew from them from Pamphylia, and went not with them to the work. ^39And there arose a sharp contention, so that they parted asunder one from the other, and Barnabas took Mark with him, and sailed away unto Cyprus; ^40but Paul choose Silas, and went forth, being commended by the brethren to the grace of the Lord. ^41And he went through Syria and Cilicia, confirming the churches.

Acts 16

16

^1And he came also to Derbe and to Lystra: and behold, a certain disciple was there, named Timothy, the son of a Jewess that believed; but his father was a Greek. ^2The same was well reported of by the brethren that were at Lystra and Iconium. ^3Him would Paul have to go forth with him; and he took and circumcised him because of the Jews that were in those parts: for they all knew that his father was a Greek. ^4And as they went on their way through the cities, they delivered them the decrees to keep which had been ordained of the apostles and elders that were at Jerusalem. ^5So the churches were strengthened in the faith, and increased in number daily. ^6And they went through the region of Phrygia and Galatia, having been forbidden of the Holy Spirit to speak the word in Asia; ^7and when they were come over against Mysia, they assayed to go into Bithynia; and the Spirit of Jesus suffered them not; ^8and passing by Mysia, they came down to Troas. ^9And a vision appeared to Paul in the night: There was a man of Macedonia standing, beseeching him, and saying, Come over into Macedonia, and help us. ^10And when he had seen the vision, straightway we sought to go forth into Macedonia, concluding that God had called us to preach the gospel to them. ^11Setting sail therefore from Troas, we made a straight course to Samothrace, and the day following to Neapolis; ^12and from thence to Philippi, which is a city of Macedonia, the first of the district, a Roman colony: and we were in this city tarrying certain days. ^13And on the sabbath day we went forth without the gate by a river side, where we supposed there was a place of prayer; and we sat down, and spake unto the women that were come together. ^14And a certain woman named Lydia, a seller of purple of the city of Thyatira, one that worshipped God, heard us: whose heart the Lord opened to give heed unto the things which were spoken by Paul. ^15And when she was baptized, and her household, she besought us, saying, If ye have judged me to be faithful to the Lord, come into my house, and abide there. And she constrained us. ^16And it came to pass, as we were going to the place of prayer, that a certain maid having a spirit of divination met us, who brought her masters much gain by soothsaying. ^17The same following after Paul and us cried out, saying, These men are servants of the Most High God, who proclaim unto you the way of salvation. ^18And this she did for many days. But Paul, being sore troubled, turned and said to the spirit, I charge thee in the name of Jesus Christ to come out of her. And it came out that very hour. ^19But when her masters saw that the hope of their gain was gone, they laid hold on Paul and Silas, and dragged them into the marketplace before the rulers, ^20and when they had brought them unto the magistrates, they said, These men, being Jews, do exceedingly trouble our city, ^21and set forth customs which it is not lawful for us to receive, or to observe, being Romans. ^22And the multitude rose up together against them: and the magistrates rent their garments off them, and commanded to beat them with rods. ^23And when they had laid many stripes upon them, they cast them into prison, charging the jailor to keep them safely: ^24who, having received such a charge, cast them into the inner prison, and made their feet fast in the stocks. ^25But about midnight Paul and Silas were praying and singing hymns unto God, and the prisoners were listening to them; ^26and suddenly there was a great earthquake, so that the foundations of the prison-house were shaken: and immediately all the doors were opened, and every one's bands were loosed. ^27And the jailor, being roused out of sleep and seeing the prison doors open, drew his sword and was about to kill himself, supposing that the prisoners had escaped. ^28But Paul cried with a loud voice, saying, Do thyself no harm: for we are all here. ^29And he called for lights and sprang in, and, trembling for fear, fell down before Paul and Silas, ^30and brought them out and said, Sirs, what must I do to be saved? ^31And they said, Believe on the Lord Jesus, and thou shalt be saved, thou and thy house. ^32And they spake the word of the Lord unto him, with all that were in his house. ^33And he took them the same hour of the night, and washed their stripes; and was baptized, he and all his, immediately. ^34And he brought them up into his house, and set food before them, and rejoiced greatly, with all his house, having believed in God. ^35But when it was day, the magistrates sent the sergeants, saying, Let those men go. ^36And the jailor reported the words to Paul, saying, The magistrates have sent to let you go: now therefore come forth, and go in peace. ^37But Paul said unto them, They have beaten us publicly, uncondemned, men that are Romans, and have cast us into prison; and do they now cast us out privily? Nay verily; but let them come themselves and bring us out. ^38And the sergeants reported these words unto the magistrates: and they feared when they heard that they were Romans; ^39and they came and besought them; and when they had brought them out, they asked them to go away from the city. ^40And they went out of the prison, and entered into the house of Lydia: and when they had seen the brethren, they comforted them, and departed.

Acts 17

17

^1Now when they had passed through Amphipolis and Apollonia, they came to Thessalonica, where was a synagogue of the Jews: ^2and Paul, as his custom was, went in unto them, and for three sabbath days reasoned with them from the spans, ^3opening and alleging that it behooved the Christ to suffer, and to rise again from the dead; and that this Jesus, whom, said he, I proclaim unto you, is the Christ. ^4And some of them were persuaded, and consorted with Paul and Silas, and of the devout Greeks a great multitude, and of the chief women not a few. ^5But the Jews, being moved with jealousy, took unto them certain vile fellows of the rabble, and gathering a crowd, set the city on an uproar; and assaulting the house of Jason, they sought to bring them forth to the people. ^6And when they found them not, they dragged Jason and certain brethren before the rulers of the city, crying, These that have turned the world upside down are come hither also; ^7whom Jason hath received: and these all act contrary to the decrees of Caesar, saying that there is another king, one Jesus. ^8And they troubled the multitude and the rulers of the city, when they heard these things. ^9And when they had taken security from Jason and the rest, they let them go. ^10And the brethren immediately sent away Paul and Silas by night unto Beroea: who when they were come thither went into the synagogue of the Jews. ^11Now these were more noble than those in Thessalonica, in that they received the word with all readiness of the mind, examining the spans daily, whether these things were so. ^12Many of them therefore believed; also of the Greek women of honorable estate, and of men, not a few. ^13But when the Jews of Thessalonica had knowledge that the word of God was proclaimed of Paul at Beroea also, they came thither likewise, stirring up and troubling the multitudes. ^14And then immediately the brethren sent forth Paul to go as far as to the sea: and Silas and Timothy abode there still. ^15But they that conducted Paul brought him as far as Athens: and receiving a commandment unto Silas and Timothy that they should come to him with all speed, they departed. ^16Now while Paul waited for them at Athens, his spirit was provoked within him as he beheld the city full of idols. ^17So he reasoned in the synagogue with Jews and the devout persons, and in the marketplace every day with them that met him. ^18And certain also of the Epicurean and Stoic philosophers encountered him. And some said, What would this babbler say? others, He seemeth to be a setter forth of strange gods: because he preached Jesus and the resurrection. ^19And they took hold of him, and brought him unto the Areopagus, saying, May we know what this new teaching is, which is spoken by thee? ^20For thou bringest certain strange things to our ears: we would know therefore what these things mean. ^21(Now all the Athenians and the strangers sojourning there spent their time in nothing else, but either to tell or to hear some new thing.) ^22And Paul stood in the midst of the Areopagus, and said, Ye men of Athens, in all things, I perceive that ye are very religious. ^23For as I passed along, and observed the objects of your worship, I found also an altar with this inscription, TO AN UNKNOWN GOD. What therefore ye worship in ignorance, this I set forth unto you. ^24The God that made the world and all things therein, he, being Lord of heaven and earth, dwelleth not in temples made with hands; ^25neither is he served by men's hands, as though he needed anything, seeing he himself giveth to all life, and breath, and all things; ^26and he made of one every nation of men to dwell on all the face of the earth, having determined their appointed seasons, and the bounds of their habitation; ^27that they should seek God, if haply they might feel after him and find him, though he is not far from each one of us: ^28for in him we live, and move, and have our being; as certain even of your own poets have said, For we are also his offspring. ^29Being then the offspring of God, we ought not to think that the Godhead is like unto gold, or silver, or stone, graven by art and device of man. ^30The times of ignorance therefore God overlooked; but now he commandeth men that they should all everywhere repent: ^31inasmuch as he hath appointed a day in which he will judge the world in righteousness by the man whom he hath ordained; whereof he hath given assurance unto all men, in that he hath raised him from the dead. ^32Now when they heard of the resurrection of the dead, some mocked; but others said, We will hear thee concerning this yet again. ^33Thus Paul went out from among them. ^34But certain men clave unto him, and believed: among whom also was Dionysius the Areopagite, and a woman named Damaris, and others with them.

Acts 18

18

^1After these things he departed from Athens, and came to Corinth. ^2And he found a certain Jew named Aquila, a man of Pontus by race, lately come from Italy, with his wife Priscilla, because Claudius had commanded all the Jews to depart from Rome: and he came unto them; ^3and because he was of the same trade, he abode with them, and they wrought, for by their trade they were tentmakers. ^4And he reasoned in the synagogue every sabbath, and persuaded Jews and Greeks. ^5But when Silas and Timothy came down from Macedonia, Paul was constrained by the word, testifying to the Jews that Jesus was the Christ. ^6And when they opposed themselves and blasphemed, he shook out his raiment and said unto them, Your blood be upon your own heads; I am clean: from henceforth I will go unto the Gentiles. ^7And he departed thence, and went into the house of a certain man named Titus Justus, one that worshipped God, whose house joined hard to the synagogue. ^8And Crispus, the ruler of the synagogue, believed in the Lord with all his house; and many of the Corinthians hearing believed, and were baptized. ^9And the Lord said unto Paul in the night by a vision, Be not afraid, but speak and hold not thy peace: ^10for I am with thee, and no man shall set on thee to harm thee: for I have much people in this city. ^11And he dwelt there a year and six months, teaching the word of God among them. ^12But when Gallio was proconsul of Achaia, the Jews with one accord rose up against Paul and brought him before the judgment-seat, ^13saying, This man persuadeth men to worship God contrary to the law. ^14But when Paul was about to open his mouth, Gallio said unto the Jews, If indeed it were a matter of wrong or of wicked villany, O ye Jews, reason would that I should bear with you: ^15but if they are questions about words and names and your own law, look to it yourselves; I am not minded to be a judge of these matters. ^16And he drove them from the judgment-seat. ^17And they all laid hold on Sosthenes, the ruler of the synagogue, and beat him before the judgment-seat. And Gallio cared for none of these things. ^18And Paul, having tarried after this yet many days, took his leave of the brethren, and sailed thence for Syria, and with him Priscilla and Aquila: having shorn his head in Cenchreae; for he had a vow. ^19And they came to Ephesus, and he left them there: but he himself entered into the synagogue, and reasoned with the Jews. ^20And when they asked him to abide a longer time, he consented not; ^21but taking his leave of them, and saying, I will return again unto you if God will, he set sail from Ephesus. ^22And when he had landed at Caesarea, he went up and saluted the church, and went down to Antioch. ^23And having spent some time there, he departed, and went through the region of Galatia, and Phrygia, in order, establishing all the disciples. ^24Now a certain Jew named Apollos, an Alexandrian by race, an eloquent man, came to Ephesus; and he was mighty in the spans. ^25This man had been instructed in the way of the Lord; and being fervent in spirit, he spake and taught accurately the things concerning Jesus, knowing only the baptism of John: ^26and he began to speak boldly in the synagogue. But when Priscilla and Aquila heard him, they took him unto them, and expounded unto him the way of God more accurately. ^27And when he was minded to pass over into Achaia, the brethren encouraged him, and wrote to the disciples to receive him: and when he was come, he helped them much that had believed through grace; ^28for he powerfully confuted the Jews, and that publicly, showing by the spans that Jesus was the Christ.

Acts 19

19

^1And it came to pass, that, while Apollos was at Corinth, Paul having passed through the upper country came to Ephesus, and found certain disciples: ^2and he said unto them, Did ye receive the Holy Spirit when ye believed? And they said unto him, Nay, we did not so much as hear whether the Holy Spirit was given. ^3And he said, Into what then were ye baptized? And they said, Into John's baptism. ^4And Paul said, John baptized with the baptism of repentance, saying unto the people that they should believe on him that should come after him, that is, on Jesus. ^5And when they heard this, they were baptized into the name of the Lord Jesus. ^6And when Paul had laid his hands upon them, the Holy Spirit came on them; and they spake with tongues, and prophesied. ^7And they were in all about twelve men. ^8And he entered into the synagogue, and spake boldly for the space of three months, reasoning and persuading as to the things concerning the kingdom of God. ^9But when some were hardened and disobedient, speaking evil of the Way before the multitude, he departed from them, and separated the disciples, reasoning daily in the school of Tyrannus. ^10And this continued for the space of two years; so that all they that dwelt in Asia heard the word of the Lord, both Jews and Greeks. ^11And God wrought special miracles by the hands of Paul: ^12insomuch that unto the sick were carried away from his body handkerchiefs or aprons, and the evil spirits went out. ^13But certain also of the strolling Jews, exorcists, took upon them to name over them that had the evil spirits the name of the Lord Jesus, saying, I adjure you by Jesus whom Paul preacheth. ^14And there were seven sons of one Sceva, a Jew, a chief priest, who did this. ^15And the evil spirit answered and said unto them, Jesus I know, and Paul I know, but who are ye? ^16And the man in whom the evil spirit was leaped on them, and mastered both of them, and prevailed against them, so that they fled out of that house naked and wounded. ^17And this became known to all, both Jews and Greeks, that dwelt at Ephesus; and fear fell upon them all, and the name of the Lord Jesus was magnified. ^18Many also of them that had believed came, confessing, and declaring their deeds. ^19And not a few of them that practised magical arts brought their books together and burned them in the sight of all; and they counted the price of them, and found it fifty thousand pieces of silver. ^20So mightily grew the word of the Lord and prevailed. ^21Now after these things were ended, Paul purposed in the spirit, when he had passed through Macedonia and Achaia, to go to Jerusalem, saying, After I have been there, I must also see Rome. ^22And having sent into Macedonia two of them that ministered unto him, Timothy and Erastus, he himself stayed in Asia for a while. ^23And about that time there arose no small stir concerning the Way. ^24For a certain man named Demetrius, a silversmith, who made silver shrines of Diana, brought no little business unto the craftsmen; ^25whom he gathered together, with the workmen of like occupation, and said, Sirs, ye know that by this business we have our wealth. ^26And ye see and hear, that not alone at Ephesus, but almost throughout all Asia, this Paul hath persuaded and turned away much people, saying that they are no gods, that are made with hands: ^27and not only is there danger that this our trade come into disrepute; but also that the temple of the great goddess Diana be made of no account, and that she should even be deposed from her magnificence whom all Asia and the world worshippeth. ^28And when they heard this they were filled with wrath, and cried out, saying, Great is Diana of the Ephesus. ^29And the city was filled with the confusion: and they rushed with one accord into the theatre, having seized Gaius and Aristarchus, men of Macedonia, Paul's companions in travel. ^30And when Paul was minded to enter in unto the people, the disciples suffered him not. ^31And certain also of the Asiarchs, being his friends, sent unto him and besought him not to adventure himself into the theatre. ^32Some therefore cried one thing, and some another: for the assembly was in confusion; and the more part knew not wherefore they were come together. ^33And they brought Alexander out of the multitude, the Jews putting him forward. And Alexander beckoned with the hand, and would have made a defense unto the people. ^34But when they perceived that he was a Jew, all with one voice about the space of two hours cried out, Great is Diana of the Ephesians. ^35And when the townclerk had quieted the multitude, he saith, Ye men of Ephesus, what man is there who knoweth not that the city of the Ephesians is temple-keeper of the great Diana, and of the image which fell down from Jupiter? ^36Seeing then that these things cannot be gainsaid, ye ought to be quiet, and to do nothing rash. ^37For ye have brought hither these men, who are neither robbers of temples nor blasphemers of our goddess. ^38If therefore Demetrius, and the craftsmen that are with him, have a matter against any man, the courts are open, and there are proconsuls: let them accuse one another. ^39But if ye seek anything about other matters, it shall be settled in the regular assembly. ^40For indeed we are in danger to be accused concerning this day's riot, there being no cause for it: and as touching it we shall not be able to give account of this concourse. ^41And when he had thus spoken, he dismissed the assembly.

Acts 20

20

^1And after the uproar ceased, Paul having sent for the disciples and exhorted them, took leave of them, and departed to go into Macedonia. ^2And when he had gone through those parts, and had given them much exhortation, he came into Greece. ^3And when he had spent three months there, and a plot was laid against him by Jews as he was about to set sail for Syria, he determined to return through Macedonia. ^4And there accompanied him as far as Asia, Sopater of Beroea, the son of Pyrrhus; and of the Thessalonians, Aristarchus and Secundus; and Gaius of Derbe, and Timothy; and of Asia, Tychicus and Trophimus. ^5But these had gone before, and were waiting for us at Troas. ^6And we sailed away from Philippi after the days of unleavened bread, and came unto them to Troas in five days, where we tarried seven days. ^7And upon the first day of the week, when we were gathered together to break bread, Paul discoursed with them, intending to depart on the morrow; and prolonged his speech until midnight. ^8And there were many lights in the upper chamber where we were gathered together. ^9And there sat in the window a certain young man named Eutychus, borne down with deep sleep; and as Paul discoursed yet longer, being borne down by his sleep he fell down from the third story, and was taken up dead. ^10And Paul went down, and fell on him, and embracing him said, Make ye no ado; for his life is in him. ^11And when he was gone up, and had broken the bread, and eaten, and had talked with them a long while, even till break of day, so he departed. ^12And they brought the lad alive, and were not a little comforted. ^13But we going before to the ship set sail for Assos, there intending to take in Paul: for so had he appointed, intending himself to go by land. ^14And when he met us at Assos, we took him in, and came to Mitylene. ^15And sailing from thence, we came the following day over against Chios; and the next day we touched at Samos; and the day after we came to Miletus. ^16For Paul had determined to sail past Ephesus, that he might not have to spend time in Asia; for he was hastening, if it were possible for him, to be at Jerusalem the day of Pentecost. ^17And from Miletus he sent to Ephesus, and called to him the elders of the church. ^18And when they were come to him, he said unto them, Ye yourselves know, from the first day that I set foot in Asia, after what manner I was with you all the time, ^19serving the Lord with all lowliness of mind, and with tears, and with trials which befell me by the plots of the Jews; ^20how I shrank not from declaring unto you anything that was profitable, and teaching you publicly, and from house to house, ^21testifying both to Jews and to Greeks repentance toward God, and faith toward our Lord Jesus Christ. ^22And now, behold, I go bound in the spirit unto Jerusalem, not knowing the things that shall befall me there: ^23save that the Holy Spirit testifieth unto me in every city, saying that bonds and afflictions abide me. ^24But I hold not my life of any account as dear unto myself, so that I may accomplish my course, and the ministry which I received from the Lord Jesus, to testify the gospel of the grace of God. ^25And now, behold, I know that ye all, among whom I went about preaching the kingdom, shall see my face no more. ^26Wherefore I testify unto you this day, that I am pure from the blood of all men. ^27For I shrank not from declaring unto you the whole counsel of God. ^28Take heed unto yourselves, and to all the flock, in which the Holy Spirit hath made you bishops, to feed the church of the Lord which he purchased with his own blood. ^29I know that after my departing grievous wolves shall enter in among you, not sparing the flock; ^30and from among your own selves shall men arise, speaking perverse things, to draw away the disciples after them. ^31Wherefore watch ye, remembering that by the space of three years I ceased not to admonish every one night and day with tears. ^32And now I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you the inheritance among all them that are sanctified. ^33I coveted no man's silver, or gold, or apparel. ^34Ye yourselves know that these hands ministered unto my necessities, and to them that were with me. ^35In all things I gave you an example, that so laboring ye ought to help the weak, and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, that he himself said, It is more blessed to give than to receive. ^36And when he had thus spoken, he kneeled down and prayed with them all. ^37And they all wept sore, and fell on Paul's neck and kissed him, ^38sorrowing most of all for the word which he had spoken, that they should behold his face no more. And they brought him on his way unto the ship.

Acts 21

21

^1And when it came to pass that were parted from them and had set sail, we came with a straight course unto Cos, and the next day unto Rhodes, and from thence unto Patara: ^2and having found a ship crossing over unto Phoenicia, we went aboard, and set sail. ^3And when we had come in sight of Cyprus, leaving it on the left hand, we sailed unto Syria, and landed at Tyre; for there the ship was to unlade her burden. ^4And having found the disciples, we tarried there seven days: and these said to Paul through the Spirit, that he should not set foot in Jerusalem. ^5And when it came to pass that we had accomplished the days, we departed and went on our journey; and they all, with wives and children, brought us on our way till we were out of the city: and kneeling down on the beach, we prayed, and bade each other farewell; ^6and we went on board the ship, but they returned home again. ^7And when we had finished the voyage from Tyre, we arrived at Ptolemais; and we saluted the brethren, and abode with them one day. ^8And on the morrow we departed, and came unto Caesarea: and entering into the house of Philip the evangelist, who was one of the seven, we abode with him. ^9Now this man had four virgin daughters, who prophesied. ^10And as we tarried there some days, there came down from Judaea a certain prophet, named Agabus. ^11And coming to us, and taking Paul's girdle, he bound his own feet and hands, and said, Thus saith the Holy Spirit, So shall the Jews at Jerusalem bind the man that owneth this girdle, and shall deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles. ^12And when we heard these things, both we and they of that place besought him not to go up to Jerusalem. ^13Then Paul answered, What do ye, weeping and breaking my heart? for I am ready not to be bound only, but also to die at Jerusalem for the name of the Lord Jesus. ^14And when he would not be persuaded, we ceased, saying, The will of the Lord be done. ^15And after these days we took up our baggage and went up to Jerusalem. ^16And there went with us also certain of the disciples from Caesarea, bringing with them one Mnason of Cyprus, an early disciple, with whom we should lodge. ^17And when we were come to Jerusalem, the brethren received us gladly. ^18And the day following Paul went in with us unto James; and all the elders were present. ^19And when he had saluted them, he rehearsed one by one the things which God had wrought among the Gentiles through his ministry. ^20And they, when they heard it, glorified God; and they said unto him, Thou seest, brother, how many thousands there are among the Jews of them that have believed; and they are all zealous for the law: ^21and they have been informed concerning thee, that thou teachest all the Jews who are among the Gentiles to forsake Moses, telling them not to circumcise their children neither to walk after the customs. ^22What is it therefore? They will certainly hear that thou art come. ^23Do therefore this that we say to thee: We have four men that have a vow on them; ^24these take, and purify thyself with them, and be at charges for them, that they may shave their heads: and all shall know that there is no truth in the things whereof they have been informed concerning thee; but that thou thyself also walkest orderly, keeping the law. ^25But as touching the Gentiles that have believed, we wrote, giving judgment that they should keep themselves from things sacrificed to idols, and from blood, and from what is strangled, and from fornication. ^26Then Paul took the men, and the next day purifying himself with them went into the temple, declaring the fulfilment of the days of purification, until the offering was offered for every one of them. ^27And when the seven days were almost completed, the Jews from Asia, when they saw him in the temple, stirred up all the multitude and laid hands on him, ^28crying out, Men of Israel, help: This is the man that teacheth all men everywhere against the people, and the law, and this place; and moreover he brought Greeks also into the temple, and hath defiled this holy place. ^29For they had before seen with him in the city Trophimus the Ephesian, whom they supposed that Paul had brought into the temple. ^30And all the city was moved, and the people ran together; and they laid hold on Paul, and dragged him out of the temple: and straightway the doors were shut. ^31And as they were seeking to kill him, tidings came up to the chief captain of the band, that all Jerusalem was in confusion. ^32And forthwith he took soldiers and centurions, and ran down upon them: and they, when they saw the chief captain and the soldiers, left off beating Paul. ^33Then the chief captain came near, and laid hold on him, and commanded him to be bound with two chains; and inquired who he was, and what he had done. ^34And some shouted one thing, some another, among the crowd: and when he could not know the certainty for the uproar, he commanded him to be brought into the castle. ^35And when he came upon the stairs, so it was that he was borne of the soldiers for the violence of the crowd; ^36for the multitude of the people followed after, crying out, Away with him. ^37And as Paul was about to be brought into the castle, he saith unto the chief captain, May I say something unto thee? And he said, Dost thou know Greek? ^38Art thou not then the Egyptian, who before these days stirred up to sedition and led out into the wilderness the four thousand men of the Assassins? ^39But Paul said, I am a Jew, of Tarsus in Cilicia, a citizen of no mean city: and I beseech thee, give me leave to speak unto the people. ^40And when he had given him leave, Paul, standing on the stairs, beckoned with the hand unto the people; and when there was made a great silence, he spake unto them in the Hebrew language, saying,

Acts 22

22

^1Brethren and fathers, hear ye the defence which I now make unto you. ^2And when they heard that he spake unto them in the Hebrew language, they were the more quiet: and he saith, ^3I am a Jew, born in Tarsus of Cilicia, but brought up in this city, at the feet of Gamaliel, instructed according to the strict manner of the law of our fathers, being zealous for God, even as ye all are this day: ^4and I persecuted this Way unto the death, binding and delivering into prisons both men and women. ^5As also the high priest doth bear me witness, and all the estate of the elders: from whom also I received letters unto the brethren, and journeyed to Damascus to bring them also that were there unto Jerusalem in bonds to be punished. ^6And it came to pass, that, as I made my journey, and drew nigh unto Damascus, about noon, suddenly there shone from heaven a great light round about me. ^7And I fell unto the ground, and heard a voice saying unto me, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? ^8And I answered, Who art thou, Lord? And he said unto me, I am Jesus of Nazareth, whom thou persecutest. ^9And they that were with me beheld indeed the light, but they heard not the voice of him that spake to me. ^10And I said, What shall I do, Lord? And the Lord said unto me, Arise, and go into Damascus; and there it shall be told thee of all things which are appointed for thee to do. ^11And when I could not see for the glory of that light, being led by the hand of them that were with me I came into Damascus. ^12And one Ananias, a devout man according to the law, well reported of by all the Jews that dwelt there, ^13came unto me, and standing by me said unto me, Brother Saul, receive thy sight. And in that very hour I looked up on him. ^14And he said, The God of our fathers hath appointed thee to know his will, and to see the Righteous One, and to hear a voice from his mouth. ^15For thou shalt be a witness for him unto all men of what thou hast seen and heard. ^16And now why tarriest thou? arise, and be baptized, and wash away thy sins, calling on his name. ^17And it came to pass, that, when I had returned to Jerusalem, and while I prayed in the temple, I fell into a trance, ^18and saw him saying unto me, Make haste, and get thee quickly out of Jerusalem; because they will not receive of thee testimony concerning me. ^19And I said, Lord, they themselves know that I imprisoned and beat in every synagogue them that believed on thee: ^20and when the blood of Stephen thy witness was shed, I also was standing by, and consenting, and keeping the garments of them that slew him. ^21And he said unto me, Depart: for I will send thee forth far hence unto the Gentiles. ^22And they gave him audience unto this word; and they lifted up their voice, and said, Away with such a fellow from the earth: for it is not fit that he should live. ^23And as they cried out, and threw off their garments, and cast dust into the air, ^24the chief captain commanded him be brought into the castle, bidding that he should be examined by scourging, that he might know for what cause they so shouted against him. ^25And when they had tied him up with the thongs, Paul said unto the centurion that stood by, Is it lawful for you to scourge a man that is a Roman, and uncondemned? ^26And when the centurion heard it, he went to the chief captain and told him, saying, What art thou about to do? for this man is a Roman. ^27And the chief captain came and said unto him, Tell me, art thou a Roman? And he said, Yea. ^28And the chief captain answered, With a great sum obtained I this citizenship. And Paul said, But I am a Roman born. ^29They then that were about to examine him straightway departed from him: and the chief captain also was afraid when he knew that he was a Roman, and because he had bound him. ^30But on the morrow, desiring to know the certainty wherefore he was accused of the Jews, he loosed him, and commanded the chief priests and all the council to come together, and brought Paul down and set him before them.

Acts 23

23

^1And Paul, looking stedfastly on the council, said, Brethren, I have lived before God in all good conscience until this day. ^2And the high priest Ananias commanded them that stood by him to smite him on the mouth. ^3Then said Paul unto him, God shall smite thee, thou whited wall: and sittest thou to judge me according to the law, and commandest me to be smitten contrary to the law? ^4And they that stood by said, Revilest thou God's high priest? ^5And Paul said, I knew not, brethren, that he was high priest: for it is written, Thou shalt not speak evil of a ruler of thy people. ^6But when Paul perceived that the one part were Sadducees and the other Pharisees, he cried out in the council, Brethren, I am a Pharisee, a son of Pharisees: touching the hope and resurrection of the dead I am called in question. ^7And when he had so said, there arose a dissension between the Pharisees and Sadducees; and the assembly was divided. ^8For the Sadducees say that there is no resurrection, neither angel, nor spirit; but the Pharisees confess both. ^9And there arose a great clamor: and some of the scribes of the Pharisees part stood up, and strove, saying, We find no evil in this man: and what if a spirit hath spoken to him, or an angel? ^10And when there arose a great dissension, the chief captain, fearing lest Paul should be torn in pieces by them, commanded the soldiers to go down and take him by force from among them, and bring him into the castle. ^11And the night following the Lord stood by him, and said, Be of good cheer: for as thou hast testified concerning me at Jerusalem, so must thou bear witness also at Rome. ^12And when it was day, the Jews banded together, and bound themselves under a curse, saying that they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed Paul. ^13And they were more than forty that made this conspiracy. ^14And they came to the chief priests and the elders, and said, We have bound ourselves under a great curse, to taste nothing until we have killed Paul. ^15Now therefore do ye with the council signify to the chief captain that he bring him down unto you, as though ye would judge of his case more exactly: and we, before he comes near, are ready to slay him. ^16But Paul's sister's son heard of their lying in wait, and he came and entered into the castle and told Paul. ^17And Paul called unto him one of the centurions, and said, Bring this young man unto the chief captain; for he hath something to tell him. ^18So he took him, and brought him to the chief captain, and saith, Paul the prisoner called me unto him, and asked me to bring this young man unto thee, who hath something to say to thee. ^19And the chief captain took him by the hand, and going aside asked him privately, What is it that thou hast to tell me? ^20And he said, The Jews have agreed to ask thee to bring down Paul tomorrow unto the council, as though thou wouldest inquire somewhat more exactly concerning him. ^21Do not thou therefore yield unto them: for there lie in wait for him of them more than forty men, who have bound themselves under a curse, neither to eat nor to drink till they have slain him: and now are they ready, looking for the promise from thee. ^22So the chief captain let the young man go, charging him, Tell no man that thou hast signified these things to me. ^23And he called unto him two of the centurions, and said, Make ready two hundred soldiers to go as far as Caesarea, and horsemen threescore and ten, and spearmen two hundred, at the third hour of the night: ^24and he bade them provide beasts, that they might set Paul thereon, and bring him safe unto Felix the governor. ^25And he wrote a letter after this form: ^26Claudius Lysias unto the most excellent governor Felix, greeting. ^27This man was seized by the Jews, and was about to be slain of them, when I came upon them with the soldiers and rescued him, having learned that he was a Roman. ^28And desiring to know the cause wherefore they accused him, I brought him down unto their council: ^29whom I found to be accused about questions of their law, but to have nothing laid to his charge worthy of death or of bonds. ^30And when it was shown to me that there would be a plot against the man, I sent him to thee forthwith, charging his accusers also to speak against him before thee. ^31So the soldiers, as it was commanded them, took Paul and brought him by night to Antipatris. ^32But on the morrow they left the horsemen to go with him, and returned to the castle: ^33and they, when they came to Caesarea and delivered the letter to the governor, presented Paul also before him. ^34And when he had read it, he asked of what province he was; and when he understood that he was of Cilicia, ^35I will hear thee fully, said he, when thine accusers also are come: and he commanded him to be kept in Herod's palace.

Acts 24

24

^1And after five days the high priest Ananias came down with certain elders, and with an orator, one Tertullus; and they informed the governor against Paul. ^2And when he was called, Tertullus began to accuse him, saying, Seeing that by thee we enjoy much peace, and that by the providence evils are corrected for this nation, ^3we accept it in all ways and in all places, most excellent Felix, with all thankfulness. ^4But, that I be not further tedious unto thee, I entreat thee to hear us of thy clemency a few words. ^5For we have found this man a pestilent fellow, and a mover of insurrections among all the Jews throughout the world, and a ringleader of the sect of the Nazarenes: ^6who moreover assayed to profane the temple: on whom also we laid hold: and we would have judged him according to our law. ^7But the chief captain Lysias came, and with great violence took him away out of our hands, ^8commanding his accusers to come before thee. from whom thou wilt be able, by examining him thyself, to take knowledge of all these things whereof we accuse him. ^9And the Jews also joined in the charge, affirming that these things were so. ^10And when the governor had beckoned unto him to speak, Paul answered, Forasmuch as I know that thou hast been of many years a judge unto this nation, I cheerfully make my defense: ^11Seeing that thou canst take knowledge that it is not more than twelve days since I went up to worship at Jerusalem: ^12and neither in the temple did they find me disputing with any man or stirring up a crowd, nor in the synagogues, nor in the city. ^13Neither can they prove to thee the things whereof they now accuse me. ^14But this I confess unto thee, that after the Way which they call a sect, so serve I the God of our fathers, believing all things which are according to the law, and which are written in the prophets; ^15having hope toward God, which these also themselves look for, that there shall be a resurrection both of the just and unjust. ^16Herein I also exercise myself to have a conscience void of offence toward God and men always. ^17Now after some years I came to bring alms to my nation, and offerings: ^18amidst which they found me purified in the temple, with no crowd, nor yet with tumult: but there were certain Jews from Asia-- ^19who ought to have been here before thee, and to make accusation, if they had aught against me. ^20Or else let these men themselves say what wrong-doing they found when I stood before the council, ^21except it be for this one voice, that I cried standing among them, Touching the resurrection of the dead I am called in question before you this day. ^22But Felix, having more exact knowledge concerning the Way, deferred them, saying, When Lysias the chief captain shall come down, I will determine your matter. ^23And he gave order to the centurion that he should be kept in charge, and should have indulgence; and not to forbid any of his friends to minister unto him. ^24But after certain days, Felix came with Drusilla, his wife, who was a Jewess, and sent for Paul, and heard him concerning the faith in Christ Jesus. ^25And as he reasoned of righteousness, and self-control, and the judgment to come, Felix was terrified, and answered, Go thy way for this time; and when I have a convenient season, I will call thee unto me. ^26He hoped withal that money would be given him of Paul: wherefore also he sent for him the oftener, and communed with him. ^27But when two years were fulfilled, Felix was succeeded by Porcius Festus; and desiring to gain favor with the Jews, Felix left Paul in bonds.

Acts 25

25

^1Festus therefore, having come into the province, after three days went up to Jerusalem from Caesarea. ^2And the chief priests and the principal men of the Jews informed him against Paul; and they besought him, ^3asking a favor against him, that he would send for him to Jerusalem; laying a plot to kill him on the way. ^4Howbeit Festus answered, that Paul was kept in charge at Caesarea, and that he himself was about to depart thither shortly. ^5Let them therefore, saith he, that are of power among you go down with me, and if there is anything amiss in the man, let them accuse him. ^6And when he had tarried among them not more than eight or ten days, he went down unto Caesarea; and on the morrow he sat on the judgment-seat, and commanded Paul to be brought. ^7And when he was come, the Jews that had come down from Jerusalem stood round about him, bringing against him many and grievous charges which they could not prove; ^8while Paul said in his defense, Neither against the law of the Jews, nor against the temple, nor against Caesar, have I sinned at all. ^9But Festus, desiring to gain favor with the Jews, answered Paul and said, Wilt thou go up to Jerusalem, and there be judged of these things before me? ^10But Paul said, I am standing before Caesar's judgment-seat, where I ought to be judged: to the Jews have I done no wrong, as thou also very well knowest. ^11If then I am a wrong-doer, and have committed anything worthy of death, I refuse not to die; but if none of those things is true whereof these accuse me, no man can give me up unto them. I appeal unto Caesar. ^12Then Festus, when he had conferred with the council, answered, Thou hast appealed unto Caesar: unto Caesar shalt thou go. ^13Now when certain days were passed, Agrippa the King and Bernice arrived at Caesarea, and saluted Festus. ^14And as they tarried there many days, Festus laid Paul's case before the King, saying, There is a certain man left a prisoner by Felix; ^15about whom, when I was at Jerusalem, the chief priests and the elders of the Jews informed me, asking for sentence against him. ^16To whom I answered, that it is not the custom of the Romans to give up any man, before that the accused have the accusers face to face, and have had opportunity to make his defense concerning the matter laid against him. ^17When therefore they were come together here, I made no delay, but on the next day sat on the judgment-seat, and commanded the man to be brought. ^18Concerning whom, when the accusers stood up, they brought no charge of such evil things as I supposed; ^19but had certain questions against him of their own religion, and of one Jesus, who was dead, whom Paul affirmed to be alive. ^20And I, being perplexed how to inquire concerning these things, asked whether he would go to Jerusalem and there be judged of these matters. ^21But when Paul had appealed to be kept for the decision of the emperor, I commanded him to be kept till I should send him to Caesar. ^22And Agrippa said unto Festus, I also could wish to hear the man myself. To-morrow, saith he, thou shalt hear him. ^23So on the morrow, when Agrippa was come, and Bernice, with great pomp, and they were entered into the place of hearing with the chief captains and principal men of the city, at the command of Festus Paul was brought in. ^24And Festus saith, King Agrippa, and all men who are here present with us, ye behold this man, about whom all the multitude of the Jews made suit to me, both at Jerusalem and here, crying that he ought not to live any longer. ^25But I found that he had committed nothing worthy of death: and as he himself appealed to the emperor I determined to send him. ^26Of whom I have no certain thing to write unto my lord. Wherefore I have brought him forth before you, and specially before thee, king Agrippa, that, after examination had, I may have somewhat to write. ^27For it seemeth to me unreasonable, in sending a prisoner, not withal to signify the charges against him.

Acts 26

26

^1And Agrippa said unto Paul, Thou art permitted to speak for thyself. Then Paul stretched forth his hand, and made his defence: ^2I think myself happy, king Agrippa, that I am to make my defense before thee this day touching all the things whereof I am accused by the Jews: ^3especially because thou art expert in all customs and questions which are among the Jews: wherefore I beseech thee to hear me patiently. ^4My manner of life then from my youth up, which was from the beginning among mine own nation and at Jerusalem, know all the Jews; ^5having knowledge of me from the first, if they be willing to testify, that after the straitest sect of our religion I lived a Pharisee. ^6And now I stand here to be judged for the hope of the promise made of God unto our fathers; ^7unto which promise our twelve tribes, earnestly serving God night and day, hope to attain. And concerning this hope I am accused by the Jews, O king! ^8Why is it judged incredible with you, if God doth raise the dead? ^9I verily thought with myself that I ought to do many things contrary to the name of Jesus of Nazareth. ^10And this I also did in Jerusalem: and I both shut up many of the saints in prisons, having received authority from the chief priests, and when they were put to death I gave my vote against them. ^11And punishing them oftentimes in all the synagogues, I strove to make them blaspheme; and being exceedingly mad against them, I persecuted them even unto foreign cities. ^12Whereupon as I journeyed to Damascus with the authority and commission of the chief priests, ^13at midday, O king, I saw on the way a light from heaven, above the brightness of the sun, shining round about me and them that journeyed with me. ^14And when we were all fallen to the earth, I heard a voice saying unto me in the Hebrew language, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? it is hard for thee to kick against the goad. ^15And I said, Who art thou, Lord? And the Lord said, I am Jesus whom thou persecutest. ^16But arise, and stand upon thy feet: for to this end have I appeared unto thee, to appoint thee a minister and a witness both of the things wherein thou hast seen me, and of the things wherein I will appear unto thee; ^17delivering thee from the people, and from the Gentiles, unto whom I send thee, ^18to open their eyes, that they may turn from darkness to light and from the power of Satan unto God, that they may receive remission of sins and an inheritance among them that are sanctified by faith in me. ^19Wherefore, O king Agrippa, I was not disobedient unto the heavenly vision: ^20but declared both to them of Damascus first and at Jerusalem, and throughout all the country of Judaea, and also to the Gentiles, that they should repent and turn to God, doing works worthy of repentance. ^21For this cause the Jews seized me in the temple, and assayed to kill me. ^22Having therefore obtained the help that is from God, I stand unto this day testifying both to small and great, saying nothing but what the prophets and Moses did say should come; ^23how that the Christ must suffer, and how that he first by the resurrection of the dead should proclaim light both to the people and to the Gentiles. ^24And as he thus made his defense, Festus saith with a loud voice, Paul, thou art mad; thy much learning is turning thee mad. ^25But Paul saith, I am not mad, most excellent Festus; but speak forth words of truth and soberness. ^26For the king knoweth of these things, unto whom also I speak freely: for I am persuaded that none of these things is hidden from him; for this hath not been done in a corner. ^27King Agrippa, believest thou the prophets? I know that thou believest. ^28And Agrippa said unto Paul, With but little persuasion thou wouldest fain make me a Christian. ^29And Paul said, I would to God, that whether with little or with much, not thou only, but also all that hear me this day, might become such as I am, except these bonds. ^30And the king rose up, and the governor, and Bernice, and they that sat with them: ^31and when they had withdrawn, they spake one to another, saying, This man doeth nothing worthy of death or of bonds. ^32And Agrippa said unto Festus, This man might have been set at liberty, if he had not appealed unto Caesar.

Acts 27

27

^1And when it was determined that we should sail for Italy, they delivered Paul and certain other prisoners to a centurion named Julius, of the Augustan band. ^2And embarking in a ship of Adramyttium, which was about to sail unto the places on the coast of Asia, we put to sea, Aristarchus, a Macedonian of Thessalonica, being with us. ^3And the next day we touched at Sidon: and Julius treated Paul kindly, and gave him leave to go unto his friends and refresh himself. ^4And putting to sea from thence, we sailed under the lee of Cyprus, because the winds were contrary. ^5And when we had sailed across the sea which is off Cilicia and Pamphylia, we came to Myra, a city of Lycia. ^6And there the centurion found a ship of Alexandria sailing for Italy; and he put us therein. ^7And when we had sailed slowly many days, and were come with difficulty over against Cnidus, the wind not further suffering us, we sailed under the lee of Crete, over against Salmone; ^8and with difficulty coasting along it we came unto a certain place called Fair Havens; nigh whereunto was the city of Lasea. ^9And when much time was spent, and the voyage was now dangerous, because the Fast was now already gone by, Paul admonished them, ^10and said unto them, Sirs, I perceive that the voyage will be with injury and much loss, not only of the lading and the ship, but also of our lives. ^11But the centurion gave more heed to the master and to the owner of the ship, than to those things which were spoken by Paul. ^12And because the haven was not commodious to winter in, the more part advised to put to sea from thence, if by any means they could reach Phoenix, and winter there; which is a haven of Crete, looking northeast and south-east. ^13And when the south wind blew softly, supposing that they had obtained their purpose, they weighed anchor and sailed along Crete, close in shore. ^14But after no long time there beat down from it a tempestuous wind, which is called Euraquilo: ^15and when the ship was caught, and could not face the wind, we gave way to it, and were driven. ^16And running under the lee of a small island called Cauda, we were able, with difficulty, to secure the boat: ^17and when they had hoisted it up, they used helps, under-girding the ship; and, fearing lest they should be cast upon the Syrtis, they lowered the gear, and so were driven. ^18And as we labored exceedingly with the storm, the next day they began to throw the the freight overboard; ^19and the third day they cast out with their own hands the tackling of the ship. ^20And when neither sun nor stars shone upon us for many days, and no small tempest lay on us, all hope that we should be saved was now taken away. ^21And when they had been long without food, then Paul stood forth in the midst of them, and said, Sirs, ye should have hearkened unto me, and not have set sail from Crete, and have gotten this injury and loss. ^22And now I exhort you to be of good cheer; for there shall be no loss of life among you, but only of the ship. ^23For there stood by me this night an angel of the God whose I am, whom also I serve, ^24saying, Fear not, Paul; thou must stand before Caesar: and lo, God hath granted thee all them that sail with thee. ^25Wherefore, sirs, be of good cheer: for I believe God, that it shall be even so as it hath been spoken unto me. ^26But we must be cast upon a certain island. ^27But when the fourteenth night was come, as we were driven to and fro in the sea of Adria, about midnight the sailors surmised that they were drawing near to some country: ^28and they sounded, and found twenty fathoms; and after a little space, they sounded again, and found fifteen fathoms. ^29And fearing lest haply we should be cast ashore on rocky ground, they let go four anchors from the stern, and wished for the day. ^30And as the sailors were seeking to flee out of the ship, and had lowered the boat into the sea, under color as though they would lay out anchors from the foreship, ^31Paul said to the centurion and to the soldiers, Except these abide in the ship, ye cannot be saved. ^32Then the soldiers cut away the ropes of the boat, and let her fall off. ^33And while the day was coming on, Paul besought them all to take some food, saying, This day is the fourteenth day that ye wait and continue fasting, having taken nothing. ^34Wherefore I beseech you to take some food: for this is for your safety: for there shall not a hair perish from the head of any of you. ^35And when he had said this, and had taken bread, he gave thanks to God in the presence of all; and he brake it, and began to eat. ^36Then were they all of good cheer, and themselves also took food. ^37And we were in all in the ship two hundred threescore and sixteen souls. ^38And when they had eaten enough, they lightened the ship, throwing out the wheat into the sea. ^39And when it was day, they knew not the land: but they perceived a certain bay with a beach, and they took counsel whether they could drive the ship upon it. ^40And casting off the anchors, they left them in the sea, at the same time loosing the bands of the rudders; and hoisting up the foresail to the wind, they made for the beach. ^41But lighting upon a place where two seas met, they ran the vessel aground; and the foreship struck and remained unmoveable, but the stern began to break up by the violence of the waves. ^42And the soldiers' counsel was to kill the prisoners, lest any of them should swim out, and escape. ^43But the centurion, desiring to save Paul, stayed them from their purpose; and commanded that they who could swim should cast themselves overboard, and get first to the land; ^44and the rest, some on planks, and some on other things from the ship. And so it came to pass, that they all escaped safe to the land.

Acts 28

28

^1And when we were escaped, then we knew that the island was called Melita. ^2And the barbarians showed us no common kindness; for they kindled a fire, and received us all, because of the present rain, and because of the cold. ^3But when Paul had gathered a bundle of sticks and laid them on the fire, a viper came out by reason of the heat, and fastened on his hand. ^4And when the barbarians saw the venomous creature hanging from his hand, they said one to another, No doubt this man is a murderer, whom, though he hath escaped from the sea, yet Justice hath not suffered to live. ^5Howbeit he shook off the creature into the fire, and took no harm. ^6But they expected that he would have swollen, or fallen down dead suddenly: but when they were long in expectation and beheld nothing amiss came to him, they changed their minds, and said that he was a god. ^7Now in the neighborhood of that place were lands belonging to the chief man of the island, named Publius, who received us, and entertained us three days courteously. ^8And it was so, that the father of Publius lay sick of fever and dysentery: unto whom Paul entered in, and prayed, and laying his hands on him healed him. ^9And when this was done, the rest also that had diseases in the island came, and were cured: ^10who also honored us with many honors; and when we sailed, they put on board such things as we needed. ^11And after three months we set sail in a ship of Alexandria which had wintered in the island, whose sign was The Twin Brothers. ^12And touching at Syracuse, we tarried there three days. ^13And from thence we made a circuit, and arrived at Rhegium: and after one day a south wind sprang up, and on the second day we came to Puteoli; ^14where we found brethren, and were entreated to tarry with them seven days: and so we came to Rome. ^15And from thence the brethren, when they heard of us, came to meet us as far as The Market of Appius and The Three Taverns; whom when Paul saw, he thanked God, and took courage. ^16And when we entered into Rome, Paul was suffered to abide by himself with the soldier that guarded him. ^17And it came to pass, that after three days he called together those that were the chief of the Jews: and when they were come together, he said unto them, I, brethren, though I had done nothing against the people, or the customs of our fathers, yet was delivered prisoner from Jerusalem into the hands of the Romans: ^18who, when they had examined me, desired to set me at liberty, because there was no cause of death in me. ^19But when the Jews spake against it, I was constrained to appeal unto Caesar; not that I had aught whereof to accuse my nation. ^20For this cause therefore did I entreat you to see and to speak with me: for because of the hope of Israel I am bound with this chain. ^21And they said unto him, We neither received letters from Judaea concerning thee, nor did any of the brethren come hither and report or speak any harm of thee. ^22But we desire to hear of thee what thou thinkest: for as concerning this sect, it is known to us that everywhere it is spoken against. ^23And when they had appointed him a day, they came to him into his lodging in great number; to whom he expounded the matter, testifying the kingdom of God, and persuading them concerning Jesus, both from the law of Moses and from the prophets, from morning till evening. ^24And some believed the things which were spoken, and some disbelieved. ^25And when they agreed not among themselves, they departed after that Paul had spoken one word, Well spake the Holy Spirit through Isaiah the prophet unto your fathers, ^26saying,

Go thou unto this people, and say,

By hearing ye shall hear, and shall in no wise understand;

And seeing ye shall see, and shall in no wise perceive:

^27For this people's heart is waxed gross,

And their ears are dull of hearing,

And their eyes they have closed;

Lest, haply they should perceive with their eyes,

And hear with their ears,

And understand with their heart,

And should turn again,

And I should heal them.

^28Be it known therefore unto you, that this salvation of God is sent unto the Gentiles: they will also hear. ^29And when he had said these words, the Jews departed, having much disputing among themselves. ^30And he abode two whole years in his own hired dwelling, and received all that went in unto him, ^31preaching the kingdom of God, and teaching the things concerning the Lord Jesus Christ with all boldness, none forbidding him.

Amos 2

2

^1Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Moab, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because he burned the bones of the king of Edom into lime: ^2but I will send a fire upon Moab, and it shall devour the palaces of Kerioth; and Moab shall die with tumult, with shouting, and with the sound of the trumpet; ^3and I will cut off the judge from the midst thereof, and will slay all the princes thereof with him, saith Jehovah. ^4Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Judah, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have rejected the law of Jehovah, and have not kept his statutes, and their lies have caused them to err, after which their fathers did walk: ^5but I will send a fire upon Judah, and it shall devour the palaces of Jerusalem. ^6Thus saith Jehovah: For three transgressions of Israel, yea, for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have sold the righteous for silver, and the needy for a pair of shoes- ^7they that pant after the dust of the earth on the head of the poor, and turn aside the way of the meek: and a man and his father go unto the same maiden, to profane my holy name: ^8and they lay themselves down beside every altar upon clothes taken in pledge; and in the house of their God they drink the wine of such as have been fined. ^9Yet destroyed I the Amorite before them, whose height was like the height of the cedars, and he was strong as the oaks; yet I destroyed his fruit from above, and his roots from beneath. ^10Also I brought you up out of the land of Egypt, and led you forty years in the wilderness, to possess the land of the Amorite. ^11And I raised up of your sons for prophets, and of your young men for Nazirites. Is it not even thus, O ye children of Israel? saith Jehovah. ^12But ye gave the Nazirites wine to drink, and commanded the prophets, saying, Prophesy not. ^13Behold, I will press you in your place, as a cart presseth that is full of sheaves. ^14And flight shall perish from the swift; and the strong shall not strengthen his force; neither shall the mighty deliver himself; ^15neither shall he stand that handleth the bow; and he that is swift of foot shall not deliver himself; neither shall he that rideth the horse deliver himself; ^16and he that is courageous among the mighty shall flee away naked in that day, saith Jehovah.

Amos 3

3

^1Hear this word that Jehovah hath spoken against you, O children of Israel, against the whole family which I brought up out of the land of Egypt, saying, ^2You only have I known of all the families of the earth: therefore I will visit upon you all your iniquities. ^3Shall two walk together, except they have agreed? ^4Will a lion roar in the forest, when he hath no prey? will a young lion cry out of his den, if he have taken nothing? ^5Can a bird fall in a snare upon the earth, where no gin is set for him? shall a snare spring up from the ground, and have taken nothing at all? ^6Shall the trumpet be blown in a city, and the people not be afraid? shall evil befall a city, and Jehovah hath not done it? ^7Surely the Lord Jehovah will do nothing, except he reveal his secret unto his servants the prophets. ^8The lion hath roared; who will not fear? The Lord Jehovah hath spoken; who can but prophesy? ^9Publish ye in the palaces at Ashdod, and in the palaces in the land of Egypt, and say, Assemble yourselves upon the mountains of Samaria, and behold what great tumults are therein, and what oppressions in the midst thereof. ^10For they know not to do right, saith Jehovah, who store up violence and robbery in their palaces. ^11Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: An adversary there shall be, even round about the land; and he shall bring down thy strength from thee, and thy palaces shall be plundered. ^12Thus saith Jehovah: As the shepherd rescueth out of the mouth of the lion two legs, or a piece of an ear, so shall the children of Israel be rescued that sit in Samaria in the corner of a couch, and on the silken cushions of a bed. ^13Hear ye, and testify against the house of Jacob, saith the Lord Jehovah, the God of hosts. ^14For in the day that I shall visit the transgressions of Israel upon him, I will also visit the altars of Beth-el; and the horns of the altar shall be cut off, and fall to the ground. ^15And I will smite the winter-house with the summer-house; and the houses of ivory shall perish, and the great houses shall have an end, saith Jehovah.

Amos 4

4

^1Hear this word, ye kine of Bashan, that are in the mountain of Samaria, that oppress the poor, that crush the needy, that say unto their lords, Bring, and let us drink. ^2The Lord Jehovah hath sworn by his holiness, that, lo, the days shall come upon you, that they shall take you away with hooks, and your residue with fish-hooks. ^3And ye shall go out at the breaches, every one straight before her; and ye shall cast yourselves into Harmon, saith Jehovah. ^4Come to Beth-el, and transgress; to Gilgal, and multiply transgression; and bring your sacrifices every morning, and your tithes every three days; ^5and offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving of that which is leavened, and proclaim freewill-offerings and publish them: for this pleaseth you, O ye children of Israel, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^6And I also have given you cleanness of teeth in all your cities, and want of bread in all your places; yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah. ^7And I also have withholden the rain from you, when there were yet three months to the harvest; and I caused it to rain upon one city, and caused it not to rain upon another city: one piece was rained upon, and the piece whereupon it rained not withered. ^8So two or three cities wandered unto one city to drink water, and were not satisfied: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah. ^9I have smitten you with blasting and mildew: the multitude of your gardens and your vineyards and your fig-trees and your olive-trees hath the palmer-worm devoured: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah. ^10I have sent among you the pestilence after the manner of Egypt: your young men have I slain with the sword, and have carried away your horses; and I have made the stench of your camp to come up even into your nostrils: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah. ^11I have overthrown cities among you, as when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah, and ye were as a brand plucked out of the burning: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith Jehovah. ^12Therefore thus will I do unto thee, O Israel; and because I will do this unto thee, prepare to meet thy God, O Israel. ^13For, lo, he that formeth the mountains, and createth the wind, and declareth unto man what is his thought; that maketh the morning darkness, and treadeth upon the high places of the Earth-jehovah, the God of hosts, is his name.

Amos 5

5

^1Hear ye this word which I take up for a lamentation over you, O house of Israel. ^2The virgin of Israel is fallen; she shall no more rise: she is cast down upon her land; there is none to raise her up. ^3For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: The city that went forth a thousand shall have a hundred left, and that which went forth a hundred shall have ten left, to the house of Israel. ^4For thus saith Jehovah unto the house of Israel, Seek ye me, and ye shall live; ^5but seek not Beth-el, nor enter into Gilgal, and pass not to Beer-sheba: for Gilgal shall surely go into captivity, and Beth-el shall come to nought. ^6Seek Jehovah, and ye shall live; lest he break out like fire in the house of Joseph, and it devour, and there be none to quench it in Beth-el. ^7Ye who turn justice to wormwood, and cast down righteousness to the earth, ^8seek him that maketh the Pleiades and Orion, and turneth the shadow of death into the morning, and maketh the day dark with night; that calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of the earth (Jehovah is his name); ^9that bringeth sudden destruction upon the strong, so that destruction cometh upon the fortress. ^10They hate him that reproveth in the gate, and they abhor him that speaketh uprightly. ^11Forasmuch therefore as ye trample upon the poor, and take exactions from him of wheat: ye have built houses of hewn stone, but ye shall not dwell in them; ye have planted pleasant vineyards, but ye shall not drink the wine thereof. ^12For I know how manifold are your transgressions, and how mighty are your sins-ye that afflict the just, that take a bribe, and that turn aside the needy in the gate from their right. ^13Therefore he that is prudent shall keep silence in such a time; for it is an evil time. ^14Seek good, and not evil, that ye may live; and so Jehovah, the God of hosts, will be with you, as ye say. ^15Hate the evil, and love the good, and establish justice in the gate: it may be that Jehovah, the God of hosts, will be gracious unto the remnant of Joseph. ^16Therefore thus saith Jehovah, the God of hosts, the Lord: Wailing shall be in all the broad ways; and they shall say in all the streets, Alas! Alas! and they shall call the husbandman to mourning, and such as are skilful in lamentation to wailing. ^17And in all vineyards shall be wailing; for I will pass through the midst of thee, saith Jehovah. ^18Woe unto you that desire the day of Jehovah! Wherefore would ye have the day of Jehovah? It is darkness, and not light. ^19As if a man did flee from a lion, and a bear met him; or went into the house and leaned his hand on the wall, and a serpent bit him. ^20Shall not the day of Jehovah be darkness, and not light? even very dark, and no brightness in it? ^21I hate, I despise your feasts, and I will take no delight in your solemn assemblies. ^22Yea, though ye offer me your burnt-offerings and meal-offerings, I will not accept them; neither will I regard the peace-offerings of your fat beasts. ^23Take thou away from me the noise of thy songs; for I will not hear the melody of thy viols. ^24But let justice roll down as waters, and righteousness as a mighty stream. ^25Did ye bring unto me sacrifices and offerings in the wilderness forty years, O house of Israel? ^26Yea, ye have borne the tabernacle of your king and the shrine of your images, the star of your god, which ye made to yourselves. ^27Therefore will I cause you to go into captivity beyond Damascus, saith Jehovah, whose name is the God of hosts.

Amos 6

6

^1Woe to them that are at ease in Zion, and to them that are secure in the mountain of Samaria, the notable men of the chief of the nations, to whom the house of Israel come! ^2Pass ye unto Calneh, and see; and from thence go ye to Hamath the great; then go down to Gath of the Philistines: are they better than these kingdoms? or is their border greater than your border? ^3-ye that put far away the evil day, and cause the seat of violence to come near; ^4that lie upon beds of ivory, and stretch themselves upon their couches, and eat the lambs out of the flock, and the calves out of the midst of the stall; ^5that sing idle songs to the sound of the viol; that invent for themselves instruments of music, like David; ^6that drink wine in bowls, and anoint themselves with the chief oils; but they are not grieved for the affliction of Joseph. ^7Therefore shall they now go captive with the first that go captive; and the revelry of them that stretched themselves shall pass away. ^8The Lord Jehovah hath sworn by himself, saith Jehovah, the God of hosts: I abhor the excellency of Jacob, and hate his palaces; therefore will I deliver up the city with all that is therein. ^9And it shall come to pass, if there remain ten men in one house, that they shall die. ^10And when a man's uncle shall take him up, even he that burneth him, to bring out the bones out of the house, and shall say unto him that is in the innermost parts of the house, Is there yet any with thee? and he shall say, No; then shall he say, Hold thy peace; for we may not make mention of the name of Jehovah. ^11For, behold, Jehovah commandeth, and the great house shall be smitten with breaches, and the little house with clefts. ^12Shall horses run upon the rock? will one plow there with oxen? that ye have turned justice into gall, and the fruit of righteousness into wormwood; ^13ye that rejoice in a thing of nought, that say, Have we not taken to us horns by our own strength? ^14For, behold, I will raise up against you a nation, O house of Israel, saith Jehovah, the God of hosts; and they shall afflict you from the entrance of Hamath unto the brook of the Arabah.

Amos 7

7

^1Thus the Lord Jehovah showed me: and, behold, he formed locusts in the beginning of the shooting up of the latter growth; and, lo, it was the latter growth after the king's mowings. ^2And it came to pass that, when they made an end of eating the grass of the land, then I said, O Lord Jehovah, forgive, I beseech thee: how shall Jacob stand? for he is small. ^3Jehovah repented concerning this: It shall not be, saith Jehovah. ^4Thus the Lord Jehovah showed me: and, behold, the Lord Jehovah called to content by fire; and it devoured the great deep, and would have eaten up the land. ^5Then said I, O Lord Jehovah, cease, I beseech thee: how shall Jacob stand? for he is small. ^6Jehovah repented concerning this: this also shall not be, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^7Thus he showed me: and, behold, the Lord stood beside a wall made by a plumb-line, with a plumb-line in his hand. ^8And Jehovah said unto me, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A plumb-line. Then said the Lord, Behold, I will set a plumb-line in the midst of my people Israel; I will not again pass by them any more; ^9and the high places of Isaac shall be desolate, and the sanctuaries of Israel shall be laid waste; and I will rise against the house of Jeroboam with the sword. ^10Then Amaziah the priest of Beth-el sent to Jeroboam king of Israel, saying, Amos hath conspired against thee in the midst of the house of Israel: the land is not able to bear all his words. ^11For thus Amos saith, Jeroboam shall die by the sword, and Israel shall surely be led away captive out of his land. ^12Also Amaziah said unto Amos, O thou seer, go, flee thou away into the land of Judah, and there eat bread, and prophesy there: ^13but prophesy not again any more at Beth-el; for it is the king's sanctuary, and it is a royal house. ^14Then answered Amos, and said to Amaziah, I was no prophet, neither was I a prophet's son; but I was a herdsman, and a dresser of sycomore-trees: ^15and Jehovah took me from following the flock, and Jehovah said unto me, Go, prophesy unto my people Israel. ^16Now therefore hear thou the word of Jehovah: Thou sayest, Prophesy not against Israel, and drop not thy word against the house of Isaac; ^17therefore thus saith Jehovah: Thy wife shall be a harlot in the city, and thy sons and thy daughters shall fall by the sword, and thy land shall be divided by line; and thou thyself shalt die in a land that is unclean, and Israel shall surely be led away captive out of his land.

Amos 8

8

^1Thus the Lord Jehovah showed me: and, behold, a basket of summer fruit. ^2And he said, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A basket of summer fruit. Then said Jehovah unto me, The end is come upon my people Israel; I will not again pass by them any more. ^3And the songs of the temple shall be wailings in that day, saith the Lord Jehovah: the dead bodies shall be many: in every place shall they cast them forth with silence. ^4Hear this, O ye that would swallow up the needy, and cause the poor of the land to fail, ^5saying, When will the new moon be gone, that we may sell grain? and the sabbath, that we may set forth wheat, making the ephah small, and the shekel great, and dealing falsely with balances of deceit; ^6that we may buy the poor for silver, and the needy for a pair of shoes, and sell the refuse of the wheat? ^7Jehovah hath sworn by the excellency of Jacob, Surely I will never forget any of their works. ^8Shall not the land tremble for this, and every one mourn that dwelleth therein? yea, it shall rise up wholly like the River; and it shall be troubled and sink again, like the River of Egypt. ^9And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord Jehovah, that I will cause the sun to go down at noon, and I will darken the earth in the clear day. ^10And I will turn your feasts into mourning, and all your songs into lamentation; and I will bring sackcloth upon all loins, and baldness upon every head; and I will make it as the mourning for an only son, and the end thereof as a bitter day. ^11Behold, the days come, saith the Lord Jehovah, that I will send a famine in the land, not a famine of bread, nor a thirst for water, but of hearing the words of Jehovah. ^12And they shall wander from sea to sea, and from the north even to the east; they shall run to and fro to seek the word of Jehovah, and shall not find it. ^13In that day shall the fair virgins and the young men faint for thirst. ^14They that swear by the sin of Samaria, and say, As thy god, O Dan, liveth; and, As the way of Beer-sheba liveth; they shall fall, and never rise up again.

Amos 9

9

^1I saw the Lord standing beside the altar: and he said, Smite the capitals, that the thresholds may shake; and break them in pieces on the head of all of them; and I will slay the last of them with the sword: there shall not one of them flee away, and there shall not one of them escape. ^2Though they dig into Sheol, thence shall my hand take them; and though they climb up to heaven, thence will I bring them down. ^3And though they hide themselves in the top of Carmel, I will search and take them out thence; and though they be hid from my sight in the bottom of the sea, thence will I command the serpent, and it shall bite them. ^4And though they go into captivity before their enemies, thence will I command the sword, and it shall slay them: and I will set mine eyes upon them for evil, and not for good. ^5For the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, is he that toucheth the land and it melteth, and all that dwell therein shall mourn; and it shall rise up wholly like the River, and shall sink again, like the River of Egypt; ^6it is he that buildeth his chambers in the heavens, and hath founded his vault upon the earth; he that calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of the earth; Jehovah is his name. ^7Are ye not as the children of the Ethiopians unto me, O children of Israel? saith Jehovah. Have not I brought up Israel out of the land of Egypt, and the Philistines from Caphtor, and the Syrians from Kir? ^8Behold, the eyes of the Lord Jehovah are upon the sinful kingdom, and I will destroy it from off the face of the earth; save that I will not utterly destroy the house of Jacob, saith Jehovah. ^9For, lo, I will command, and I will sift the house of Israel among all the nations, like as grain is sifted in a sieve, yet shall not the least kernel fall upon the earth. ^10All the sinners of my people shall die by the sword, who say, The evil shall not overtake nor meet us. ^11In that day will I raise up the tabernacle of David that is fallen, and close up the breaches thereof; and I will raise up its ruins, and I will build it as in the days of old; ^12that they may possess the remnant of Edom, and all the nations that are called by my name, saith Jehovah that doeth this. ^13Behold, the days come, saith Jehovah, that the plowman shall overtake the reaper, and the treader of grapes him that soweth seed; and the mountains shall drop sweet wine, and all the hills shall melt. ^14And I will bring back the captivity of my people Israel, and they shall build the waste cities, and inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and drink the wine thereof; they shall also make gardens, and eat the fruit of them. ^15And I will plant them upon their land, and they shall no more be plucked up out of their land which I have given them, saith Jehovah thy God.

Colossians 2

2

^1For I would have you know how greatly I strive for you, and for them at Laodicea, and for as many as have not seen my face in the flesh; ^2that their hearts may be comforted, they being knit together in love, and unto all riches of the full assurance of understanding, that they may know the mystery of God, even Christ, ^3in whom are all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge hidden. ^4This I say, that no one may delude you with persuasiveness of speech. ^5For though I am absent in the flesh, yet am I with you in the spirit, joying and beholding your order, and the stedfastness of your faith in Christ. ^6As therefore ye received Christ Jesus the Lord, so walk in him, ^7rooted and builded up in him, and established in your faith, even as ye were taught, abounding in thanksgiving. ^8Take heed lest there shall be any one that maketh spoil of you through his philosophy and vain deceit, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Christ: ^9for in him dwelleth all the fulness of the Godhead bodily, ^10and in him ye are made full, who is the head of all principality and power: ^11in whom ye were also circumcised with a circumcision not made with hands, in the putting off of the body of the flesh, in the circumcision of Christ; ^12having been buried with him in baptism, wherein ye were also raised with him through faith in the working of God, who raised him from the dead. ^13And you, being dead through your trespasses and the uncircumcision of your flesh, you, I say, did he make alive together with him, having forgiven us all our trespasses; ^14having blotted out the bond written in ordinances that was against us, which was contrary to us: and he hath taken it out that way, nailing it to the cross; ^15having despoiled the principalities and the powers, he made a show of them openly, triumphing over them in it. ^16Let no man therefore judge you in meat, or in drink, or in respect of a feast day or a new moon or a sabbath day: ^17which are a shadow of the things to come; but the body is Christ's. ^18Let no man rob you of your prize by a voluntary humility and worshipping of the angels, dwelling in the things which he hath seen, vainly puffed up by his fleshly mind, ^19and not holding fast the Head, from whom all the body, being supplied and knit together through the joints and bands, increasing with the increase of God. ^20If ye died with Christ from the rudiments of the world, why, as though living in the world, do ye subject yourselves to ordinances, ^21Handle not, nor taste, nor touch ^22(all which things are to perish with the using), after the precepts and doctrines of men? ^23Which things have indeed a show of wisdom in will-worship, and humility, and severity to the body; but are not of any value against the indulgence of the flesh.

Colossians 3

3

^1If then ye were raised together with Christ, seek the things that are above, where Christ is, seated on the right hand of God. ^2Set your mind on the things that are above, not on the things that are upon the earth. ^3For ye died, and your life is hid with Christ in God. ^4When Christ, who is our life, shall be manifested, then shall ye also with him be manifested in glory. ^5Put to death therefore your members which are upon the earth: fornication, uncleanness, passion, evil desire, and covetousness, which is idolatry; ^6for which things' sake cometh the wrath of God upon the sons of disobedience: ^7wherein ye also once walked, when ye lived in these things; ^8but now do ye also put them all away: anger, wrath, malice, railing, shameful speaking out of your mouth: ^9lie not one to another; seeing that ye have put off the old man with his doings, ^10and have put on the new man, that is being renewed unto knowledge after the image of him that created him: ^11where there cannot be Greek and Jew, circumcision and uncircumcision, barbarian, Scythian, bondman, freeman; but Christ is all, and in all. ^12Put on therefore, as God's elect, holy and beloved, a heart of compassion, kindness, lowliness, meekness, longsuffering; ^13forbearing one another, and forgiving each other, if any man have a complaint against any; even as the Lord forgave you, so also do ye: ^14and above all these things put on love, which is the bond of perfectness. ^15And let the peace of Christ rule in your hearts, to the which also ye were called in one body; and be ye thankful. ^16Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly; in all wisdom teaching and admonishing one another with psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing with grace in your hearts unto God. ^17And whatsoever ye do, in word or in deed, do all in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving thanks to God the Father through him. ^18Wives, be in subjection to your husbands, as is fitting in the Lord. ^19Husbands, love your wives, and be not bitter against them. ^20Children, obey your parents in all things, for this is well-pleasing in the Lord. ^21Fathers, provoke not your children, that they be not discouraged. ^22Servants, obey in all things them that are your masters according to the flesh; not with eye-service, as men-pleasers, but in singleness of heart, fearing the Lord: ^23whatsoever ye do, work heartily, as unto the Lord, and not unto men; ^24knowing that from the Lord ye shall receive the recompense of the inheritance: ye serve the Lord Christ. ^25For he that doeth wrong shall receive again for the wrong that he hath done: and there is no respect of persons.

Colossians 4

4

^1Masters, render unto your servants that which is just and equal; knowing that ye also have a Master in heaven. ^2Continue stedfastly in prayer, watching therein with thanksgiving; ^3withal praying for us also, that God may open unto us a door for the word, to speak the mystery of Christ, for which I am also in bonds; ^4that I may make it manifest, as I ought to speak. ^5Walk in wisdom toward them that are without, redeeming the time. ^6Let your speech be always with grace, seasoned with salt, that ye may know how ye ought to answer each one. ^7All my affairs shall Tychicus make known unto you, the beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow-servant in the Lord: ^8whom I have sent you for this very purpose, that ye may know our state, and that he may comfort your hearts; ^9together with Onesimus, the faithful and beloved brother, who is one of you. They shall make known unto you all things that are done here. ^10Aristarchus my fellow-prisoner saluteth you, and Mark, the cousin of Barnabas (touching whom ye received commandments; if he come unto you, receive him), ^11and Jesus that is called Justus, who are of the circumcision: these only are my fellow-workers unto the kingdom of God, men that have been a comfort unto me. ^12Epaphras, who is one of you, a servant of Christ Jesus, saluteth you, always striving for you in his prayers, that ye may stand perfect and fully assured in all the will of God. ^13For I bear him witness, that he hath much labor for you, and for them in Laodicea, and for them in Hierapolis. ^14Luke, the beloved physician, and Demas salute you. ^15Salute the brethren that are in Laodicea, and Nymphas, and the church that is in their house. ^16And when this epistle hath been read among you, cause that it be read also in the church of the Laodiceans; and that ye also read the epistle from Laodicea. ^17And say to Archippus, Take heed to the ministry which thou hast received in the Lord, that thou fulfil it. ^18The salutation of me Paul with mine own hand. Remember my bonds. Grace be with you.

Daniel 2

2

^1And in the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams; and his spirit was troubled, and his sleep went from him. ^2Then the king commanded to call the magicians, and the enchanters, and the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans, to tell the king his dreams. So they came in and stood before the king. ^3And the king said unto them, I have dreamed a dream, and my spirit is troubled to know the dream. ^4Then spake the Chaldeans to the king in the Syrian language, O king, live for ever: tell thy servants the dream, and we will show the interpretation. ^5The king answered and said to the Chaldeans, The thing is gone from me: if ye make not known unto me the dream and the interpretation thereof, ye shall be cut in pieces, and your houses shall be made a dunghill. ^6But if ye show the dream and the interpretation thereof, ye shall receive of me gifts and rewards and great honor: therefore show me the dream and the interpretation thereof. ^7They answered the second time and said, Let the king tell his servants the dream, and we will show the interpretation. ^8The king answered and said, I know of a certainty that ye would gain time, because ye see the thing is gone from me. ^9But if ye make not known unto me the dream, there is but one law for you; for ye have prepared lying and corrupt words to speak before me, till the time be changed: therefore tell me the dream, and I shall know that ye can show me the interpretation thereof. ^10The Chaldeans answered before the king, and said, There is not a man upon the earth that can show the king's matter, forasmuch as no king, lord, or ruler, hath asked such a thing of any magician, or enchanter, or Chaldean. ^11And it is a rare thing that the king requireth, and there is no other that can show it before the king, except the gods, whose dwelling is not with flesh. ^12For this cause the king was angry and very furious, and commanded to destroy all the wise men of Babylon. ^13So the decree went forth, and the wise men were to be slain; and they sought Daniel and his companions to be slain. ^14Then Daniel returned answer with counsel and prudence to Arioch the captain of the king's guard, who was gone forth to slay the wise men of Babylon; ^15he answered and said to Arioch the king's captain, Wherefore is the decree so urgent from the king? Then Arioch made the thing known to Daniel. ^16And Daniel went in, and desired of the king that he would appoint him a time, and he would show the king the interpretation. ^17Then Daniel went to his house, and made the thing known to Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, his companions: ^18that they would desire mercies of the God of heaven concerning this secret; that Daniel and his companions should not perish with the rest of the wise men of Babylon. ^19Then was the secret revealed unto Daniel in a vision of the night. Then Daniel blessed the God of heaven. ^20Daniel answered and said, Blessed be the name of God for ever and ever; for wisdom and might are his. ^21And he changeth the times and the seasons; he removeth kings, and setteth up kings; he giveth wisdom unto the wise, and knowledge to them that have understanding; ^22he revealeth the deep and secret things; he knoweth what is in the darkness, and the light dwelleth with him. ^23I thank thee, and praise thee, O thou God of my fathers, who hast given me wisdom and might, and hast now made known unto me what we desired of thee; for thou hast made known unto us the king's matter. ^24Therefore Daniel went in unto Arioch, whom the king had appointed to destroy the wise men of Babylon; he went and said thus unto him: Destroy not the wise men of Babylon; bring me in before the king, and I will show unto the king the interpretation. ^25Then Arioch brought in Daniel before the king in haste, and said thus unto him, I have found a man of the children of the captivity of Judah, that will make known unto the king the interpretation. ^26The king answered and said to Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, Art thou able to make known unto me the dream which I have seen, and the interpretation thereof? ^27Daniel answered before the king, and said, The secret which the king hath demanded can neither wise men, enchanters, magicians, nor soothsayers, show unto the king; ^28but there is a God in heaven that revealeth secrets, and he hath made known to the king Nebuchadnezzar what shall be in the latter days. Thy dream, and the visions of thy head upon thy bed, are these: ^29as for thee, O king, thy thoughts came into thy mind upon thy bed, what should come to pass hereafter; and he that revealeth secrets hath made known to thee what shall come to pass. ^30But as for me, this secret is not revealed to me for any wisdom that I have more than any living, but to the intent that the interpretation may be made known to the king, and that thou mayest know the thoughts of thy heart. ^31Thou, O king, sawest, and, behold, a great image. This image, which was mighty, and whose brightness was excellent, stood before thee; and the aspect thereof was terrible. ^32As for this image, its head was of fine gold, its breast and its arms of silver, its belly and its thighs of brass, ^33its legs of iron, its feet part of iron, and part of clay. ^34Thou sawest till that a stone was cut out without hands, which smote the image upon its feet that were of iron and clay, and brake them in pieces. ^35Then was the iron, the clay, the brass, the silver, and the gold, broken in pieces together, and became like the chaff of the summer threshing-floors; and the wind carried them away, so that no place was found for them: and the stone that smote the image became a great mountain, and filled the whole earth. ^36This is the dream; and we will tell the interpretation thereof before the king. ^37Thou, O king, art king of kings, unto whom the God of heaven hath given the kingdom, the power, and the strength, and the glory; ^38and wheresoever the children of men dwell, the beasts of the field and the birds of the heavens hath he given into thy hand, and hath made thee to rule over them all: thou art the head of gold. ^39And after thee shall arise another kingdom inferior to thee; and another third kingdom of brass, which shall bear rule over all the earth. ^40And the fourth kingdom shall be strong as iron, forasmuch as iron breaketh in pieces and subdueth all things; and as iron that crusheth all these, shall it break in pieces and crush. ^41And whereas thou sawest the feet and toes, part of potters' clay, and part of iron, it shall be a divided kingdom; but there shall be in it of the strength of the iron, forasmuch as thou sawest the iron mixed with miry clay. ^42And as the toes of the feet were part of iron, and part of clay, so the kingdom shall be partly strong, and partly broken. ^43And whereas thou sawest the iron mixed with miry clay, they shall mingle themselves with the seed of men; but they shall not cleave one to another, even as iron doth not mingle with clay. ^44And in the days of those kings shall the God of heaven set up a kingdom which shall never be destroyed, nor shall the sovereignty thereof be left to another people; but it shall break in pieces and consume all these kingdoms, and it shall stand for ever. ^45Forasmuch as thou sawest that a stone was cut out of the mountain without hands, and that it brake in pieces the iron, the brass, the clay, the silver, and the gold; the great God hath made known to the king what shall come to pass hereafter: and the dream is certain, and the interpretation thereof sure. ^46Then the king Nebuchadnezzar fell upon his face, and worshipped Daniel, and commanded that they should offer an oblation and sweet odors unto him. ^47The king answered unto Daniel, and said, Of a truth your God is the God of gods, and the Lord of kings, and a revealer of secrets, seeing thou hast been able to reveal this secret. ^48Then the king made Daniel great, and gave him many great gifts, and made him to rule over the whole province of Babylon, and to be chief governor over all the wise men of Babylon. ^49And Daniel requested of the king, and he appointed Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, over the affairs of the province of Babylon: but Daniel was in the gate of the king.

Daniel 3

3

^1Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height was threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof six cubits: he set it up in the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon. ^2Then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, to come to the dedication of the image which Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up. ^3Then the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, were gathered together unto the dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up; and they stood before the image that Nebuchadnezzar had set up. ^4Then the herald cried aloud, To you it is commanded, O peoples, nations, and languages, ^5that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, dulcimer, and all kinds of music, ye fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king hath set up; ^6and whoso falleth not down and worshippeth shall the same hour be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace. ^7Therefore at that time, when all the peoples heard the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and all kinds of music, all the peoples, the nations, and the languages, fell down and worshipped the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up. ^8Wherefore at that time certain Chaldeans came near, and brought accusation against the Jews. ^9They answered and said to Nebuchadnezzar the king, O king, live for ever. ^10Thou, O king, hast made a decree, that every man that shall hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of music, shall fall down and worship the golden image; ^11and whoso falleth not down and worshippeth, shall be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace. ^12There are certain Jews whom thou hast appointed over the affairs of the province of Babylon: Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego; these men, O king, have not regarded thee: they serve not thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up. ^13Then Nebuchadnezzar in his rage and fury commanded to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego. Then they brought these men before the king. ^14Nebuchadnezzar answered and said unto them, Is it of purpose, O Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, that ye serve not my god, nor worship the golden image which I have set up? ^15Now if ye be ready that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of music, ye fall down and worship the image which I have made, well: but if ye worship not, ye shall be cast the same hour into the midst of a burning fiery furnace; and who is that god that shall deliver you out of my hands? ^16Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego answered and said to the king, O Nebuchadnezzar, we have no need to answer thee in this matter. ^17If it be so, our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace; and he will deliver us out of thy hand, O king. ^18But if not, be it known unto thee, O king, that we will not serve thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up. ^19Then was Nebuchadnezzar full of fury, and the form of his visage was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego: therefore he spake, and commanded that they should heat the furnace seven times more than it was wont to be heated. ^20And he commanded certain mighty men that were in his army to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, and to cast them into the burning fiery furnace. ^21Then these men were bound in their hosen, their tunics, and their mantles, and their other garments, and were cast into the midst of the burning fiery furnace. ^22Therefore because the king's commandment was urgent, and the furnace exceeding hot, the flame of the fire slew those men that took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego. ^23And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, fell down bound into the midst of the burning fiery furnace. ^24Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was astonished, and rose up in haste: he spake and said unto his counsellors, Did not we cast three men bound into the midst of the fire? They answered and said unto the king, True, O king. ^25He answered and said, Lo, I see four men loose, walking in the midst of the fire, and they have no hurt; and the aspect of the fourth is like a son of the gods. ^26Then Nebuchadnezzar came near to the mouth of the burning fiery furnace: he spake and said, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, ye servants of the Most High God, come forth, and come hither. Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego came forth out of the midst of the fire. ^27And the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, and the king's counsellors, being gathered together, saw these men, that the fire had no power upon their bodies, nor was the hair of their head singed, neither were their hosen changed, nor had the smell of fire passed on them. ^28Nebuchadnezzar spake and said, Blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, who hath sent his angel, and delivered his servants that trusted in him, and have changed the king's word, and have yielded their bodies, that they might not serve nor worship any god, except their own God. ^29Therefore I make a decree, that every people, nation, and language, which speak anything amiss against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, shall be cut in pieces, and their houses shall be made a dunghill; because there is no other god that is able to deliver after this sort. ^30Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego in the province of Babylon.

Daniel 4

4

^1Nebuchadnezzar the king, unto all the peoples, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth: Peace be multiplied unto you. ^2It hath seemed good unto me to show the signs and wonders that the Most High God hath wrought toward me. ^3How great are his signs! and how mighty are his wonders! his kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and his dominion is from generation to generation. ^4I, Nebuchadnezzar, was at rest in my house, and flourishing in my palace. ^5I saw a dream which made me afraid; and the thoughts upon my bed and the visions of my head troubled me. ^6Therefore made I a decree to bring in all the wise men of Babylon before me, that they might make known unto me the interpretation of the dream. ^7Then came in the magicians, the enchanters, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers; and I told the dream before them; but they did not make known unto me the interpretation thereof. ^8But at the last Daniel came in before me, whose name was Belteshazzar, according to the name of my god, and in whom is the spirit of the holy gods: and I told the dream before him, saying, ^9O Belteshazzar, master of the magicians, because I know that the spirit of the holy gods is in thee, and no secret troubleth thee, tell me the visions of my dream that I have seen, and the interpretation thereof. ^10Thus were the visions of my head upon my bed: I saw, and, behold, a tree in the midst of the earth; and the height thereof was great. ^11The tree grew, and was strong, and the height thereof reached unto heaven, and the sight thereof to the end of all the earth. ^12The leaves thereof were fair, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was food for all: the beasts of the field had shadow under it, and the birds of the heavens dwelt in the branches thereof, and all flesh was fed from it. ^13I saw in the visions of my head upon my bed, and, behold, a watcher and a holy one came down from heaven. ^14He cried aloud, and said thus, Hew down the tree, and cut off its branches, shake off its leaves, and scatter its fruit: let the beasts get away from under it, and the fowls from its branches. ^15Nevertheless leave the stump of its roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be wet with the dew of heaven: and let his portion be with the beasts in the grass of the earth: ^16let his heart be changed from man's, and let a beast's heart be given unto him; and let seven times pass over him. ^17The sentence is by the decree of the watchers, and the demand by the word of the holy ones; to the intent that the living may know that the Most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will, and setteth up over it the lowest of men. ^18This dream I, king Nebuchadnezzar, have seen; and thou, O Belteshazzar, declare the interpretation, forasmuch as all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to make known unto me the interpretation; but thou art able; for the spirit of the holy gods is in thee. ^19Then Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, was stricken dumb for a while, and his thoughts troubled him. The king answered and said, Belteshazzar, let not the dream, or the interpretation, trouble thee. Belteshazzar answered and said, My lord, the dream be to them that hate thee, and the interpretation thereof to thine adversaries. ^20The tree that thou sawest, which grew, and was strong, whose height reached unto heaven, and the sight thereof to all the earth; ^21whose leaves were fair, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was food for all; under which the beasts of the field dwelt, and upon whose branches the birds of the heavens had their habitation: ^22it is thou, O king, that art grown and become strong; for thy greatness is grown, and reacheth unto heaven, and thy dominion to the end of the earth. ^23And whereas the king saw a watcher and a holy one coming down from heaven, and saying, Hew down the tree, and destroy it; nevertheless leave the stump of the roots thereof in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field, and let it be wet with the dew of heaven: and let his portion be with the beasts of the field, till seven times pass over him; ^24this is the interpretation, O king, and it is the decree of the Most High, which is come upon my lord the king: ^25that thou shalt be driven from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field, and thou shalt be made to eat grass as oxen, and shalt be wet with the dew of heaven, and seven times shall pass over thee; till thou know that the Most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will. ^26And whereas they commanded to leave the stump of the roots of the tree; thy kingdom shall be sure unto thee, after that thou shalt have known that the heavens do rule. ^27Wherefore, O king, let my counsel be acceptable unto thee, and break off thy sins by righteousness, and thine iniquities by showing mercy to the poor; if there may be a lengthening of thy tranquillity. ^28All this came upon the king Nebuchadnezzar. ^29At the end of twelve months he was walking in the royal palace of Babylon. ^30The king spake and said, Is not this great Babylon, which I have built for the royal dwelling-place, by the might of my power and for the glory of my majesty? ^31While the word was in the king's mouth, there fell a voice from heaven, saying, O king Nebuchadnezzar, to thee it is spoken: The kingdom is departed from thee: ^32and thou shalt be driven from men; and they dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field; thou shalt be made to eat grass as oxen; and seven times shall pass over thee; until thou know that the Most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will. ^33The same hour was the thing fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar: and he was driven from men, and did eat grass as oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven, till his hair was grown like eagles' feathers, and his nails like birds' claws. ^34And at the end of the days I, Nebuchadnezzar, lifted up mine eyes unto heaven, and mine understanding returned unto me, and I blessed the Most High, and I praised and honored him that liveth for ever; for his dominion is an everlasting dominion, and his kingdom from generation to generation. ^35And all the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing; and he doeth according to his will in the army of heaven, and among the inhabitants of the earth; and none can stay his hand, or say unto him, What doest thou? ^36At the same time mine understanding returned unto me; and for the glory of my kingdom, my majesty and brightness returned unto me; and my counsellors and my lords sought unto me; and I was established in my kingdom, and excellent greatness was added unto me. ^37Now I, Nebuchadnezzar, praise and extol and honor the King of heaven; for all his works are truth, and his ways justice; and those that walk in pride he is able to abase.

Daniel 5

5

^1Belshazzar the king made a great feast to a thousand of his lords, and drank wine before the thousand. ^2Belshazzar, while he tasted the wine, commanded to bring the golden and silver vessels which Nebuchadnezzar his father had taken out of the temple which was in Jerusalem; that the king and his lords, his wives and his concubines, might drink therefrom. ^3Then they brought the golden vessels that were taken out of the temple of the house of God which was at Jerusalem; and the king and his lords, his wives and his concubines, drank from them. ^4They drank wine, and praised the gods of gold, and of silver, of brass, of iron, of wood, and of stone. ^5In the same hour came forth the fingers of a man's hand, and wrote over against the candlestick upon the plaster of the wall of the king's palace: and the king saw the part of the hand that wrote. ^6Then the king's countenance was changed in him, and his thoughts troubled him; and the joints of his loins were loosed, and his knees smote one against another. ^7The king cried aloud to bring in the enchanters, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers. The king spake and said to the wise men of Babylon, Whosoever shall read this writing, and show me the interpretation thereof, shall be clothed with purple, and have a chain of gold about his neck, and shall be the third ruler in the kingdom. ^8Then came in all the king's wise men; but they could not read the writing, nor make known to the king the interpretation. ^9Then was king Belshazzar greatly troubled, and his countenance was changed in him, and his lords were perplexed. ^10Now the queen by reason of the words of the king and his lords came into the banquet house: the queen spake and said, O king, live forever; let not thy thoughts trouble thee, nor let thy countenance be changed. ^11There is a man in thy kingdom, in whom is the spirit of the holy gods; and in the days of thy father light and understanding and wisdom, like the wisdom of the gods, were found in him; and the king Nebuchadnezzar thy father, the king, I say, thy father, made him master of the magicians, enchanters, Chaldeans, and soothsayers; ^12forasmuch as an excellent spirit, and knowledge, and understanding, interpreting of dreams, and showing of dark sentences, and dissolving of doubts, were found in the same Daniel, whom the king named Belteshazzar. Now let Daniel be called, and he will show the interpretation. ^13Then was Daniel brought in before the king. The king spake and said unto Daniel, Art thou that Daniel, who art of the children of the captivity of Judah, whom the king my father brought out of Judah? ^14I have heard of thee, that the spirit of the gods is in thee, and that light and understanding and excellent wisdom are found in thee. ^15And now the wise men, the enchanters, have been brought in before me, that they should read this writing, and make known unto me the interpretation thereof; but they could not show the interpretation of the thing. ^16But I have heard of thee, that thou canst give interpretations, and dissolve doubts; now if thou canst read the writing, and make known to me the interpretation thereof, thou shalt be clothed with purple, and have a chain of gold about thy neck, and shalt be the third ruler in the kingdom. ^17Then Daniel answered and said before the king, Let thy gifts be to thyself, and give thy rewards to another; nevertheless I will read the writing unto the king, and make known to him the interpretation. ^18O thou king, the Most High God gave Nebuchadnezzar thy father the kingdom, and greatness, and glory, and majesty: ^19and because of the greatness that he gave him, all the peoples, nations, and languages trembled and feared before him: whom he would he slew, and whom he would he kept alive; and whom he would he raised up, and whom he would he put down. ^20But when his heart was lifted up, and his spirit was hardened so that he dealt proudly, he was deposed from his kingly throne, and they took his glory from him: ^21and he was driven from the sons of men, and his heart was made like the beasts', and his dwelling was with the wild asses; he was fed with grass like oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven; until he knew that the Most High God ruleth in the kingdom of men, and that he setteth up over it whomsoever he will. ^22And thou his son, O Belshazzar, hast not humbled thy heart, though thou knewest all this, ^23but hast lifted up thyself against the Lord of heaven; and they have brought the vessels of his house before thee, and thou and thy lords, thy wives and thy concubines, have drunk wine from them; and thou hast praised the gods of silver and gold, of brass, iron, wood, and stone, which see not, nor hear, nor know; and the God in whose hand thy breath is, and whose are all thy ways, hast thou not glorified. ^24Then was the part of the hand sent from before him, and this writing was inscribed. ^25And this is the writing that was inscribed: MENE, MENE, TEKEL, UPHARSIN. ^26This is the interpretation of the thing: MENE; God hath numbered thy kingdom, and brought it to an end; ^27TEKEL; thou art weighed in the balances, and art found wanting. ^28PERES; thy kingdom is divided, and given to the Medes and Persians. ^29Then commanded Belshazzar, and they clothed Daniel with purple, and put a chain of gold about his neck, and made proclamation concerning him, that he should be the third ruler in the kingdom. ^30In that night Belshazzar the Chaldean King was slain. ^31And Darius the Mede received the kingdom, being about threescore and two years old.

Daniel 6

6

^1It pleased Darius to set over the kingdom a hundred and twenty satraps, who should be throughout the whole kingdom; ^2and over them three presidents, of whom Daniel was one; that these satraps might give account unto them, and that the king should have no damage. ^3Then this Daniel was distinguished above the presidents and the satraps, because an excellent spirit was in him; and the king thought to set him over the whole realm. ^4Then the presidents and the satraps sought to find occasion against Daniel as touching the kingdom; but they could find no occasion nor fault, forasmuch as he was faithful, neither was there any error or fault found in him. ^5Then said these men, We shall not find any occasion against this Daniel, except we find it against him concerning the law of his God. ^6Then these presidents and satraps assembled together to the king, and said thus unto him, King Darius, live for ever. ^7All the presidents of the kingdom, the deputies and the satraps, the counsellors and the governors, have consulted together to establish a royal statute, and to make a strong interdict, that whosoever shall ask a petition of any god or man for thirty days, save of thee, O king, he shall be cast into the den of lions. ^8Now, O king, establish the interdict, and sign the writing, that it be not changed, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which altereth not. ^9Wherefore king Darius signed the writing and the interdict. ^10And when Daniel knew that the writing was signed, he went into his house (now his windows were open in his chamber toward Jerusalem) and he kneeled upon his knees three times a day, and prayed, and gave thanks before his God, as he did aforetime. ^11Then these men assembled together, and found Daniel making petition and supplication before his God. ^12Then they came near, and spake before the king concerning the king's interdict: Hast thou not signed an interdict, that every man that shall make petition unto any god or man within thirty days, save unto thee, O king, shall be cast into the den of lions? The king answered and said, The thing is true, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which altereth not. ^13Then answered they and said before the king, That Daniel, who is of the children of the captivity of Judah, regardeth not thee, O king, nor the interdict that thou hast signed, but maketh his petition three times a day. ^14Then the king, when he heard these words, was sore displeased, and set his heart on Daniel to deliver him; and he labored till the going down of the sun to rescue him. ^15Then these men assembled together unto the king, and said unto the king, Know, O king, that it is a law of the Medes and Persians, that no interdict nor statute which the king establisheth may be changed. ^16Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel, and cast him into the den of lions. Now the king spake and said unto Daniel, Thy God whom thou servest continually, he will deliver thee. ^17And a stone was brought, and laid upon the mouth of the den; and the king sealed it with his own signet, and with the signet of his lords; that nothing might be changed concerning Daniel. ^18Then the king went to his palace, and passed the night fasting; neither were instruments of music brought before him: and his sleep fled from him. ^19Then the king arose very early in the morning, and went in haste unto the den of lions. ^20And when he came near unto the den to Daniel, he cried with a lamentable voice; the king spake and said to Daniel, O Daniel, servant of the living God, is thy God, whom thou servest continually, able to deliver thee from the lions? ^21Then said Daniel unto the king, O king, live for ever. ^22My God hath sent his angel, and hath shut the lions' mouths, and they have not hurt me; forasmuch as before him innocency was found in me; and also before thee, O king, have I done no hurt. ^23Then was the king exceeding glad, and commanded that they should take Daniel up out of the den. So Daniel was taken up out of the den, and no manner of hurt was found upon him, because he had trusted in his God. ^24And the king commanded, and they brought those men that had accused Daniel, and they cast them into the den of lions, them, their children, and their wives; and the lions had the mastery of them, and brake all their bones in pieces, before they came to the bottom of the den. ^25Then king Darius wrote unto all the peoples, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth: Peace be multiplied unto you. ^26I make a decree, that in all the dominion of my kingdom men tremble and fear before the God of Daniel; for he is the living God, and stedfast for ever, And his kingdom that which shall not be destroyed; and his dominion shall be even unto the end. ^27He delivereth and rescueth, and he worketh signs and wonders in heaven and in earth, who hath delivered Daniel from the power of the lions. ^28So this Daniel prospered in the reign of Darius, and in the reign of Cyrus the Persian.

Daniel 7

7

^1In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon Daniel had a dream and visions of his head upon his bed: then he wrote the dream and told the sum of the matters. ^2Daniel spake and said, I saw in my vision by night, and, behold, the four winds of heaven brake forth upon the great sea. ^3And four great beasts came up from the sea, diverse one from another. ^4The first was like a lion, and had eagle's wings: I beheld till the wings thereof were plucked, and it was lifted up from the earth, and made to stand upon two feet as a man; and a man's heart was given to it. ^5And, behold, another beast, a second, like to a bear; and it was raised up on one side, and three ribs were in its mouth between its teeth: and they said thus unto it, Arise, devour much flesh. ^6After this I beheld, and, lo, another, like a leopard, which had upon its back four wings of a bird; the beast had also four heads; and dominion was given to it. ^7After this I saw in the night-visions, and, behold, a fourth beast, terrible and powerful, and strong exceedingly; and it had great iron teeth; it devoured and brake in pieces, and stamped the residue with its feet: and it was diverse from all the beasts that were before it; and it had ten horns. ^8I considered the horns, and, behold, there came up among them another horn, a little one, before which three of the first horns were plucked up by the roots: and, behold, in this horn were eyes like the eyes of a man, and a mouth speaking great things. ^9I beheld till thrones were placed, and one that was ancient of days did sit: his raiment was white as snow, and the hair of his head like pure wool; his throne was fiery flames, and the wheels thereof burning fire. ^10A fiery stream issued and came forth from before him: thousands of thousands ministered unto him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him: the judgment was set, and the books were opened. ^11I beheld at that time because of the voice of the great words which the horn spake; I beheld even till the beast was slain, and its body destroyed, and it was given to be burned with fire. ^12And as for the rest of the beasts, their dominion was taken away: yet their lives were prolonged for a season and a time. ^13I saw in the night-visions, and, behold, there came with the clouds of heaven one like unto a son of man, and he came even to the ancient of days, and they brought him near before him. ^14And there was given him dominion, and glory, and a kingdom, that all the peoples, nations, and languages should serve him: his dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away, and his kingdom that which shall not be destroyed. ^15As for me, Daniel, my spirit was grieved in the midst of my body, and the visions of my head troubled me. ^16I came near unto one of them that stood by, and asked him the truth concerning all this. So he told me, and made me know the interpretation of the things. ^17These great beasts, which are four, are four kings, that shall arise out of the earth. ^18But the saints of the Most High shall receive the kingdom, and possess the kingdom for ever, even for ever and ever. ^19Then I desired to know the truth concerning the fourth beast, which was diverse from all of them, exceeding terrible, whose teeth were of iron, and its nails of brass; which devoured, brake in pieces, and stamped the residue with its feet; ^20and concerning the ten horns that were on its head, and the other horn which came up, and before which three fell, even that horn that had eyes, and a mouth that spake great things, whose look was more stout than its fellows. ^21I beheld, and the same horn made war with the saints, and prevailed against them; ^22until the ancient of days came, and judgment was given to the saints of the Most High, and the time came that the saints possessed the kingdom. ^23Thus he said, The fourth beast shall be a fourth kingdom upon earth, which shall be diverse from all the kingdoms, and shall devour the whole earth, and shall tread it down, and break it in pieces. ^24And as for the ten horns, out of this kingdom shall ten kings arise: and another shall arise after them; and he shall be diverse from the former, and he shall put down three kings. ^25And he shall speak words against the Most High, and shall wear out the saints of the Most High; and he shall think to change the times and the law; and they shall be given into his hand until a time and times and half a time. ^26But the judgment shall be set, and they shall take away his dominion, to consume and to destroy it unto the end. ^27And the kingdom and the dominion, and the greatness of the kingdoms under the whole heaven, shall be given to the people of the saints of the Most High: his kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and all dominions shall serve and obey him. ^28Here is the end of the matter. As for me, Daniel, my thoughts much troubled me, and my countenance was changed in me: but I kept the matter in my heart.

Daniel 8

8

^1In the third year of the reign of king Belshazzar a vision appeared unto me, even unto me, Daniel, after that which appeared unto me at the first. ^2And I saw in the vision; now it was so, that when I saw, I was in Shushan the palace, which is in the province of Elam; and I saw in the vision, and I was by the river Ulai. ^3Then I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and, behold, there stood before the river a ram which had two horns: and the two horns were high; but one was higher than the other, and the higher came up last. ^4I saw the ram pushing westward, and northward, and southward; and no beasts could stand before him, neither was there any that could deliver out of his hand; but he did according to his will, and magnified himself. ^5And as I was considering, behold, a he-goat came from the west over the face of the whole earth, and touched not the ground: and the goat had a notable horn between his eyes. ^6And he came to the ram that had the two horns, which I saw standing before the river, and ran upon him in the fury of his power. ^7And I saw him come close unto the ram, and he was moved with anger against him, and smote the ram, and brake his two horns; and there was no power in the ram to stand before him; but he cast him down to the ground, and trampled upon him; and there was none that could deliver the ram out of his hand. ^8And the he-goat magnified himself exceedingly: and when he was strong, the great horn was broken; and instead of it there came up four notable horns toward the four winds of heaven. ^9And out of one of them came forth a little horn, which waxed exceeding great, toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the glorious land. ^10And it waxed great, even to the host of heaven; and some of the host and of the stars it cast down to the ground, and trampled upon them. ^11Yea, it magnified itself, even to the prince of the host; and it took away from him the continual burnt-offering, and the place of his sanctuary was cast down. ^12And the host was given over to it together with the continual burnt-offering through transgression; and it cast down truth to the ground, and it did its pleasure and prospered. ^13Then I heard a holy one speaking; and another holy one said unto that certain one who spake, How long shall be the vision concerning the continual burnt-offering, and the transgression that maketh desolate, to give both the sanctuary and the host to be trodden under foot? ^14And he said unto me, Unto two thousand and three hundred evenings and mornings; then shall the sanctuary be cleansed. ^15And it came to pass, when I, even I Daniel, had seen the vision, that I sought to understand it; and, behold, there stood before me as the appearance of a man. ^16And I heard a man's voice between the banks of the Ulai, which called, and said, Gabriel, make this man to understand the vision. ^17So he came near where I stood; and when he came, I was affrighted, and fell upon my face: but he said unto me, Understand, O son of man; for the vision belongeth to the time of the end. ^18Now as he was speaking with me, I fell into a deep sleep with my face toward the ground; but he touched me, and set me upright. ^19And he said, Behold, I will make thee know what shall be in the latter time of the indignation; for it belongeth to the appointed time of the end. ^20The ram which thou sawest, that had the two horns, they are the kings of Media and Persia. ^21And the rough he-goat is the king of Greece: and the great horn that is between his eyes is the first king. ^22And as for that which was broken, in the place whereof four stood up, four kingdoms shall stand up out of the nation, but not with his power. ^23And in the latter time of their kingdom, when the transgressors are come to the full, a king of fierce countenance, and understanding dark sentences, shall stand up. ^24And his power shall be mighty, but not by his own power; and he shall destroy wonderfully, and shall prosper and do his pleasure; and he shall destroy the mighty ones and the holy people. ^25And through his policy he shall cause craft to prosper in his hand; and he shall magnify himself in his heart, and in their security shall he destroy many: he shall also stand up against the prince of princes; but he shall be broken without hand. ^26And the vision of the evenings and mornings which hath been told is true: but shut thou up the vision; for it belongeth to many days to come. ^27And I, Daniel, fainted, and was sick certain days; then I rose up, and did the king's business: and I wondered at the vision, but none understood it.

Daniel 9

9

^1In the first year of Darius the son of Ahasuerus, of the seed of the Medes, who was made king over the realm of the Chaldeans, ^2in the first year of his reign I, Daniel, understood by the books the number of the years whereof the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah the prophet, for the accomplishing of the desolations of Jerusalem, even seventy years. ^3And I set my face unto the Lord God, to seek by prayer and supplications, with fasting and sackcloth and ashes. ^4And I prayed unto Jehovah my God, and made confession, and said, Oh, Lord, the great and dreadful God, who keepeth covenant and lovingkindness with them that love him and keep his commandments, ^5we have sinned, and have dealt perversely, and have done wickedly, and have rebelled, even turning aside from thy precepts and from thine ordinances; ^6neither have we hearkened unto thy servants the prophets, that spake in thy name to our kings, our princes, and our fathers, and to all the people of the land. ^7O Lord, righteousness belongeth unto thee, but unto us confusion of face, as at this day; to the men of Judah, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and unto all Israel, that are near, and that are far off, through all the countries whither thou hast driven them, because of their trespass that they have trespassed against thee. ^8O Lord, to us belongeth confusion of face, to our kings, to our princes, and to our fathers, because we have sinned against thee. ^9To the Lord our God belong mercies and forgiveness; for we have rebelled against him; ^10neither have we obeyed the voice of Jehovah our God, to walk in his laws, which he set before us by his servants the prophets. ^11Yea, all Israel have transgressed thy law, even turning aside, that they should not obey thy voice: therefore hath the curse been poured out upon us, and the oath that is written in the law of Moses the servant of God; for we have sinned against him. ^12And he hath confirmed his words, which he spake against us, and against our judges that judged us, by bringing upon us a great evil; for under the whole heaven hath not been done as hath been done upon Jerusalem. ^13As it is written in the law of Moses, all this evil is come upon us: yet have we not entreated the favor of Jehovah our God, that we should turn from our iniquities, and have discernment in thy truth. ^14Therefore hath Jehovah watched over the evil, and brought it upon us; for Jehovah our God is righteous in all his works which he doeth, and we have not obeyed his voice. ^15And now, O Lord our God, that hast brought thy people forth out of the land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and hast gotten thee renown, as at this day; we have sinned, we have done wickedly. ^16O Lord, according to all thy righteousness, let thine anger and thy wrath, I pray thee, be turned away from thy city Jerusalem, thy holy mountain; because for our sins, and for the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and thy people are become a reproach to all that are round about us. ^17Now therefore, O our God, hearken unto the prayer of thy servant, and to his supplications, and cause thy face to shine upon thy sanctuary that is desolate, for the Lord's sake. ^18O my God, incline thine ear, and hear; open thine eyes, and behold our desolations, and the city which is called by thy name: for we do not present our supplications before thee for our righteousness, but for thy great mercies' sake. ^19O Lord, hear; O Lord, forgive; O Lord, hearken and do; defer not, for thine own sake, O my God, because thy city and thy people are called by thy name. ^20And while I was speaking, and praying, and confessing my sin and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my supplication before Jehovah my God for the holy mountain of my God; ^21yea, while I was speaking in prayer, the man Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, being caused to fly swiftly, touched me about the time of the evening oblation. ^22And he instructed me, and talked with me, and said, O Daniel, I am now come forth to give thee wisdom and understanding. ^23At the beginning of thy supplications the commandment went forth, and I am come to tell thee; for thou art greatly beloved: therefore consider the matter, and understand the vision. ^24Seventy weeks are decreed upon thy people and upon thy holy city, to finish transgression, and to make an end of sins, and to make reconciliation for iniquity, and to bring in everlasting righteousness, and to seal up vision and prophecy, and to anoint the most holy. ^25Know therefore and discern, that from the going forth of the commandment to restore and to build Jerusalem unto the anointed one, the prince, shall be seven weeks, and threescore and two weeks: it shall be built again, with street and moat, even in troublous times. ^26And after the threescore and two weeks shall the anointed one be cut off, and shall have nothing: and the people of the prince that shall come shall destroy the city and the sanctuary; and the end thereof shall be with a flood, and even unto the end shall be war; desolations are determined. ^27And he shall make a firm covenant with many for one week: and in the midst of the week he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease; and upon the wing of abominations shall come one that maketh desolate; and even unto the full end, and that determined, shall wrath be poured out upon the desolate.

Daniel 10

10

^1In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a thing was revealed unto Daniel, whose name was called Belteshazzar; and the thing was true, even a great warfare: and he understood the thing, and had understanding of the vision. ^2In those days I, Daniel, was mourning three whole weeks. ^3I ate no pleasant bread, neither came flesh nor wine into my mouth, neither did I anoint myself at all, till three whole weeks were fulfilled. ^4And in the four and twentieth day of the first month, as I was by the side of the great river, which is Hiddekel, ^5I lifted up mine eyes, and looked, and, behold, a man clothed in linen, whose loins were girded with pure gold of Uphaz: ^6his body also was like the beryl, and his face as the appearance of lightning, and his eyes as flaming torches, and his arms and his feet like unto burnished brass, and the voice of his words like the voice of a multitude. ^7And I, Daniel, alone saw the vision; for the men that were with me saw not the vision; but a great quaking fell upon them, and they fled to hide themselves. ^8So I was left alone, and saw this great vision, and there remained no strength in me; for my comeliness was turned in me into corruption, and I retained no strength. ^9Yet heard I the voice of his words; and when I heard the voice of his words, then was I fallen into a deep sleep on my face, with my face toward the ground. ^10And, behold, a hand touched me, which set me upon my knees and upon the palms of my hands. ^11And he said unto me, O Daniel, thou man greatly beloved, understand the words that I speak unto thee, and stand upright; for unto thee am I now sent. And when he had spoken this word unto me, I stood trembling. ^12Then said he unto me, Fear not, Daniel; for from the first day that thou didst set thy heart to understand, and to humble thyself before thy God, thy words were heard: and I am come for thy words' sake. ^13But the prince of the kingdom of Persia withstood me one and twenty days; but, lo, Michael, one of the chief princes, came to help me: and I remained there with the kings of Persia. ^14Now I am come to make thee understand what shall befall thy people in the latter days; for the vision is yet for many days: ^15and when he had spoken unto me according to these words, I set my face toward the ground, and was dumb. ^16And, behold, one in the likeness of the sons of men touched my lips: then I opened my mouth, and spake and said unto him that stood before me, O my lord, by reason of the vision my sorrows are turned upon me, and I retain no strength. ^17For how can the servant of this my lord talk with this my lord? for as for me, straightway there remained no strength in me, neither was there breath left in me. ^18Then there touched me again one like the appearance of a man, and he strengthened me. ^19And he said, O man greatly beloved, fear not: peace be unto thee, be strong, yea, be strong. And when he spake unto me, I was strengthened, and said, Let my lord speak; for thou hast strengthened me. ^20Then said he, Knowest thou wherefore I am come unto thee? and now will I return to fight with the prince of Persia: and when I go forth, lo, the prince of Greece shall come. ^21But I will tell thee that which is inscribed in the writing of truth: and there is none that holdeth with me against these, but Michael your prince.

Daniel 11

11

^1And as for me, in the first year of Darius the Mede, I stood up to confirm and strengthen him. ^2And now will I show thee the truth. Behold, there shall stand up yet three kings in Persia; and the fourth shall be far richer than they all: and when he is waxed strong through his riches, he shall stir up all against the realm of Greece. ^3And a mighty king shall stand up, that shall rule with great dominion, and do according to his will. ^4And when he shall stand up, his kingdom shall be broken, and shall be divided toward the four winds of heaven, but not to his posterity, nor according to his dominion wherewith he ruled; for his kingdom shall be plucked up, even for others besides these. ^5And the king of the south shall be strong, and one of his princes; and he shall be strong above him, and have dominion; his dominion shall be a great dominion. ^6And at the end of years they shall join themselves together; and the daughter of the king of the south shall come to the king of the north to make an agreement: but she shall not retain the strength of her arm; neither shall he stand, nor his arm; but she shall be given up, and they that brought her, and he that begat her, and he that strengthened her in those times. ^7But out of a shoot from her roots shall one stand up in his place, who shall come unto the army, and shall enter into the fortress of the king of the north, and shall deal against them, and shall prevail. ^8And also their gods, with their molten images, and with their goodly vessels of silver and of gold, shall he carry captive into Egypt; and he shall refrain some years from the king of the north. ^9And he shall come into the realm of the king of the south, but he shall return into his own land. ^10And his sons shall war, and shall assemble a multitude of great forces, which shall come on, and overflow, and pass through; and they shall return and war, even to his fortress. ^11And the king of the south shall be moved with anger, and shall come forth and fight with him, even with the king of the north; and he shall set forth a great multitude, and the multitude shall be given into his hand. ^12And the multitude shall be lifted up, and his heart shall be exalted; and he shall cast down tens of thousands, but he shall not prevail. ^13And the king of the north shall return, and shall set forth a multitude greater than the former; and he shall come on at the end of the times, even of years, with a great army and with much substance. ^14And in those times there shall many stand up against the king of the south: also the children of the violent among thy people shall lift themselves up to establish the vision; but they shall fall. ^15So the king of the north shall come, and cast up a mound, and take a well-fortified city: and the forces of the south shall not stand, neither his chosen people, neither shall there be any strength to stand. ^16But he that cometh against him shall do according to his own will, and none shall stand before him; and he shall stand in the glorious land, and in his hand shall be destruction. ^17And he shall set his face to come with the strength of his whole kingdom, and with him equitable conditions; and he shall perform them: and he shall give him the daughter of women, to corrupt her; but she shall not stand, neither be for him. ^18After this shall he turn his face unto the isles, and shall take many: but a prince shall cause the reproach offered by him to cease; yea, moreover, he shall cause his reproach to turn upon him. ^19Then he shall turn his face toward the fortresses of his own land; but he shall stumble and fall, and shall not be found. ^20Then shall stand up in his place one that shall cause an exactor to pass through the glory of the kingdom; but within few days he shall be destroyed, neither in anger, nor in battle. ^21And in his place shall stand up a contemptible person, to whom they had not given the honor of the kingdom: but he shall come in time of security, and shall obtain the kingdom by flatteries. ^22And the overwhelming forces shall be overwhelmed from before him, and shall be broken; yea, also the prince of the covenant. ^23And after the league made with him he shall work deceitfully; for he shall come up, and shall become strong, with a small people. ^24In time of security shall he come even upon the fattest places of the province; and he shall do that which his fathers have not done, nor his fathers' fathers; he shall scatter among them prey, and spoil, and substance: yea, he shall devise his devices against the strongholds, even for a time. ^25And he shall stir up his power and his courage against the king of the south with a great army; and the king of the south shall war in battle with an exceeding great and mighty army; but he shall not stand; for they shall devise devices against him. ^26Yea, they that eat of his dainties shall destroy him, and his army shall overflow; and many shall fall down slain. ^27And as for both these kings, their hearts shall be to do mischief, and they shall speak lies at one table: but it shall not prosper; for yet the end shall be at the time appointed. ^28Then shall he return into his land with great substance; and his heart shall be against the holy covenant; and he shall do his pleasure, and return to his own land. ^29At the time appointed he shall return, and come into the south; but it shall not be in the latter time as it was in the former. ^30For ships of Kittim shall come against him; therefore he shall be grieved, and shall return, and have indignation against the holy covenant, and shall do his pleasure: he shall even return, and have regard unto them that forsake the holy covenant. ^31And forces shall stand on his part, and they shall profane the sanctuary, even the fortress, and shall take away the continual burnt-offering, and they shall set up the abomination that maketh desolate. ^32And such as do wickedly against the covenant shall he pervert by flatteries; but the people that know their God shall be strong, and do exploits. ^33And they that are wise among the people shall instruct many; yet they shall fall by the sword and by flame, by captivity and by spoil, many days. ^34Now when they shall fall, they shall be helped with a little help; but many shall join themselves unto them with flatteries. ^35And some of them that are wise shall fall, to refine them, and to purify, and to make them white, even to the time of the end; because it is yet for the time appointed. ^36And the king shall do according to his will; and he shall exalt himself, and magnify himself above every god, and shall speak marvellous things against the God of gods; and he shall prosper till the indignation be accomplished; for that which is determined shall be done. ^37Neither shall he regard the gods of his fathers, nor the desire of women, nor regard any god; for he shall magnify himself above all. ^38But in his place shall he honor the god of fortresses; and a god whom his fathers knew not shall he honor with gold, and silver, and with precious stones, and pleasant things. ^39And he shall deal with the strongest fortresses by the help of a foreign god: whosoever acknowledgeth him he will increase with glory; and he shall cause them to rule over many, and shall divide the land for a price. ^40And at the time of the end shall the king of the south contend with him; and the king of the north shall come against him like a whirlwind, with chariots, and with horsemen, and with many ships; and he shall enter into the countries, and shall overflow and pass through. ^41He shall enter also into the glorious land, and many countries shall be overthrown; but these shall be delivered out of his hand: Edom, and Moab, and the chief of the children of Ammon. ^42He shall stretch forth his hand also upon the countries; and the land of Egypt shall not escape. ^43But he shall have power over the treasures of gold and of silver, and over all the precious things of Egypt; and the Libyans and the Ethiopians shall be at his steps. ^44But tidings out of the east and out of the north shall trouble him; and he shall go forth with great fury to destroy and utterly to sweep away many. ^45And he shall plant the tents of his palace between the sea and the glorious holy mountain; yet he shall come to his end, and none shall help him.

Daniel 12

12

^1And at that time shall Michael stand up, the great prince who standeth for the children of thy people; and there shall be a time of trouble, such as never was since there was a nation even to that same time: and at that time thy people shall be delivered, every one that shall be found written in the book. ^2And many of them that sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake, some to everlasting life, and some to shame and everlasting contempt. ^3And they that are wise shall shine as the brightness of the firmament; and they that turn many to righteousness as the stars for ever and ever. ^4But thou, O Daniel, shut up the words, and seal the book, even to the time of the end: many shall run to and fro, and knowledge shall be increased. ^5Then I, Daniel, looked, and, behold, there stood other two, the one on the brink of the river on this side, and the other on the brink of the river on that side. ^6And one said to the man clothed in linen, who was above the waters of the river, How long shall it be to the end of these wonders? ^7And I heard the man clothed in linen, who was above the waters of the river, when he held up his right hand and his left hand unto heaven, and sware by him that liveth for ever that it shall be for a time, times, and a half; and when they have made an end of breaking in pieces the power of the holy people, all these things shall be finished. ^8And I heard, but I understood not: then said I, O my lord, what shall be the issue of these things? ^9And he said, Go thy way, Daniel; for the words are shut up and sealed till the time of the end. ^10Many shall purify themselves, and make themselves white, and be refined; but the wicked shall do wickedly; and none of the wicked shall understand; but they that are wise shall understand. ^11And from the time that the continual burnt-offering shall be taken away, and the abomination that maketh desolate set up, there shall be a thousand and two hundred and ninety days. ^12Blessed is he that waiteth, and cometh to the thousand three hundred and five and thirty days. ^13But go thou thy way till the end be; for thou shalt rest, and shalt stand in thy lot, at the end of the days.

Deuteronomy 2

2

^1Then we turned, and took our journey into the wilderness by the way to the Red Sea, as Jehovah spake unto me; and we compassed mount Seir many days. ^2And Jehovah spake unto me, saying, ^3Ye have compassed this mountain long enough: turn you northward. ^4And command thou the people, saying, Ye are to pass through the border of your brethren the children of Esau, that dwell in Seir; and they will be afraid of you: take ye good heed unto yourselves therefore; ^5contend not with them; for I will not give you of their land, no, not so much as for the sole of the foot to tread on; because I have given mount Seir unto Esau for a possession. ^6Ye shall purchase food of them for money, that ye may eat; and ye shall also buy water of them for money, that ye may drink. ^7For Jehovah thy God hath blessed thee in all the work of thy hand; he hath known thy walking through this great wilderness: these forty years Jehovah thy God hath been with thee; thou hast lacked nothing. ^8So we passed by from our brethren the children of Esau, that dwell in Seir, from the way of the Arabah from Elath and from Ezion-geber.

And we turned and passed by the way of the wilderness of Moab. ^9And Jehovah said unto me, Vex not Moab, neither contend with them in battle; for I will not give thee of his land for a possession; because I have given Ar unto the children of Lot for a possession. ^10(The Emim dwelt therein aforetime, a people great, and many, and tall, as the Anakim: ^11these also are accounted Rephaim, as the Anakim; but the Moabites call them Emim. ^12The Horites also dwelt in Seir aforetime, but the children of Esau succeeded them; and they destroyed them from before them, and dwelt in their stead; as Israel did unto the land of his possession, which Jehovah gave unto them.) ^13Now rise up, and get you over the brook Zered. And we went over the brook Zered. ^14And the days in which we came from Kadesh-barnea, until we were come over the brook Zered, were thirty and eight years; until all the generation of the men of war were consumed from the midst of the camp, as Jehovah sware unto them. ^15Moreover the hand of Jehovah was against them, to destroy them from the midst of the camp, until they were consumed.

^16So it came to pass, when all the men of war were consumed and dead from among the people, ^17that Jehovah spake unto me, saying, ^18Thou art this day to pass over Ar, the border of Moab: ^19and when thou comest nigh over against the children of Ammon, vex them not, nor contend with them; for I will not give thee of the land of the children of Ammon for a possession; because I have given it unto the children of Lot for a possession. ^20(That also is accounted a land of Rephaim: Rephaim dwelt therein aforetime; but the Ammonites call them Zamzummim, ^21a people great, and many, and tall, as the Anakim; but Jehovah destroyed them before them; and they succeeded them, and dwelt in their stead; ^22as he did for the children of Esau, that dwell in Seir, when he destroyed the Horites from before them; and they succeeded them, and dwelt in their stead even unto this day: ^23and the Avvim, that dwelt in villages as far as Gaza, the Caphtorim, that came forth out of Caphtor, destroyed them, and dwelt in their stead.) ^24Rise ye up, take your journey, and pass over the valley of the Arnon: behold, I have given into thy hand Sihon the Amorite, king of Heshbon, and his land; begin to possess it, and contend with him in battle. ^25This day will I begin to put the dread of thee and the fear of thee upon the peoples that are under the whole heaven, who shall hear the report of thee, and shall tremble, and be in anguish because of thee.

^26And I sent messengers out of the wilderness of Kedemoth unto Sihon king of Heshbon with words of peace, saying, ^27Let me pass through thy land: I will go along by the highway, I will turn neither unto the right hand nor to the left. ^28Thou shalt sell me food for money, that I may eat; and give me water for money, that I may drink: only let me pass through on my feet, ^29as the children of Esau that dwell in Seir, and the Moabites that dwell in Ar, did unto me; until I shall pass over the Jordan into the land which Jehovah our God giveth us. ^30But Sihon king of Heshbon would not let us pass by him; for Jehovah thy God hardened his spirit, and made his heart obstinate, that he might deliver him into thy hand, as at this day. ^31And Jehovah said unto me, Behold, I have begun to deliver up Sihon and his land before thee: begin to possess, that thou mayest inherit his land. ^32Then Sihon came out against us, he and all his people, unto battle at Jahaz. ^33And Jehovah our God delivered him up before us; and we smote him, and his sons, and all his people. ^34And we took all his cities at that time, and utterly destroyed every inhabited city, with the women and the little ones; we left none remaining: ^35only the cattle we took for a prey unto ourselves, with the spoil of the cities which we had taken. ^36From Aroer, which is on the edge of the valley of the Arnon, and from the city that is in the valley, even unto Gilead, there was not a city too high for us; Jehovah our God delivered up all before us: ^37only to the land of the children of Ammon thou camest not near; all the side of the river Jabbok, and the cities of the hill-country, and wheresoever Jehovah our God forbade us.

Deuteronomy 3

3

^1Then we turned, and went up the way to Bashan: and Og the king of Bashan came out against us, he and all his people, unto battle at Edrei. ^2And Jehovah said unto me, Fear him not; for I have delivered him, and all his people, and his land, into thy hand; and thou shalt do unto him as thou didst unto Sihon king of the Amorites, who dwelt at Heshbon. ^3So Jehovah our God delivered into our hand Og also, the king of Bashan, and all his people: and we smote him until none was left to him remaining. ^4And we took all his cities at that time; there was not a city which we took not from them; threescore cities, all the region of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Bashan. ^5All these were cities fortified with high walls, gates, and bars; besides the unwalled towns a great many. ^6And we utterly destroyed them, as we did unto Sihon king of Heshbon, utterly destroying every inhabited city, with the women and the little ones. ^7But all the cattle, and the spoil of the cities, we took for a prey unto ourselves. ^8And we took the land at that time out of the hand of the two kings of the Amorites that were beyond the Jordan, from the valley of the Arnon unto mount Hermon; ^9(which Hermon the Sidonians call Sirion, and the Amorites call it Senir;) ^10all the cities of the plain, and all Gilead, and all Bashan, unto Salecah and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan. ^11(For only Og king of Bashan remained of the remnant of the Rephaim; behold, his bedstead was a bedstead of iron; is it not in Rabbah of the children of Ammon? nine cubits was the length thereof, and four cubits the breadth of it, after the cubit of a man.)

^12And this land we took in possession at that time: from Aroer, which is by the valley of the Arnon, and half the hill-country of Gilead, and the cities thereof, gave I unto the Reubenites and to the Gadites: ^13and the rest of Gilead, and all Bashan, the kingdom of Og, gave I unto the half-tribe of Manasseh; all the region of Argob, even all Bashan. (The same is called the land of Rephaim. ^14Jair the son of Manasseh took all the region of Argob, unto the border of the Geshurites and the Maacathites, and called them, even Bashan, after his own name, Havvoth-jair, unto this day.) ^15And I gave Gilead unto Machir. ^16And unto the Reubenites and unto the Gadites I gave from Gilead even unto the valley of the Arnon, the middle of the valley, and the border thereof, even unto the river Jabbok, which is the border of the children of Ammon; ^17the Arabah also, and the Jordan and the border thereof, from Chinnereth even unto the sea of the Arabah, the Salt Sea, under the slopes of Pisgah eastward.

^18And I commanded you at that time, saying, Jehovah your God hath given you this land to possess it: ye shall pass over armed before your brethren the children of Israel, all the men of valor. ^19But your wives, and your little ones, and your cattle, (I know that ye have much cattle,) shall abide in your cities which I have given you, ^20until Jehovah give rest unto your brethren, as unto you, and they also possess the land which Jehovah your God giveth them beyond the Jordan: then shall ye return every man unto his possession, which I have given you. ^21And I commanded Joshua at that time, saying, Thine eyes have seen all that Jehovah your God hath done unto these two kings: so shall Jehovah do unto all the kingdoms whither thou goest over. ^22Ye shall not fear them; for Jehovah your God, he it is that fighteth for you.

^23And I besought Jehovah at that time, saying, ^24O Lord Jehovah, thou hast begun to show thy servant thy greatness, and thy strong hand: for what god is there in heaven or in earth, that can do according to thy works, and according to thy mighty acts? ^25Let me go over, I pray thee, and see the good land that is beyond the Jordan, that goodly mountain, and Lebanon. ^26But Jehovah was wroth with me for your sakes, and hearkened not unto me; and Jehovah said unto me, Let it suffice thee; speak no more unto me of this matter. ^27Get thee up unto the top of Pisgah, and lift up thine eyes westward, and northward, and southward, and eastward, and behold with thine eyes: for thou shalt not go over this Jordan. ^28But charge Joshua, and encourage him, and strengthen him; for he shall go over before this people, and he shall cause them to inherit the land which thou shalt see. ^29So we abode in the valley over against Beth-peor.

Deuteronomy 5

5

^1And Moses called unto all Israel, and said unto them, Hear, O Israel, the statutes and the ordinances which I speak in your ears this day, that ye may learn them, and observe to do them. ^2Jehovah our God made a covenant with us in Horeb. ^3Jehovah made not this covenant with our fathers, but with us, even us, who are all of us here alive this day. ^4Jehovah spake with you face to face in the mount out of the midst of the fire, ^5(I stood between Jehovah and you at that time, to show you the word of Jehovah: for ye were afraid because of the fire, and went not up into the mount;) saying,

^6I am Jehovah thy God, who brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage.

^7Thou shalt have no other gods before me.

^8Thou shalt not make unto thee a graven image, nor any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth: ^9thou shalt not bow down thyself unto them, nor serve them; for I, Jehovah, thy God, am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children, and upon the third and upon the fourth generation of them that hate me; ^10and showing lovingkindness unto thousands of them that love me and keep my commandments.

^11Thou shalt not take the name of Jehovah thy God in vain: for Jehovah will not hold him guiltless that taketh his name in vain.

^12Observe the sabbath day, to keep it holy, as Jehovah thy God commanded thee. ^13Six days shalt thou labor, and do all thy work; ^14but the seventh day is a sabbath unto Jehovah thy God: in it thou shalt not do any work, thou, nor thy son, nor thy daughter, nor thy man-servant, nor thy maid-servant, nor thine ox, nor thine ass, nor any of thy cattle, nor thy stranger that is within thy gates; that thy man-servant and thy maid-servant may rest as well as thou. ^15And thou shalt remember that thou wast a servant in the land of Egypt, and Jehovah thy God brought thee out thence by a mighty hand and by an outstretched arm: therefore Jehovah thy God commanded thee to keep the sabbath day.

^16Honor thy father and thy mother, as Jehovah thy God commanded thee; that thy days may be long, and that it may go well with thee, in the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee.

^17Thou shalt not kill.

^18Neither shalt thou commit adultery.

^19Neither shalt thou steal.

^20Neither shalt thou bear false witness against thy neighbor.

^21Neither shalt thou covet thy neighbor's wife; neither shalt thou desire thy neighbor's house, his field, or his man-servant, or his maid-servant, his ox, or his ass, or anything that is thy neighbor's.

^22These words Jehovah spake unto all your assembly in the mount out of the midst of the fire, of the cloud, and of the thick darkness, with a great voice: and he added no more. And he wrote them upon two tables of stone, and gave them unto me. ^23And it came to pass, when ye heard the voice out of the midst of the darkness, while the mountain was burning with fire, that ye came near unto me, even all the heads of your tribes, and your elders; ^24and ye said, Behold, Jehovah our God hath showed us his glory and his greatness, and we have heard his voice out of the midst of the fire: we have seen this day that God doth speak with man, and he liveth. ^25Now therefore why should we die? for this great fire will consume us: if we hear the voice of Jehovah our God any more, then we shall die. ^26For who is there of all flesh, that hath heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as we have, and lived? ^27Go thou near, and hear all that Jehovah our God shall say: and speak thou unto us all that Jehovah our God shall speak unto thee; and we will hear it, and do it.

^28And Jehovah heard the voice of your words, when ye spake unto me; and Jehovah said unto me, I have heard the voice of the words of this people, which they have spoken unto thee: they have well said all that they have spoken. ^29Oh that there were such a heart in them, that they would fear me, and keep all my commandments always, that it might be well with them, and with their children for ever! ^30Go say to them, Return ye to your tents. ^31But as for thee, stand thou here by me, and I will speak unto thee all the commandment, and the statutes, and the ordinances, which thou shalt teach them, that they may do them in the land which I give them to possess it. ^32Ye shall observe to do therefore as Jehovah your God hath commanded you: ye shall not turn aside to the right hand or to the left. ^33Ye shall walk in all the way which Jehovah your God hath commanded you, that ye may live, and that it may be well with you, and that ye may prolong your days in the land which ye shall possess.

Deuteronomy 6

6

^1Now this is the commandment, the statutes, and the ordinances, which Jehovah your God commanded to teach you, that ye might do them in the land whither ye go over to possess it; ^2that thou mightest fear Jehovah thy God, to keep all his statutes and his commandments, which I command thee, thou, and thy son, and thy son's son, all the days of thy life; and that thy days may be prolonged. ^3Hear therefore, O Israel, and observe to do it; that it may be well with thee, and that ye may increase mightily, as Jehovah, the God of thy fathers, hath promised unto thee, in a land flowing with milk and honey. ^4Hear, O Israel: Jehovah our God is one Jehovah: ^5and thou shalt love Jehovah thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy might. ^6And these words, which I command thee this day, shall be upon thy heart; ^7and thou shalt teach them diligently unto thy children, and shalt talk of them when thou sittest in thy house, and when thou walkest by the way, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up. ^8And thou shalt bind them for a sign upon thy hand, and they shall be for frontlets between thine eyes. ^9And thou shalt write them upon the door-posts of thy house, and upon thy gates.

^10And it shall be, when Jehovah thy God shall bring thee into the land which he sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give thee, great and goodly cities, which thou buildest not, ^11and houses full of all good things, which thou filledst not, and cisterns hewn out, which thou hewedst not, vineyards and olive-trees, which thou plantedst not, and thou shalt eat and be full; ^12then beware lest thou forget Jehovah, who brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage. ^13Thou shalt fear Jehovah thy God; and him shalt thou serve, and shalt swear by his name. ^14Ye shall not go after other gods, of the gods of the peoples that are round about you; ^15for Jehovah thy God in the midst of thee is a jealous God; lest the anger of Jehovah thy God be kindled against thee, and he destroy thee from off the face of the earth.

^16Ye shall not tempt Jehovah your God, as ye tempted him in Massah. ^17Ye shall diligently keep the commandments of Jehovah your God, and his testimonies, and his statutes, which he hath commanded thee. ^18And thou shalt do that which is right and good in the sight of Jehovah; that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest go in and possess the good land which Jehovah sware unto thy fathers, ^19to thrust out all thine enemies from before thee, as Jehovah hath spoken.

^20When thy son asketh thee in time to come, saying, What mean the testimonies, and the statutes, and the ordinances, which Jehovah our God hath commanded you? ^21then thou shalt say unto thy son, We were Pharaoh's bondmen in Egypt: and Jehovah brought us out of Egypt with a mighty hand; ^22and Jehovah showed signs and wonders, great and sore, upon Egypt, upon Pharaoh, and upon all his house, before our eyes; ^23and he brought us out from thence, that he might bring us in, to give us the land which he sware unto our fathers. ^24And Jehovah commanded us to do all these statutes, to fear Jehovah our God, for our good always, that he might preserve us alive, as at this day. ^25And it shall be righteousness unto us, if we observe to do all this commandment before Jehovah our God, as he hath commanded us.

Deuteronomy 7

7

^1When Jehovah thy God shall bring thee into the land whither thou goest to possess it, and shall cast out many nations before thee, the Hittite, and the Girgashite, and the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite, seven nations greater and mightier than thou; ^2and when Jehovah thy God shall deliver them up before thee, and thou shalt smite them; then thou shalt utterly destroy them: thou shalt make no covenant with them, nor show mercy unto them; ^3neither shalt thou make marriages with them; thy daughter thou shalt not give unto his son, nor his daughter shalt thou take unto thy son. ^4For he will turn away thy son from following me, that they may serve other gods: so will the anger of Jehovah be kindled against you, and he will destroy thee quickly. ^5But thus shall ye deal with them: ye shall break down their altars, and dash in pieces their pillars, and hew down their Asherim, and burn their graven images with fire.

^6For thou art a holy people unto Jehovah thy God: Jehovah thy God hath chosen thee to be a people for his own possession, above all peoples that are upon the face of the earth. ^7Jehovah did not set his love upon you, nor choose you, because ye were more in number than any people; for ye were the fewest of all peoples: ^8but because Jehovah loveth you, and because he would keep the oath which he sware unto your fathers, hath Jehovah brought you out with a mighty hand, and redeemed you out of the house of bondage, from the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt. ^9Know therefore that Jehovah thy God, he is God, the faithful God, who keepeth covenant and lovingkindness with them that love him and keep his commandments to a thousand generations, ^10and repayeth them that hate him to their face, to destroy them: he will not be slack to him that hateth him, he will repay him to his face. ^11Thou shalt therefore keep the commandment, and the statutes, and the ordinances, which I command thee this day, to do them.

^12And it shall come to pass, because ye hearken to these ordinances, and keep and do them, that Jehovah thy God will keep with thee the covenant and the lovingkindness which he sware unto thy fathers: ^13and he will love thee, and bless thee, and multiply thee; he will also bless the fruit of thy body and the fruit of thy ground, thy grain and thy new wine and thine oil, the increase of thy cattle and the young of thy flock, in the land which he sware unto thy fathers to give thee. ^14Thou shalt be blessed above all peoples: there shall not be male or female barren among you, or among your cattle. ^15And Jehovah will take away from thee all sickness; and none of the evil diseases of Egypt, which thou knowest, will he put upon thee, but will lay them upon all them that hate thee. ^16And thou shalt consume all the peoples that Jehovah thy God shall deliver unto thee; thine eye shall not pity them: neither shalt thou serve their gods; for that will be a snare unto thee.

^17If thou shalt say in thy heart, These nations are more than I; how can I dispossess them? ^18thou shalt not be afraid of them: thou shalt well remember what Jehovah thy God did unto Pharaoh, and unto all Egypt; ^19the great trials which thine eyes saw, and the signs, and the wonders, and the mighty hand, and the outstretched arm, whereby Jehovah thy God brought thee out: so shall Jehovah thy God do unto all the peoples of whom thou art afraid. ^20Moreover Jehovah thy God will send the hornet among them, until they that are left, and hide themselves, perish from before thee. ^21Thou shalt not be affrighted at them; for Jehovah thy God is in the midst of thee, a great God and a terrible. ^22And Jehovah thy God will cast out those nations before thee by little and little: thou mayest not consume them at once, lest the beasts of the field increase upon thee. ^23But Jehovah thy God will deliver them up before thee, and will discomfit them with a great discomfiture, until they be destroyed. ^24And he will deliver their kings into thy hand, and thou shalt make their name to perish from under heaven: there shall no man be able to stand before thee, until thou have destroyed them. ^25The graven images of their gods shall ye burn with fire: thou shalt not covet the silver or the gold that is on them, nor take it unto thee, lest thou be snared therein; for it is an abomination to Jehovah thy God. ^26And thou shalt not bring an abomination into thy house, and become a devoted thing like unto it: thou shalt utterly detest it, and thou shalt utterly abhor it; for it is a devoted thing.

Deuteronomy 8

8

^1All the commandment which I command thee this day shall ye observe to do, that ye may live, and multiply, and go in and possess the land which Jehovah sware unto your fathers. ^2And thou shalt remember all the way which Jehovah thy God hath led thee these forty years in the wilderness, that he might humble thee, to prove thee, to know what was in thy heart, whether thou wouldest keep his commandments, or not. ^3And he humbled thee, and suffered thee to hunger, and fed thee with manna, which thou knewest not, neither did thy fathers know; that he might make thee know that man doth not live by bread only, but by everything that proceedeth out of the mouth of Jehovah doth man live. ^4Thy raiment waxed not old upon thee, neither did thy foot swell, these forty years. ^5And thou shalt consider in thy heart, that, as a man chasteneth his son, so Jehovah thy God chasteneth thee. ^6And thou shalt keep the commandments of Jehovah thy God, to walk in his ways, and to fear him. ^7For Jehovah thy God bringeth thee into a good land, a land of brooks of water, of fountains and springs, flowing forth in valleys and hills; ^8a land of wheat and barley, and vines and fig-trees and pomegranates; a land of olive-trees and honey; ^9a land wherein thou shalt eat bread without scarceness, thou shalt not lack anything in it; a land whose stones are iron, and out of whose hills thou mayest dig copper. ^10And thou shalt eat and be full, and thou shalt bless Jehovah thy God for the good land which he hath given thee.

^11Beware lest thou forget Jehovah thy God, in not keeping his commandments, and his ordinances, and his statutes, which I command thee this day: ^12lest, when thou hast eaten and art full, and hast built goodly houses, and dwelt therein; ^13and when thy herds and thy flocks multiply, and thy silver and thy gold is multiplied, and all that thou hast is multiplied; ^14then thy heart be lifted up, and thou forget Jehovah thy God, who brought thee forth out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage; ^15who led thee through the great and terrible wilderness, wherein were fiery serpents and scorpions, and thirsty ground where was no water; who brought thee forth water out of the rock of flint; ^16who fed thee in the wilderness with manna, which thy fathers knew not; that he might humble thee, and that he might prove thee, to do thee good at thy latter end: ^17and lest thou say in thy heart, My power and the might of my hand hath gotten me this wealth. ^18But thou shalt remember Jehovah thy God, for it is he that giveth thee power to get wealth; that he may establish his covenant which he sware unto thy fathers, as at this day. ^19And it shall be, if thou shalt forget Jehovah thy God, and walk after other gods, and serve them, and worship them, I testify against you this day that ye shall surely perish. ^20As the nations that Jehovah maketh to perish before you, so shall ye perish; because ye would not hearken unto the voice of Jehovah your God.

Deuteronomy 9

9

^1Hear, O Israel: thou art to pass over the Jordan this day, to go in to dispossess nations greater and mightier than thyself, cities great and fortified up to heaven, ^2a people great and tall, the sons of the Anakim, whom thou knowest, and of whom thou hast heard say, Who can stand before the sons of Anak? ^3Know therefore this day, that Jehovah thy God is he who goeth over before thee as a devouring fire; he will destroy them, and he will bring them down before thee: so shalt thou drive them out, and make them to perish quickly, as Jehovah hath spoken unto thee. ^4Speak not thou in thy heart, after that Jehovah thy God hath thrust them out from before thee, saying, For my righteousness Jehovah hath brought me in to possess this land; whereas for the wickedness of these nations Jehovah doth drive them out from before thee. ^5Not for thy righteousness, or for the uprightness of thy heart, dost thou go in to possess their land; but for the wickedness of these nations Jehovah thy God doth drive them out from before thee, and that he may establish the word which Jehovah sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob.

^6Know therefore, that Jehovah thy God giveth thee not this good land to possess it for thy righteousness; for thou art a stiffnecked people. ^7Remember, forget thou not, how thou provokedst Jehovah thy God to wrath in the wilderness: from the day that thou wentest forth out of the land of Egypt, until ye came unto this place, ye have been rebellious against Jehovah. ^8Also in Horeb ye provoked Jehovah to wrath, and Jehovah was angry with you to destroy you. ^9When I was gone up into the mount to receive the tables of stone, even the tables of the covenant which Jehovah made with you, then I abode in the mount forty days and forty nights; I did neither eat bread nor drink water. ^10And Jehovah delivered unto me the two tables of stone written with the finger of God; and on them was written according to all the words, which Jehovah speak with you in the mount out of the midst of the fire in the day of the assembly. ^11And it came to pass at the end of forty days and forty nights, that Jehovah gave me the two tables of stone, even the tables of the covenant. ^12And Jehovah said unto me, Arise, get thee down quickly from hence; for thy people that thou hast brought forth out of Egypt have corrupted themselves; they are quickly turned aside out of the way which I commanded them; they have made them a molten image. ^13Furthermore Jehovah spake unto me, saying, I have seen this people, and, behold, it is a stiffnecked people: ^14let me alone, that I may destroy them, and blot out their name from under heaven; and I will make of thee a nation mightier and greater than they. ^15So I turned and came down from the mount, and the mount was burning with fire: and the two tables of the covenant were in my two hands. ^16And I looked, and, behold, ye had sinned against Jehovah your God; ye had made you a molten calf: ye had turned aside quickly out of the way which Jehovah had commanded you. ^17And I took hold of the two tables, and cast them out of my two hands, and brake them before your eyes. ^18And I fell down before Jehovah, as at the first, forty days and forty nights; I did neither eat bread nor drink water; because of all your sin which ye sinned, in doing that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, to provoke him to anger. ^19For I was afraid of the anger and hot displeasure, wherewith Jehovah was wroth against you to destroy you. But Jehovah hearkened unto me that time also. ^20And Jehovah was very angry with Aaron to destroy him: and I prayed for Aaron also at the same time. ^21And I took your sin, the calf which ye had made, and burnt it with fire, and stamped it, grinding it very small, until it was as fine as dust: and I cast the dust thereof into the brook that descended out of the mount.

^22And at Taberah, and at Massah, and at Kibroth-hattaavah, ye provoked Jehovah to wrath. ^23And when Jehovah sent you from Kadesh-barnea, saying, Go up and possess the land which I have given you; then ye rebelled against the commandment of Jehovah your God, and ye believed him not, nor hearkened to his voice. ^24Ye have been rebellious against Jehovah from the day that I knew you.

^25So I fell down before Jehovah the forty days and forty nights that I fell down, because Jehovah had said he would destroy you. ^26And I prayed unto Jehovah, and said, O Lord Jehovah, destroy not thy people and thine inheritance, that thou hast redeemed through thy greatness, that thou hast brought forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand. ^27Remember thy servants, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob; look not unto the stubbornness of this people, nor to their wickedness, nor to their sin, ^28lest the land whence thou broughtest us out say, Because Jehovah was not able to bring them into the land which he promised unto them, and because he hated them, he hath brought them out to slay them in the wilderness. ^29Yet they are thy people and thine inheritance, which thou broughtest out by thy great power and by thine outstretched arm.

Deuteronomy 10

10

^1At that time Jehovah said unto me, Hew thee two tables of stone like unto the first, and come up unto me into the mount, and make thee an ark of wood. ^2And I will write on the tables the words that were on the first tables which thou brakest, and thou shalt put them in the ark. ^3So I made an ark of acacia wood, and hewed two tables of stone like unto the first, and went up into the mount, having the two tables in my hand. ^4And he wrote on the tables, according to the first writing, the ten commandments, which Jehovah spake unto you in the mount out of the midst of the fire in the day of the assembly: and Jehovah gave them unto me. ^5And I turned and came down from the mount, and put the tables in the ark which I had made; and there they are as Jehovah commanded me. ^6(And the children of Israel journeyed from Beeroth Bene-jaakan to Moserah. There Aaron died, and there he was buried; and Eleazar his son ministered in the priest's office in his stead. ^7From thence they journeyed unto Gudgodah; and from Gudgodah to Jotbathah, a land of brooks of water. ^8At that time Jehovah set apart the tribe of Levi, to bear the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, to stand before Jehovah to minister unto him, and to bless in his name, unto this day. ^9Wherefore Levi hath no portion nor inheritance with his brethren; Jehovah is his inheritance, according as Jehovah thy God spake unto him.) ^10And I stayed in the mount, as at the first time, forty days and forty nights: and Jehovah hearkened unto me that time also; Jehovah would not destroy thee. ^11And Jehovah said unto me, Arise, take thy journey before the people; and they shall go in and possess the land, which I sware unto their fathers to give unto them.

^12And now, Israel, what doth Jehovah thy God require of thee, but to fear Jehovah thy God, to walk in all his ways, and to love him, and to serve Jehovah thy God with all thy heart and with all thy soul, ^13to keep the commandments of Jehovah, and his statutes, which I command thee this day for thy good? ^14Behold, unto Jehovah thy God belongeth heaven and the heaven of heavens, the earth, with all that is therein. ^15Only Jehovah had a delight in thy fathers to love them, and he chose their seed after them, even you above all peoples, as at this day. ^16Circumcise therefore the foreskin of your heart, and be no more stiffnecked. ^17For Jehovah your God, he is God of gods, and Lord of lords, the great God, the mighty, and the terrible, who regardeth not persons, nor taketh reward. ^18He doth execute justice for the fatherless and widow, and loveth the sojourner, in giving him food and raiment. ^19Love ye therefore the sojourner; for ye were sojourners in the land of Egypt. ^20Thou shalt fear Jehovah thy God; him shalt thou serve; and to him shalt thou cleave, and by his name shalt thou swear. ^21He is thy praise, and he is thy God, that hath done for thee these great and terrible things, which thine eyes have seen. ^22Thy fathers went down into Egypt with threescore and ten persons; and now Jehovah thy God hath made thee as the stars of heaven for multitude.

Deuteronomy 11

11

^1Therefore thou shalt love Jehovah thy God, and keep his charge, and his statutes, and his ordinances, and his commandments, alway. ^2And know ye this day: for I speak not with your children that have not known, and that have not seen the chastisement of Jehovah your God, his greatness, his mighty hand, and his outstretched arm, ^3and his signs, and his works, which he did in the midst of Egypt unto Pharaoh the king of Egypt, and unto all his land; ^4and what he did unto the army of Egypt, unto their horses, and to their chariots; how he made the water of the Red Sea to overflow them as they pursued after you, and how Jehovah hath destroyed them unto this day; ^5and what he did unto you in the wilderness, until ye came unto this place; ^6and what he did unto Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, the son of Reuben; how the earth opened its mouth, and swallowed them up, and their households, and their tents, and every living thing that followed them, in the midst of all Israel: ^7but your eyes have seen all the great work of Jehovah which he did.

^8Therefore shall ye keep all the commandment which I command thee this day, that ye may be strong, and go in and possess the land, whither ye go over to possess it; ^9and that ye may prolong your days in the land, which Jehovah sware unto your fathers to give unto them and to their seed, a land flowing with milk and honey. ^10For the land, whither thou goest in to possess it, is not as the land of Egypt, from whence ye came out, where thou sowedst thy seed, and wateredst it with thy foot, as a garden of herbs; ^11but the land, whither ye go over to possess it, is a land of hills and valleys, and drinketh water of the rain of heaven, ^12a land which Jehovah thy God careth for: the eyes of Jehovah thy God are always upon it, from the beginning of the year even unto the end of the year.

^13And it shall come to pass, if ye shall hearken diligently unto my commandments which I command you this day, to love Jehovah your God, and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul, ^14that I will give the rain of your land in its season, the former rain and the latter rain, that thou mayest gather in thy grain, and thy new wine, and thine oil. ^15And I will give grass in thy fields for thy cattle, and thou shalt eat and be full. ^16Take heed to yourselves, lest your heart be deceived, and ye turn aside, and serve other gods, and worship them; ^17and the anger of Jehovah be kindled against you, and he shut up the heavens, so that there shall be no rain, and the land shall not yield its fruit; and ye perish quickly from off the good land which Jehovah giveth you.

^18Therefore shall ye lay up these my words in your heart and in your soul; and ye shall bind them for a sign upon your hand, and they shall be for frontlets between your eyes. ^19And ye shall teach them your children, talking of them, when thou sittest in thy house, and when thou walkest by the way, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up. ^20And thou shalt write them upon the door-posts of thy house, and upon thy gates; ^21that your days may be multiplied, and the days of your children, in the land which Jehovah sware unto your fathers to give them, as the days of the heavens above the earth. ^22For if ye shall diligently keep all this commandment which I command you, to do it, to love Jehovah your God, to walk in all his ways, and to cleave unto him; ^23then will Jehovah drive out all these nations from before you, and ye shall dispossess nations greater and mightier than yourselves. ^24Every place whereon the sole of your foot shall tread shall be yours: from the wilderness, and Lebanon, from the river, the river Euphrates, even unto the hinder sea shall be your border. ^25There shall no man be able to stand before you: Jehovah your God shall lay the fear of you and the dread of you upon all the land that ye shall tread upon, as he hath spoken unto you.

^26Behold, I set before you this day a blessing and a curse: ^27the blessing, if ye shall hearken unto the commandments of Jehovah your God, which I command you this day; ^28and the curse, if ye shall not hearken unto the commandments of Jehovah your God, but turn aside out of the way which I command you this day, to go after other gods, which ye have not known. ^29And it shall come to pass, when Jehovah thy God shall bring thee into the land whither thou goest to possess it, that thou shalt set the blessing upon mount Gerizim, and the curse upon mount Ebal. ^30Are they not beyond the Jordan, behind the way of the going down of the sun, in the land of the Canaanites that dwell in the Arabah, over against Gilgal, beside the oaks of Moreh? ^31For ye are to pass over the Jordan to go in to possess the land which Jehovah your God giveth you, and ye shall possess it, and dwell therein. ^32And ye shall observe to do all the statutes and the ordinances which I set before you this day.

Deuteronomy 12

12

^1These are the statutes and the ordinances which ye shall observe to do in the land which Jehovah, the God of thy fathers, hath given thee to possess it, all the days that ye live upon the earth. ^2Ye shall surely destroy all the places wherein the nations that ye shall dispossess served their gods, upon the high mountains, and upon the hills, and under every green tree: ^3and ye shall break down their altars, and dash in pieces their pillars, and burn their Asherim with fire; and ye shall hew down the graven images of their gods; and ye shall destroy their name out of that place. ^4Ye shall not do so unto Jehovah your God. ^5But unto the place which Jehovah your God shall choose out of all your tribes, to put his name there, even unto his habitation shall ye seek, and thither thou shalt come; ^6and thither ye shall bring your burnt-offerings, and your sacrifices, and your tithes, and the heave-offering of your hand, and your vows, and your freewill-offerings, and the firstlings of your herd and of your flock: ^7and there ye shall eat before Jehovah your God, and ye shall rejoice in all that ye put your hand unto, ye and your households, wherein Jehovah thy God hath blessed thee. ^8Ye shall not do after all the things that we do here this day, every man whatsoever is right in his own eyes; ^9for ye are not as yet come to the rest and to the inheritance, which Jehovah thy God giveth thee. ^10But when ye go over the Jordan, and dwell in the land which Jehovah your God causeth you to inherit, and he giveth you rest from all your enemies round about, so that ye dwell in safety; ^11then it shall come to pass that to the place which Jehovah your God shall choose, to cause his name to dwell there, thither shall ye bring all that I command you: your burnt-offerings, and your sacrifices, your tithes, and the heave-offering of your hand, and all your choice vows which ye vow unto Jehovah. ^12And ye shall rejoice before Jehovah your God, ye, and your sons, and your daughters, and your men-servants, and your maid-servants, and the Levite that is within your gates, forasmuch as he hath no portion nor inheritance with you. ^13Take heed to thyself that thou offer not thy burnt-offerings in every place that thou seest; ^14but in the place which Jehovah shall choose in one of thy tribes, there thou shalt offer thy burnt-offerings, and there thou shalt do all that I command thee.

^15Notwithstanding, thou mayest kill and eat flesh within all thy gates, after all the desire of thy soul, according to the blessing of Jehovah thy God which he hath given thee: the unclean and the clean may eat thereof, as of the gazelle, and as of the hart. ^16Only ye shall not eat the blood; thou shalt pour it out upon the earth as water. ^17Thou mayest not eat within thy gates the tithe of thy grain, or of thy new wine, or of thine oil, or the firstlings of thy herd or of thy flock, nor any of thy vows which thou vowest, nor thy freewill-offerings, nor the heave-offering of thy hand; ^18but thou shalt eat them before Jehovah thy God in the place which Jehovah thy God shall choose, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy man-servant, and thy maid-servant, and the Levite that is within thy gates: and thou shalt rejoice before Jehovah thy God in all that thou puttest thy hand unto. ^19Take heed to thyself that thou forsake not the Levite as long as thou livest in thy land.

^20When Jehovah thy God shall enlarge thy border, as he hath promised thee, and thou shalt say, I will eat flesh, because thy soul desireth to eat flesh; thou mayest eat flesh, after all the desire of thy soul. ^21If the place which Jehovah thy God shall choose, to put his name there, be too far from thee, then thou shalt kill of thy herd and of thy flock, which Jehovah hath given thee, as I have commanded thee; and thou mayest eat within thy gates, after all the desire of thy soul. ^22Even as the gazelle and as the hart is eaten, so thou shalt eat thereof: the unclean and the clean may eat thereof alike. ^23Only be sure that thou eat not the blood: for the blood is the life; and thou shalt not eat the life with the flesh. ^24Thou shalt not eat it; thou shalt pour it out upon the earth as water. ^25Thou shalt not eat it; that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee, when thou shalt do that which is right in the eyes of Jehovah. ^26Only thy holy things which thou hast, and thy vows, thou shalt take, and go unto the place which Jehovah shall choose: ^27and thou shalt offer thy burnt-offerings, the flesh and the blood, upon the altar of Jehovah thy God; and the blood of thy sacrifices shall be poured out upon the altar of Jehovah thy God; and thou shalt eat the flesh. ^28Observe and hear all these words which I command thee, that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee for ever, when thou doest that which is good and right in the eyes of Jehovah thy God.

^29When Jehovah thy God shall cut off the nations from before thee, whither thou goest in to dispossess them, and thou dispossessest them, and dwellest in their land; ^30take heed to thyself that thou be not ensnared to follow them, after that they are destroyed from before thee; and that thou inquire not after their gods, saying, How do these nations serve their gods? even so will I do likewise. ^31Thou shalt not do so unto Jehovah thy God: for every abomination to Jehovah, which he hateth, have they done unto their gods; for even their sons and their daughters do they burn in the fire to their gods.

^32What thing soever I command you, that shall ye observe to do: thou shalt not add thereto, nor diminish from it.

Deuteronomy 14

14

^1Ye are the children of Jehovah your God: ye shall not cut yourselves, nor make any baldness between your eyes for the dead. ^2For thou art a holy people unto Jehovah thy God, and Jehovah hath chosen thee to be a people for his own possession, above all peoples that are upon the face of the earth.

^3Thou shalt not eat any abominable thing. ^4These are the beasts which ye may eat: the ox, the sheep, and the goat, ^5the hart, and the gazelle, and the roebuck, and the wild goat, and the pygarg, and the antelope, and the chamois. ^6And every beast that parteth the hoof, and hath the hoof cloven in two, and cheweth the cud, among the beasts, that may ye eat. ^7Nevertheless these ye shall not eat of them that chew the cud, or of them that have the hoof cloven: the camel, and the hare, and the coney; because they chew the cud but part not the hoof, they are unclean unto you. ^8And the swine, because he parteth the hoof but cheweth not the cud, he is unclean unto you: of their flesh ye shall not eat, and their carcasses ye shall not touch.

^9These ye may eat of all that are in the waters: whatsoever hath fins and scales may ye eat; ^10and whatsoever hath not fins and scales ye shall not eat; it is unclean unto you.

^11Of all clean birds ye may eat. ^12But these are they of which ye shall not eat: the eagle, and the gier-eagle, and the ospray, ^13and the glede, and the falcon, and the kite after its kind, ^14and every raven after its kind, ^15and the ostrich, and the night-hawk, and the sea-mew, and the hawk after its kind, ^16the little owl, and the great owl, and the horned owl, ^17and the pelican, and the vulture, and the cormorant, ^18and the stork, and the heron after its kind, and the hoopoe, and the bat. ^19And all winged creeping things are unclean unto you: they shall not be eaten. ^20Of all clean birds ye may eat.

^21Ye shall not eat of anything that dieth of itself: thou mayest give it unto the sojourner that is within thy gates, that he may eat it; or thou mayest sell it unto a foreigner: for thou art a holy people unto Jehovah thy God. Thou shalt not boil a kid in its mother's milk.

^22Thou shalt surely tithe all the increase of thy seed, that which cometh forth from the field year by year. ^23And thou shalt eat before Jehovah thy God, in the place which he shall choose, to cause his name to dwell there, the tithe of thy grain, of thy new wine, and of thine oil, and the firstlings of thy herd and of thy flock; that thou mayest learn to fear Jehovah thy God always. ^24And if the way be too long for thee, so that thou art not able to carry it, because the place is too far from thee, which Jehovah thy God shall choose, to set his name there, when Jehovah thy God shall bless thee; ^25then shalt thou turn it into money, and bind up the money in thy hand, and shalt go unto the place which Jehovah thy God shall choose: ^26and thou shalt bestow the money for whatsoever thy soul desireth, for oxen, or for sheep, or for wine, or for strong drink, or for whatsoever thy soul asketh of thee; and thou shalt eat there before Jehovah thy God, and thou shalt rejoice, thou and thy household. ^27And the Levite that is within thy gates, thou shalt not forsake him; for he hath no portion nor inheritance with thee.

^28At the end of every three years thou shalt bring forth all the tithe of thine increase in the same year, and shalt lay it up within thy gates: ^29and the Levite, because he hath no portion nor inheritance with thee, and the sojourner, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are within thy gates, shall come, and shall eat and be satisfied; that Jehovah thy God may bless thee in all the work of thy hand which thou doest.

Deuteronomy 15

15

^1At the end of every seven years thou shalt make a release. ^2And this is the manner of the release: every creditor shall release that which he hath lent unto his neighbor; he shall not exact it of his neighbor and his brother; because Jehovah's release hath been proclaimed. ^3Of a foreigner thou mayest exact it: but whatsoever of thine is with thy brother thy hand shall release. ^4Howbeit there shall be no poor with thee; (for Jehovah will surely bless thee in the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to possess it;) ^5if only thou diligently hearken unto the voice of Jehovah thy God, to observe to do all this commandment which I command thee this day. ^6For Jehovah thy God will bless thee, as he promised thee: and thou shalt lend unto many nations, but thou shalt not borrow; and thou shalt rule over many nations, but they shall not rule over thee.

^7If there be with thee a poor man, one of thy brethren, within any of thy gates in thy land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not harden thy heart, nor shut thy hand from thy poor brother; ^8but thou shalt surely open thy hand unto him, and shalt surely lend him sufficient for his need in that which he wanteth. ^9Beware that there be not a base thought in thy heart, saying, The seventh year, the year of release, is at hand; and thine eye be evil against thy poor brother, and thou give him nought; and he cry unto Jehovah against thee, and it be sin unto thee. ^10Thou shalt surely give him, and thy heart shall not be grieved when thou givest unto him; because that for this thing Jehovah thy God will bless thee in all thy work, and in all that thou puttest thy hand unto. ^11For the poor will never cease out of the land: therefore I command thee, saying, Thou shalt surely open thy hand unto thy brother, to thy needy, and to thy poor, in thy land.

^12If thy brother, a Hebrew man, or a Hebrew woman, be sold unto thee, and serve thee six years; then in the seventh year thou shalt let him go free from thee. ^13And when thou lettest him go free from thee, thou shalt not let him go empty: ^14thou shalt furnish him liberally out of thy flock, and out of thy threshing-floor, and out of thy winepress; as Jehovah thy God hath blessed thee thou shalt give unto him. ^15And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt, and Jehovah thy God redeemed thee: therefore I command thee this thing to-day. ^16And it shall be, if he say unto thee, I will not go out from thee; because he loveth thee and thy house, because he is well with thee; ^17then thou shalt take an awl, and thrust it through his ear unto the door, and he shall be thy servant for ever. And also unto thy maid-servant thou shalt do likewise. ^18It shall not seem hard unto thee, when thou lettest him go free from thee; for to the double of the hire of a hireling hath he served thee six years: and Jehovah thy God will bless thee in all that thou doest.

^19All the firstling males that are born of thy herd and of thy flock thou shalt sanctify unto Jehovah thy God: thou shalt do no work with the firstling of thy herd, nor shear the firstling of thy flock. ^20Thou shalt eat it before Jehovah thy God year by year in the place which Jehovah shall choose, thou and thy household. ^21And if it have any blemish, as if it be lame or blind, any ill blemish whatsoever, thou shalt not sacrifice it unto Jehovah thy God. ^22Thou shalt eat it within thy gates: the unclean and the clean shall eat it alike, as the gazelle, and as the hart. ^23Only thou shalt not eat the blood thereof; thou shalt pour it out upon the ground as water.

Deuteronomy 16

16

^1Observe the month of Abib, and keep the passover unto Jehovah thy God; for in the month of Abib Jehovah thy God brought thee forth out of Egypt by night. ^2And thou shalt sacrifice the passover unto Jehovah thy God, of the flock and the herd, in the place which Jehovah shall choose, to cause his name to dwell there. ^3Thou shalt eat no leavened bread with it; seven days shalt thou eat unleavened bread therewith, even the bread of affliction; for thou camest forth out of the land of Egypt in haste: that thou mayest remember the day when thou camest forth out of the land of Egypt all the days of thy life. ^4And there shall be no leaven seen with thee in all thy borders seven days; neither shall any of the flesh, which thou sacrificest the first day at even, remain all night until the morning. ^5Thou mayest not sacrifice the passover within any of thy gates, which Jehovah thy God giveth thee; ^6but at the place which Jehovah thy God shall choose, to cause his name to dwell in, there thou shalt sacrifice the passover at even, at the going down of the sun, at the season that thou camest forth out of Egypt. ^7And thou shalt roast and eat it in the place which Jehovah thy God shall choose: and thou shalt turn in the morning, and go unto thy tents. ^8Six days thou shalt eat unleavened bread; and on the seventh day shall be a solemn assembly to Jehovah thy God; thou shalt do no work therein.

^9Seven weeks shalt thou number unto thee: from the time thou beginnest to put the sickle to the standing grain shalt thou begin to number seven weeks. ^10And thou shalt keep the feast of weeks unto Jehovah thy God with a tribute of a freewill-offering of thy hand, which thou shalt give, according as Jehovah thy God blesseth thee: ^11and thou shalt rejoice before Jehovah thy God, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy man-servant, and thy maid-servant, and the Levite that is within thy gates, and the sojourner, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are in the midst of thee, in the place which Jehovah thy God shall choose, to cause his name to dwell there. ^12And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt: and thou shalt observe and do these statutes.

^13Thou shalt keep the feast of tabernacles seven days, after that thou hast gathered in from thy threshing-floor and from thy winepress: ^14and thou shalt rejoice in thy feast, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy man-servant, and thy maid-servant, and the Levite, and the sojourner, and the fatherless, and the widow, that are within thy gates. ^15Seven days shalt thou keep a feast unto Jehovah thy God in the place which Jehovah shall choose; because Jehovah thy God will bless thee in all thine increase, and in all the work of thy hands, and thou shalt be altogether joyful. ^16Three times in a year shall all thy males appear before Jehovah thy God in the place which he shall choose: in the feast of unleavened bread, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of tabernacles; and they shall not appear before Jehovah empty: ^17every man shall give as he is able, according to the blessing of Jehovah thy God which he hath given thee.

^18Judges and officers shalt thou make thee in all thy gates, which Jehovah thy God giveth thee, according to thy tribes; and they shall judge the people with righteous judgment. ^19Thou shalt not wrest justice: thou shalt not respect persons; neither shalt thou take a bribe; for a bribe doth blind the eyes of the wise, and pervert the words of the righteous. ^20That which is altogether just shalt thou follow, that thou mayest live, and inherit the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee.

^21Thou shalt not plant thee an Asherah of any kind of tree beside the altar of Jehovah thy God, which thou shalt make thee. ^22Neither shalt thou set thee up a pillar; which Jehovah thy God hateth.

Deuteronomy 17

17

^1Thou shalt not sacrifice unto Jehovah thy God an ox, or a sheep, wherein is a blemish, or anything evil; for that is an abomination unto Jehovah thy God.

^2If there be found in the midst of thee, within any of thy gates which Jehovah thy God giveth thee, man or woman, that doeth that which is evil in the sight of Jehovah thy God, in transgressing his covenant, ^3and hath gone and served other gods, and worshipped them, or the sun, or the moon, or any of the host of heaven, which I have not commanded; ^4and it be told thee, and thou hast heard of it, then shalt thou inquire diligently; and, behold, if it be true, and the thing certain, that such abomination is wrought in Israel, ^5then shalt thou bring forth that man or that woman, who hath done this evil thing, unto thy gates, even the man or the woman; and thou shalt stone them to death with stones. ^6At the mouth of two witnesses, or three witnesses, shall he that is to die be put to death; at the mouth of one witness he shall not be put to death. ^7The hand of the witnesses shall be first upon him to put him to death, and afterward the hand of all the people. So thou shalt put away the evil from the midst of thee.

^8If there arise a matter too hard for thee in judgment, between blood and blood, between plea and plea, and between stroke and stroke, being matters of controversy within thy gates; then shalt thou arise, and get thee up unto the place which Jehovah thy God shall choose; ^9and thou shalt come unto the priests the Levites, and unto the judge that shall be in those days: and thou shalt inquire; and they shall show thee the sentence of judgment. ^10And thou shalt do according to the tenor of the sentence which they shall show thee from that place which Jehovah shall choose; and thou shalt observe to do according to all that they shall teach thee: ^11according to the tenor of the law which they shall teach thee, and according to the judgment which they shall tell thee, thou shalt do; thou shalt not turn aside from the sentence which they shall show thee, to the right hand, nor to the left. ^12And the man that doeth presumptuously, in not hearkening unto the priest that standeth to minister there before Jehovah thy God, or unto the judge, even that man shall die: and thou shalt put away the evil from Israel. ^13And all the people shall hear, and fear, and do no more presumptuously.

^14When thou art come unto the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee, and shalt possess it, and shalt dwell therein, and shalt say, I will set a king over me, like all the nations that are round about me; ^15thou shalt surely set him king over thee, whom Jehovah thy God shall choose: one from among thy brethren shalt thou set king over thee; thou mayest not put a foreigner over thee, who is not thy brother. ^16Only he shall not multiply horses to himself, nor cause the people to return to Egypt, to the end that he may multiply horses; forasmuch as Jehovah hath said unto you, Ye shall henceforth return no more that way. ^17Neither shall he multiply wives to himself, that his heart turn not away: neither shall he greatly multiply to himself silver and gold.

^18And it shall be, when he sitteth upon the throne of his kingdom, that he shall write him a copy of this law in a book, out of that which is before the priests the Levites: ^19and it shall be with him, and he shall read therein all the days of his life; that he may learn to fear Jehovah his God, to keep all the words of this law and these statutes, to do them; ^20that his heart be not lifted up above his brethren, and that he turn not aside from the commandment, to the right hand, or to the left: to the end that he may prolong his days in his kingdom, he and his children, in the midst of Israel.

Deuteronomy 18

18

^1The priests the Levites, even all the tribe of Levi, shall have no portion nor inheritance with Israel: they shall eat the offerings of Jehovah made by fire, and his inheritance. ^2And they shall have no inheritance among their brethren: Jehovah is their inheritance, as he hath spoken unto them. ^3And this shall be the priests' due from the people, from them that offer a sacrifice, whether it be ox or sheep, that they shall give unto the priest the shoulder, and the two cheeks, and the maw. ^4The first-fruits of thy grain, of thy new wine, and of thine oil, and the first of the fleece of thy sheep, shalt thou give him. ^5For Jehovah thy God hath chosen him out of all thy tribes, to stand to minister in the name of Jehovah, him and his sons for ever.

^6And if a Levite come from any of thy gates out of all Israel, where he sojourneth, and come with all the desire of his soul unto the place which Jehovah shall choose; ^7then he shall minister in the name of Jehovah his God, as all his brethren the Levites do, who stand there before Jehovah. ^8They shall have like portions to eat, besides that which cometh of the sale of his patrimony. ^9When thou art come into the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not learn to do after the abominations of those nations. ^10There shall not be found with thee any one that maketh his son or his daughter to pass through the fire, one that useth divination, one that practiseth augury, or an enchanter, or a sorcerer, ^11or a charmer, or a consulter with a familiar spirit, or a wizard, or a necromancer. ^12For whosoever doeth these things is an abomination unto Jehovah: and because of these abominations Jehovah thy God doth drive them out from before thee. ^13Thou shalt be perfect with Jehovah thy God. ^14For these nations, that thou shalt dispossess, hearken unto them that practise augury, and unto diviners; but as for thee, Jehovah thy God hath not suffered thee so to do.

^15Jehovah thy God will raise up unto thee a prophet from the midst of thee, of thy brethren, like unto me; unto him ye shall hearken; ^16according to all that thou desiredst of Jehovah thy God in Horeb in the day of the assembly, saying, Let me not hear again the voice of Jehovah my God, neither let me see this great fire any more, that I die not. ^17And Jehovah said unto me, They have well said that which they have spoken. ^18I will raise them up a prophet from among their brethren, like unto thee; and I will put my words in his mouth, and he shall speak unto them all that I shall command him. ^19And it shall come to pass, that whosoever will not hearken unto my words which he shall speak in my name, I will require it of him.

^20But the prophet, that shall speak a word presumptuously in my name, which I have not commanded him to speak, or that shall speak in the name of other gods, that same prophet shall die. ^21And if thou say in thy heart, How shall we know the word which Jehovah hath not spoken? ^22when a prophet speaketh in the name of Jehovah, if the thing follow not, nor come to pass, that is the thing which Jehovah hath not spoken: the prophet hath spoken it presumptuously, thou shalt not be afraid of him.

Deuteronomy 19

19

^1When Jehovah thy God shall cut off the nations, whose land Jehovah thy God giveth thee, and thou succeedest them, and dwellest in their cities, and in their houses; ^2thou shalt set apart three cities for thee in the midst of thy land, which Jehovah thy God giveth thee to possess it. ^3Thou shalt prepare thee the way, and divide the borders of thy land, which Jehovah thy God causeth thee to inherit, into three parts, that every manslayer may flee thither.

^4And this is the case of the manslayer, that shall flee thither and live: whoso killeth his neighbor unawares, and hated him not in time past; ^5as when a man goeth into the forest with his neighbor to hew wood, and his hand fetcheth a stroke with the axe to cut down the tree, and the head slippeth from the helve, and lighteth upon his neighbor, so that he dieth; he shall flee unto one of these cities and live: ^6lest the avenger of blood pursue the manslayer, while his heart is hot, and overtake him, because the way is long, and smite him mortally; whereas he was not worthy of death, inasmuch as he hated him not in time past. ^7Wherefore I command thee, saying, Thou shalt set apart three cities for thee. ^8And if Jehovah thy God enlarge thy border, as he hath sworn unto thy fathers, and give thee all the land which he promised to give unto thy fathers; ^9if thou shalt keep all this commandment to do it, which I command thee this day, to love Jehovah thy God, and to walk ever in his ways; then shalt thou add three cities more for thee, besides these three: ^10that innocent blood be not shed in the midst of thy land, which Jehovah thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, and so blood be upon thee.

^11But if any man hate his neighbor, and lie in wait for him, and rise up against him, and smite him mortally so that he dieth, and he flee into one of these cities; ^12then the elders of his city shall send and fetch him thence, and deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood, that he may die. ^13Thine eye shall not pity him, but thou shalt put away the innocent blood from Israel, that it may go well with thee.

^14Thou shalt not remove thy neighbor's landmark, which they of old time have set, in thine inheritance which thou shalt inherit, in the land that Jehovah thy God giveth thee to possess it.

^15One witness shall not rise up against a man for any iniquity, or for any sin, in any sin that he sinneth: at the mouth of two witnesses, or at the mouth of three witnesses, shall a matter be established. ^16If an unrighteous witness rise up against any man to testify against him of wrong-doing, ^17then both the men, between whom the controversy is, shall stand before Jehovah, before the priests and the judges that shall be in those days; ^18and the judges shall make diligent inquisition: and, behold, if the witness be a false witness, and have testified falsely against his brother; ^19then shall ye do unto him, as he had thought to do unto his brother: so shalt thou put away the evil from the midst of thee. ^20And those that remain shall hear, and fear, and shall henceforth commit no more any such evil in the midst of thee. ^21And thine eyes shall not pity; life shall go for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.

Deuteronomy 20

20

^1When thou goest forth to battle against thine enemies, and seest horses, and chariots, and a people more than thou, thou shalt not be afraid of them; for Jehovah thy God is with thee, who brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. ^2And it shall be, when ye draw nigh unto the battle, that the priest shall approach and speak unto the people, ^3and shall say unto them, Hear, O Israel, ye draw nigh this day unto battle against your enemies: let not your heart faint; fear not, nor tremble, neither be ye affrighted at them; ^4for Jehovah your God is he that goeth with you, to fight for you against your enemies, to save you. ^5And the officers shall speak unto the people, saying, What man is there that hath built a new house, and hath not dedicated it? let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man dedicate it. ^6And what man is there that hath planted a vineyard, and hath not used the fruit thereof? let him go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man use the fruit thereof. ^7And what man is there that hath betrothed a wife, and hath not taken her? let him go and return unto his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man take her. ^8And the officers shall speak further unto the people, and they shall say, What man is there that is fearful and faint-hearted? let him go and return unto his house, lest his brethren's heart melt as his heart. ^9And it shall be, when the officers have made an end of speaking unto the people, that they shall appoint captains of hosts at the head of the people.

^10When thou drawest nigh unto a city to fight against it, then proclaim peace unto it. ^11And it shall be, if it make thee answer of peace, and open unto thee, then it shall be, that all the people that are found therein shall become tributary unto thee, and shall serve thee. ^12And if it will make no peace with thee, but will make war against thee, then thou shalt besiege it: ^13and when Jehovah thy God delivereth it into thy hand, thou shalt smite every male thereof with the edge of the sword: ^14but the women, and the little ones, and the cattle, and all that is in the city, even all the spoil thereof, shalt thou take for a prey unto thyself; and thou shalt eat the spoil of thine enemies, which Jehovah thy God hath given thee. ^15Thus shalt thou do unto all the cities which are very far off from thee, which are not of the cities of these nations. ^16But of the cities of these peoples, that Jehovah thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, thou shalt save alive nothing that breatheth; ^17but thou shalt utterly destroy them: the Hittite, and the Amorite, the Canaanite, and the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite; as Jehovah thy God hath commanded thee; ^18that they teach you not to do after all their abominations, which they have done unto their gods; so would ye sin against Jehovah your God.

^19When thou shalt besiege a city a long time, in making war against it to take it, thou shalt not destroy the trees thereof by wielding an axe against them; for thou mayest eat of them, and thou shalt not cut them down; for is the tree of the field man, that it should be besieged of thee? ^20Only the trees of which thou knowest that they are not trees for food, thou shalt destroy and cut them down; and thou shalt build bulwarks against the city that maketh war with thee, until it fall.

Deuteronomy 21

21

^1If one be found slain in the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee to possess it, lying in the field, and it be not known who hath smitten him; ^2then thy elders and thy judges shall come forth, and they shall measure unto the cities which are round about him that is slain: ^3and it shall be, that the city which is nearest unto the slain man, even the elders of that city shall take a heifer of the herd, which hath not been wrought with, and which hath not drawn in the yoke; ^4and the elders of that city shall bring down the heifer unto a valley with running water, which is neither plowed nor sown, and shall break the heifer's neck there in the valley. ^5And the priests the sons of Levi shall come near; for them Jehovah thy God hath chosen to minister unto him, and to bless in the name of Jehovah; and according to their word shall every controversy and every stroke be. ^6And all the elders of that city, who are nearest unto the slain man, shall wash their hands over the heifer whose neck was broken in the valley; ^7and they shall answer and say, Our hands have not shed this blood, neither have our eyes seen it. ^8Forgive, O Jehovah, thy people Israel, whom thou hast redeemed, and suffer not innocent blood to remain in the midst of thy people Israel. And the blood shall be forgiven them. ^9So shalt thou put away the innocent blood from the midst of thee, when thou shalt do that which is right in the eyes of Jehovah.

^10When thou goest forth to battle against thine enemies, and Jehovah thy God delivereth them into thy hands, and thou carriest them away captive, ^11and seest among the captives a beautiful woman, and thou hast a desire unto her, and wouldest take her to thee to wife; ^12then thou shalt bring her home to thy house; and she shall shave her head, and pare her nails; ^13and she shall put the raiment of her captivity from off her, and shall remain in thy house, and bewail her father and her mother a full month: and after that thou shalt go in unto her, and be her husband, and she shall be thy wife. ^14And it shall be, if thou have no delight in her, then thou shalt let her go whither she will; but thou shalt not sell her at all for money, thou shalt not deal with her as a slave, because thou hast humbled her.

^15If a man have two wives, the one beloved, and the other hated, and they have borne him children, both the beloved and the hated; and if the first-born son be hers that was hated; ^16then it shall be, in the day that he causeth his sons to inherit that which he hath, that he may not make the son of the beloved the first-born before the son of the hated, who is the first-born: ^17but he shall acknowledge the first-born, the son of the hated, by giving him a double portion of all that he hath; for he is the beginning of his strength; the right of the first-born is his.

^18If a man have a stubborn and rebellious son, that will not obey the voice of his father, or the voice of his mother, and, though they chasten him, will not hearken unto them; ^19then shall his father and his mother lay hold on him, and bring him out unto the elders of his city, and unto the gate of his place; ^20and they shall say unto the elders of his city, This our son is stubborn and rebellious, he will not obey our voice; he is a glutton, and a drunkard. ^21And all the men of his city shall stone him to death with stones: so shalt thou put away the evil from the midst of thee; and all Israel shall hear, and fear.

^22And if a man have committed a sin worthy of death, and he be put to death, and thou hang him on a tree; ^23his body shall not remain all night upon the tree, but thou shalt surely bury him the same day; for he that is hanged is accursed of God; that thou defile not thy land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee for an inheritance.

Deuteronomy 22

22

^1Thou shalt not see thy brother's ox or his sheep go astray, and hide thyself from them: thou shalt surely bring them again unto thy brother. ^2And if thy brother be not nigh unto thee, or if thou know him not, then thou shalt bring it home to thy house, and it shall be with thee until thy brother seek after it, and thou shalt restore it to him. ^3And so shalt thou do with his ass; and so shalt thou do with his garment; and so shalt thou do with every lost thing of thy brother's, which he hath lost, and thou hast found: thou mayest not hide thyself. ^4Thou shalt not see thy brother's ass or his ox fallen down by the way, and hide thyself from them: thou shalt surely help him to lift them up again.

^5A woman shall not wear that which pertaineth unto a man, neither shall a man put on a woman's garment; for whosoever doeth these things is an abomination unto Jehovah thy God.

^6If a bird's nest chance to be before thee in the way, in any tree or on the ground, with young ones or eggs, and the dam sitting upon the young, or upon the eggs, thou shalt not take the dam with the young: ^7thou shalt surely let the dam go, but the young thou mayest take unto thyself; that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest prolong thy days.

^8When thou buildest a new house, then thou shalt make a battlement for thy roof, that thou bring not blood upon thy house, if any man fall from thence.

^9Thou shalt not sow thy vineyard with two kinds of seed, lest the whole fruit be forfeited, the seed which thou hast sown, and the increase of the vineyard. ^10Thou shalt not plow with an ox and an ass together. ^11Thou shalt not wear a mingled stuff, wool and linen together.

^12Thou shalt make thee fringes upon the four borders of thy vesture, wherewith thou coverest thyself.

^13If any man take a wife, and go in unto her, and hate her, ^14and lay shameful things to her charge, and bring up an evil name upon her, and say, I took this woman, and when I came nigh to her, I found not in her the tokens of virginity; ^15then shall the father of the damsel, and her mother, take and bring forth the tokens of the damsel's virginity unto the elders of the city in the gate; ^16and the damsel's father shall say unto the elders, I gave my daughter unto this man to wife, and he hateth her; ^17and, lo, he hath laid shameful things to her charge, saying, I found not in thy daughter the tokens of virginity; and yet these are the tokens of my daughter's virginity. And they shall spread the garment before the elders of the city. ^18And the elders of that city shall take the man and chastise him; ^19and they shall fine him a hundred shekels of silver, and give them unto the father of the damsel, because he hath brought up an evil name upon a virgin of Israel: and she shall be his wife; he may not put her away all his days. ^20But if this thing be true, that the tokens of virginity were not found in the damsel; ^21then they shall bring out the damsel to the door of her father's house, and the men of her city shall stone her to death with stones, because she hath wrought folly in Israel, to play the harlot in her father's house: so shalt thou put away the evil from the midst of thee.

^22If a man be found lying with a woman married to a husband, then they shall both of them die, the man that lay with the woman, and the woman: so shalt thou put away the evil from Israel.

^23If there be a damsel that is a virgin betrothed unto a husband, and a man find her in the city, and lie with her; ^24then ye shall bring them both out unto the gate of that city, and ye shall stone them to death with stones; the damsel, because she cried not, being in the city; and the man, because he hath humbled his neighbor's wife: so thou shalt put away the evil from the midst of thee.

^25But if the man find the damsel that is betrothed in the field, and the man force her, and lie with her; then the man only that lay with her shall die: ^26but unto the damsel thou shalt do nothing; there is in the damsel no sin worthy of death: for as when a man riseth against his neighbor, and slayeth him, even so is this matter; ^27for he found her in the field, the betrothed damsel cried, and there was none to save her.

^28If a man find a damsel that is a virgin, that is not betrothed, and lay hold on her, and lie with her, and they be found; ^29then the man that lay with her shall give unto the damsel's father fifty shekels of silver, and she shall be his wife, because he hath humbled her; he may not put her away all his days.

^30A man shall not take his father's wife, and shall not uncover his father's skirt.

Deuteronomy 23

23

^1He that is wounded in the stones, or hath his privy member cut off, shall not enter into the assembly of Jehovah.

^2A bastard shall not enter into the assembly of Jehovah; even to the tenth generation shall none of his enter into the assembly of Jehovah.

^3An Ammonite or a Moabite shall not enter into the assembly of Jehovah; even to the tenth generation shall none belonging to them enter into the assembly of Jehovah for ever: ^4because they met you not with bread and with water in the way, when ye came forth out of Egypt, and because they hired against thee Balaam the son of Beor from Pethor of Mesopotamia, to curse thee. ^5Nevertheless Jehovah thy God would not hearken unto Balaam; but Jehovah thy God turned the curse into a blessing unto thee, because Jehovah thy God loved thee. ^6Thou shalt not seek their peace nor their prosperity all thy days for ever.

^7Thou shalt not abhor an Edomite; for he is thy brother: thou shalt not abhor an Egyptian, because thou wast a sojourner in his land. ^8The children of the third generation that are born unto them shall enter into the assembly of Jehovah.

^9When thou goest forth in camp against thine enemies, then thou shalt keep thee from every evil thing. ^10If there be among you any man, that is not clean by reason of that which chanceth him by night, then shall he go abroad out of the camp, he shall not come within the camp: ^11but it shall be, when evening cometh on, he shall bathe himself in water; and when the sun is down, he shall come within the camp. ^12Thou shalt have a place also without the camp, whither thou shalt go forth abroad: ^13and thou shalt have a paddle among thy weapons; and it shall be, when thou sittest down abroad, thou shalt dig therewith, and shalt turn back and cover that which cometh from thee: ^14for Jehovah thy God walketh in the midst of thy camp, to deliver thee, and to give up thine enemies before thee; therefore shall thy camp be holy, that he may not see an unclean thing in thee, and turn away from thee.

^15Thou shalt not deliver unto his master a servant that is escaped from his master unto thee: ^16he shall dwell with thee, in the midst of thee, in the place which he shall choose within one of thy gates, where it pleaseth him best: thou shalt not oppress him.

^17There shall be no prostitute of the daughters of Israel, neither shall there be a sodomite of the sons of Israel. ^18Thou shalt not bring the hire of a harlot, or the wages of a dog, into the house of Jehovah thy God for any vow: for even both these are an abomination unto Jehovah thy God.

^19Thou shalt not lend upon interest to thy brother; interest of money, interest of victuals, interest of anything that is lent upon interest: ^20unto a foreigner thou mayest lend upon interest; but unto thy brother thou shalt not lend upon interest, that Jehovah thy God may bless thee in all that thou puttest thy hand unto, in the land whither thou goest in to possess it.

^21When thou shalt vow a vow unto Jehovah thy God, thou shalt not be slack to pay it: for Jehovah thy God will surely require it of thee; and it would be sin in thee. ^22But if thou shalt forbear to vow, it shall be no sin in thee. ^23That which is gone out of thy lips thou shalt observe and do; according as thou hast vowed unto Jehovah thy God, a freewill-offering, which thou hast promised with thy mouth.

^24When thou comest into thy neighbor's vineyard, then thou mayest eat of grapes thy fill at thine own pleasure; but thou shalt not put any in thy vessel. ^25When thou comest into thy neighbor's standing grain, then thou mayest pluck the ears with thy hand; but thou shalt not move a sickle unto thy neighbor's standing grain.

Deuteronomy 24

24

^1When a man taketh a wife, and marrieth her, then it shall be, if she find no favor in his eyes, because he hath found some unseemly thing in her, that he shall write her a bill of divorcement, and give it in her hand, and send her out of his house. ^2And when she is departed out of his house, she may go and be another man's wife. ^3And if the latter husband hate her, and write her a bill of divorcement, and give it in her hand, and send her out of his house; or if the latter husband die, who took her to be his wife; ^4her former husband, who sent her away, may not take her again to be his wife, after that she is defiled; for that is abomination before Jehovah: and thou shalt not cause the land to sin, which Jehovah thy God giveth thee for an inheritance.

^5When a man taketh a new wife, he shall not go out in the host, neither shall he be charged with any business: he shall be free at home one year, and shall cheer his wife whom he hath taken.

^6No man shall take the mill or the upper millstone to pledge; for he taketh a man's life to pledge.

^7If a man be found stealing any of his brethren of the children of Israel, and he deal with him as a slave, or sell him; then that thief shall die: so shalt thou put away the evil from the midst of thee.

^8Take heed in the plague of leprosy, that thou observe diligently, and do according to all that the priests the Levites shall teach you: as I commanded them, so ye shall observe to do. ^9Remember what Jehovah thy God did unto Miriam, by the way as ye came forth out of Egypt.

^10When thou dost lend thy neighbor any manner of loan, thou shalt not go into his house to fetch his pledge. ^11Thou shalt stand without, and the man to whom thou dost lend shall bring forth the pledge without unto thee. ^12And if he be a poor man, thou shalt not sleep with his pledge; ^13thou shalt surely restore to him the pledge when the sun goeth down, that he may sleep in his garment, and bless thee: and it shall be righteousness unto thee before Jehovah thy God.

^14Thou shalt not oppress a hired servant that is poor and needy, whether he be of thy brethren, or of thy sojourners that are in thy land within thy gates: ^15in his day thou shalt give him his hire, neither shall the sun go down upon it; for he is poor, and setteth his heart upon it: lest he cry against thee unto Jehovah, and it be sin unto thee.

^16The fathers shall not be put to death for the children, neither shall the children be put to death for the fathers: every man shall be put to death for his own sin.

^17Thou shalt not wrest the justice due to the sojourner, or to the fatherless, nor take the widow's raiment to pledge; ^18but thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt, and Jehovah thy God redeemed thee thence: therefore I command thee to do this thing.

^19When thou reapest thy harvest in thy field, and hast forgot a sheaf in the field, thou shalt not go again to fetch it: it shall be for the sojourner, for the fatherless, and for the widow; that Jehovah thy God may bless thee in all the work of thy hands. ^20When thou beatest thine olive-tree, thou shalt not go over the boughs again: it shall be for the sojourner, for the fatherless, and for the widow. ^21When thou gatherest the grapes of thy vineyard, thou shalt not glean it after thee: it shall be for the sojourner, for the fatherless, and for the widow. ^22And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt: therefore I command thee to do this thing.

Deuteronomy 25

25

^1If there be a controversy between men, and they come unto judgment, and the judges judge them; then they shall justify the righteous, and condemn the wicked; ^2and it shall be, if the wicked man be worthy to be beaten, that the judge shall cause him to lie down, and to be beaten before his face, according to his wickedness, by number. ^3Forty stripes he may give him, he shall not exceed; lest, if he should exceed, and beat him above these with many stripes, then thy brother should seem vile unto thee.

^4Thou shalt not muzzle the ox when he treadeth out the grain.

^5If brethren dwell together, and one of them die, and have no son, the wife of the dead shall not be married without unto a stranger: her husband's brother shall go in unto her, and take her to him to wife, and perform the duty of a husband's brother unto her. ^6And it shall be, that the first-born that she beareth shall succeed in the name of his brother that is dead, that his name be not blotted out of Israel. ^7And if the man like not to take his brother's wife, then his brother's wife shall go up to the gate unto the elders, and say, My husband's brother refuseth to raise up unto his brother a name in Israel; he will not perform the duty of a husband's brother unto me. ^8Then the elders of his city shall call him, and speak unto him: and if he stand, and say, I like not to take her; ^9then shall his brother's wife come unto him in the presence of the elders, and loose his shoe from off his foot, and spit in his face; and she shall answer and say, So shall it be done unto the man that doth not build up his brother's house. ^10And his name shall be called in Israel, The house of him that hath his shoe loosed.

^11When men strive together one with another, and the wife of the one draweth near to deliver her husband out of the hand of him that smiteth him, and putteth forth her hand, and taketh him by the secrets; ^12then thou shalt cut off her hand, thine eye shall have no pity.

^13Thou shalt not have in thy bag diverse weights, a great and a small. ^14Thou shalt not have in thy house diverse measures, a great and a small. ^15A perfect and just weight shalt thou have; a perfect and just measure shalt thou have: that thy days may be long in the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee. ^16For all that do such things, even all that do unrighteously, are an abomination unto Jehovah thy God.

^17Remember what Amalek did unto thee by the way as ye came forth out of Egypt; ^18how he met thee by the way, and smote the hindmost of thee, all that were feeble behind thee, when thou wast faint and weary; and he feared not God. ^19Therefore it shall be, when Jehovah thy God hath given thee rest from all thine enemies round about, in the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to possess it, that thou shalt blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under heaven; thou shalt not forget.

Deuteronomy 26

26

^1And it shall be, when thou art come in unto the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, and possessest it, and dwellest therein, ^2that thou shalt take of the first of all the fruit of the ground, which thou shalt bring in from thy land that Jehovah thy God giveth thee; and thou shalt put it in a basket, and shalt go unto the place which Jehovah thy God shall choose, to cause his name to dwell there. ^3And thou shalt come unto the priest that shall be in those days, and say unto him, I profess this day unto Jehovah thy God, that I am come unto the land which Jehovah sware unto our fathers to give us. ^4And the priest shall take the basket out of thy hand, and set it down before the altar of Jehovah thy God. ^5And thou shalt answer and say before Jehovah thy God, A Syrian ready to perish was my father; and he went down into Egypt, and sojourned there, few in number; and he became there a nation, great, mighty, and populous. ^6And the Egyptians dealt ill with us, and afflicted us, and laid upon us hard bondage: ^7and we cried unto Jehovah, the God of our fathers, and Jehovah heard our voice, and saw our affliction, and our toil, and our oppression; ^8and Jehovah brought us forth out of Egypt with a mighty hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with great terribleness, and with signs, and with wonders; ^9and he hath brought us into this place, and hath given us this land, a land flowing with milk and honey. ^10And now, behold, I have brought the first of the fruit of the ground, which thou, O Jehovah, hast given me. And thou shalt set it down before Jehovah thy God, and worship before Jehovah thy God: ^11and thou shalt rejoice in all the good which Jehovah thy God hath given unto thee, and unto thy house, thou, and the Levite, and the sojourner that is in the midst of thee.

^12When thou hast made an end of tithing all the tithe of thine increase in the third year, which is the year of tithing, then thou shalt give it unto the Levite, to the sojourner, to the fatherless, and to the widow, that they may eat within thy gates, and be filled. ^13And thou shalt say before Jehovah thy God, I have put away the hallowed things out of my house, and also have given them unto the Levite, and unto the sojourner, to the fatherless, and to the widow, according to all thy commandment which thou hast commanded me: I have not transgressed any of thy commandments, neither have I forgotten them: ^14I have not eaten thereof in my mourning, neither have I put away thereof, being unclean, nor given thereof for the dead: I have hearkened to the voice of Jehovah my God; I have done according to all that thou hast commanded me. ^15Look down from thy holy habitation, from heaven, and bless thy people Israel, and the ground which thou hast given us, as thou swarest unto our fathers, a land flowing with milk and honey.

^16This day Jehovah thy God commandeth thee to do these statutes and ordinances: thou shalt therefore keep and do them with all thy heart, and with all thy soul. ^17Thou hast avouched Jehovah this day to be thy God, and that thou wouldest walk in his ways, and keep his statutes, and his commandments, and his ordinances, and hearken unto his voice: ^18and Jehovah hath avouched thee this day to be a people for his own possession, as he hath promised thee, and that thou shouldest keep all his commandments; ^19and to make thee high above all nations that he hath made, in praise, and in name, and in honor; and that thou mayest be a holy people unto Jehovah thy God, as he hath spoken.

Deuteronomy 27

27

^1And Moses and the elders of Israel commanded the people, saying, Keep all the commandment which I command you this day. ^2And it shall be on the day when ye shall pass over the Jordan unto the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee, that thou shalt set thee up great stones, and plaster them with plaster: ^3and thou shalt write upon them all the words of this law, when thou art passed over; that thou mayest go in unto the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee, a land flowing with milk and honey, as Jehovah, the God of thy fathers, hath promised thee. ^4And it shall be, when ye are passed over the Jordan, that ye shall set up these stones, which I command you this day, in mount Ebal, and thou shalt plaster them with plaster. ^5And there shalt thou build an altar unto Jehovah thy God, an altar of stones: thou shalt lift up no iron tool upon them. ^6Thou shalt build the altar of Jehovah thy God of unhewn stones; and thou shalt offer burnt-offerings thereon unto Jehovah thy God: ^7and thou shalt sacrifice peace-offerings, and shalt eat there; and thou shalt rejoice before Jehovah thy God. ^8And thou shalt write upon the stones all the words of this law very plainly.

^9And Moses and the priests the Levites spake unto all Israel, saying, Keep silence, and hearken, O Israel: this day thou art become the people of Jehovah thy God. ^10Thou shalt therefore obey the voice of Jehovah thy God, and do his commandments and his statutes, which I command thee this day.

^11And Moses charged the people the same day, saying, ^12These shall stand upon mount Gerizim to bless the people, when ye are passed over the Jordan: Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Joseph, and Benjamin. ^13And these shall stand upon mount Ebal for the curse: Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali. ^14And the Levites shall answer, and say unto all the men of Israel with a loud voice,

^15Cursed be the man that maketh a graven or molten image, an abomination unto Jehovah, the work of the hands of the craftsman, and setteth it up in secret. And all the people shall answer and say, Amen.

^16Cursed be he that setteth light by his father or his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^17Cursed be he that removeth his neighbor's landmark. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^18Cursed be he that maketh the blind to wander out of the way. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^19Cursed be he that wresteth the justice due to the sojourner, fatherless, and widow. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^20Cursed be he that lieth with his father's wife, because he hath uncovered his father's skirt. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^21Cursed be he that lieth with any manner of beast. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^22Cursed be he that lieth with his sister, the daughter of his father, or the daughter of his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^23Cursed be he that lieth with his mother-in-law. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^24Cursed be he that smiteth his neighbor in secret. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^25Cursed be he that taketh a bribe to slay an innocent person. And all the people shall say, Amen.

^26Cursed be he that confirmeth not the words of this law to do them. And all the people shall say, Amen.

Deuteronomy 28

28

^1And it shall come to pass, if thou shalt hearken diligently unto the voice of Jehovah thy God, to observe to do all his commandments which I command thee this day, that Jehovah thy God will set thee on high above all the nations of the earth: ^2and all these blessings shall come upon thee, and overtake thee, if thou shalt hearken unto the voice of Jehovah thy God. ^3Blessed shalt thou be in the city, and blessed shalt thou be in the field. ^4Blessed shall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, and the fruit of thy beasts, the increase of thy cattle, and the young of thy flock. ^5Blessed shall be thy basket and thy kneading-trough. ^6Blessed shalt thou be when thou comest in, and blessed shalt thou be when thou goest out.

^7Jehovah will cause thine enemies that rise up against thee to be smitten before thee: they shall come out against thee one way, and shall flee before thee seven ways. ^8Jehovah will command the blessing upon thee in thy barns, and in all that thou puttest thy hand unto; and he will bless thee in the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee. ^9Jehovah will establish thee for a holy people unto himself, as he hath sworn unto thee; if thou shalt keep the commandments of Jehovah thy God, and walk in his ways. ^10And all the peoples of the earth shall see that thou art called by the name of Jehovah; and they shall be afraid of thee. ^11And Jehovah will make thee plenteous for good, in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy ground, in the land which Jehovah sware unto thy fathers to give thee. ^12Jehovah will open unto thee his good treasure the heavens, to give the rain of thy land in its season, and to bless all the work of thy hand: and thou shalt lend unto many nations, and thou shalt not borrow. ^13And Jehovah will make thee the head, and not the tail; and thou shalt be above only, and thou shalt not be beneath; if thou shalt hearken unto the commandments of Jehovah thy God, which I command thee this day, to observe and to do them, ^14and shalt not turn aside from any of the words which I command you this day, to the right hand, or to the left, to go after other gods to serve them.

^15But it shall come to pass, if thou wilt not hearken unto the voice of Jehovah thy God, to observe to do all his commandments and his statutes which I command thee this day, that all these curses shall come upon thee, and overtake thee. ^16Cursed shalt thou be in the city, and cursed shalt thou be in the field. ^17Cursed shall be thy basket and thy kneading-trough. ^18Cursed shall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, the increase of thy cattle, and the young of thy flock. ^19Cursed shalt thou be when thou comest in, and cursed shalt thou be when thou goest out.

^20Jehovah will send upon thee cursing, discomfiture, and rebuke, in all that thou puttest thy hand unto to do, until thou be destroyed, and until thou perish quickly; because of the evil of thy doings, whereby thou hast forsaken me. ^21Jehovah will make the pestilence cleave unto thee, until he hath consumed thee from off the land, whither thou goest in to possess it. ^22Jehovah will smite thee with consumption, and with fever, and with inflammation, and with fiery heat, and with the sword, and with blasting, and with mildew; and they shall pursue thee until thou perish. ^23And thy heaven that is over thy head shall be brass, and the earth that is under thee shall be iron. ^24Jehovah will make the rain of thy land powder and dust: from heaven shall it come down upon thee, until thou be destroyed.

^25Jehovah will cause thee to be smitten before thine enemies; thou shalt go out one way against them, and shalt flee seven ways before them: and thou shalt be tossed to and from among all the kingdoms of the earth. ^26And thy dead body shall be food unto all birds of the heavens, and unto the beasts of the earth; and there shall be none to frighten them away. ^27Jehovah will smite thee with the boil of Egypt, and with the emerods, and with the scurvy, and with the itch, whereof thou canst not be healed. ^28Jehovah will smite thee with madness, and with blindness, and with astonishment of heart; ^29and thou shalt grope at noonday, as the blind gropeth in darkness, and thou shalt not prosper in thy ways: and thou shalt be only oppressed and robbed alway, and there shall be none to save thee. ^30Thou shalt betroth a wife, and another man shall lie with her: thou shalt build a house, and thou shalt not dwell therein: thou shalt plant a vineyard, and shalt not use the fruit thereof. ^31Thine ox shall be slain before thine eyes, and thou shalt not eat thereof: thine ass shall be violently taken away from before thy face, and shall not be restored to thee: thy sheep shall be given unto thine enemies, and thou shalt have none to save thee. ^32Thy sons and thy daughters shall be given unto another people; and thine eyes shall look, and fail with longing for them all the day: and there shall be nought in the power of thy hand. ^33The fruit of thy ground, and all thy labors, shall a nation which thou knowest not eat up; and thou shalt be only oppressed and crushed alway; ^34so that thou shalt be mad for the sight of thine eyes which thou shalt see. ^35Jehovah will smite thee in the knees, and in the legs, with a sore boil, whereof thou canst not be healed, from the sole of thy foot unto the crown of thy head.

^36Jehovah will bring thee, and thy king whom thou shalt set over thee, unto a nation that thou hast not known, thou nor thy fathers; and there shalt thou serve other gods, wood and stone. ^37And thou shalt become an astonishment, a proverb, and a byword, among all the peoples whither Jehovah shall lead thee away. ^38Thou shalt carry much seed out into the field, and shalt gather little in; for the locust shall consume it. ^39Thou shalt plant vineyards and dress them, but thou shalt neither drink of the wine, nor gather the grapes; for the worm shall eat them. ^40Thou shalt have olive-trees throughout all thy borders, but thou shalt not anoint thyself with the oil; for thine olive shall cast its fruit. ^41Thou shalt beget sons and daughters, but they shall not be thine; for they shall go into captivity. ^42All thy trees and the fruit of thy ground shall the locust possess. ^43The sojourner that is in the midst of thee shall mount up above thee higher and higher; and thou shalt come down lower and lower. ^44He shall lend to thee, and thou shalt not lend to him: he shall be the head, and thou shalt be the tail. ^45And all these curses shall come upon thee, and shall pursue thee, and overtake thee, till thou be destroyed; because thou hearkenedst not unto the voice of Jehovah thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which he commanded thee: ^46and they shall be upon thee for a sign and for a wonder, and upon thy seed for ever.

^47Because thou servedst not Jehovah thy God with joyfulness, and with gladness of heart, by reason of the abundance of all things; ^48therefore shalt thou serve thine enemies that Jehovah shall send against thee, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakedness, and in want of all things: and he shall put a yoke of iron upon thy neck, until he have destroyed thee. ^49Jehovah will bring a nation against thee from far, from the end of the earth, as the eagle flieth; a nation whose tongue thou shalt not understand; ^50a nation of fierce countenance, that shall not regard the person of the old, nor show favor to the young, ^51and shall eat the fruit of thy cattle, and the fruit of thy ground, until thou be destroyed; that also shall not leave thee grain, new wine, or oil, the increase of thy cattle, or the young of thy flock, until they have caused thee to perish. ^52And they shall besiege thee in all thy gates, until thy high and fortified walls come down, wherein thou trustedst, throughout all thy land; and they shall besiege thee in all thy gates throughout all thy land, which Jehovah thy God hath given thee. ^53And thou shalt eat the fruit of thine own body, the flesh of thy sons and of thy daughters, whom Jehovah thy God hath given thee, in the siege and in the distress wherewith thine enemies shall distress thee. ^54The man that is tender among you, and very delicate, his eye shall be evil toward his brother, and toward the wife of his bosom, and toward the remnant of his children whom he hath remaining; ^55so that he will not give to any of them of the flesh of his children whom he shall eat, because he hath nothing left him, in the siege and in the distress wherewith thine enemy shall distress thee in all thy gates. ^56The tender and delicate woman among you, who would not adventure to set the sole of her foot upon the ground for delicateness and tenderness, her eye shall be evil toward the husband of her bosom, and toward her son, and toward her daughter, ^57and toward her young one that cometh out from between her feet, and toward her children whom she shall bear; for she shall eat them for want of all things secretly, in the siege and in the distress wherewith thine enemy shall distress thee in thy gates.

^58If thou wilt not observe to do all the words of this law that are written in this book, that thou mayest fear this glorious and fearful name, JEHOVAH THY GOD; ^59then Jehovah will make thy plagues wonderful, and the plagues of thy seed, even great plagues, and of long continuance, and sore sicknesses, and of long continuance. ^60And he will bring upon thee again all the diseases of Egypt, which thou wast afraid of; and they shall cleave unto thee. ^61Also every sickness, and every plague, which is not written in the book of this law, them will Jehovah bring upon thee, until thou be destroyed. ^62And ye shall be left few in number, whereas ye were as the stars of heaven for multitude; because thou didst not hearken unto the voice of Jehovah thy God. ^63And it shall come to pass, that, as Jehovah rejoiced over you to do you good, and to multiply you, so Jehovah will rejoice over you to cause you to perish, and to destroy you; and ye shall be plucked from off the land whither thou goest in to possess it. ^64And Jehovah will scatter thee among all peoples, from the one end of the earth even unto the other end of the earth; and there thou shalt serve other gods, which thou hast not known, thou nor thy fathers, even wood and stone. ^65And among these nations shalt thou find no ease, and there shall be no rest for the sole of thy foot: but Jehovah will give thee there a trembling heart, and failing of eyes, and pining of soul; ^66and thy life shall hang in doubt before thee; and thou shalt fear night and day, and shalt have no assurance of thy life. ^67In the morning thou shalt say, Would it were even! and at even thou shalt say, Would it were morning! for the fear of thy heart which thou shalt fear, and for the sight of thine eyes which thou shalt see. ^68And Jehovah will bring thee into Egypt again with ships, by the way whereof I said unto thee, Thou shalt see it no more again: and there ye shall sell yourselves unto your enemies for bondmen and for bondwomen, and no man shall buy you.

Deuteronomy 29

29

^1These are the words of the covenant which Jehovah commanded Moses to make with the children of Israel in the land of Moab, besides the covenant which he made with them in Horeb.

^2And Moses called unto all Israel, and said unto them, Ye have seen all that Jehovah did before your eyes in the land of Egypt unto Pharaoh, and unto all his servants, and unto all his land; ^3the great trials which thine eyes saw, the signs, and those great wonders: ^4but Jehovah hath not given you a heart to know, and eyes to see, and ears to hear, unto this day. ^5And I have led you forty years in the wilderness: your clothes are not waxed old upon you, and thy shoe is not waxed old upon thy foot. ^6Ye have not eaten bread, neither have ye drunk wine or strong drink; that ye may know that I am Jehovah your God. ^7And when ye came unto this place, Sihon the king of Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, came out against us unto battle, and we smote them: ^8and we took their land, and gave it for an inheritance unto the Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to the half-tribe of the Manassites. ^9Keep therefore the words of this covenant, and do them, that ye may prosper in all that ye do.

^10Ye stand this day all of you before Jehovah your God; your heads, your tribes, your elders, and your officers, even all the men of Israel, ^11your little ones, your wives, and thy sojourner that is in the midst of thy camps, from the hewer of thy wood unto the drawer of thy water; ^12that thou mayest enter into the covenant of Jehovah thy God, and into his oath, which Jehovah thy God maketh with thee this day; ^13that he may establish thee this day unto himself for a people, and that he may be unto thee a God, as he spake unto thee, and as he sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob.

^14Neither with you only do I make this covenant and this oath, ^15but with him that standeth here with us this day before Jehovah our God, and also with him that is not here with us this day ^16(for ye know how we dwelt in the land of Egypt, and how we came through the midst of the nations through which ye passed; ^17and ye have seen their abominations, and their idols, wood and stone, silver and gold, which were among them); ^18lest there should be among you man, or woman, or family, or tribe, whose heart turneth away this day from Jehovah our God, to go to serve the gods of those nations; lest there should be among you a root that beareth gall and wormwood; ^19and it come to pass, when he heareth the words of this curse, that he bless himself in his heart, saying, I shall have peace, though I walk in the stubbornness of my heart, to destroy the moist with the dry. ^20Jehovah will not pardon him, but then the anger of Jehovah and his jealousy will smoke against that man, and all the curse that is written in this book shall lie upon him, and Jehovah will blot out his name from under heaven. ^21And Jehovah will set him apart unto evil out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the curses of the covenant that is written in this book of the law.

^22And the generation to come, your children that shall rise up after you, and the foreigner that shall come from a far land, shall say, when they see the plagues of that land, and the sicknesses wherewith Jehovah hath made it sick; ^23and that the whole land thereof is brimstone, and salt, and a burning, that it is not sown, nor beareth, nor any grass groweth therein, like the overthrow of Sodom and Gomorrah, Admah and Zeboiim, which Jehovah overthrew in his anger, and in his wrath: ^24even all the nations shall say, Wherefore hath Jehovah done thus unto this land? what meaneth the heat of this great anger? ^25Then men shall say, Because they forsook the covenant of Jehovah, the God of their fathers, which he made with them when he brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, ^26and went and served other gods, and worshipped them, gods that they knew not, and that he had not given unto them: ^27therefore the anger of Jehovah was kindled against this land, to bring upon it all the curse that is written in this book; ^28and Jehovah rooted them out of their land in anger, and in wrath, and in great indignation, and cast them into another land, as at this day. ^29The secret things belong unto Jehovah our God; but the things that are revealed belong unto us and to our children for ever, that we may do all the words of this law.

Deuteronomy 30

30

^1And it shall come to pass, when all these things are come upon thee, the blessing and the curse, which I have set before thee, and thou shalt call them to mind among all the nations, whither Jehovah thy God hath driven thee, ^2and shalt return unto Jehovah thy God, and shalt obey his voice according to all that I command thee this day, thou and thy children, with all thy heart, and with all thy soul; ^3that then Jehovah thy God will turn thy captivity, and have compassion upon thee, and will return and gather thee from all the peoples, whither Jehovah thy God hath scattered thee. ^4If any of thine outcasts be in the uttermost parts of heaven, from thence will Jehovah thy God gather thee, and from thence will he fetch thee: ^5and Jehovah thy God will bring thee into the land which thy fathers possessed, and thou shalt possess it; and he will do thee good, and multiply thee above thy fathers. ^6And Jehovah thy God will circumcise thy heart, and the heart of thy seed, to love Jehovah thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, that thou mayest live. ^7And Jehovah thy God will put all these curses upon thine enemies, and on them that hate thee, that persecuted thee. ^8And thou shalt return and obey the voice of Jehovah, and do all his commandments which I command thee this day. ^9And Jehovah thy God will make thee plenteous in all the work of thy hand, in the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy ground, for good: for Jehovah will again rejoice over thee for good, as he rejoiced over thy fathers; ^10if thou shalt obey the voice of Jehovah thy God, to keep his commandments and his statutes which are written in this book of the law; if thou turn unto Jehovah thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul.

^11For this commandment which I command thee this day, it is not too hard for thee, neither is it far off. ^12It is not in heaven, that thou shouldest say, Who shall go up for us to heaven, and bring it unto us, and make us to hear it, that we may do it? ^13Neither is it beyond the sea, that thou shouldest say, Who shall go over the sea for us, and bring it unto us, and make us to hear it, that we may do it? ^14But the word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayest do it.

^15See, I have set before thee this day life and good, and death and evil; ^16in that I command thee this day to love Jehovah thy God, to walk in his ways, and to keep his commandments and his statutes and his ordinances, that thou mayest live and multiply, and that Jehovah thy God may bless thee in the land whither thou goest in to possess it. ^17But if thy heart turn away, and thou wilt not hear, but shalt be drawn away, and worship other gods, and serve them; ^18I denounce unto you this day, that ye shall surely perish; ye shall not prolong your days in the land, whither thou passest over the Jordan to go in to possess it. ^19I call heaven and earth to witness against you this day, that I have set before thee life and death, the blessing and the curse: therefore choose life, that thou mayest live, thou and thy seed; ^20to love Jehovah thy God, to obey his voice, and to cleave unto him; for he is thy life, and the length of thy days; that thou mayest dwell in the land which Jehovah sware unto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give them.

Deuteronomy 31

31

^1And Moses went and spake these words unto all Israel. ^2And he said unto them, I am a hundred and twenty years old this day; I can no more go out and come in: and Jehovah hath said unto me, Thou shalt not go over this Jordan. ^3Jehovah thy God, he will go over before thee; he will destroy these nations from before thee, and thou shalt dispossess them: and Joshua, he shall go over before thee, as Jehovah hath spoken. ^4And Jehovah will do unto them as he did to Sihon and to Og, the kings of the Amorites, and unto their land; whom he destroyed. ^5And Jehovah will deliver them up before you, and ye shall do unto them according unto all the commandment which I have commanded you. ^6Be strong and of good courage, fear not, nor be affrighted at them: for Jehovah thy God, he it is that doth go with thee; he will not fail thee, nor forsake thee. ^7And Moses called unto Joshua, and said unto him in the sight of all Israel, Be strong and of good courage: for thou shalt go with this people into the land which Jehovah hath sworn unto their fathers to give them; and thou shalt cause them to inherit it. ^8And Jehovah, he it is that doth go before thee; he will be with thee, he will not fail thee, neither forsake thee: fear not, neither be dismayed.

^9And Moses wrote this law, and delivered it unto the priests the sons of Levi, that bare the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, and unto all the elders of Israel. ^10And Moses commanded them, saying, At the end of every seven years, in the set time of the year of release, in the feast of tabernacles, ^11when all Israel is come to appear before Jehovah thy God in the place which he shall choose, thou shalt read this law before all Israel in their hearing. ^12Assemble the people, the men and the women and the little ones, and thy sojourner that is within thy gates, that they may hear, and that they may learn, and fear Jehovah your God, and observe to do all the words of this law; ^13and that their children, who have not known, may hear, and learn to fear Jehovah your God, as long as ye live in the land whither ye go over the Jordan to possess it.

^14And Jehovah said unto Moses, Behold, thy days approach that thou must die: call Joshua, and present yourselves in the tent of meeting, that I may give him a charge. And Moses and Joshua went, and presented themselves in the tent of meeting. ^15And Jehovah appeared in the Tent in a pillar of cloud: and the pillar of cloud stood over the door of the Tent. ^16And Jehovah said unto Moses, Behold, thou shalt sleep with thy fathers; and this people will rise up, and play the harlot after the strange gods of the land, whither they go to be among them, and will forsake me, and break my covenant which I have made with them. ^17Then my anger shall be kindled against them in that day, and I will forsake them, and I will hide my face from them, and they shall be devoured, and many evils and troubles shall come upon them; so that they will say in that day, Are not these evils come upon us because our God is not among us? ^18And I will surely hide my face in that day for all the evil which they shall have wrought, in that they are turned unto other gods. ^19Now therefore write ye this song for you, and teach thou it the children of Israel: put it in their mouths, that this song may be a witness for me against the children of Israel. ^20For when I shall have brought them into the land which I sware unto their fathers, flowing with milk and honey, and they shall have eaten and filled themselves, and waxed fat; then will they turn unto other gods, and serve them, and despise me, and break my covenant. ^21And it shall come to pass, when many evils and troubles are come upon them, that this song shall testify before them as a witness; for it shall not be forgotten out of the mouths of their seed: for I know their imagination which they frame this day, before I have brought them into the land which I sware. ^22So Moses wrote this song the same day, and taught it the children of Israel. ^23And he gave Joshua the son of Nun a charge, and said, Be strong and of good courage; for thou shalt bring the children of Israel into the land which I sware unto them: and I will be with thee.

^24And it came to pass, when Moses had made an end of writing the words of this law in a book, until they were finished, ^25that Moses commanded the Levites, that bare the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, saying, ^26Take this book of the law, and put it by the side of the ark of the covenant of Jehovah your God, that it may be there for a witness against thee. ^27For I know thy rebellion, and thy stiff neck: behold, while I am yet alive with you this day, ye have been rebellious against Jehovah; and how much more after my death? ^28Assemble unto me all the elders of your tribes, and your officers, that I may speak these words in their ears, and call heaven and earth to witness against them. ^29For I know that after my death ye will utterly corrupt yourselves, and turn aside from the way which I have commanded you; and evil will befall you in the latter days; because ye will do that which is evil in the sight of Jehovah, to provoke him to anger through the work of your hands.

^30And Moses spake in the ears of all the assembly of Israel the words of this song, until they were finished.

Deuteronomy 34

34

^1And Moses went up from the plains of Moab unto mount Nebo, to the top of Pisgah, that is over against Jericho. And Jehovah showed him all the land of Gilead, unto Dan, ^2and all Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim and Manasseh, and all the land of Judah, unto the hinder sea, ^3and the South, and the Plain of the valley of Jericho the city of palm-trees, unto Zoar. ^4And Jehovah said unto him, This is the land which I sware unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, saying, I will give it unto thy seed: I have caused thee to see it with thine eyes, but thou shalt not go over thither. ^5So Moses the servant of Jehovah died there in the land of Moab, according to the word of Jehovah. ^6And he buried him in the valley in the land of Moab over against Beth-peor: but no man knoweth of his sepulchre unto this day. ^7And Moses was a hundred and twenty years old when he died: his eye was not dim, nor his natural force abated. ^8And the children of Israel wept for Moses in the plains of Moab thirty days: so the days of weeping in the mourning for Moses were ended.

^9And Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom; for Moses had laid his hands upon him: and the children of Israel hearkened unto him, and did as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^10And there hath not arisen a prophet since in Israel like unto Moses, whom Jehovah knew face to face, ^11in all the signs and the wonders, which Jehovah sent him to do in the land of Egypt, to Pharaoh, and to all his servants, and to all his land, ^12and in all the mighty hand, and in all the great terror, which Moses wrought in the sight of all Israel.

Ecclesiastes 2

2

^1I said in my heart, Come now, I will prove thee with mirth; therefore enjoy pleasure: and, behold, this also was vanity. ^2I said of laughter, It is mad; and of mirth, What doeth it? ^3I searched in my heart how to cheer my flesh with wine, my heart yet guiding me with wisdom, and how to lay hold on folly, till I might see what it was good for the sons of men that they should do under heaven all the days of their life. ^4I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me vineyards; ^5I made me gardens and parks, and I planted trees in them of all kinds of fruit; ^6I made me pools of water, to water therefrom the forest where trees were reared; ^7I bought men-servants and maid-servants, and had servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of herds and flocks, above all that were before me in Jerusalem; ^8I gathered me also silver and gold, and the treasure of kings and of the provinces; I gat me men-singers and women-singers, and the delights of the sons of men, musical instruments, and that of all sorts. ^9So I was great, and increased more than all that were before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom remained with me. ^10And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them; I withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced because of all my labor; and this was my portion from all my labor. ^11Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought, and on the labor that I had labored to do; and, behold, all was vanity and a striving after wind, and there was no profit under the sun. ^12And I turned myself to behold wisdom, and madness, and folly: for what can the man do that cometh after the king? even that which hath been done long ago. ^13Then I saw that wisdom excelleth folly, as far as light excelleth darkness. ^14The wise man's eyes are in his head, and the fool walketh in darkness: and yet I perceived that one event happeneth to them all. ^15Then said I in my heart, As it happeneth to the fool, so will it happen even to me; and why was I then more wise? Then said I in my heart, that this also is vanity. ^16For of the wise man, even as of the fool, there is no remembrance for ever; seeing that in the days to come all will have been long forgotten. And how doth the wise man die even as the fool! ^17So I hated life, because the work that is wrought under the sun was grievous unto me; for all is vanity and a striving after wind. ^18And I hated all my labor wherein I labored under the sun, seeing that I must leave it unto the man that shall be after me. ^19And who knoweth whether he will be a wise man or a fool? yet will he have rule over all my labor wherein I have labored, and wherein I have showed myself wise under the sun. This also is vanity. ^20Therefore I turned about to cause my heart to despair concerning all the labor wherein I had labored under the sun. ^21For there is a man whose labor is with wisdom, and with knowledge, and with skilfulness; yet to a man that hath not labored therein shall he leave it for his portion. This also is vanity and a great evil. ^22For what hath a man of all his labor, and of the striving of his heart, wherein he laboreth under the sun? ^23For all his days are but sorrows, and his travail is grief; yea, even in the night his heart taketh no rest. This also is vanity. ^24There is nothing better for a man than that he should eat and drink, and make his soul enjoy good in his labor. This also I saw, that it is from the hand of God. ^25For who can eat, or who can have enjoyment, more than I? ^26For to the man that pleaseth him God giveth wisdom, and knowledge, and joy; but to the sinner he giveth travail, to gather and to heap up, that he may give to him that pleaseth God. This also is vanity and a striving after wind.

Ecclesiastes 3

3

^1For everything there is a season, and a time for very purpose under heaven: ^2a time to be born, and a time to die; a time to plant, and a time to pluck up that which is planted; ^3a time to kill, and a time to heal; a time to break down, and a time to build up; ^4a time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to dance; ^5a time to cast away stones, and a time to gather stones together; a time to embrace, and a time to refrain from embracing; ^6a time to seek, and a time to lose; a time to keep, and a time to cast away; ^7a time to rend, and a time to sew; a time to keep silence, and a time to speak; ^8a time to love, and a time to hate; a time for war, and a time for peace. ^9What profit hath he that worketh in that wherein he laboreth? ^10I have seen the travail which God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised therewith. ^11He hath made everything beautiful in its time: also he hath set eternity in their heart, yet so that man cannot find out the work that God hath done from the beginning even to the end. ^12I know that there is nothing better for them, than to rejoice, and to do good so long as they live. ^13And also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy good in all his labor, is the gift of God. ^14I know that, whatsoever God doeth, it shall be for ever: nothing can be put to it, nor anything taken from it; and God hath done it, that men should fear before him. ^15That which is hath been long ago; and that which is to be hath long ago been: and God seeketh again that which is passed away. ^16And moreover I saw under the sun, in the place of justice, that wickedness was there; and in the place of righteousness, that wickedness was there. ^17I said in my heart, God will judge the righteous and the wicked; for there is a time there for every purpose and for every work. ^18I said in my heart, It is because of the sons of men, that God may prove them, and that they may see that they themselves are but as beasts. ^19For that which befalleth the sons of men befalleth beasts; even one thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the other; yea, they have all one breath; and man hath no preeminence above the beasts: for all is vanity. ^20All go unto one place; all are of the dust, and all turn to dust again. ^21Who knoweth the spirit of man, whether it goeth upward, and the spirit of the beast, whether it goeth downward to the earth? ^22Wherefore I saw that there is nothing better, than that a man should rejoice in his works; for that is his portion: for who shall bring him back to see what shall be after him?

Ecclesiastes 4

4

^1Then I returned and saw all the oppressions that are done under the sun: and, behold, the tears of such as were oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors there was power; but they had no comforter. ^2Wherefore I praised the dead that have been long dead more than the living that are yet alive; ^3yea, better than them both did I esteem him that hath not yet been, who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun. ^4Then I saw all labor and every skilful work, that for this a man is envied of his neighbor. This also is vanity and a striving after wind. ^5The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own flesh. ^6Better is a handful, with quietness, than two handfuls with labor and striving after wind. ^7Then I returned and saw vanity under the sun. ^8There is one that is alone, and he hath not a second; yea, he hath neither son nor brother; yet is there no end of all his labor, neither are his eyes satisfied with riches. For whom then, saith he, do I labor, and deprive my soul of good? This also is vanity, yea, it is a sore travail. ^9Two are better than one, because they have a good reward for their labor. ^10For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow; but woe to him that is alone when he falleth, and hath not another to lift him up. ^11Again, if two lie together, then they have warmth; but how can one be warm alone? ^12And if a man prevail against him that is alone, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken. ^13Better is a poor and wise youth than an old and foolish king, who knoweth not how to receive admonition any more. ^14For out of prison he came forth to be king; yea, even in his kingdom he was born poor. ^15I saw all the living that walk under the sun, that they were with the youth, the second, that stood up in his stead. ^16There was no end of all the people, even of all them over whom he was: yet they that come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and a striving after wind.

Ecclesiastes 5

5

^1Keep thy foot when thou goest to the house of God; for to draw nigh to hear is better than to give the sacrifice of fools: for they know not that they do evil. ^2Be not rash with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be hasty to utter anything before God; for God is in heaven, and thou upon earth: therefore let thy words be few. ^3For a dream cometh with a multitude of business, and a fool's voice with a multitude of words. ^4When thou vowest a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for he hath no pleasure in fools: pay that which thou vowest. ^5Better is it that thou shouldest not vow, than that thou shouldest vow and not pay. ^6Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin; neither say thou before the angel, that is was an error: wherefore should God be angry at thy voice, and destroy the work of thy hands? ^7For in the multitude of dreams there are vanities, and in many words: but fear thou God. ^8If thou seest the oppression of the poor, and the violent taking away of justice and righteousness in a province, marvel not at the matter: for one higher than the high regardeth; and there are higher than they. ^9Moreover the profit of the earth is for all: the king himself is served by the field. ^10He that loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he that loveth abundance, with increase: this also is vanity. ^11When goods increase, they are increased that eat them; and what advantage is there to the owner thereof, save the beholding of them with his eyes? ^12The sleep of a laboring man is sweet, whether he eat little or much; but the fulness of the rich will not suffer him to sleep. ^13There is a grievous evil which I have seen under the sun, namely, riches kept by the owner thereof to his hurt: ^14and those riches perish by evil adventure; and if he hath begotten a son, there is nothing in his hand. ^15As he came forth from his mother's womb, naked shall he go again as he came, and shall take nothing for his labor, which he may carry away in his hand. ^16And this also is a grievous evil, that in all points as he came, so shall he go: and what profit hath he that he laboreth for the wind? ^17All his days also he eateth in darkness, and he is sore vexed, and hath sickness and wrath. ^18Behold, that which I have seen to be good and to be comely is for one to eat and to drink, and to enjoy good in all his labor, wherein he laboreth under the sun, all the days of his life which God hath given him: for this is his portion. ^19Every man also to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoice in his labor-this is the gift of God. ^20For he shall not much remember the days of his life; because God answereth him in the joy of his heart.

Ecclesiastes 6

6

^1There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, and it is heavy upon men: ^2a man to whom God giveth riches, wealth, and honor, so that he lacketh nothing for his soul of all that he desireth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but an alien eateth it; this is vanity, and it is an evil disease. ^3If a man beget a hundred children, and live many years, so that the days of his years are many, but his soul be not filled with good, and moreover he have no burial; I say, that an untimely birth is better than he: ^4for it cometh in vanity, and departeth in darkness, and the name thereof is covered with darkness; ^5moreover it hath not seen the sun nor known it; this hath rest rather than the other: ^6yea, though he live a thousand years twice told, and yet enjoy no good, do not all go to one place? ^7All the labor of man is for his mouth, and yet the appetite is not filled. ^8For what advantage hath the wise more than the fool? or what hath the poor man, that knoweth how to walk before the living? ^9Better is the sight of the eyes than the wandering of the desire: this also is vanity and a striving after wind. ^10Whatsoever hath been, the name thereof was given long ago; and it is know what man is; neither can he contend with him that is mightier than he. ^11Seeing there are many things that increase vanity, what is man the better? ^12For who knoweth what is good for man in his life, all the days of his vain life which he spendeth as a shadow? for who can tell a man what shall be after him under the sun?

Ecclesiastes 7

7

^1A good name is better than precious oil; and the day of death, than the day of one's birth. ^2It is better to go to the house of mourning than to go to the house of feasting: for that is the end of all men; and the living will lay it to his heart. ^3Sorrow is better than laughter; for by the sadness of the countenance the heart is made glad. ^4The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning; but the heart of fools is in the house of mirth. ^5It is better to hear the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools. ^6For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the laughter of the fool: this also is vanity. ^7Surely extortion maketh the wise man foolish; and a bribe destroyeth the understanding. ^8Better is the end of a thing than the beginning thereof; and the patient in spirit is better than the proud in spirit. ^9Be not hasty in thy spirit to be angry; for anger resteth in the bosom of fools. ^10Say not thou, What is the cause that the former days were better than these? for thou dost not inquire wisely concerning this. ^11Wisdom is as good as an inheritance; yea, more excellent is it for them that see the sun. ^12For wisdom is a defence, even as money is a defence; but the excellency of knowledge is, that wisdom preserveth the life of him that hath it. ^13Consider the work of God: for who can make that straight, which he hath made crooked? ^14In the day of prosperity be joyful, and in the day of adversity consider; yea, God hath made the one side by side with the other, to the end that man should not find out anything that shall be after him. ^15All this have I seen in my days of vanity: there is a righteous man that perisheth in his righteousness, and there is a wicked man that prolongeth his life in his evil-doing. ^16Be not righteous overmuch; neither make thyself overwise: why shouldest thou destroy thyself? ^17Be not overmuch wicked, neither be thou foolish: why shouldest thou die before thy time? ^18It is good that thou shouldest take hold of this; yea, also from that withdraw not thy hand: for he that feareth God shall come forth from them all. ^19Wisdom is a strength to the wise man more than ten rulers that are in a city. ^20Surely there is not a righteous man upon earth, that doeth good, and sinneth not. ^21Also take not heed unto all words that are spoken, lest thou hear thy servant curse thee; ^22for oftentimes also thine own heart knoweth that thou thyself likewise hast cursed others. ^23All this have I proved in wisdom: I said, I will be wise; but it was far from me. ^24That which is, is far off and exceeding deep; who can find it out? ^25I turned about, and my heart was set to know and to search out, and to seek wisdom and the reason of things, and to know that wickedness is folly, and that foolishness is madness. ^26And I find more bitter than death the woman whose heart is snares and nets, and whose hands are bands: whoso pleaseth God shall escape from her; but the sinner shall be taken by her. ^27Behold, this have I found, saith the Preacher, laying one thing to another, to find out the account; ^28which my soul still seeketh, but I have not found: one man among a thousand have I found; but a woman among all those have I not found. ^29Behold, this only have I found: that God made man upright; but they have sought out many inventions.

Ecclesiastes 8

8

^1Who is as the wise man? and who knoweth the interpretation of a thing? A man's wisdom maketh his face to shine, and the hardness of his face is changed. ^2I counsel thee, Keep the king's command, and that in regard of the oath of God. ^3Be not hasty to go out of his presence; persist not in an evil thing: for he doeth whatsoever pleaseth him. ^4For the king's word hath power; and who may say unto him, What doest thou? ^5Whoso keepeth the commandment shall know no evil thing; and a wise man's heart discerneth time and judgment: ^6for to every purpose there is a time and judgment; because the misery of man is great upon him: ^7for he knoweth not that which shall be; for who can tell him how it shall be? ^8There is no man that hath power over the spirit to retain the spirit; neither hath he power over the day of death; and there is no discharge in war: neither shall wickedness deliver him that is given to it. ^9All this have I seen, and applied my heart unto every work that is done under the sun: there is a time wherein one man hath power over another to his hurt. ^10So I saw the wicked buried, and they came to the grave; and they that had done right went away from the holy place, and were forgotten in the city: this also is vanity. ^11Because sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is fully set in them to do evil. ^12Though a sinner do evil a hundred times, and prolong his days, yet surely I know that it shall be well with them that fear God, that fear before him: ^13but it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he prolong his days, which are as a shadow; because he feareth not before God. ^14There is a vanity which is done upon the earth, that there are righteous men unto whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked; again, there are wicked men to whom it happeneth according to the work of the righteous: I said that this also is vanity. ^15Then I commended mirth, because a man hath no better thing under the sun, than to eat, and to drink, and to be joyful: for that shall abide with him in his labor all the days of his life which God hath given him under the sun. ^16When I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to see the business that is done upon the earth (for also there is that neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eyes), ^17then I beheld all the work of God, that man cannot find out the work that is done under the sun: because however much a man labor to seek it out, yet he shall not find it; yea moreover, though a wise man think to know it, yet shall he not be able to find it.

Ecclesiastes 9

9

^1For all this I laid to my heart, even to explore all this: that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, are in the hand of God; whether it be love or hatred, man knoweth it not; all is before them. ^2All things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous and to the wicked; to the good and to the clean and to the unclean; to him that sacrificeth and to him that sacrificeth not; as is the good, so is the sinner; and he that sweareth, as he that feareth an oath. ^3This is an evil in all that is done under the sun, that there is one event unto all: yea also, the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that they go to the dead. ^4For to him that is joined with all the living there is hope; for a living dog is better than a dead lion. ^5For the living know that they shall die: but the dead know not anything, neither have they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten. ^6As well their love, as their hatred and their envy, is perished long ago; neither have they any more a portion for ever in anything that is done under the sun. ^7Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart; for God hath already accepted thy works. ^8Let thy garments be always white; and let not thy head lack oil. ^9Live joyfully with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of thy life of vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun, all thy days of vanity: for that is thy portion in life, and in thy labor wherein thou laborest under the sun. ^10Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in Sheol, whither thou goest. ^11I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favor to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all. ^12For man also knoweth not his time: as the fishes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the snare, even so are the sons of men snared in an evil time, when it falleth suddenly upon them. ^13I have also seen wisdom under the sun on this wise, and it seemed great unto me: ^14There was a little city, and few men within it; and there came a great king against it, and besieged it, and built great bulwarks against it. ^15Now there was found in it a poor wise man, and he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor man. ^16Then said I, Wisdom is better than strength: nevertheless the poor man's wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard. ^17The words of the wise heard in quiet are better than the cry of him that ruleth among fools. ^18Wisdom is better than weapons of war; but one sinner destroyeth much good.

Ecclesiastes 10

10

^1Dead flies cause the oil of the perfumer to send forth an evil odor; so doth a little folly outweigh wisdom and honor. ^2A wise man's heart is at his right hand; but a fool's heart at his left. ^3Yea also, when the fool walketh by the way, his understanding faileth him, and he saith to every one that he is a fool. ^4If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not thy place; for gentleness allayeth great offences. ^5There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, as it were an error which proceedeth from the ruler: ^6folly is set in great dignity, and the rich sit in a low place. ^7I have seen servants upon horses, and princes walking like servants upon the earth. ^8He that diggeth a pit shall fall into it; and whoso breaketh through a wall, a serpent shall bite him. ^9Whoso heweth out stones shall be hurt therewith; and he that cleaveth wood is endangered thereby. ^10If the iron be blunt, and one do not whet the edge, then must he put to more strength: but wisdom is profitable to direct. ^11If the serpent bite before it is charmed, then is there no advantage in the charmer. ^12The words of a wise man's mouth are gracious; but the lips of a fool will swallow up himself. ^13The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishness; and the end of his talk is mischievous madness. ^14A fool also multiplieth words: yet man knoweth not what shall be; and that which shall be after him, who can tell him? ^15The labor of fools wearieth every one of them; for he knoweth not how to go to the city. ^16Woe to thee, O land, when thy king is a child, and thy princes eat in the morning! ^17Happy art thou, O land, when thy king is the son of nobles, and thy princes eat in due season, for strength, and not for drunkenness! ^18By slothfulness the roof sinketh in; and through idleness of the hands the house leaketh. ^19A feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh glad the life; and money answereth all things. ^20Revile not the king, no, not in thy thought; and revile not the rich in thy bedchamber: for a bird of the heavens shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall tell the matter.

Ecclesiastes 11

11

^1Cast thy bread upon the waters; for thou shalt find it after many days. ^2Give a portion to seven, yea, even unto eight; for thou knowest not what evil shall be upon the earth. ^3If the clouds be full of rain, they empty themselves upon the earth; and if a tree fall toward the south, or toward the north, in the place where the tree falleth, there shall it be. ^4He that observeth the wind shall not sow; and he that regardeth the clouds shall not reap. ^5As thou knowest not what is the way of the wind, nor how the bones do grow in the womb of her that is with child; even so thou knowest not the work of God who doeth all. ^6In the morning sow thy seed, and in the evening withhold not thy hand; for thou knowest not which shall prosper, whether this or that, or whether they both shall be alike good. ^7Truly the light is sweet, and a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to behold the sun. ^8Yea, if a man live many years, let him rejoice in them all; but let him remember the days of darkness, for they shall be many. All that cometh is vanity. ^9Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the sight of thine eyes; but know thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgment. ^10Therefore remove sorrow from thy heart, and put away evil from thy flesh; for youth and the dawn of life are vanity.

Ecclesiastes 12

12

^1Remember also thy Creator in the days of thy youth, before the evil days come, and the years draw nigh, when thou shalt say, I have no pleasure in them; ^2before the sun, and the light, and the moon, and the stars, are darkened, and the clouds return after the rain; ^3in the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow themselves, and the grinders cease because they are few, and those that look out of the windows shall be darkened, ^4and the doors shall be shut in the street; when the sound of the grinding is low, and one shall rise up at the voice of a bird, and all the daughters of music shall be brought low; ^5yea, they shall be afraid of that which is high, and terrors shall be in the way; and the almond-tree shall blossom, and the grasshopper shall be a burden, and desire shall fail; because man goeth to his everlasting home, and the mourners go about the streets: ^6before the silver cord is loosed, or the golden bowl is broken, or the pitcher is broken at the fountain, or the wheel broken at the cistern, ^7and the dust returneth to the earth as it was, and the spirit returneth unto God who gave it. ^8Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher; all is vanity. ^9And further, because the Preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge; yea, he pondered, and sought out, and set in order many proverbs. ^10The Preacher sought to find out acceptable words, and that which was written uprightly, even words of truth. ^11The words of the wise are as goads; and as nails well fastened are the words of the masters of assemblies, which are given from one shepherd. ^12And furthermore, my son, be admonished: of making many books there is no end; and much study is a weariness of the flesh. ^13This is the end of the matter; all hath been heard: fear God, and keep his commandments; for this is the whole duty of man. ^14For God will bring every work into judgment, with every hidden thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.

Ephesians 4

4

^1I therefore, the prisoner in the Lord, beseech you to walk worthily of the calling wherewith ye were called, ^2with all lowliness and meekness, with longsuffering, forbearing one another in love; ^3giving diligence to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. ^4There is one body, and one Spirit, even as also ye were called in one hope of your calling; ^5one Lord, one faith, one baptism, ^6one God and Father of all, who is over all, and through all, and in all. ^7But unto each one of us was the grace given according to the measure of the gift of Christ. ^8Wherefore he saith, When he ascended on high, he led captivity captive, And gave gifts unto men. ^9(Now this, He ascended, what is it but that he also descended into the lower parts of the earth? ^10He that descended is the same also that ascended far above all the heavens, that he might fill all things.) ^11And he gave some to be apostles; and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some, pastors and teachers; ^12for the perfecting of the saints, unto the work of ministering, unto the building up of the body of Christ: ^13till we all attain unto the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a fullgrown man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ: ^14that we may be no longer children, tossed to and fro and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the sleight of men, in craftiness, after the wiles of error; ^15but speaking truth in love, we may grow up in all things into him, who is the head, even Christ; ^16from whom all the body fitly framed and knit together through that which every joint supplieth, according to the working in due measure of each several part, maketh the increase of the body unto the building up of itself in love. ^17This I say therefore, and testify in the Lord, that ye no longer walk as the Gentiles also walk, in the vanity of their mind, ^18being darkened in their understanding, alienated from the life of God, because of the ignorance that is in them, because of the hardening of their heart; ^19who being past feeling gave themselves up to lasciviousness, to work all uncleanness with greediness. ^20But ye did not so learn Christ; ^21if so be that ye heard him, and were taught in him, even as truth is in Jesus: ^22that ye put away, as concerning your former manner of life, the old man, that waxeth corrupt after the lusts of deceit; ^23and that ye be renewed in the spirit of your mind, ^24and put on the new man, that after God hath been created in righteousness and holiness of truth. ^25Wherefore, putting away falsehood, speak ye truth each one with his neighbor: for we are members one of another. ^26Be ye angry, and sin not: let not the sun go down upon your wrath: ^27neither give place to the devil. ^28Let him that stole steal no more: but rather let him labor, working with his hands the thing that is good, that he may have whereof to give to him that hath need. ^29Let no corrupt speech proceed out of your mouth, but such as is good for edifying as the need may be, that it may give grace to them that hear. ^30And grieve not the Holy Spirit of God, in whom ye were sealed unto the day of redemption. ^31Let all bitterness, and wrath, and anger, and clamor, and railing, be put away from you, with all malice: ^32and be ye kind one to another, tenderhearted, forgiving each other, even as God also in Christ forgave you.

Ephesians 5

5

^1Be ye therefore imitators of God, as beloved children; ^2and walk in love, even as Christ also loved you, and gave himself up for us, an offering and a sacrifice to God for an odor of a sweet smell. ^3But fornication, and all uncleanness, or covetousness, let it not even be named among you, as becometh saints; ^4nor filthiness, nor foolish talking, or jesting, which are not befitting: but rather giving of thanks. ^5For this ye know of a surety, that no fornicator, nor unclean person, nor covetous man, who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and God. ^6Let no man deceive you with empty words: for because of these things cometh the wrath of God upon the sons of disobedience. ^7Be not ye therefore partakers with them; ^8For ye were once darkness, but are now light in the Lord: walk as children of light ^9(for the fruit of the light is in all goodness and righteousness and truth), ^10proving what is well-pleasing unto the Lord; ^11and have no fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but rather even reprove them; ^12for the things which are done by them in secret it is a shame even to speak of. ^13But all things when they are reproved are made manifest by the light: for everything that is made manifest is light. ^14Wherefore he saith, Awake, thou that sleepest, and arise from the dead, and Christ shall shine upon thee. ^15Look therefore carefully how ye walk, not as unwise, but as wise; ^16redeeming the time, because the days are evil. ^17Wherefore be ye not foolish, but understand what the will of the Lord is. ^18And be not drunken with wine, wherein is riot, but be filled with the Spirit; ^19speaking one to another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and making melody with your heart to the Lord; ^20giving thanks always for all things in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ to God, even the Father; ^21subjecting yourselves one to another in the fear of Christ. ^22Wives, be in subjection unto your own husbands, as unto the Lord. ^23For the husband is the head of the wife, and Christ also is the head of the church, being himself the saviour of the body. ^24But as the church is subject to Christ, so let the wives also be to their husbands in everything. ^25Husbands, love your wives, even as Christ also loved the church, and gave himself up for it; ^26that he might sanctify it, having cleansed it by the washing of water with the word, ^27that he might present the church to himself a glorious church, not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing; but that it should be holy and without blemish. ^28Even so ought husbands also to love their own wives as their own bodies. He that loveth his own wife loveth himself: ^29for no man ever hated his own flesh; but nourisheth and cherisheth it, even as Christ also the church; ^30because we are members of his body. ^31For this cause shall a man leave his father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife; and the two shall become one flesh. ^32This mystery is great: but I speak in regard of Christ and of the church. ^33Nevertheless do ye also severally love each one his own wife even as himself; and let the wife see that she fear her husband.

Ephesians 6

6

^1Children, obey your parents in the Lord: for this is right. ^2Honor thy father and mother (which is the first commandment with promise), ^3that it may be well with thee, and thou mayest live long on the earth. ^4And, ye fathers, provoke not your children to wrath: but nurture them in the chastening and admonition of the Lord. ^5Servants, be obedient unto them that according to the flesh are your masters, with fear and trembling, in singleness of your heart, as unto Christ; ^6not in the way of eyeservice, as men-pleasers; but as servants of Christ, doing the will of God from the heart; ^7with good will doing service, as unto the Lord, and not unto men: ^8knowing that whatsoever good thing each one doeth, the same shall he receive again from the Lord, whether he be bond or free. ^9And, ye masters, do the same things unto them, and forbear threatening: knowing that he who is both their Master and yours is in heaven, and there is no respect of persons with him. ^10Finally, be strong in the Lord, and in the strength of his might. ^11Put on the whole armor of God, that ye may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil. ^12For our wrestling is not against flesh and blood, but against the principalities, against the powers, against the world-rulers of this darkness, against the spiritual hosts of wickedness in the heavenly places. ^13Wherefore take up the whole armor of God, that ye may be able to withstand in the evil day, and, having done all, to stand. ^14Stand therefore, having girded your loins with truth, and having put on the breastplate of righteousness, ^15and having shod your feet with the preparation of the gospel of peace; ^16withal taking up the shield of faith, wherewith ye shall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the evil one. ^17And take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God: ^18with all prayer and supplication praying at all seasons in the Spirit, and watching thereunto in all perseverance and supplication for all the saints, ^19And on my behalf, that utterance may be given unto me in opening my mouth, to make known with boldness the mystery of the gospel, ^20for which I am an ambassador in chains; that in it I may speak boldly, as I ought to speak. ^21But that ye also may know my affairs, how I do, Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, shall make known to you all things: ^22whom I have sent unto you for this very purpose, that ye may know our state, and that he may comfort your hearts. ^23Peace be to the brethren, and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. ^24Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jesus Christ with a love incorruptible.

Esther 2

2

^1After these things, when the wrath of king Ahasuerus was pacified, he remembered Vashti, and what she had done, and what was decreed against her. ^2Then said the king's servants that ministered unto him, Let there be fair young virgins sought for the king: ^3and let the king appoint officers in all the provinces of his kingdom, that they may gather together all the fair young virgins unto Shushan the palace, to the house of the women, unto the custody of Hegai the king's chamberlain, keeper of the women; and let their things for purification be given them; ^4and let the maiden that pleaseth the king be queen instead of Vashti. And the thing pleased the king; and he did so. ^5There was a certain Jew in Shushan the palace, whose name was Mordecai, the son of Jair, the son of Shimei, the son of Kish, a Benjamite, ^6who had been carried away from Jerusalem with the captives that had been carried away with Jeconiah king of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away. ^7And he brought up Hadassah, that is, Esther, his uncle's daughter: for she had neither father nor mother, and the maiden was fair and beautiful; and when her father and mother were dead, Mordecai took her for his own daughter. ^8So it came to pass, when the king's commandment and his decree was heard, and when many maidens were gathered together unto Shushan the palace, to the custody of Hegai, that Esther was taken into the king's house, to the custody of Hegai, keeper of the women. ^9And the maiden pleased him, and she obtained kindness of him; and he speedily gave her her things for purification, with her portions, and the seven maidens who were meet to be given her out of the king's house: and he removed her and her maidens to the best place of the house of the women. ^10Esther had not made known her people nor her kindred; for Mordecai had charged her that she should not make it known. ^11And Mordecai walked every day before the court of the women's house, to know how Esther did, and what would become of her. ^12Now when the turn of every maiden was come to go in to king Ahasuerus, after that it had been done to her according to the law for the women twelve months (for so were the days of their purifications accomplished, to wit, six months with oil of myrrh, and six months with sweet odors and with the things for the purifying of the women), ^13then in this wise came the maiden unto the king: whatsoever she desired was given her to go with her out of the house of the women unto the king's house. ^14In the evening she went, and on the morrow she returned into the second house of the women, to the custody of Shaashgaz, the king's chamberlain, who kept the concubines: she came in unto the king no more, except the king delighted in her, and she were called by name. ^15Now when the turn of Esther, the daughter of Abihail the uncle of Mordecai, who had taken her for his daughter, was come to go in unto the king, she required nothing but what Hegai the king's chamberlain, the keeper of the women, appointed. And Esther obtained favor in the sight of all them that looked upon her. ^16So Esther was taken unto king Ahasuerus into his house royal in the tenth month, which is the month Tebeth, in the seventh year of his reign. ^17And the king loved Esther above all the women, and she obtained favor and kindness in his sight more than all the virgins; so that he set the royal crown upon her head, and made her queen instead of Vashti. ^18Then the king made a great feast unto all his princes and his servants, even Esther's feast; and he made a release to the provinces, and gave gifts, according to the bounty of the king. ^19And when the virgins were gathered together the second time, then Mordecai was sitting in the king's gate. ^20Esther had not yet made known her kindred nor her people; as Mordecai had charged her: for Esther did the commandment of Mordecai, like as when she was brought up with him. ^21In those days, while Mordecai was sitting in the king's gate, two of the king's chamberlains, Bigthan and Teresh, of those that kept the threshold, were wroth, and sought to lay hands on the king Ahasuerus. ^22And the thing became known to Mordecai, who showed it unto Esther the queen; and Esther told the king thereof in Mordecai's name. ^23And when inquisition was made of the matter, and it was found to be so, they were both hanged on a tree: and it was written in the book of the chronicles before the king.

Esther 3

3

^1After these things did king Ahasuerus promote Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, and advanced him, and set his seat above all the princes that were with him. ^2And all the king's servants, that were in the king's gate, bowed down, and did reverence to Haman; for the king had so commanded concerning him. But Mordecai bowed not down, nor did him reverence. ^3Then the king's servants, that were in the king's gate, said unto Mordecai, Why transgressest thou the king's commandment? ^4Now it came to pass, when they spake daily unto him, and he hearkened not unto them, that they told Haman, to see whether Mordecai's matters would stand: for he had told them that he was a Jew. ^5And when Haman saw that Mordecai bowed not down, nor did him reverence, then was Haman full of wrath. ^6But he thought scorn to lay hands on Mordecai alone; for they had made known to him the people of Mordecai: wherefore Haman sought to destroy all the Jews that were throughout the whole kingdom of Ahasuerus, even the people of Mordecai. ^7In the first month, which is the month Nisan, in the twelfth year of king Ahasuerus, they cast Pur, that is, the lot, before Haman from day to day, and from month to month, to the twelfth month, which is the month Adar. ^8And Haman said unto king Ahasuerus, There is a certain people scattered abroad and dispersed among the peoples in all the provinces of thy kingdom; and their laws are diverse from those of every people; neither keep they the king's laws: therefore it is not for the king's profit to suffer them. ^9If it please the king, let it be written that they be destroyed: and I will pay ten thousand talents of silver into the hands of those that have the charge of the king's business, to bring it into the king's treasuries. ^10And the king took his ring from his hand, and gave it unto Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the Jews' enemy. ^11And the king said unto Haman, The silver is given to thee, the people also, to do with them as it seemeth good to thee. ^12Then were the king's scribes called in the first month, on the thirteenth day thereof; and there was written according to all that Haman commanded unto the king's satraps, and to the governors that were over every province, and to the princes of every people, to every province according to the writing thereof, and to every people after their language; in the name of king Ahasuerus was it written, and it was sealed with the king's ring. ^13And letters were sent by posts into all the king's provinces, to destroy, to slay, and to cause to perish, all Jews, both young and old, little children and women, in one day, even upon the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is the month Adar, and to take the spoil of them for a prey. ^14A copy of the writing, that the decree should be given out in every province, was published unto all the peoples, that they should be ready against that day. ^15The posts went forth in haste by the king's commandment, and the decree was given out in Shushan the palace. And the king and Haman sat down to drink; but the city of Shushan was perplexed.

Esther 4

4

^1Now when Mordecai knew all that was done, Mordecai rent his clothes, and put on sackcloth with ashes, and went out into the midst of the city, and cried with a loud and a bitter cry; ^2and he came even before the king's gate: for none might enter within the king's gate clothed with sackcloth. ^3And in every province, whithersoever the king's commandment and his decree came, there was great mourning among the Jews, and fasting, and weeping, and wailing; and many lay in sackcloth and ashes. ^4And Esther's maidens and her chamberlains came and told it her; and the queen was exceedingly grieved: and she sent raiment to clothe Mordecai, and to take his sackcloth from off him; but he received it not. ^5Then called Esther for Hathach, one of the king's chamberlains, whom he had appointed to attend upon her, and charged him to go to Mordecai, to know what this was, and why it was. ^6So Hathach went forth to Mordecai unto the broad place of the city, which was before the king's gate. ^7And Mordecai told him of all that had happened unto him, and the exact sum of the money that Haman had promised to pay to the king's treasuries for the Jews, to destroy them. ^8Also he gave him the copy of the writing of the decree that was given out in Shushan to destroy them, to show it unto Esther, and to declare it unto her, and to charge her that she should go in unto the king, to make supplication unto him, and to make request before him, for her people. ^9And Hathach came and told Esther the words of Mordecai. ^10Then Esther spake unto Hathach, and gave him a message unto Mordecai saying: ^11All the king's servants, and the people of the king's provinces, do know, that whosoever, whether man or woman, shall come unto the king into the inner court, who is not called, there is one law for him, that he be put to death, except those to whom the king shall hold out the golden sceptre, that he may live: but I have not been called to come in unto the king these thirty days. ^12And they told to Mordecai Esther's words. ^13Then Mordecai bade them return answer unto Esther, Think not with thyself that thou shalt escape in the king's house, more than all the Jews. ^14For if thou altogether holdest thy peace at this time, then will relief and deliverance arise to the Jews from another place, but thou and thy father's house will perish: and who knoweth whether thou art not come to the kingdom for such a time as this? ^15Then Esther bade them return answer unto Mordecai, ^16Go, gather together all the Jews that are present in Shushan, and fast ye for me, and neither eat nor drink three days, night or day: I also and my maidens will fast in like manner; and so will I go in unto the king, which is not according to the law: and if I perish, I perish. ^17So Mordecai went his way, and did according to all that Esther had commanded him.

Esther 5

5

^1Now it came to pass on the third day, that Esther put on her royal apparel, and stood in the inner court of the king's house, over against the king's house: and the king sat upon his royal throne in the royal house, over against the entrance of the house. ^2And it was so, when the king saw Esther the queen standing in the court, that she obtained favor in his sight; and the king held out to Esther the golden sceptre that was in his hand. So Esther drew near, and touched the top of the sceptre. ^3Then said the king unto her, What wilt thou, queen Esther? and what is thy request? it shall be given thee even to the half of the kingdom. ^4And Esther said, If it seem good unto the king, let the king and Haman come this day unto the banquet that I have prepared for him. ^5Then the king said, Cause Haman to make haste, that it may be done as Esther hath said. So the king and Haman came to the banquet that Esther had prepared. ^6And the king said unto Esther at the banquet of wine, What is thy petition? and it shall be granted thee: and what is thy request? even to the half of the kingdom it shall be performed. ^7Then answered Esther, and said, My petition and my request is: ^8if I have found favor in the sight of the king, and if it please the king to grant my petition, and to perform my request, let the king and Haman come to the banquet that I shall prepare for them, and I will do to-morrow as the king hath said. ^9Then went Haman forth that day joyful and glad of heart: but when Haman saw Mordecai in the king's gate, that he stood not up nor moved for him, he was filled with wrath against Mordecai. ^10Nevertheless Haman refrained himself, and went home; and he sent and fetched his friends and Zeresh his wife. ^11And Haman recounted unto them the glory of his riches, and the multitude of his children, and all the things wherein the king had promoted him, and how he had advanced him above the princes and servants of the king. ^12Haman said moreover, Yea, Esther the queen did let no man come in with the king unto the banquet that she had prepared but myself; and to-morrow also am I invited by her together with the king. ^13Yet all this availeth me nothing, so long as I see Mordecai the Jew sitting at the king's gate. ^14Then said Zeresh his wife and all his friends unto him, Let a gallows be made fifty cubits high, and in the morning speak thou unto the king that Mordecai may be hanged thereon: then go thou in merrily with the king unto the banquet. And the thing pleased Haman; and he caused the gallows to be made.

Esther 6

6

^1On that night could not the king sleep; and he commanded to bring the book of records of the chronicles, and they were read before the king. ^2And it was found written, that Mordecai had told of Bigthana and Teresh, two of the king's chamberlains, of those that kept the threshold, who had sought to lay hands on the king Ahasuerus. ^3And the king said, What honor and dignity hath been bestowed on Mordecai for this? Then said the king's servants that ministered unto him, There is nothing done for him. ^4And the king said, Who is in the court? Now Haman was come into the outward court of the king's house, to speak unto the king to hang Mordecai on the gallows that he had prepared for him. ^5And the king's servants said unto him, Behold, Haman standeth in the court. And the king said, Let him come in. ^6So Haman came in. And the king said unto him, What shall be done unto the man whom the king delighteth to honor? Now Haman said in his heart, To whom would the king delight to do honor more than to myself? ^7And Haman said unto the king, For the man whom the king delighteth to honor, ^8let royal apparel be brought which the king useth to wear, and the horse that the king rideth upon, and on the head of which a crown royal is set: ^9and let the apparel and the horse be delivered to the hand of one of the king's most noble princes, that they may array the man therewith whom the king delighteth to honor, and cause him to ride on horseback through the street of the city, and proclaim before him, Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delighteth to honor. ^10Then the king said to Haman, Make haste, and take the apparel and the horse, as thou hast said, and do even so to Mordecai the Jew, that sitteth at the king's gate: let nothing fail of all that thou hast spoken. ^11Then took Haman the apparel and the horse, and arrayed Mordecai, and caused him to ride through the street of the city, and proclaimed before him, Thus shall it be done unto the man whom the king delighteth to honor. ^12And Mordecai came again to the king's gate. But Haman hasted to his house, mourning and having his head covered. ^13And Haman recounted unto Zeresh his wife and all his friends everything that had befallen him. Then said his wise men and Zeresh his wife unto him, If Mordecai, before whom thou hast begun to fall, be of the seed of the Jews, thou shalt not prevail against him, but shalt surely fall before him. ^14While they were yet talking with him, came the king's chamberlains, and hasted to bring Haman unto the banquet that Esther had prepared.

Esther 7

7

^1So the king and Haman came to banquet with Esther the queen. ^2And the king said again unto Esther on the second day at the banquet of wine, What is thy petition, queen Esther? and it shall be granted thee: and what is thy request? even to the half of the kingdom it shall be performed. ^3Then Esther the queen answered and said, If I have found favor in thy sight, O king, and if it please the king, let my life be given me at my petition, and my people at my request: ^4for we are sold, I and my people, to be destroyed, to be slain, and to perish. But if we had been sold for bondmen and bondwomen, I had held my peace, although the adversary could not have compensated for the king's damage. ^5Then spake the king Ahasuerus and said unto Esther the queen, Who is he, and where is he, that durst presume in his heart to do so? ^6And Esther said, An adversary and an enemy, even this wicked Haman. Then Haman was afraid before the king and the queen. ^7And the king arose in his wrath from the banquet of wine and went into the palace garden: and Haman stood up to make request for his life to Esther the queen; for he saw that there was evil determined against him by the king. ^8Then the king returned out of the palace garden into the place of the banquet of wine; and Haman was fallen upon the couch whereon Esther was. Then said the king, Will he even force the queen before me in the house? As the word went out of the king's mouth, they covered Haman's face. ^9Then said Harbonah, one of the chamberlains that were before the king, Behold also, the gallows fifty cubits high, which Haman hath made for Mordecai, who spake good for the king, standeth in the house of Haman. And the king said, Hang him thereon. ^10So they hanged Haman on the gallows that he had prepared for Mordecai. Then was the king's wrath pacified.

Esther 8

8

^1On that day did the king Ahasuerus give the house of Haman the Jews' enemy unto Esther the queen. And Mordecai came before the king; for Esther had told what he was unto her. ^2And the king took off his ring, which he had taken from Haman, and gave it unto Mordecai. And Esther set Mordecai over the house of Haman. ^3And Esther spake yet again before the king, and fell down at his feet, and besought him with tears to put away the mischief of Haman the Agagite, and his device that he had devised against the Jews. ^4Then the king held out to Esther the golden sceptre. So Esther arose, and stood before the king. ^5And she said, If it please the king, and if I have found favor in his sight, and the thing seem right before the king, and I be pleasing in his eyes, let it be written to reverse the letters devised by Haman, the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, which he wrote to destroy the Jews that are in all the king's provinces: ^6for how can I endure to see the evil that shall come unto my people? or how can I endure to see the destruction of my kindred? ^7Then the king Ahasuerus said unto Esther the queen and to Mordecai the Jew, Behold, I have given Esther the house of Haman, and him they have hanged upon the gallows, because he laid his hand upon the Jews. ^8Write ye also to the Jews, as it pleaseth you, in the king's name, and seal it with the king's ring; for the writing which is written in the king's name, and sealed with the king's ring, may no man reverse. ^9Then were the king's scribes called at that time, in the third month Sivan, on the three and twentieth day thereof; and it was written according to all that Mordecai commanded unto the Jews, and to the satraps, and the governors and princes of the provinces which are from India unto Ethiopia, a hundred twenty and seven provinces, unto every province according to the writing thereof, and unto every people after their language, and to the Jews according to their writing, and according to their language. ^10And he wrote the name of king Ahasuerus, and sealed it with the king's ring, and sent letters by post on horseback, riding on swift steeds that were used in the king's service, bred of the stud: ^11wherein the king granted the Jews that were in every city to gather themselves together, and to stand for their life, to destroy, to slay, and to cause to perish, all the power of the people and province that would assault them, their little ones and women, and to take the spoil of them for a prey, ^12upon one day in all the provinces of king Ahasuerus, namely, upon the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is the month Adar. ^13A copy of the writing, that the decree should be given out in every province, was published unto all the peoples, and that the Jews should be ready against that day to avenge themselves on their enemies. ^14So the posts that rode upon swift steeds that were used in the king's service went out, being hastened and pressed on by the king's commandment; and the decree was given out in Shushan the palace. ^15And Mordecai went forth from the presence of the king in royal apparel of blue and white, and with a great crown of gold, and with a robe of fine linen and purple: and the city of Shushan shouted and was glad. ^16The Jews had light and gladness, and joy and honor. ^17And in every province, and in every city, whithersoever the king's commandment and his decree came, the Jews had gladness and joy, a feast and a good day. And many from among the peoples of the land became Jews; for the fear of the Jews was fallen upon them.

Esther 9

9

^1Now in the twelfth month, which is the month Adar, on the thirteenth day of the same, when the king's commandment and his decree drew near to be put in execution, on the day that the enemies of the Jews hoped to have rule over them, (whereas it was turned to the contrary, that the Jews had rule over them that hated them,) ^2the Jews gathered themselves together in their cities throughout all the provinces of the king Ahasuerus, to lay hand on such as sought their hurt: and no man could withstand them; for the fear of them was fallen upon all the peoples. ^3And all the princes of the provinces, and the satraps, and the governors, and they that did the king's business, helped the Jews; because the fear of Mordecai was fallen upon them. ^4For Mordecai was great in the king's house, and his fame went forth throughout all the provinces; for the man Mordecai waxed greater and greater. ^5And the Jews smote all their enemies with the stroke of the sword, and with slaughter and destruction, and did what they would unto them that hated them. ^6And in Shushan the palace the Jews slew and destroyed five hundred men. ^7And Parshandatha, and Dalphon, and Aspatha, ^8and Poratha, and Adalia, and Aridatha, ^9and Parmashta, and Arisai, and Aridai, and Vaizatha, ^10the ten sons of Haman the son of Hammedatha, the Jew's enemy, slew they; but on the spoil they laid not their hand. ^11On that day the number of those that were slain in Shushan the palace was brought before the king. ^12And the king said unto Esther the queen, The Jews have slain and destroyed five hundred men in Shushan the palace, and the ten sons of Haman; what then have they done in the rest of the king's provinces! Now what is thy petition? and it shall be granted thee: or what is thy request further? and it shall be done. ^13Then said Esther, If it please the king, let it be granted to the Jews that are in Shushan to do to-morrow also according unto this day's decree, and let Haman's ten sons be hanged upon the gallows. ^14And the king commanded it so to be done: and a decree was given out in Shushan; and they hanged Haman's ten sons. ^15And the Jews that were in Shushan gathered themselves together on the fourteenth day also of the month Adar, and slew three hundred men in Shushan; but on the spoil they laid not their hand. ^16And the other Jews that were in the king's provinces gathered themselves together, and stood for their lives, and had rest from their enemies, and slew of them that hated them seventy and five thousand; but on the spoil they laid not their hand. ^17This was done on the thirteenth day of the month Adar; and on the fourteenth day of the same they rested, and made it a day of feasting and gladness. ^18But the Jews that were in Shushan assembled together on the thirteenth day thereof, and on the fourteenth thereof; and on the fifteenth day of the same they rested, and made it a day of feasting and gladness. ^19Therefore do the Jews of the villages, that dwell in the unwalled towns, make the fourteenth day of the month Adar a day of gladness and feasting, and a good day, and of sending portions one to another. ^20And Mordecai wrote these things, and sent letters unto all the Jews that were in all the provinces of the king Ahasuerus, both nigh and far, ^21to enjoin them that they should keep the fourteenth day of the month Adar, and the fifteenth day of the same, yearly, ^22as the days wherein the Jews had rest from their enemies, and the month which was turned unto them from sorrow to gladness, and from mourning into a good day; that they should make them days of feasting and gladness, and of sending portions one to another, and gifts to the poor. ^23And the Jews undertook to do as they had begun, and as Mordecai had written unto them; ^24because Haman the son of Hammedatha, the Agagite, the enemy of all the Jews, had plotted against the Jews to destroy them, and had cast Pur, that is the lot, to consume them, and to destroy them; ^25but when the matter came before the king, he commanded by letters that his wicked device, which he had devised against the Jews, should return upon his own head, and that he and his sons should be hanged on the gallows. ^26Wherefore they called these days Purim, after the name of Pur. Therefore because of all the words of this letter, and of that which they had seen concerning this matter, and that which had come unto them, ^27the Jews ordained, and took upon them, and upon their seed, and upon all such as joined themselves unto them, so that it should not fail, that they would keep these two days according to the writing thereof, and according to the appointed time thereof, every year; ^28and that these days should be remembered and kept throughout every generation, every family, every province, and every city; and that these days of Purim should not fail from among the Jews, nor the remembrance of them perish from their seed. ^29Then Esther the queen, the daughter of Abihail, and Mordecai the Jew, wrote with all authority to confirm this second letter of Purim. ^30And he sent letters unto all the Jews, to the hundred twenty and seven provinces of the kingdom of Ahasuerus, with words of peace and truth, ^31to confirm these days of Purim in their appointed times, according as Mordecai the Jew and Esther the queen had enjoined them, and as they had ordained for themselves and for their seed, in the matter of the fastings and their cry. ^32And the commandment of Esther confirmed these matters of Purim; and it was written in the book.

Exodus 2

2

^1And there went a man of the house of Levi, and took to wife a daughter of Levi. ^2And the woman conceived, and bare a son: and when she saw him that he was a goodly child, she hid him three months. ^3And when she could not longer hide him, she took for him an ark of bulrushes, and daubed it with slime and with pitch; and she put the child therein, and laid it in the flags by the river's brink. ^4And his sister stood afar off, to know what would be done to him. ^5And the daughter of Pharaoh came down to bathe at the river; and her maidens walked along by the river-side; and she saw the ark among the flags, and sent her handmaid to fetch it. ^6And she opened it, and saw the child: and, behold, the babe wept. And she had compassion on him, and said, This is one of the Hebrews' children. ^7Then said his sister to Pharaoh's daughter, Shall I go and call thee a nurse of the Hebrew women, that she may nurse the child for thee? ^8And Pharaoh's daughter said to her, Go. And the maiden went and called the child's mother. ^9And Pharaoh's daughter said unto her, Take this child away, and nurse it for me, and I will give thee thy wages. And the woman took the child, and nursed it. ^10And the child grew, and she brought him unto Pharaoh's daughter, and he became her son. And she called his name Moses, and said, Because I drew him out of the water.

^11And it came to pass in those days, when Moses was grown up, that he went out unto his brethren, and looked on their burdens: and he saw an Egyptian smiting a Hebrew, one of his brethren. ^12And he looked this way and that way, and when he saw that there was no man, he smote the Egyptian, and hid him in the sand. ^13And he went out the second day, and, behold, two men of the Hebrews were striving together: and he said to him that did the wrong, Wherefore smitest thou thy fellow? ^14And he said, Who made thee a prince and a judge over us? Thinkest thou to kill me, as thou killedst the Egyptian? And Moses feared, and said, Surely the thing is known. ^15Now when Pharaoh heard this thing, he sought to slay Moses. But Moses fled from the face of Pharaoh, and dwelt in the land of Midian: and he sat down by a well.

^16Now the priest of Midian had seven daughters: and they came and drew water, and filled the troughs to water their father's flock. ^17And the shepherds came and drove them away; but Moses stood up and helped them, and watered their flock. ^18And when they came to Reuel their father, he said, How is it that ye are come so soon to-day? ^19And they said, An Egyptian delivered us out of the hand of the shepherds, and moreover he drew water for us, and watered the flock. ^20And he said unto his daughters, And where is he? Why is it that ye have left the man? Call him, that he may eat bread. ^21And Moses was content to dwell with the man: and he gave Moses Zipporah his daughter. ^22And she bare a son, and he called his name Gershom; for he said, I have been a sojourner in a foreign land.

^23And it came to pass in the course of those many days, that the king of Egypt died: and the children of Israel sighed by reason of the bondage, and they cried, and their cry came up unto God by reason of the bondage. ^24And God heard their groaning, and God remembered his covenant with Abraham, with Isaac, and with Jacob. ^25And God saw the children of Israel, and God took knowledge of them.

Exodus 4

4

^1And Moses answered and said, But, behold, they will not believe me, nor hearken unto my voice; for they will say, Jehovah hath not appeared unto thee. ^2And Jehovah said unto him, What is that in thy hand? And he said, A rod. ^3And he said, Cast in on the ground. And he cast it on the ground, and it became a serpent; and Moses fled from before it. ^4And Jehovah said unto Moses, Put forth thy hand, and take it by the tail: (and he put forth his hand, and laid hold of it, and it became a rod in his hand:) ^5That they may believe that Jehovah, the God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, hath appeared unto thee. ^6And Jehovah said furthermore unto him, Put now thy hand into thy bosom. And he put his hand into his bosom: and when he took it out, behold, his hand was leprous, as white as snow. ^7And he said, Put thy hand into thy bosom again. (And he put his hand into his bosom again; and when he took it out of his bosom, behold, it was turned again as his other flesh.) ^8And it shall come to pass, if they will not believe thee, neither hearken to the voice of the first sign, that they will believe the voice of the latter sign. ^9And it shall come to pass, if they will not believe even these two signs, neither hearken unto thy voice, that thou shalt take of the water of the river, and pour it upon the dry land: and the water which thou takest out of the river shall become blood upon the dry land.

^10And Moses said unto Jehovah, Oh, Lord, I am not eloquent, neither heretofore, nor since thou hast spoken unto thy servant; for I am slow of speech, and of a slow tongue. ^11And Jehovah said unto him, Who hath made man's mouth? Or who maketh a man dumb, or deaf, or seeing, or blind? Is it not I, Jehovah? ^12Now therefore go, and I will be with thy mouth, and teach thee what thou shalt speak. ^13And he said, Oh, Lord, send, I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou wilt send. ^14And the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Moses, and he said, Is there not Aaron thy brother the Levite? I know that he can speak well. And also, behold, he cometh forth to meet thee: and when he seeth thee, he will be glad in his heart. ^15And thou shalt speak unto him, and put the words in his mouth: and I will be with thy mouth, and with his mouth, and will teach you what ye shall do. ^16And he shall be thy spokesman unto the people; and it shall come to pass, that he shall be to thee a mouth, and thou shalt be to him as God. ^17And thou shalt take in thy hand this rod, wherewith thou shalt do the signs. ^18And Moses went and returned to Jethro his father-in-law, and said unto him, Let me go, I pray thee, and return unto my brethren that are in Egypt, and see whether they be yet alive. And Jethro said to Moses, Go in peace. ^19And Jehovah said unto Moses in Midian, Go, return into Egypt; for all the men are dead that sought thy life. ^20And Moses took his wife and his sons, and set them upon an ass, and he returned to the land of Egypt: and Moses took the rod of God in his hand. ^21And Jehovah said unto Moses, When thou goest back into Egypt, see that thou do before Pharaoh all the wonders which I have put in thy hand: but I will harden his heart and he will not let the people go. ^22And thou shalt say unto Pharaoh, Thus saith Jehovah, Israel is my son, my first-born: ^23and I have said unto thee, Let my son go, that he may serve me; and thou hast refused to let him go: behold, I will slay thy son, thy first-born. ^24And it came to pass on the way at the lodging-place, that Jehovah met him, and sought to kill him. ^25Then Zipporah took a flint, and cut off the foreskin of her son, and cast it at his feet; and she said, Surely a bridegroom of blood art thou to me. ^26So he let him alone. Then she said, A bridegroom of blood art thou, because of the circumcision.

^27And Jehovah said to Aaron, Go into the wilderness to meet Moses. And he went, and met him in the mountain of God, and kissed him. ^28And Moses told Aaron all the words of Jehovah wherewith he had sent him, and all the signs wherewith he had charged him. ^29And Moses and Aaron went and gathered together all the elders of the children of Israel: ^30and Aaron spake all the words which Jehovah had spoken unto Moses, and did the signs in the sight of the people. ^31And the people believed: and when they heard that Jehovah had visited the children of Israel, and that he had seen their affliction, then they bowed their heads and worshipped.

Exodus 5

5

^1And afterward Moses and Aaron came, and said unto Pharaoh, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, Let my people go, that they may hold a feast unto me in the wilderness. ^2And Pharaoh said, Who is Jehovah, that I should hearken unto his voice to let Israel go? I know not Jehovah, and moreover I will not let Israel go. ^3And they said, The God of the Hebrews hath met with us: let us go, we pray thee, three days' journey into the wilderness, and sacrifice unto Jehovah our God, lest he fall upon us with pestilence, or with the sword. ^4And the king of Egypt said unto them, Wherefore do ye, Moses and Aaron, loose the people from their works? get you unto your burdens. ^5And Pharaoh said, Behold, the people of the land are now many, and ye make them rest from their burdens. ^6And the same day Pharaoh commanded the taskmasters of the people, and their officers, saying, ^7Ye shall no more give the people straw to make brick, as heretofore: let them go and gather straw for themselves. ^8And the number of the bricks, which they did make heretofore, ye shall lay upon them; ye shall not diminish aught thereof: for they are idle; therefore they cry, saying, Let us go and sacrifice to our God. ^9Let heavier work be laid upon the men, that they may labor therein; and let them not regard lying words.

^10And the taskmasters of the people went out, and their officers, and they spake to the people, saying, Thus saith Pharaoh, I will not give you straw. ^11Go yourselves, get you straw where ye can find it: for nought of your work shall be diminished. ^12So the people were scattered abroad throughout all the land of Egypt to gather stubble for straw. ^13And the taskmasters were urgent saying, Fulfil your works, your daily tasks, as when there was straw. ^14And the officers of the children of Israel, whom Pharaoh's taskmasters had set over them, were beaten, and demanded, Wherefore have ye not fulfilled your task both yesterday and to-day, in making brick as heretofore?

^15Then the officers of the children of Israel came and cried unto Pharaoh, saying, Wherefore dealest thou thus with thy servants? ^16There is no straw given unto thy servants, and they say to us, Make brick: and, behold, thy servants are beaten; but the fault it in thine own people. ^17But he said, Ye are idle, ye are idle: therefore ye say, Let us go and sacrifice to Jehovah. ^18Go therefore now, and work; for there shall no straw be given you, yet shall ye deliver the number of bricks. ^19And the officers of the children of Israel did see that they were in evil case, when it was said, Ye shall not diminish aught from your bricks, your daily tasks. ^20And they met Moses and Aaron, who stood in the way, as they came forth from Pharaoh: ^21and they said unto them, Jehovah look upon you, and judge: because ye have made our savor to be abhorred in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of his servants, to put a sword in their hand to slay us.

^22And Moses returned unto Jehovah, and said, Lord, wherefore hast thou dealt ill with this people? why is it that thou hast sent me? ^23For since I came to Pharaoh to speak in thy name, he hath dealt ill with this people; neither hast thou delivered thy people at all.

Exodus 6

6

^1And Jehovah said unto Moses, Now shalt thou see what I will do to Pharaoh: for by a strong hand shall he let them go, and by a strong hand shall he drive them out of his land.

^2And God spake unto Moses, and said unto him, I am Jehovah: ^3and I appeared unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, as God Almighty; but by my name Jehovah I was not known to them. ^4And I have also established my covenant with them, to give them the land of Canaan, the land of their sojournings, wherein they sojourned. ^5And moreover I have heard the groaning of the children of Israel, whom the Egyptians keep in bondage; and I have remembered my covenant. ^6Wherefore say unto the children of Israel, I am Jehovah, and I will bring you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians, and I will rid you out of their bondage, and I will redeem you with an outstretched arm, and with great judgments: ^7and I will take you to me for a people, and I will be to you a God; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah your God, who bringeth you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians. ^8And I will bring you in unto the land which I sware to give to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob; and I will give it you for a heritage: I am Jehovah. ^9And Moses spake so unto the children of Israel: but they hearkened not unto Moses for anguish of spirit, and for cruel bondage.

^10And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^11Go in, speak unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, that he let the children of Israel go out of his land. ^12And Moses spake before Jehovah, saying, Behold, the children of Israel have not hearkened unto me; how then shall Pharaoh hear me, who am of uncircumcised lips? ^13And Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, and gave them a charge unto the children of Israel, and unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt.

^14These are the heads of their fathers' houses. The sons of Reuben the first-born of Israel: Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi; these are the families of Reuben. ^15And the sons of Simeon: Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul the son of a Canaanitish woman; these are the families of Simeon. ^16And these are the names of the sons of Levi according to their generations: Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari; and the years of the life of Levi were a hundred thirty and seven years. ^17The sons of Gershon: Libni and Shimei, according to their families. ^18And the sons of Kohath: Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel; and the years of the life of Kohath were a hundred thirty and three years. ^19And the sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. These are the families of the Levites according to their generations. ^20And Amram took him Jochebed his father's sister to wife; and she bare him Aaron and Moses: and the years of the life of Amram were a hundred and thirty and seven years. ^21And the sons of Izhar: Korah, and Nepheg, and Zichri. ^22And the sons of Uzziel: Mishael, and Elzaphan, and Sithri. ^23And Aaron took him Elisheba, the daughter of Amminadab, the sister of Nahshon, to wife; and she bare him Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar. ^24And the sons of Korah: Assir, and Elkanah, and Abiasaph; these are the families of the Korahites. ^25And Eleazar Aaron's son took him one of the daughters of Putiel to wife; and she bare him Phinehas. These are the heads of the fathers' houses of the Levites according to their families. ^26These are that Aaron and Moses, to whom Jehovah said, Bring out the children of Israel from the land of Egypt according to their hosts. ^27These are they that spake to Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring out the children of Israel from Egypt: these are that Moses and Aaron.

^28And it came to pass on the day when Jehovah spake unto Moses in the land of Egypt, ^29that Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, I am Jehovah: speak thou unto Pharaoh king of Egypt all that I speak unto thee. ^30And Moses said before Jehovah, Behold, I am of uncircumcised lips, and how shall Pharaoh hearken unto me?

Exodus 7

7

^1And Jehovah said unto Moses, See, I have made thee as God to Pharaoh; and Aaron thy brother shall be thy prophet. ^2Thou shalt speak all that I command thee; and Aaron thy brother shall speak unto Pharaoh, that he let the children of Israel go out of his land. ^3And I will harden Pharaoh's heart, and multiply my signs and my wonders in the land of Egypt. ^4But Pharaoh will not hearken unto you, and I will lay my hand upon Egypt, and bring forth my hosts, my people the children of Israel, out of the land of Egypt by great judgments. ^5And the Egyptians shall know that I am Jehovah, when I stretch forth my hand upon Egypt, and bring out the children of Israel from among them. ^6And Moses and Aaron did so; as Jehovah commanded them, so did they. ^7And Moses was fourscore years old, and Aaron fourscore and three years old, when they spake unto Pharaoh.

^8And Jehovah spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying, ^9When Pharaoh shall speak unto you, saying, Show a wonder for you; then thou shalt say unto Aaron, Take thy rod, and cast it down before Pharaoh, that it become a serpent. ^10And Moses and Aaron went in unto Pharaoh, and they did so, as Jehovah had commanded: and Aaron cast down his rod before Pharaoh and before his servants, and it became a serpent. ^11Then Pharaoh also called for the wise men and the sorcerers: and they also, the magicians of Egypt, did in like manner with their enchantments. ^12For they cast down every man his rod, and they became serpents: but Aaron's rod swallowed up their rods. ^13And Pharaoh's heart was hardened, and he hearkened not unto them; as Jehovah had spoken.

^14And Jehovah said unto Moses, Pharaoh's heart is stubborn, he refuseth to let the people go. ^15Get thee unto Pharaoh in the morning; lo, he goeth out unto the water; and thou shalt stand by the river's brink to meet him; and the rod which was turned to a serpent shalt thou take in thy hand. ^16And thou shalt say unto him, Jehovah, the God of the Hebrews, hath sent me unto thee, saying, Let my people go, that they may serve me in the wilderness: and, behold, hitherto thou hast not hearkened. ^17Thus saith Jehovah, In this thou shalt know that I am Jehovah: behold, I will smite with the rod that is in my hand upon the waters which are in the river, and they shall be turned to blood. ^18And the fish that are in the river shall die, and the river shall become foul; and the Egyptians shall loathe to drink water from the river. ^19And Jehovah said unto Moses, Say unto Aaron, Take thy rod, and stretch out thy hand over the waters of Egypt, over their rivers, over their streams, and over their pools, and over all their ponds of water, that they may become blood; and there shall be blood throughout all the land of Egypt, both in vessels of wood and in vessels of stone.

^20And Moses and Aaron did so, as Jehovah commanded; and he lifted up the rod, and smote the waters that were in the river, in the sight of Pharaoh, and in the sight of his servants; and all the waters that were in the river were turned to blood. ^21And the fish that were in the river died; and the river became foul, and the Egyptians could not drink water from the river; and the blood was throughout all the land of Egypt. ^22And the magicians of Egypt did in like manner with their enchantments: and Pharaoh's heart was hardened, and he hearkened not unto them; as Jehovah had spoken. ^23And Pharaoh turned and went into his house, neither did he lay even this to heart. ^24And all the Egyptians digged round about the river for water to drink; for they could not drink of the water of the river. ^25And seven days were fulfilled, after that Jehovah had smitten the river.

Exodus 8

8

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, Go in unto Pharaoh, and say unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, Let my people go, that they may serve me. ^2And if thou refuse to let them go, behold, I will smite all thy borders with frogs: ^3and the river shall swarm with frogs, which shall go up and come into thy house, and into thy bedchamber, and upon thy bed, and into the house of thy servants, and upon thy people, and into thine ovens, and into thy kneading-troughs: ^4and the frogs shall come up both upon thee, and upon thy people, and upon all thy servants. ^5And Jehovah said unto Moses, Say unto Aaron, Stretch forth thy hand with thy rod over the rivers, over the streams, and over the pools, and cause frogs to come up upon the land of Egypt. ^6And Aaron stretched out his hand over the waters of Egypt; and the frogs came up, and covered the land of Egypt. ^7And the magicians did in like manner with their enchantments, and brought up frogs upon the land of Egypt.

^8Then Pharaoh called for Moses and Aaron, and said, Entreat Jehovah, that he take away the frogs from me, and from my people; and I will let the people go, that they may sacrifice unto Jehovah. ^9And Moses said unto Pharaoh, Have thou this glory over me: against what time shall I entreat for thee, and for thy servants, and for thy people, that the frogs be destroyed from thee and thy houses, and remain in the river only? ^10And he said, Against to-morrow. And he said, Be it according to thy word; that thou mayest know that there is none like unto Jehovah our God. ^11And the frogs shall depart from thee, and from thy houses, and from thy servants, and from thy people; they shall remain in the river only. ^12And Moses and Aaron went out from Pharaoh: and Moses cried unto Jehovah concerning the frogs which he had brought upon Pharaoh. ^13And Jehovah did according to the word of Moses; and the frogs died out of the houses, out of the courts, and out of the fields. ^14And they gathered them together in heaps; and the land stank. ^15But when Pharaoh saw that there was respite, he hardened his heart, and hearkened not unto them, as Jehovah had spoken.

^16And Jehovah said unto Moses, Say unto Aaron, Stretch out thy rod, and smite the dust of the earth, that is may become lice throughout all the land of Egypt. ^17And they did so; and Aaron stretched out his hand with his rod, and smote the dust of the earth, and there were lice upon man, and upon beast; all the dust of the earth became lice throughout all the land of Egypt. ^18And the magicians did so with their enchantments to bring forth lice, but they could not: and there were lice upon man, and upon beast. ^19Then the magicians said unto Pharaoh, This is the finger of God: and Pharaoh's heart was hardened, and he hearkened not unto them; as Jehovah had spoken.

^20And Jehovah said unto Moses, Rise up early in the morning, and stand before Pharaoh; lo, he cometh forth to the water; and say unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, Let my people go, that they may serve me. ^21Else, if thou wilt not let my people go, behold, I will send swarms of flies upon thee, and upon they servants, and upon thy people, and into thy houses: and the houses of the Egyptians shall be full of swarms of flies, and also the ground whereon they are. ^22And I will set apart in that day the land of Goshen, in which my people dwell, that no swarms of flies shall be there; to the end thou mayest know that I am Jehovah in the midst of the earth. ^23And I will put a division between my people and thy people: by to-morrow shall this sign be. ^24And Jehovah did so; and there came grievous swarms of flies into the house of Pharaoh, and into his servants' houses: and in all the land of Egypt the land was corrupted by reason of the swarms of flies.

^25And Pharaoh called for Moses and for Aaron, and said, Go ye, sacrifice to your God in the land. ^26And Moses said, It is not meet so to do; for we shall sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians to Jehovah our God: lo, shall we sacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians before their eyes, and will they not stone us? ^27We will go three days' journey into the wilderness, and sacrifice to Jehovah our God, as he shall command us. ^28And Pharaoh said, I will let you go, that ye may sacrifice to Jehovah your God in the wilderness; only ye shall not go very far away: entreat for me. ^29And Moses said, Behold, I go out from thee, and I will entreat Jehovah that the swarms of flies may depart from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people, to-morrow: only let not Pharaoh deal deceitfully any more in not letting the people go to sacrifice to Jehovah. ^30And Moses went out from Pharaoh, and entreated Jehovah. ^31And Jehovah did according to the word of Moses; and he removed the swarms of flies from Pharaoh, from his servants, and from his people; there remained not one. ^32And Pharaoh hardened his heart this time also, and he did not let the people go.

Exodus 9

9

^1Then Jehovah said unto Moses, Go in unto Pharaoh, and tell him, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of the Hebrews, Let my people go, that they may serve me. ^2For if thou refuse to let them go, and wilt hold them still, ^3behold, the hand of Jehovah is upon thy cattle which are in the field, upon the horses, upon the asses, upon the camels, upon the herds, and upon the flocks: there shall be a very grievous murrain. ^4And Jehovah shall make a distinction between the cattle of Israel and the cattle of Egypt; and there shall nothing die of all that belongeth to the children of Israel. ^5And Jehovah appointed a set time, saying, To-morrow Jehovah shall do this thing in the land. ^6And Jehovah did that thing on the morrow; and all the cattle of Egypt died; but of the cattle of the children of Israel died not one. ^7And Pharaoh sent, and, behold, there was not so much as one of the cattle of the Israelites dead. But the heart of Pharaoh was stubborn, and he did not let the people go.

^8And Jehovah said unto Moses and unto Aaron, Take to you handfuls of ashes of the furnace, and let Moses sprinkle it toward heaven in the sight of Pharaoh. ^9And it shall become small dust over all the land of Egypt, and shall be a boil breaking forth with blains upon man and upon beast, throughout all the land of Egypt. ^10And they took ashes of the furnace, and stood before Pharaoh; and Moses sprinkled it up toward heaven; and it became a boil breaking forth with blains upon man and upon beast. ^11And the magicians could not stand before Moses because of the boils; for the boils were upon the magicians, and upon all the Egyptians. ^12And Jehovah hardened the heart of Pharaoh, and he hearkened not unto them, as Jehovah had spoken unto Moses. ^13And Jehovah said unto Moses, Rise up early in the morning, and stand before Pharaoh, and say unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of the Hebrews, Let my people go, that they may serve me. ^14For I will this time send all my plagues upon thy heart, and upon thy servants, and upon thy people; that thou mayest know that there is none like me in all the earth. ^15For now I had put forth my hand, and smitten thee and thy people with pestilence, and thou hadst been cut off from the earth: ^16but in very deed for this cause have I made thee to stand, to show thee my power, and that my name may be declared throughout all the earth. ^17As yet exaltest thou thyself against my people, that thou wilt not let them go? ^18Behold, to-morrow about this time I will cause it to rain a very grievous hail, such as hath not been in Egypt since the day it was founded even until now. ^19Now therefore send, hasten in thy cattle and all that thou hast in the field; for every man and beast that shall be found in the field, and shall not be brought home, the hail shall come down upon them, and they shall die. ^20He that feared the word of Jehovah among the servants of Pharaoh made his servants and his cattle flee into the houses. ^21And he that regarded not the word of Jehovah left his servants and his cattle in the field.

^22And Jehovah said unto Moses, Stretch forth thy hand toward heaven, that there may be hail in all the land of Egypt, upon man, and upon beast, and upon every herb of the field, throughout the land of Egypt. ^23And Moses stretched forth his rod toward heaven: and Jehovah sent thunder and hail, and fire ran down unto the earth; and Jehovah rained hail upon the land of Egypt. ^24So there was hail, and fire mingled with the hail, very grievous, such as had not been in all the land of Egypt since it became a nation. ^25And the hail smote throughout all the land of Egypt all that was in the field, both man and beast; and the hail smote every herb of the field, and brake every tree of the field. ^26Only in the land of Goshen, where the children of Israel were, was there no hail.

^27And Pharaoh sent, and called for Moses and Aaron, and said unto them, I have sinned this time: Jehovah is righteous, and I and my people are wicked. ^28Entreat Jehovah; for there hath been enough of these mighty thunderings and hail; and I will let you go, and ye shall stay no longer. ^29And Moses said unto him, As soon as I am gone out of the city, I will spread abroad my hands unto Jehovah; the thunders shall cease, neither shall there be any more hail; that thou mayest know that the earth is Jehovah's. ^30But as for thee and thy servants, I know that ye will not yet fear Jehovah God. ^31And the flax and the barley were smitten: for the barley was in the ear, and the flax was in bloom. ^32But the wheat and the spelt were not smitten: for they were not grown up. ^33And Moses went out of the city from Pharaoh, and spread abroad his hands unto Jehovah: and the thunders and hail ceased, and the rain was not poured upon the earth. ^34And when Pharaoh saw that the rain and the hail and the thunders were ceased, he sinned yet more, and hardened his heart, he and his servants. ^35And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did not let the children of Israel go, as Jehovah had spoken by Moses.

Exodus 10

10

^1And Jehovah said unto Moses, Go in unto Pharaoh: for I have hardened his heart, and the heart of his servants, that I may show these my signs in the midst of them, ^2and that thou mayest tell in the ears of thy son, and of thy son's son, what things I have wrought upon Egypt, and my signs which I have done among them; that ye may know that I am Jehovah. ^3And Moses and Aaron went in unto Pharaoh, and said unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of the Hebrews, How long wilt thou refuse to humble thyself before me? let my people go, that they may serve me. ^4Else, if thou refuse to let my people go, behold, to-morrow will I bring locusts into thy border: ^5and they shall cover the face of the earth, so that one shall not be able to see the earth: and they shall eat the residue of that which is escaped, which remaineth unto you from the hail, and shall eat every tree which groweth for you out of the field: ^6and thy houses shall be filled, and the houses of all thy servants, and the houses of all the Egyptians; as neither thy fathers nor thy fathers' fathers have seen, since the day that they were upon the earth unto this day. And he turned, and went out from Pharaoh. ^7And Pharaoh's servants said unto him, How long shall this man be a snare unto us? let the men go, that they may serve Jehovah their God: knowest thou not yet that Egypt is destroyed? ^8And Moses and Aaron were brought again unto Pharaoh: and he said unto them, Go, serve Jehovah your God; but who are they that shall go? ^9And Moses said, We will go with our young and with our old; with our sons and with our daughters, with our flocks and with our herds will we go; for we must hold a feast unto Jehovah. ^10And he said unto them, So be Jehovah with you, as I will let you go, and your little ones: look to it; for evil is before you. ^11Not so: go now ye that are men, and serve Jehovah; for that is what ye desire. And they were driven out from Pharaoh's presence.

^12And Jehovah said unto Moses, Stretch out thy hand over the land of Egypt for the locusts, that they may come up upon the land of Egypt, and eat every herb of the land, even all that the hail hath left. ^13And Moses stretched forth his rod over the land of Egypt, and Jehovah brought an east wind upon the land all that day, and all the night; and when it was morning, the east wind brought the locusts. ^14And the locusts went up over all the land of Egypt, and rested in all the borders of Egypt; very grievous were they; before them there were no such locusts as they, neither after them shall be such. ^15For they covered the face of the whole earth, so that the land was darkened; and they did eat every herb of the land, and all the fruit of the trees which the hail had left: and there remained not any green thing, either tree or herb of the field, through all the land of Egypt. ^16Then Pharaoh called for Moses and Aaron in haste; and he said, I have sinned against Jehovah your God, and against you. ^17Now therefore forgive, I pray thee, my sin only this once, and entreat Jehovah your God, that he may take away from me this death only. ^18And he went out from Pharaoh, and entreated Jehovah. ^19And Jehovah turned an exceeding strong west wind, which took up the locusts, and drove them into the Red Sea; there remained not one locust in all the border of Egypt. ^20But Jehovah hardened Pharaoh's heart, and he did not let the children of Israel go.

^21And Jehovah said unto Moses, Stretch out thy hand toward heaven, that there may be darkness over the land of Egypt, even darkness which may be felt. ^22And Moses stretched forth his hand toward heaven; and there was a thick darkness in all the land of Egypt three days; ^23they saw not one another, neither rose any one from his place for three days: but all the children of Israel had light in their dwellings. ^24And Pharaoh called unto Moses, and said, Go ye, serve Jehovah; only let your flocks and your herds be stayed: let your little ones also go with you. ^25And Moses said, Thou must also give into our hand sacrifices and burnt-offerings, that we may sacrifice unto Jehovah our God. ^26Our cattle also shall go with us; there shall not a hoof be left behind: for thereof must we take to serve Jehovah our God; and we know not with what we must serve Jehovah, until we come thither. ^27But Jehovah hardened Pharaoh's heart, and he would not let them go. ^28And Pharaoh said unto him, Get thee from me, take heed to thyself, see my face no more; for in the day thou seest my face thou shalt die. ^29And Moses said, Thou hast spoken well. I will see thy face again no more.

Exodus 11

11

^1And Jehovah said unto Moses, Yet one plague more will I bring upon Pharaoh, and upon Egypt; afterwards he will let you go hence: when he shall let you go, he shall surely thrust you out hence altogether. ^2Speak now in the ears of the people, and let them ask every man of his neighbor, and every woman of her neighbor, jewels of silver, and jewels of gold. ^3And Jehovah gave the people favor in the sight of the Egyptians. Moreover the man Moses was very great in the land of Egypt, in the sight of Pharaoh's servants, and in the sight of the people.

^4And Moses said, Thus saith Jehovah, About midnight will I go out into the midst of Egypt: ^5and all the first-born in the land of Egypt shall die, from the first-born of Pharaoh that sitteth upon his throne, even unto the first-born of the maid-servant that is behind the mill; and all the first-born of cattle. ^6And there shall be a great cry throughout all the land of Egypt, such as there hath not been, nor shall be any more. ^7But against any of the children of Israel shall not a dog move his tongue, against man or beast: that ye may know how that Jehovah doth make a distinction between the Egyptians and Israel. ^8And all these thy servants shall come down unto me, and bow down themselves unto me, saying, Get thee out, and all the people that follow thee: and after that I will go out. And he went out from Pharaoh in hot anger.

^9And Jehovah said unto Moses, Pharaoh will not hearken unto you; that my wonders may be multiplied in the land of Egypt. ^10And Moses and Aaron did all these wonders before Pharaoh: and Jehovah hardened Pharaoh's heart, and he did not let the children of Israel go out of his land.

Exodus 12

12

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt, saying, ^2This month shall be unto you the beginning of months: it shall be the first month of the year to you. ^3Speak ye unto all the congregation of Israel, saying, In the tenth day of this month they shall take to them every man a lamb, according to their fathers' houses, a lamb for a household: ^4and if the household be too little for a lamb, then shall he and his neighbor next unto his house take one according to the number of the souls; according to every man's eating ye shall make your count for the lamb. ^5Your lamb shall be without blemish, a male a year old: ye shall take it from the sheep, or from the goats: ^6and ye shall keep it until the fourteenth day of the same month; and the whole assembly of the congregation of Israel shall kill it at even. ^7And they shall take of the blood, and put it on the two side-posts and on the lintel, upon the houses wherein they shall eat it. ^8And they shall eat the flesh in that night, roast with fire, and unleavened bread; with bitter herbs they shall eat it. ^9Eat not of it raw, nor boiled at all with water, but roast with fire; its head with its legs and with the inwards thereof. ^10And ye shall let nothing of it remain until the morning; but that which remaineth of it until the morning ye shall burn with fire. ^11And thus shall ye eat it: with your loins girded, your shoes on your feet, and your staff in your hand; and ye shall eat it in haste: it is Jehovah's passover. ^12For I will go through the land of Egypt in that night, and will smite all the first-born in the land of Egypt, both man and beast; and against all the gods of Egypt I will execute judgments: I am Jehovah. ^13And the blood shall be to you for a token upon the houses where ye are: and when I see the blood, I will pass over you, and there shall no plague be upon you to destroy you, when I smite the land of Egypt. ^14And this day shall be unto you for a memorial, and ye shall keep it a feast to Jehovah: throughout your generations ye shall keep it a feast by an ordinance for ever.

^15Seven days shall ye eat unleavened bread; even the first day ye shall put away leaven out of your houses: for whosoever eateth leavened bread from the first day until the seventh day, that soul shall be cut off from Israel. ^16And in the first day there shall be to you a holy convocation, and in the seventh day a holy convocation; no manner of work shall be done in them, save that which every man must eat, that only may be done by you. ^17And ye shall observe the feast of unleavened bread; for in this selfsame day have I brought your hosts out of the land of Egypt: therefore shall ye observe this day throughout your generations by an ordinance for ever. ^18In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at even, ye shall eat unleavened bread, until the one and twentieth day of the month at even. ^19Seven days shall there be no leaven found in your houses: for whosoever eateth that which is leavened, that soul shall be cut off from the congregation of Israel, whether he be a sojourner, or one that is born in the land. ^20Ye shall eat nothing leavened; in all your habitations shall ye eat unleavened bread.

^21Then Moses called for all the elders of Israel, and said unto them, Draw out, and take you lambs according to your families, and kill the passover. ^22And ye shall take a bunch of hyssop, and dip it in the blood that is in the basin, and strike the lintel and the two side-posts with the blood that is in the basin; and none of you shall go out of the door of his house until the morning. ^23For Jehovah will pass through to smite the Egyptians; and when he seeth the blood upon the lintel, and on the two side-posts, Jehovah will pass over the door, and will not suffer the destroyer to come in unto your houses to smite you. ^24And ye shall observe this thing for an ordinance to thee and to thy sons for ever. ^25And it shall come to pass, when ye are come to the land which Jehovah will give you, according as he hath promised, that ye shall keep this service. ^26And it shall come to pass, when your children shall say unto you, What mean ye by this service? ^27that ye shall say, It is the sacrifice of Jehovah's passover, who passed over the houses of the children of Israel in Egypt, when he smote the Egyptians, and delivered our houses. And the people bowed the head and worshipped. ^28And the children of Israel went and did so; as Jehovah had commanded Moses and Aaron, so did they.

^29And it came to pass at midnight, that Jehovah smote all the first-born in the land of Egypt, from the first-born of Pharaoh that sat on his throne unto the first-born of the captive that was in the dungeon; and all the first-born of cattle. ^30And Pharaoh rose up in the night, he, and all his servants, and all the Egyptians; and there was a great cry in Egypt, for there was not a house where there was not one dead. ^31And he called for Moses and Aaron by night, and said, Rise up, get you forth from among my people, both ye and the children of Israel; and go, serve Jehovah, as ye have said. ^32Take both your flocks and your herds, as ye have said, and be gone; and bless me also. ^33And the Egyptians were urgent upon the people, to send them out of the land in haste; for they said, We are all dead men. ^34And the people took their dough before it was leavened, their kneading-troughs being bound up in their clothes upon their shoulders. ^35And the children of Israel did according to the word of Moses; and they asked of the Egyptians jewels of silver, and jewels of gold, and raiment. ^36And Jehovah gave the people favor in the sight of the Egyptians, so that they let them have what they asked. And they despoiled the Egyptians.

^37And the children of Israel journeyed from Rameses to Succoth, about six hundred thousand on foot that were men, besides children. ^38And a mixed multitude went up also with them; and flocks, and herds, even very much cattle. ^39And they baked unleavened cakes of the dough which they brought forth out of Egypt; for it was not leavened, because they were thrust out of Egypt, and could not tarry, neither had they prepared for themselves any victuals. ^40Now the time that the children of Israel dwelt in Egypt was four hundred and thirty years. ^41And it came to pass at the end of four hundred and thirty years, even the selfsame day it came to pass, that all the hosts of Jehovah went out from the land of Egypt. ^42It is a night to be much observed unto Jehovah for bringing them out from the land of Egypt: this is that night of Jehovah, to be much observed of all the children of Israel throughout their generations.

^43And Jehovah said unto Moses and Aaron, This is the ordinance of the passover: there shall no foreigner eat thereof; ^44but every man's servant that is bought for money, when thou hast circumcised him, then shall he eat thereof. ^45A sojourner and a hired servant shall not eat thereof. ^46In one house shall it be eaten; thou shalt not carry forth aught of the flesh abroad out of the house; neither shall ye break a bone thereof. ^47All the congregation of Israel shall keep it. ^48And when a stranger shall sojourn with thee, and will keep the passover to Jehovah, let all his males be circumcised, and then let him come near and keep it; and he shall be as one that is born in the land: but no uncircumcised person shall eat thereof. ^49One law shall be to him that is home-born, and unto the stranger that sojourneth among you. ^50Thus did all the children of Israel; as Jehovah commanded Moses and Aaron, so did they. ^51And it came to pass the selfsame day, that Jehovah did bring the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt by their hosts.

Exodus 13

13

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Sanctify unto me all the first-born, whatsoever openeth the womb among the children of Israel, both of man and of beast: it is mine.

^3And Moses said unto the people, Remember this day, in which ye came out from Egypt, out of the house of bondage; for by strength of hand Jehovah brought you out from this place: there shall no leavened bread be eaten. ^4This day ye go forth in the month Abib. ^5And it shall be, when Jehovah shall bring thee into the land of the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Amorite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite, which he sware unto thy fathers to give thee, a land flowing with milk and honey, that thou shalt keep this service in this month. ^6Seven days thou shalt eat unleavened bread, and in the seventh day shall be a feast to Jehovah. ^7Unleavened bread shall be eaten throughout the seven days; and there shall no leavened bread be seen with thee, neither shall there be leaven seen with thee, in all thy borders. ^8And thou shalt tell thy son in that day, saying, It is because of that which Jehovah did for me when I came forth out of Egypt. ^9And it shall be for a sign unto thee upon thy hand, and for a memorial between thine eyes, that the law of Jehovah may be in thy mouth: for with a strong hand hath Jehovah brought thee out of Egypt. ^10Thou shalt therefore keep this ordinance in its season from year to year.

^11And it shall be, when Jehovah shall bring thee into the land of the Canaanite, as he sware unto thee and to thy fathers, and shall give it thee, ^12that thou shalt set apart unto Jehovah all that openeth the womb, and every firstling which thou hast that cometh of a beast; the males shall be Jehovah's. ^13And every firstling of an ass thou shalt redeem with a lamb; and if thou wilt not redeem it, then thou shalt break its neck: and all the first-born of man among thy sons shalt thou redeem. ^14And it shall be, when thy son asketh thee in time to come, saying, What is this? that thou shalt say unto him, By strength of hand Jehovah brought us out from Egypt, from the house of bondage: ^15and it came to pass, when Pharaoh would hardly let us go, that Jehovah slew all the first-born in the land of Egypt, both the first-born of man, and the first-born of beast: therefore I sacrifice to Jehovah all that openeth the womb, being males; but all the first-born of my sons I redeem. ^16And it shall be for a sign upon thy hand, and for frontlets between thine eyes: for by strength of hand Jehovah brought us forth out of Egypt.

^17And it came to pass, when Pharaoh had let the people go, that God led them not by the way of the land of the Philistines, although that was near; for God said, Lest peradventure the people repent when they see war, and they return to Egypt: ^18but God led the people about, by the way of the wilderness by the Red Sea: and the children of Israel went up armed out of the land of Egypt. ^19And Moses took the bones of Joseph with him: for he had straitly sworn the children of Israel, saying, God will surely visit you; and ye shall carry up my bones away hence with you. ^20And they took their journey from Succoth, and encamped in Etham, in the edge of the wilderness. ^21And Jehovah went before them by day in a pillar of cloud, to lead them the way, and by night in a pillar of fire, to give them light, that they might go by day and by night: ^22the pillar of cloud by day, and the pillar of fire by night, departed not from before the people.

Exodus 14

14

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, that they turn back and encamp before Pihahiroth, between Migdol and the sea, before Baal-zephon: over against it shall ye encamp by the sea. ^3And Pharaoh will say of the children of Israel, They are entangled in the land, the wilderness hath shut them in. ^4And I will harden Pharaoh's heart, and he shall follow after them; and I will get me honor upon Pharaoh, and upon all his host: and the Egyptians shall know that I am Jehovah. And they did so. ^5And it was told the king of Egypt that the people were fled: and the heart of Pharaoh and of his servants was changed towards the people, and they said, What is this we have done, that we have let Israel go from serving us? ^6And he made ready his chariot, and took his people with him: ^7and he took six hundred chosen chariots, and all the chariots of Egypt, and captains over all of them. ^8And Jehovah hardened the heart of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and he pursued after the children of Israel: for the children of Israel went out with a high hand. ^9And the Egyptians pursued after them, all the horses and chariots of Pharaoh, and his horsemen, and his army, and overtook them encamping by the sea, beside Pihahiroth, before Baal-zephon.

^10And when Pharaoh drew nigh, the children of Israel lifted up their eyes, and, behold, the Egyptians were marching after them; and they were sore afraid: and the children of Israel cried out unto Jehovah. ^11And they said unto Moses, Because there were no graves in Egypt, hast thou taken us away to die in the wilderness? wherefore hast thou dealt thus with us, to bring us forth out of Egypt? ^12Is not this the word that we spake unto thee in Egypt, saying, Let us alone, that we may serve the Egyptians? For it were better for us to serve the Egyptians, than that we should die in the wilderness. ^13And Moses said unto the people, Fear ye not, stand still, and see the salvation of Jehovah, which he will work for you to-day: for the Egyptians whom ye have seen to-day, ye shall see them again no more for ever. ^14Jehovah will fight for you, and ye shall hold your peace.

^15And Jehovah said unto Moses, Wherefore criest thou unto me? speak unto the children of Israel, that they go forward. ^16And lift thou up thy rod, and stretch out thy hand over the sea, and divide it: and the children of Israel shall go into the midst of the sea on dry ground. ^17And I, behold, I will harden the hearts of the Egyptians, and they shall go in after them: and I will get me honor upon Pharaoh, and upon all his host, upon his chariots, and upon his horsemen. ^18And the Egyptians shall know that I am Jehovah, when I have gotten me honor upon Pharaoh, upon his chariots, and upon his horsemen. ^19And the angel of God, who went before the camp of Israel, removed and went behind them; and the pillar of cloud removed from before them, and stood behind them: ^20and it came between the camp of Egypt and the camp of Israel; and there was the cloud and the darkness, yet gave it light by night: and the one came not near the other all the night.

^21And Moses stretched out his hand over the sea; and Jehovah caused the sea to go back by a strong east wind all the night, and made the sea dry land, and the waters were divided. ^22And the children of Israel went into the midst of the sea upon the dry ground: and the waters were a wall unto them on their right hand, and on their left. ^23And the Egyptians pursued, and went in after them into the midst of the sea, all Pharaoh's horses, his chariots, and his horsemen. ^24And it came to pass in the morning watch, that Jehovah looked forth upon the host of the Egyptians through the pillar of fire and of cloud, and discomfited the host of the Egyptians. ^25And he took off their chariot wheels, and they drove them heavily; so that the Egyptians said, Let us flee from the face of Israel; for Jehovah fighteth for them against the Egyptians.

^26And Jehovah said unto Moses, Stretch out thy hand over the sea, that the waters may come again upon the Egyptians, upon their chariots, and upon their horsemen. ^27And Moses stretched forth his hand over the sea, and the sea returned to its strength when the morning appeared; and the Egyptians fled against it; and Jehovah overthrew the Egyptians in the midst of the sea. ^28And the waters returned, and covered the chariots, and the horsemen, even all the host of Pharaoh that went in after them into the sea; there remained not so much as one of them. ^29But the children of Israel walked upon dry land in the midst of the sea; and the waters were a wall unto them on their right hand, and on their left. ^30Thus Jehovah saved Israel that day out of the hand of the Egyptians; and Israel saw the Egyptians dead upon the sea-shore. ^31And Israel saw the great work which Jehovah did upon the Egyptians, and the people feared Jehovah: and they believed in Jehovah, and in his servant Moses.

Exodus 15

15

^1Then sang Moses and the children of Israel this song unto Jehovah, and spake, saying,

I will sing unto Jehovah, for he hath triumphed gloriously:

The horse and his rider hath he thrown into the sea.

^2Jehovah is my strength and song,

And he is become my salvation:

This is my God, and I will praise him;

My father's God, and I will exalt him.

^3Jehovah is a man of war:

Jehovah is his name.

^4Pharaoh's chariots and his host hath he cast into the sea;

And his chosen captains are sunk in the Red Sea.

^5The deeps cover them:

They went down into the depths like a stone.

^6Thy right hand, O Jehovah, is glorious in power,

Thy right hand, O Jehovah, dasheth in pieces the enemy.

^7And in the greatness of thine excellency thou overthrowest them that rise up against thee: Thou sendest forth thy wrath, it consumeth them as stubble.

^8And with the blast of thy nostrils the waters were piled up,

The floods stood upright as a heap;

The deeps were congealed in the heart of the sea.

^9The enemy said, I will pursue, I will overtake, I will divide the spoil;

My desire shall be satisfied upon them;

I will draw my sword, my hand shall destroy them.

^10Thou didst blow with thy wind, the sea covered them:

They sank as lead in the mighty waters.

^11Who is like unto thee, O Jehovah, among the gods?

Who is like thee, glorious in holiness,

Fearful in praises, doing wonders?

^12Thou stretchedst out thy right hand,

The earth swallowed them.

^13Thou in thy lovingkindness hast led the people that thou hast redeemed:

Thou hast guided them in thy strength to thy holy habitation.

^14The peoples have heard, they tremble:

Pangs have taken hold on the inhabitants of Philistia.

^15Then were the chiefs of Edom dismayed;

The mighty men of Moab, trembling taketh hold upon them:

All the inhabitants of Canaan are melted away.

^16Terror and dread falleth upon them;

By the greatness of thine arm they are as still as a stone;

Till thy people pass over, O Jehovah,

Till the people pass over that thou hast purchased.

^17Thou wilt bring them in, and plant them in the mountain of thine inheritance,

The place, O Jehovah, which thou hast made for thee to dwell in,

The sanctuary, O Lord, which thy hands have established.

^18Jehovah shall reign for ever and ever.

^19For the horses of Pharaoh went in with his chariots and with his horsemen into the sea, and Jehovah brought back the waters of the sea upon them; but the children of Israel walked on dry land in the midst of the sea. ^20And Miriam the prophetess, the sister of Aaron, took a timbrel in her hand; and all the women went out after her with timbrels and with dances. ^21And Miriam answered them,

Sing ye to Jehovah, for he hath triumphed gloriously;

The horse and his rider hath he thrown into the sea.

^22And Moses led Israel onward from the Red Sea, and they went out into the wilderness of Shur; and they went three days in the wilderness, and found no water. ^23And when they came to Marah, they could not drink of the waters of Marah, for they were bitter: therefore the name of it was called Marah. ^24And the people murmured against Moses, saying, What shall we drink? ^25An he cried unto Jehovah; And Jehovah showed him a tree, and he cast it into the waters, and the waters were made sweet. There he made for them a statute and an ordinance, and there he proved them; ^26and he said, If thou wilt diligently hearken to the voice of Jehovah thy God, and wilt do that which is right in his eyes, and wilt give ear to his commandments, and keep all his statutes, I will put none of the diseases upon thee, which I have put upon the Egyptians: for I am Jehovah that healeth thee. ^27And they came to Elim, where were twelve springs of water, and threescore and ten palm-trees: and they encamped there by the waters.

Exodus 16

16

^1And they took their journey from Elim, and all the congregation of the children of Israel came unto the wilderness of Sin, which is between Elim and Sinai, on the fifteenth day of the second month after their departing out of the land of Egypt. ^2And the whole congregation of the children of Israel murmured against Moses and against Aaron in the wilderness: ^3and the children of Israel said unto them, Would that we had died by the hand of Jehovah in the land of Egypt, when we sat by the flesh-pots, when we did eat bread to the full; for ye have brought us forth into this wilderness, to kill this whole assembly with hunger.

^4Then said Jehovah unto Moses, Behold, I will rain bread from heaven for you; and the people shall go out and gather a day's portion every day, that I may prove them, whether they will walk in my law, or not. ^5And it shall come to pass on the sixth day, that they shall prepare that which they bring in, and it shall be twice as much as they gather daily. ^6And Moses and Aaron said unto all the children of Israel, At even, then ye shall know that Jehovah hath brought you out from the land of Egypt; ^7and in the morning, then ye shall see the glory of Jehovah; for that he heareth your murmurings against Jehovah: and what are we, that ye murmur against us? ^8And Moses said, This shall be, when Jehovah shall give you in the evening flesh to eat, and in the morning bread to the full; for that Jehovah heareth your murmurings which ye murmur against him: and what are we? your murmurings are not against us, but against Jehovah. ^9And Moses said unto Aaron, Say unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, Come near before Jehovah; for he hath heard your murmurings. ^10And it came to pass, as Aaron spake unto the whole congregation of the children of Israel, that they looked toward the wilderness, and, behold, the glory of Jehovah appeared in the cloud. ^11And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^12I have heard the murmurings of the children of Israel: speak unto them, saying, At even ye shall eat flesh, and in the morning ye shall be filled with bread: and ye shall know that I am Jehovah your God.

^13And it came to pass at even, that the quails came up, and covered the camp: and in the morning the dew lay round about the camp. ^14And when the dew that lay was gone up, behold, upon the face of the wilderness a small round thing, small as the hoar-frost on the ground. ^15And when the children of Israel saw it, they said one to another, What is it? For they knew not what it was. And Moses said unto them, It is the bread which Jehovah hath given you to eat. ^16This is the thing which Jehovah hath commanded, Gather ye of it every man according to his eating; an omer a head, according to the number of your persons, shall ye take it, every man for them that are in his tent. ^17And the children of Israel did so, and gathered some more, some less. ^18And when they measured it with an omer, he that gathered much had nothing over, and he that gathered little had no lack; they gathered every man according to his eating. ^19And Moses said unto them, Let no man leave of it till the morning. ^20Notwithstanding they hearkened not unto Moses; but some of them left of it until the morning, and it bred worms, and became foul: and Moses was wroth with them. ^21And they gathered it morning by morning, every man according to his eating: and when the sun waxed hot, it melted. ^22And it came to pass, that on the sixth day they gathered twice as much bread, two omers for each one: and all the rulers of the congregation came and told Moses. ^23And he said unto them, This is that which Jehovah hath spoken, Tomorrow is a solemn rest, a holy sabbath unto Jehovah: bake that which ye will bake, and boil that which ye will boil; and all that remaineth over lay up for you to be kept until the morning. ^24And they laid it up till the morning, as Moses bade: and it did not become foul, neither was there any worm therein. ^25And Moses said, Eat that to-day; for to-day is a sabbath unto Jehovah: to-day ye shall not find it in the field. ^26Six days ye shall gather it; but on the seventh day is the sabbath, in it there shall be none. ^27And it came to pass on the seventh day, that there went out some of the people to gather, and they found none. ^28And Jehovah said unto Moses, How long refuse ye to keep my commandments and my laws? ^29See, for that Jehovah hath given you the sabbath, therefore he giveth you on the sixth day the bread of two days; abide ye every man in his place, let no man go out of his place on the seventh day. ^30So the people rested on the seventh day.

^31And the house of Israel called the name thereof Manna: and it was like coriander seed, white; and the taste of it was like wafers made with honey. ^32And Moses said, This is the thing which Jehovah hath commanded, Let an omerful of it be kept throughout your generations, that they may see the bread wherewith I fed you in the wilderness, when I brought you forth from the land of Egypt. ^33And Moses said unto Aaron, Take a pot, and put an omerful of manna therein, and lay it up before Jehovah, to be kept throughout your generations. ^34As Jehovah commanded Moses, so Aaron laid it up before the Testimony, to be kept. ^35And the children of Israel did eat the manna forty years, until they came to a land inhabited; they did eat the manna, until they came unto the borders of the land of Canaan. ^36Now an omer is the tenth part of an ephah.

Exodus 17

17

^1And all the congregation of the children of Israel journeyed from the wilderness of Sin, by their journeys, according to the commandment of Jehovah, and encamped in Rephidim: and there was no water for the people to drink. ^2Wherefore the people stove with Moses, and said, Give us water that we may drink. And Moses said unto them, Why strive ye with me? Wherefore do ye tempt Jehovah? ^3And the people thirsted there for water; and the people murmured against Moses, and said, Wherefore hast thou brought us up out of Egypt, to kill us and our children and our cattle with thirst? ^4And Moses cried unto Jehovah, saying, What shall I do unto this people? They are almost ready to stone me. ^5And Jehovah said unto Moses, Pass on before the people, and take with thee of the elders of Israel; and they rod, wherewith thou smotest the river, take in thy hand, and go. ^6Behold, I will stand before thee there upon the rock in Horeb; and thou shalt smite the rock, and there shall come water out of it, that the people may drink. And Moses did so in the sight of the elders of Israel. ^7And he called the name of the place Massah, and Meribah, because of the striving of the children of Israel, and because they tempted Jehovah, saying, Is Jehovah among us, or not?

^8Then came Amalek, and fought with Israel in Rephidim. ^9And Moses said unto Joshua, Choose us out men, and go out, fight with Amalek: to-morrow I will stand on the top of the hill with the rod of God in my hand. ^10So Joshua did as Moses had said to him, and fought with Amalek: and Moses, Aaron, and Hur went up to the top of the hill. ^11And it came to pass, when Moses held up his hand, that Israel prevailed; and when he let down his hand, Amalek prevailed. ^12But Moses' hands were heavy; and they took a stone, and put it under him, and he sat thereon; and Aaron and Hur stayed up his hands, the one on the one side, and the other on the other side; And his hands were steady until the going down of the sun. ^13And Joshua discomfited Amalek and his people with the edge of the sword. ^14And Jehovah said unto Moses, Write this for a memorial in a book, and rehearse it in the ears of Joshua: that I will utterly blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under heaven. ^15And Moses built an altar, and called the name of it Jehovah-nissi; ^16And he said, Jehovah hath sworn: Jehovah will have war with Amalek from generation to generation.

Exodus 18

18

^1Now Jethro, the priest of Midian, Moses' father-in-law, heard of all that God had done for Moses, and for Israel his people, how that Jehovah had brought Israel out of Egypt. ^2And Jethro, Moses' father-in-law, took Zipporah, Moses' wife, after he had sent her away, ^3and her two sons; of whom the name of the one was Gershom; for he said, I have been a sojourner in a foreign land: ^4and the name of the other was Eliezer; for he said, The God of my father was my help, and delivered me from the sword of Pharaoh. ^5And Jethro, Moses' father-in-law, came with his sons and his wife unto Moses into the wilderness where he was encamped, at the mount of God: ^6and he said unto Moses, I, thy father-in-law Jethro, am come unto thee, and thy wife, and her two sons with her. ^7And Moses went out to meet his father-in-law, and did obeisance, and kissed him: and they asked each other of their welfare; and they came into the tent. ^8And Moses told his father-in-law all that Jehovah had done unto Pharaoh and to the Egyptians for Israel's sake, all the travail that had come upon them by the way, and how Jehovah delivered them. ^9And Jethro rejoiced for all the goodness which Jehovah had done to Israel, in that he had delivered them out of the hand of the Egyptians. ^10And Jethro said, Blessed be Jehovah, who hath delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of Pharaoh; who hath delivered the people from under the hand of the Egyptians. ^11Now I know that Jehovah is greater than all gods; yea, in the thing wherein they dealt proudly against them. ^12And Jethro, Moses' father-in-law, took a burnt-offering and sacrifices for God: and Aaron came, and all the elders of Israel, to eat bread with Moses' father-in-law before God.

^13And it came to pass on the morrow, that Moses sat to judge the people: and the people stood about Moses from the morning unto the evening. ^14And when Moses' father-in-law saw all that he did to the people, he said, What is this thing that thou doest to the people? why sittest thou thyself alone, and all the people stand about thee from morning unto even? ^15And Moses said unto his father-in-law, Because the people come unto me to inquire of God: ^16when they have a matter, they come unto me; and I judge between a man and his neighbor, and I make them know the statutes of God, and his laws. ^17And Moses' father-in-law said unto him, The thing that thou doest is not good. ^18Thou wilt surely wear away, both thou, and this people that is with thee: for the thing is too heavy for thee; thou art not able to perform it thyself alone. ^19Hearken now unto my voice, I will give thee counsel, and God be with thee: be thou for the people to God-ward, and bring thou the causes unto God: ^20and thou shalt teach them the statutes and the laws, and shalt show them the way wherein they must walk, and the work that they must do. ^21Moreover thou shalt provide out of all the people able men, such as fear God, men of truth, hating unjust gain; and place such over them, to be rulers of thousands, rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens: ^22and let them judge the people at all seasons: and it shall be, that every great matter they shall bring unto thee, but every small matter they shall judge themselves: so shall it be easier for thyself, and they shall bear the burden with thee. ^23If thou shalt do this thing, and God command thee so, then thou shalt be able to endure, and all this people also shall go to their place in peace. ^24So Moses hearkened to the voice of his father-in-law, and did all that he had said. ^25And Moses chose able men out of all Israel, and made them heads over the people, rulers of thousands, rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and rulers of tens. ^26And they judged the people at all seasons: the hard causes they brought unto Moses, but every small matter they judged themselves. ^27And Moses let his father-in-law depart; and he went his way into his own land.

Exodus 19

19

^1In the third month after the children of Israel were gone forth out of the land of Egypt, the same day came they into the wilderness of Sinai. ^2And when they were departed from Rephidim, and were come to the wilderness of Sinai, they encamped in the wilderness; and there Israel encamped before the mount. ^3And Moses went up unto God, and Jehovah called unto him out of the mountain, saying, Thus shalt thou say to the house of Jacob, and tell the children of Israel: ^4Ye have seen what I did unto the Egyptians, and how I bare you on eagles' wings, and brought you unto myself. ^5Now therefore, if ye will obey my voice indeed, and keep my covenant, then ye shall be mine own possession from among all peoples: for all the earth is mine: ^6and ye shall be unto me a kingdom of priests, and a holy nation. These are the words which thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel.

^7And Moses came and called for the elders of the people, and set before them all these words which Jehovah commanded him. ^8And all the people answered together, and said, All that Jehovah hath spoken we will do. And Moses reported the words of the people unto Jehovah. ^9And Jehovah said unto Moses, Lo, I come unto thee in a thick cloud, that the people may hear when I speak with thee, and may also believe thee for ever. And Moses told the words of the people unto Jehovah. ^10And Jehovah said unto Moses, Go unto the people, and sanctify them to-day and to-morrow, and let them wash their garments, ^11and be ready against the third day; for the third day Jehovah will come down in the sight of all the people upon mount Sinai. ^12And thou shalt set bounds unto the people round about, saying, Take heed to yourselves, that ye go not up into the mount, or touch the border of it: whosoever toucheth the mount shall be surely put to death: ^13no hand shall touch him, but he shall surely be stoned, or shot through; whether it be beast or man, he shall not live: when the trumpet soundeth long, they shall come up to the mount. ^14And Moses went down from the mount unto the people, and sanctified the people; and they washed their garments. ^15And he said unto the people, Be ready against the third day: come not near a woman.

^16And it came to pass on the third day, when it was morning, that there were thunders and lightnings, and a thick cloud upon the mount, and the voice of a trumpet exceeding loud; and all the people that were in the camp trembled. ^17And Moses brought forth the people out of the camp to meet God; and they stood at the nether part of the mount. ^18And mount Sinai, the whole of it, smoked, because Jehovah descended upon it in fire; and the smoke thereof ascended as the smoke of a furnace, and the whole mount quaked greatly. ^19And when the voice of the trumpet waxed louder and louder, Moses spake, and God answered him by a voice. ^20And Jehovah came down upon mount Sinai, to the top of the mount: and Jehovah called Moses to the top of the mount; and Moses went up. ^21And Jehovah said unto Moses, Go down, charge the people, lest they break through unto Jehovah to gaze, and many of them perish. ^22And let the priests also, that come near to Jehovah, sanctify themselves, lest Jehovah break forth upon them. ^23And Moses said unto Jehovah, The people cannot come up to mount Sinai: for thou didst charge us, saying, Set bounds about the mount, and sanctify it. ^24And Jehovah said unto him, Go, get thee down; and thou shalt come up, thou, and Aaron with thee: but let not the priests and the people break through to come up unto Jehovah, lest he break forth upon them. ^25So Moses went down unto the people, and told them.

Exodus 20

20

^1And God spake all these words, saying, ^2I am Jehovah thy God, who brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage. ^3Thou shalt have no other gods before me.

^4Thou shalt not make unto thee a graven image, nor any likeness of any thing that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth. ^5Thou shalt not bow down thyself unto them, nor serve them, for I Jehovah thy God am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children, upon the third and upon the fourth generation of them that hate me, ^6and showing lovingkindness unto thousands of them that love me and keep my commandments.

^7Thou shalt not take the name of Jehovah thy God in vain; for Jehovah will not hold him guiltless that taketh his name in vain.

^8Remember the sabbath day, to keep it holy. ^9Six days shalt thou labor, and do all thy work; ^10but the seventh day is a sabbath unto Jehovah thy God: in it thou shalt not do any work, thou, nor thy son, nor thy daughter, thy man-servant, nor thy maid-servant, nor thy cattle, nor thy stranger that is within thy gates: ^11for in six days Jehovah made heaven and earth, the sea, and all that in them is, and rested the seventh day: wherefore Jehovah blessed the sabbath day, and hallowed it.

^12Honor thy father and thy mother, that thy days may be long in the land which Jehovah thy God giveth thee.

^13Thou shalt not kill.

^14Thou shalt not commit adultery.

^15Thou shalt not steal.

^16Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbor.

^17Thou shalt not covet thy neighbor's house, thou shalt not covet thy neighbor's wife, nor his man-servant, nor his maid-servant, nor his ox, nor his ass, nor anything that is thy neighbor's.

^18And all the people perceived the thunderings, and the lightnings, and the voice of the trumpet, and the mountain smoking: and when the people saw it, they trembled, and stood afar off. ^19And they said unto Moses, Speak thou with us, and we will hear; but let not God speak with us, lest we die. ^20And Moses said unto the people, Fear not: for God is come to prove you, and that his fear may be before you, that ye sin not. ^21And the people stood afar off, and Moses drew near unto the thick darkness where God was.

^22And Jehovah said unto Moses, Thus thou shalt say unto the children of Israel, Ye yourselves have seen that I have talked with you from heaven. ^23Ye shall not make other gods with me; gods of silver, or gods of gold, ye shall not make unto you. ^24An altar of earth thou shalt make unto me, and shalt sacrifice thereon thy burnt-offerings, and thy peace-offerings, thy sheep, and thine oxen: in every place where I record my name I will come unto thee and I will bless thee. ^25And if thou make me an altar of stone, thou shalt not build it of hewn stones; for if thou lift up thy tool upon it, thou hast polluted it. ^26Neither shalt thou go up by steps unto mine altar, that thy nakedness be not uncovered thereon.

Exodus 21

21

^1Now these are the ordinances which thou shalt set before them.

^2If thou buy a Hebrew servant, six years he shall serve: and in the seventh he shall go out free for nothing. ^3If he come in by himself, he shall go out by himself: if he be married, then his wife shall go out with him. ^4If his master give him a wife and she bear him sons or daughters; the wife and her children shall be her master's, and he shall go out by himself. ^5But if the servant shall plainly say, I love my master, my wife, and my children; I will not go out free: ^6then his master shall bring him unto God, and shall bring him to the door, or unto the door-post; and his master shall bore his ear through with an awl; and he shall serve him for ever.

^7And if a man sell his daughter to be a maid-servant, she shall not go out as the men-servants do. ^8If she please not her master, who hath espoused her to himself, then shall he let her be redeemed: to sell her unto a foreign people he shall have no power, seeing he hath dealt deceitfully with her. ^9And if he espouse her unto his son, he shall deal with her after the manner of daughters. ^10If he take him another wife; her food, her raiment, and her duty of marriage, shall he not diminish. ^11And if he do not these three things unto her, then shall she go out for nothing, without money.

^12He that smiteth a man, so that he dieth, shall surely be put to death. ^13And if a man lie not in wait, but God deliver him into his hand; then I will appoint thee a place whither he shall flee. ^14And if a man come presumptuously upon his neighbor, to slay him with guile; thou shalt take him from mine altar, that he may die.

^15And he that smiteth his father, or his mother, shall be surely put to death.

^16And he that stealeth a man, and selleth him, or if he be found in his hand, he shall surely be put to death.

^17And he that curseth his father or his mother, shall surely be put to death.

^18And if men contend, and one smite the other with a stone, or with his fist, and he die not, but keep his bed; ^19if he rise again, and walk abroad upon his staff, then shall he that smote him be quit: only he shall pay for the loss of his time, and shall cause him to be thoroughly healed.

^20And if a man smite his servant, or his maid, with a rod, and he die under his hand; he shall surely be punished. ^21Notwithstanding, if he continue a day or two, he shall not be punished: for he is his money.

^22And if men strive together, and hurt a woman with child, so that her fruit depart, and yet no harm follow; he shall be surely fined, according as the woman's husband shall lay upon him; and he shall pay as the judges determine. ^23But if any harm follow, then thou shalt give life for life, ^24eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot, ^25burning for burning, wound for wound, stripe for stripe.

^26And if a man smite the eye of his servant, or the eye of his maid, and destroy it; he shall let him go free for his eye's sake. ^27And if he smite out his man-servant's tooth, or his maid-servant's tooth, he shall let him go free for his tooth's sake.

^28And if an ox gore a man or a woman to death, the ox shall be surely stoned, and its flesh shall not be eaten; but the owner of the ox shall be quit. ^29But if the ox was wont to gore in time past, and it hath been testified to its owner, and he hath not kept it in, but it hath killed a man or a woman, the ox shall be stoned, and its owner also shall be put to death. ^30If there be laid on him a ransom, then he shall give for the redemption of his life whatsoever is laid upon him. ^31Whether it have gored a son, or have gored a daughter, according to this judgment shall it be done unto him. ^32If the ox gore a man-servant or a maid-servant, there shall be given unto their master thirty shekels of silver, and the ox shall be stoned.

^33And if a man shall open a pit, or if a man shall dig a pit and not cover it, and an ox or an ass fall therein, ^34the owner of the pit shall make it good; he shall give money unto the owner thereof, and the dead beast shall be his.

^35And if one man's ox hurt another's, so that it dieth, then they shall sell the live ox, and divide the price of it: and the dead also they shall divide. ^36Or if it be known that the ox was wont to gore in time past, and its owner hath not kept it in, he shall surely pay ox for ox, and the dead beast shall be his own.

Exodus 22

22

^1If a man shall steal an ox, or a sheep, and kill it, or sell it; he shall pay five oxen for an ox, and four sheep for a sheep. ^2If the thief be found breaking in, and be smitten so that he dieth, there shall be no bloodguiltiness for him. ^3If the sun be risen upon him, there shall be bloodguiltiness for him; he shall make restitution: if he have nothing, then he shall be sold for his theft. ^4If the theft be found in his hand alive, whether it be ox, or ass, or sheep, he shall pay double.

^5If a man shall cause a field or vineyard to be eaten, and shall let his beast loose, and it feed in another man's field; of the best of his own field, and of the best of his own vineyard, shall he make restitution.

^6If fire break out, and catch in thorns, so that the shocks of grain, or the standing grain, or the field are consumed; he that kindled the fire shall surely make restitution.

^7If a man shall deliver unto his neighbor money or stuff to keep, and it be stolen out of the man's house; if the thief be found, he shall pay double. ^8If the thief be not found, then the master of the house shall come near unto God, to see whether he have not put his hand unto his neighbor's goods. ^9For every matter of trespass, whether it be for ox, for ass, for sheep, for raiment, or for any manner of lost thing, whereof one saith, This is it, the cause of both parties shall come before God; he whom God shall condemn shall pay double unto his neighbor.

^10If a man deliver unto his neighbor an ass, or an ox, or a sheep, or any beast, to keep; and it die, or be hurt, or driven away, no man seeing it: ^11the oath of Jehovah shall be between them both, whether he hath not put his hand unto his neighbor's goods; and the owner thereof shall accept it, and he shall not make restitution. ^12But if it be stolen from him, he shall make restitution unto the owner thereof. ^13If it be torn in pieces, let him bring it for witness: he shall not make good that which was torn.

^14And if a man borrow aught of his neighbor, and it be hurt, or die, the owner thereof not being with it, he shall surely make restitution. ^15If the owner thereof be with it, he shall not make it good: if it be a hired thing, it came for its hire.

^16And if a man entice a virgin that is not betrothed, and lie with her, he shall surely pay a dowry for her to be his wife. ^17If her father utterly refuse to give her unto him, he shall pay money according to the dowry of virgins.

^18Thou shalt not suffer a sorceress to live.

^19Whosoever lieth with a beast shall surely be put to death.

^20He that sacrificeth unto any god, save unto Jehovah only, shall be utterly destroyed. ^21And a sojourner shalt thou not wrong, neither shalt thou oppress him: for ye were sojourners in the land of Egypt. ^22Ye shall not afflict any widow, or fatherless child. ^23If thou afflict them at all, and they cry at all unto me, I will surely hear their cry; ^24and my wrath shall wax hot, and I will kill you with the sword; and your wives shall be widows, and your children fatherless.

^25If thou lend money to any of my people with thee that is poor, thou shalt not be to him as a creditor; neither shall ye lay upon him interest. ^26If thou at all take thy neighbor's garment to pledge, thou shalt restore it unto him before the sun goeth down: ^27for that is his only covering, it is his garment for his skin: wherein shall he sleep? And it shall come to pass, when he crieth unto me, that I will hear; for I am gracious.

^28Thou shalt not revile God, nor curse a ruler of thy people. ^29Thou shalt not delay to offer of thy harvest, and of the outflow of thy presses. The first-born of thy sons shalt thou give unto me. ^30Likewise shalt thou do with thine oxen, and with thy sheep: seven days it shall be with its dam; on the eighth day thou shalt give it me. ^31And ye shall be holy men unto me: therefore ye shall not eat any flesh that is torn of beasts in the field; ye shall cast it to the dogs.

Exodus 23

23

^1Thou shalt not take up a false report: put not thy hand with the wicked to be an unrighteous witness. ^2Thou shalt not follow a multitude to do evil; neither shalt thou speak in a cause to turn aside after a multitude to wrest justice: ^3neither shalt thou favor a poor man in his cause.

^4If thou meet thine enemy's ox or his ass going astray, thou shalt surely bring it back to him again. ^5If thou see the ass of him that hateth thee lying under his burden, thou shalt forbear to leave him, thou shalt surely release it with him.

^6Thou shalt not wrest the justice due to thy poor in his cause. ^7Keep thee far from a false matter; and the innocent and righteous slay thou not: for I will not justify the wicked. ^8And thou shalt take no bribe: for a bribe blindeth them that have sight, and perverteth the words of the righteous. ^9And a sojourner shalt thou not oppress: for ye know the heart of a sojourner, seeing ye were sojourners in the land of Egypt.

^10And six years thou shalt sow thy land, and shalt gather in the increase thereof: ^11but the seventh year thou shalt let it rest and lie fallow; that the poor of thy people may eat: and what they leave the beast of the field shall eat. In like manner thou shalt deal with thy vineyard, and with thy oliveyard. ^12Six days thou shalt do thy work, and on the seventh day thou shalt rest; that thine ox and thine ass may have rest, and the son of thy handmaid, and the sojourner, may be refreshed. ^13And in all things that I have said unto you take ye heed: and make no mention of the name of other gods, neither let it be heard out of thy mouth.

^14Three times thou shalt keep a feast unto me in the year. ^15The feast of unleavened bread shalt thou keep: seven days thou shalt eat unleavened bread, as I commanded thee, at the time appointed in the month Abib (for in it thou camest out from Egypt); and none shall appear before me empty: ^16and the feast of harvest, the first-fruits of thy labors, which thou sowest in the field: and the feast of ingathering, at the end of the year, when thou gatherest in thy labors out of the field. ^17Three times in the year all thy males shall appear before the Lord Jehovah.

^18Thou shalt not offer the blood of my sacrifice with leavened bread; neither shall the fat of my feast remain all night until the morning. ^19The first of the first-fruits of thy ground thou shalt bring into the house of Jehovah thy God. Thou shalt not boil a kid in it mother's milk.

^20Behold, I send an angel before thee, to keep thee by the way, and to bring thee into the place which I have prepared. ^21Take ye heed before him, and hearken unto his voice; provoke him not; for he will not pardon your transgression: for my name is in him. ^22But if thou shalt indeed hearken unto his voice, and do all that I speak; then I will be an enemy unto thine enemies, and an adversary unto thine adversaries. ^23For mine angel shall go before thee, and bring thee in unto the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Canaanite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite: and I will cut them off. ^24Thou shalt not bow down to their gods, nor serve them, nor do after their works; but thou shalt utterly overthrow them, and break in pieces their pillars. ^25And ye shall serve Jehovah your God, and he will bless thy bread, and thy water; and I will take sickness away from the midst of thee. ^26There shall none cast her young, nor be barren, in thy land: the number of thy days I will fulfil. ^27I will send my terror before thee, and will discomfit all the people to whom thou shalt come, and I will make all thine enemies turn their backs unto thee. ^28And I will send the hornet before thee, which shall drive out the Hivite, the Canaanite, and the Hittite, from before thee. ^29I will not drive them out from before thee in one year, lest the land become desolate, and the beasts of the field multiply against thee. ^30By little and little I will drive them out from before thee, until thou be increased, and inherit the land. ^31And I will set thy border from the Red Sea even unto the sea of the Philistines, and from the wilderness unto the River: for I will deliver the inhabitants of the land into your hand: and thou shalt drive them out before thee. ^32Thou shalt make no covenant with them, nor with their gods. ^33They shall not dwell in thy land, lest they make thee sin against me; for if thou serve their gods, it will surely be a snare unto thee.

Exodus 24

24

^1And he said unto Moses, Come up unto Jehovah, thou, and Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel; and worship ye afar off: ^2and Moses alone shall come near unto Jehovah; but they shall not come near; neither shall the people go up with him. ^3And Moses came and told the people all the words of Jehovah, and all the ordinances: and all the people answered with one voice, and said, All the words which Jehovah hath spoken will we do. ^4And Moses wrote all the words of Jehovah, and rose up early in the morning, and builded an altar under the mount, and twelve pillars, according to the twelve tribes of Israel. ^5And he sent young men of the children of Israel, who offered burnt-offerings, and sacrificed peace-offerings of oxen unto Jehovah. ^6And Moses took half of the blood, and put it in basins; and half of the blood he sprinkled on the altar. ^7And he took the book of the covenant, and read in the audience of the people: and they said, All that Jehovah hath spoken will we do, and be obedient. ^8And Moses took the blood, and sprinkled it on the people, and said, Behold the blood of the covenant, which Jehovah hath made with you concerning all these words.

^9Then went up Moses, and Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, and seventy of the elders of Israel. ^10And they saw the God of Israel; and there was under his feet as it were a paved work of sapphire stone, and as it were the very heaven for clearness. ^11And upon the nobles of the children of Israel he laid not his hand: and they beheld God, and did eat and drink.

^12And Jehovah said unto Moses, Come up to me into the mount, and be there: and I will give thee the tables of stone, and the law and the commandment, which I have written, that thou mayest teach them. ^13And Moses rose up, and Joshua his minister: and Moses went up into the mount of God. ^14And he said unto the elders, Tarry ye here for us, until we come again unto you: and, behold, Aaron and Hur are with you: whosoever hath a cause, let him come near unto them. ^15And Moses went up into the mount, and the cloud covered the mount. ^16And the glory of Jehovah abode upon mount Sinai, and the cloud covered it six days: and the seventh day he called unto Moses out of the midst of the cloud. ^17And the appearance of the glory of Jehovah was like devouring fire on the top of the mount in the eyes of the children of Israel. ^18And Moses entered into the midst of the cloud, and went up into the mount: and Moses was in the mount forty days and forty nights.

Exodus 25

25

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2Speak unto the children of Israel, that they take for me an offering: of every man whose heart maketh him willing ye shall take my offering. ^3And this is the offering which ye shall take of them: gold, and silver, and brass, ^4and blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen, and goats' hair, ^5and rams' skins dyed red, and sealskins, and acacia wood, ^6oil for the light, spices for the anointing oil, and for the sweet incense, ^7onyx stones, and stones to be set, for the ephod, and for the breastplate. ^8And let them make me a sanctuary, that I may dwell among them. ^9According to all that I show thee, the pattern of the tabernacle, and the pattern of all the furniture thereof, even so shall ye make it.

^10And they shall make an ark of acacia wood: two cubits and a half shall be the length thereof, and a cubit and a half the breadth thereof, and a cubit and a half the height thereof. ^11And thou shalt overlay it with pure gold, within and without shalt thou overlay it, and shalt make upon it a crown of gold round about. ^12And thou shalt cast four rings of gold for it, and put them in the four feet thereof; and two rings shall be on the one side of it, and two rings on the other side of it. ^13And thou shalt make staves of acacia wood, and overlay them with gold. ^14And thou shalt put the staves into the rings on the sides of the ark, wherewith to bear the ark. ^15The staves shall be in the rings of the ark: they shall not be taken from it. ^16And thou shalt put into the ark the testimony which I shall give thee. ^17And thou shalt make a mercy-seat of pure gold: two cubits and a half shall be the length thereof, and a cubit and a half the breadth thereof. ^18And thou shalt make two cherubim of gold; of beaten work shalt thou make them, at the two ends of the mercy-seat. ^19And make one cherub at the one end, and one cherub at the other end: of one piece with the mercy-seat shall ye make the cherubim on the two ends thereof. ^20And the cherubim shall spread out their wings on high, covering the mercy-seat with their wings, with their faces one to another; toward the mercy-seat shall the faces of the cherubim be. ^21And thou shalt put the mercy-seat above upon the ark; and in the ark thou shalt put the testimony that I shall give thee. ^22And there I will meet with thee, and I will commune with thee from above the mercy-seat, from between the two cherubim which are upon the ark of the testimony, of all things which I will give thee in commandment unto the children of Israel.

^23And thou shalt make a table of acacia wood: two cubits shall be the length thereof, and a cubit the breadth thereof, and a cubit and a half the height thereof. ^24And thou shalt overlay it with pure gold, and make thereto a crown of gold round about. ^25And thou shalt make unto it a border of a handbreadth round about; and thou shalt make a golden crown to the border thereof round about. ^26And thou shalt make for it four rings of gold, and put the rings in the four corners that are on the four feet thereof. ^27Close by the border shall the rings be, for places for the staves to bear the table. ^28And thou shalt make the staves of acacia wood, and overlay them with gold, that the table may be borne with them. ^29And thou shalt make the dishes thereof, and the spoons thereof, and the flagons thereof, and the bowls thereof, wherewith to pour out: of pure gold shalt thou make them. ^30And thou shalt set upon the table showbread before me alway.

^31And thou shalt make a candlestick of pure gold: of beaten work shall the candlestick be made, even its base, and its shaft; its cups, its knops, and its flowers, shall be of one piece with it. ^32And there shall be six branches going out of the sides thereof; three branches of the candlestick out of the one side thereof, and three branches of the candlestick out of the other side thereof: ^33three cups made like almond-blossoms in one branch, a knop and a flower; and three cups made like almond-blossoms in the other branch, a knop and a flower: so for the six branches going out of the candlestick: ^34and in the candlestick four cups made like almond-blossoms, the knops thereof, and the flowers thereof; ^35and a knop under two branches of one piece with it, and a knop under two branches of one piece with it, and a knop under two branches of one piece with it, for the six branches going out of the candlestick. ^36Their knops and their branches shall be of one piece with it; the whole of it one beaten work of pure gold. ^37And thou shalt make the lamps thereof, seven: and they shall light the lamps thereof, to give light over against it. ^38And the snuffers thereof, and the snuffdishes thereof, shall be of pure gold. ^39Of a talent of pure gold shall it be made, with all these vessels. ^40And see that thou make them after their pattern, which hath been showed thee in the mount.

Exodus 26

26

^1Moreover thou shalt make the tabernacle with ten curtains; of fine twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, with cherubim the work of the skilful workman shalt thou make them. ^2The length of each curtain shall be eight and twenty cubits, and the breadth of each curtain four cubits: all the curtains shall have one measure. ^3Five curtains shall be coupled together one to another; and the other five curtains shall be coupled one to another. ^4And thou shalt make loops of blue upon the edge of the one curtain from the selvedge in the coupling; and likewise shalt thou make in the edge of the curtain that is outmost in the second coupling. ^5Fifty loops shalt thou make in the one curtain, and fifty loops shalt thou make in the edge of the curtain that is in the second coupling; the loops shall be opposite one to another. ^6And thou shalt make fifty clasps of gold, and couple the curtains one to another with the clasps: and the tabernacle shall be one whole.

^7And thou shalt make curtains of goats' hair for a tent over the tabernacle: eleven curtains shalt thou make them. ^8The length of each curtain shall be thirty cubits, and the breadth of each curtain four cubits: the eleven curtains shall have one measure. ^9And thou shalt couple five curtains by themselves, and six curtains by themselves, and shalt double over the sixth curtain in the forefront of the tent. ^10And thou shalt make fifty loops on the edge of the one curtain that is outmost in the coupling, and fifty loops upon the edge of the curtain which is outmost in the second coupling. ^11And thou shalt make fifty clasps of brass, and put the clasps into the loops, and couple the tent together, that it may be one. ^12And the overhanging part that remaineth of the curtains of the tent, the half curtain that remaineth, shall hang over the back of the tabernacle. ^13And the cubit on the one side, and the cubit on the other side, of that which remaineth in the length of the curtains of the tent, shall hang over the sides of the tabernacle on this side and on that side, to cover it. ^14And thou shalt make a covering for the tent of rams' skins dyed red, and a covering of sealskins above.

^15And thou shalt make the boards for the tabernacle of acacia wood, standing up. ^16Ten cubits shall be the length of a board, and a cubit and a half the breadth of each board. ^17Two tenons shall there be in each board, joined one to another: thus shalt thou make for all the boards of the tabernacle. ^18And thou shalt make the boards for the tabernacle, twenty boards for the south side southward. ^19And thou shalt make forty sockets of silver under the twenty boards; two sockets under one board for its two tenons, and two sockets under another board for its two tenons. ^20And for the second side of the tabernacle, on the north side, twenty boards, ^21and their forty sockets of silver; two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board. ^22And for the hinder part of the tabernacle westward thou shalt make six boards. ^23And two boards shalt thou make for the corners of the tabernacle in the hinder part. ^24And they shall be double beneath, and in like manner they shall be entire unto the top thereof unto one ring: thus shall it be for them both; they shall be for the two corners. ^25And there shall be eight boards, and their sockets of silver, sixteen sockets; two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board.

^26And thou shalt make bars of acacia wood: five for the boards of the one side of the tabernacle, ^27and five bars for the boards of the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the side of the tabernacle, for the hinder part westward. ^28And the middle bar in the midst of the boards shall pass through from end to end. ^29And thou shalt overlay the boards with gold, and make their rings of gold for places for the bars: and thou shalt overlay the bars with gold. ^30And thou shalt rear up the tabernacle according to the fashion thereof which hath been showed thee in the mount.

^31And thou shalt make a veil of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen: with cherubim the work of the skilful workman shall it be made. ^32And thou shalt hang it upon four pillars of acacia overlaid with gold; their hooks shall be of gold, upon four sockets of silver. ^33And thou shalt hang up the veil under the clasps, and shalt bring in thither within the veil the ark of the testimony: and the veil shall separate unto you between the holy place and the most holy. ^34And thou shalt put the mercy-seat upon the ark of the testimony in the most holy place. ^35And thou shalt set the table without the veil, and the candlestick over against the table on the side of the tabernacle toward the south: and thou shalt put the table on the north side.

^36And thou shalt make a screen for the door of the Tent, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, the work of the embroiderer. ^37And thou shalt make for the screen five pillars of acacia, and overlay them with gold: their hooks shall be of gold: and thou shalt cast five sockets of brass for them.

Exodus 27

27

^1And thou shalt make the altar of acacia wood, five cubits long, and five cubits broad; the altar shall be foursquare: and the height thereof shall be three cubits. ^2And thou shalt make the horns of it upon the four corners thereof; the horns thereof shall be of one piece with it: and thou shalt overlay it with brass. ^3And thou shalt make its pots to take away its ashes, and its shovels, and its basins, and its flesh-hooks, and its firepans: all the vessels thereof thou shalt make of brass. ^4And thou shalt make for it a grating of network of brass: and upon the net shalt thou make four brazen rings in the four corners thereof. ^5And thou shalt put it under the ledge round the altar beneath, that the net may reach halfway up the altar. ^6And thou shalt make staves for the altar, staves of acacia wood, and overlay them with brass. ^7And the staves thereof shall be put into the rings, and the staves shall be upon the two sides of the altar, in bearing it. ^8Hollow with planks shalt thou make it: as it hath been showed thee in the mount, so shall they make it.

^9And thou shalt make the court of the tabernacle: for the south side southward there shall be hangings for the court of fine twined linen a hundred cubits long for one side: ^10and the pillars thereof shall be twenty, and their sockets twenty, of brass; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets shall be of silver. ^11And likewise for the north side in length there shall be hangings a hundred cubits long, and the pillars thereof twenty, and their sockets twenty, of brass; the hooks of the pillars, and their fillets, of silver. ^12And for the breadth of the court on the west side shall be hangings of fifty cubits; their pillars ten, and their sockets ten. ^13And the breadth of the court on the east side eastward shall be fifty cubits. ^14The hangings for the one side of the gate shall be fifteen cubits; their pillars three, and their sockets three. ^15And for the other side shall be hangings of fifteen cubits; their pillars three, and their sockets three. ^16And for the gate of the court shall be a screen of twenty cubits, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, the work of the embroiderer; their pillars four, and their sockets four. ^17All the pillars of the court round about shall be filleted with silver; their hooks of silver, and their sockets of brass. ^18The length of the court shall be a hundred cubits, and the breadth fifty every where, and the height five cubits, of fine twined linen, and their sockets of brass. ^19All the instruments of the tabernacle in all the service thereof, and all the pins thereof, and all the pins of the court, shall be of brass.

^20And thou shalt command the children of Israel, that they bring unto thee pure olive oil beaten for the light, to cause a lamp to burn continually. ^21In the tent of meeting, without the veil which is before the testimony, Aaron and his sons shall keep it in order from evening to morning before Jehovah: it shall be a statue for ever throughout their generations on the behalf of the children of Israel.

Exodus 28

28

^1And bring thou near unto thee Aaron thy brother, and his sons with him, from among the children of Israel, that he may minister unto me in the priest's office, even Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar, Aaron's sons. ^2And thou shalt make holy garments for Aaron thy brother, for glory and for beauty. ^3And thou shalt speak unto all that are wise-hearted, whom I have filled with the spirit of wisdom, that they make Aaron's garments to sanctify him, that he may minister unto me in the priest's office. ^4And these are the garments which they shall make: a breastplate, and an ephod, and a robe, and a coat of checker work, a mitre, and a girdle: and they shall make holy garments for Aaron thy brother, and his sons, that he may minister unto me in the priest's office. ^5And they shall take the gold, and the blue, and the purple, and the scarlet, and the fine linen.

^6And they shall make the ephod of gold, of blue, and purple, scarlet, and fine twined linen, the work of the skilful workman. ^7It shall have two shoulder-pieces joined to the two ends thereof, that it may be joined together. ^8And the skilfully woven band, which is upon it, wherewith to gird it on, shall be like the work thereof and of the same piece; of gold, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen. ^9And thou shalt take two onyx stones, and grave on them the names of the children of Israel: ^10six of their names on the one stone, and the names of the six that remain on the other stone, according to their birth. ^11With the work of an engraver in stone, like the engravings of a signet, shalt thou engrave the two stones, according to the names of the children of Israel: thou shalt make them to be inclosed in settings of gold. ^12And thou shalt put the two stones upon the shoulder-pieces of the ephod, to be stones of memorial for the children of Israel: and Aaron shall bear their names before Jehovah upon his two shoulders for a memorial. ^13And thou shalt make settings of gold, ^14and two chains of pure gold; like cords shalt thou make them, of wreathen work: and thou shalt put the wreathen chains on the settings.

^15And thou shalt make a breastplate of judgment, the work of the skilful workman; like the work of the ephod thou shalt make it; of gold, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, shalt thou make it. ^16Foursquare it shall be and double; a span shall be the length thereof, and a span the breadth thereof. ^17And thou shalt set in it settings of stones, four rows of stones: a row of sardius, topaz, and carbuncle shall be the first row; ^18and the second row an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond; ^19and the third row a jacinth, an agate, and an amethyst; ^20and the fourth row a beryl, and an onyx, and a jasper: they shall be inclosed in gold in their settings. ^21And the stones shall be according to the names of the children of Israel, twelve, according to their names; like the engravings of a signet, every one according to his name, they shall be for the twelve tribes. ^22And thou shalt make upon the breastplate chains like cords, of wreathen work of pure gold. ^23And thou shalt make upon the breastplate two rings of gold, and shalt put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate. ^24And thou shalt put the two wreathen chains of gold in the two rings at the ends of the breastplate. ^25And the other two ends of the two wreathen chains thou shalt put on the two settings, and put them on the shoulder-pieces of the ephod in the forepart thereof. ^26And thou shalt make two rings of gold, and thou shalt put them upon the two ends of the breastplate, upon the edge thereof, which is toward the side of the ephod inward. ^27And thou shalt make two rings of gold, and shalt put them on the two shoulder-pieces of the ephod underneath, in the forepart thereof, close by the coupling thereof, above the skilfully woven band of the ephod. ^28And they shall bind the breastplate by the rings thereof unto the rings of the ephod with a lace of blue, that it may be upon the skilfully woven band of the ephod, and that the breastplate be not loosed from the ephod. ^29And Aaron shall bear the names of the children of Israel in the breastplate of judgment upon his heart, when he goeth in unto the holy place, for a memorial before Jehovah continually. ^30And thou shalt put in the breastplate of judgment the Urim and the Thummim; and they shall be upon Aaron's heart, when he goeth in before Jehovah: and Aaron shall bear the judgment of the children of Israel upon his heart before Jehovah continually.

^31And thou shalt make the robe of the ephod all of blue. ^32And it shall have a hole for the head in the midst thereof: it shall have a binding of woven work round about the hole of it, as it were the hole of a coat of mail, that it be not rent. ^33And upon the skirts of it thou shalt make pomegranates of blue, and of purple, and of scarlet, round about the skirts thereof; and bells of gold between them round about: ^34a golden bell and a pomegranate, a golden bell and a pomegranate, upon the skirts of the robe round about. ^35And it shall be upon Aaron to minister: and the sound thereof shall be heard when he goeth in unto the holy place before Jehovah, and when he cometh out, that he die not.

^36And thou shalt make a plate of pure gold, and grave upon it, like the engravings of a signet, HOLY TO JEHOVAH. ^37And thou shalt put it on a lace of blue, and it shall be upon the mitre; upon the forefront of the mitre it shall be. ^38And it shall be upon Aaron's forehead, and Aaron shall bear the iniquity of the holy things, which the children of Israel shall hallow in all their holy gifts; and it shall be always upon his forehead, that they may be accepted before Jehovah. ^39And thou shalt weave the coat in checker work of fine linen, and thou shalt make a mitre of fine linen, and thou shalt make a girdle, the work of the embroiderer.

^40And for Aaron's sons thou shalt make coats, and thou shalt make for them girdles, and head-tires shalt thou make for them, for glory and for beauty. ^41And thou shalt put them upon Aaron thy brother, and upon his sons with him, and shalt anoint them, and consecrate them, and sanctify them, that they may minister unto me in the priest's office. ^42And thou shalt make them linen breeches to cover the flesh of their nakedness; from the loins even unto the thighs they shall reach: ^43And they shall be upon Aaron, and upon his sons, when they go in unto the tent of meeting, or when they come near unto the altar to minister in the holy place; that they bear not iniquity, and die: it shall be a statute for ever unto him and unto his seed after him.

Exodus 29

29

^1And this is the thing that thou shalt do unto them to hallow them, to minister unto me in the priest's office: take one young bullock and two rams without blemish, ^2and unleavened bread, and cakes unleavened mingled with oil, and wafers unleavened anointed with oil: of fine wheaten flour shalt thou make them. ^3And thou shalt put them into one basket, and bring them in the basket, with the bullock and the two rams. ^4And Aaron and his sons thou shalt bring unto the door of the tent of meeting, and shalt wash them with water. ^5And thou shalt take the garments, and put upon Aaron the coat, and the robe of the ephod, and the ephod, and the breastplate, and gird him with the skilfully woven band of the ephod; ^6and thou shalt set the mitre upon his head, and put the holy crown upon the mitre. ^7Then shalt thou take the anointing oil, and pour it upon his head, and anoint him. ^8And thou shalt bring his sons, and put coats upon them. ^9And thou shalt gird them with girdles, Aaron and his sons, and bind head-tires on them: and they shall have the priesthood by a perpetual statute: and thou shalt consecrate Aaron and his sons.

^10And thou shalt bring the bullock before the tent of meeting: and Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands upon the head of the bullock. ^11And thou shalt kill the bullock before Jehovah, at the door of the tent of meeting. ^12And thou shalt take of the blood of the bullock, and put it upon the horns of the altar with thy finger; and thou shalt pour out all the blood at the base of the altar. ^13And thou shalt take all the fat that covereth the inwards, and the caul upon the liver, and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, and burn them upon the altar. ^14But the flesh of the bullock, and its skin, and it dung, shalt thou burn with fire without the camp: it is a sin-offering.

^15Thou shalt also take the one ram; and Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands upon the head of the ram. ^16And thou shalt slay the ram, and thou shalt take its blood, and sprinkle it round about upon the altar. ^17And thou shalt cut the ram into its pieces, and wash its inwards, and its legs, and put them with its pieces, and with its head. ^18And thou shalt burn the whole ram upon the altar: it is a burnt-offering unto Jehovah; it is a sweet savor, an offering made by fire unto Jehovah.

^19And thou shalt take the other ram; and Aaron and his sons shall lay their hands upon the head of the ram. ^20Then shalt thou kill the ram, and take of its blood, and put it upon the tip of the right ear of Aaron, and upon the tip of the right ear of his sons, and upon the thumb of their right hand, and upon the great toe of their right foot, and sprinkle the blood upon the altar round about. ^21And thou shalt take of the blood that is upon the altar, and of the anointing oil, and sprinkle it upon Aaron, and upon his garments, and upon his sons, and upon the garments of his sons with him: and he shall be hallowed, and his garments, and his sons, and his sons' garments with him. ^22Also thou shalt take of the ram the fat, and the fat tail, and the fat that covereth the inwards, and the caul of the liver, and the two kidneys, and the fat that is upon them, and the right thigh (for it is a ram of consecration), ^23and one loaf of bread, and one cake of oiled bread, and one wafer, out of the basket of unleavened bread that is before Jehovah. ^24And thou shalt put the whole upon the hands of Aaron, and upon the hands of his sons, and shalt wave them for a wave-offering before Jehovah. ^25And thou shalt take them from their hands, and burn them on the altar upon the burnt-offering, for a sweet savor before Jehovah: it is an offering made by fire unto Jehovah.

^26And thou shalt take the breast of Aaron's ram of consecration, and wave it for a wave-offering before Jehovah: and it shall be thy portion. ^27And thou shalt sanctify the breast of the wave-offering, and the thigh of the heave-offering, which is waved, and which is heaved up, of the ram of consecration, even of that which is for Aaron, and of that which is for his sons: ^28and it shall be for Aaron and his sons as their portion for ever from the children of Israel; for it is a heave-offering: and it shall be a heave-offering from the children of Israel of the sacrifices of their peace-offerings, even their heave-offering unto Jehovah.

^29And the holy garments of Aaron shall be for his sons after him, to be anointed in them, and to be consecrated in them. ^30Seven days shall the son that is priest in his stead put them on, when he cometh into the tent of meeting to minister in the holy place.

^31And thou shalt take the ram of consecration, and boil its flesh in a holy place. ^32And Aaron and his sons shall eat the flesh of the ram, and the bread that is in the basket, at the door of the tent of meeting. ^33And they shall eat those things wherewith atonement was made, to consecrate and to sanctify them: but a stranger shall not eat thereof, because they are holy. ^34And if aught of the flesh of the consecration, or of the bread, remain unto the morning, then thou shalt burn the remainder with fire: it shall not be eaten, because it is holy.

^35And thus shalt thou do unto Aaron, and to his sons, according to all that I have commanded thee: seven days shalt thou consecrate them. ^36And every day shalt thou offer the bullock of sin-offering for atonement: and thou shalt cleanse the altar, when thou makest atonement for it; and thou shalt anoint it, to sanctify it. ^37Seven days thou shalt make atonement for the altar, and sanctify it: and the altar shall be most holy; whatsoever toucheth the altar shall be holy.

^38Now this is that which thou shalt offer upon the altar: two lambs a year old day by day continually. ^39The one lamb thou shalt offer in the morning; and the other lamb thou shalt offer at even: ^40and with the one lamb a tenth part of an ephah of fine flour mingled with the fourth part of a hin of beaten oil, and the fourth part of a hin of wine for a drink-offering. ^41And the other lamb thou shalt offer at even, and shalt do thereto according to the meal-offering of the morning, and according to the drink-offering thereof, for a sweet savor, an offering made by fire unto Jehovah. ^42It shall be a continual burnt-offering throughout your generations at the door of the tent of meeting before Jehovah, where I will meet with you, to speak there unto thee. ^43And there I will meet with the children of Israel; and the Tent shall be sanctified by my glory. ^44And I will sanctify the tent of meeting, and the altar: Aaron also and his sons will I sanctify, to minister to me in the priest's office. ^45And I will dwell among the children of Israel, and will be their God. ^46And they shall know that I am Jehovah their God, that brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, that I might dwell among them: I am Jehovah their God.

Exodus 31

31

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2See, I have called by name Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah: ^3and I have filled him with the Spirit of God, in wisdom, and in understanding, and in knowledge, and in all manner of workmanship, ^4to devise skilful works, to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, ^5and in cutting of stones for setting, and in carving of wood, to work in all manner of workmanship. ^6And I, behold, I have appointed with him Oholiab, the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan; and in the heart of all that are wise-hearted I have put wisdom, that they may make all that I have commanded thee: ^7the tent of meeting, and the ark of the testimony, and the mercy-seat that is thereupon, and all the furniture of the Tent, ^8and the table and its vessels, and the pure candlestick with all its vessels, and the altar of incense, ^9and the altar of burnt-offering with all its vessels, and the laver and its base, ^10and the finely wrought garments, and the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, to minister in the priest's office, ^11and the anointing oil, and the incense of sweet spices for the holy place: according to all that I have commanded thee shall they do.

^12And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^13Speak thou also unto the children of Israel, saying, Verily ye shall keep my sabbaths: for it is a sign between me and you throughout your generations; that ye may know that I am Jehovah who sanctifieth you. ^14Ye shall keep the sabbath therefore; for it is holy unto you: every one that profaneth it shall surely be put to death; for whosoever doeth any work therein, that soul shall be cut off from among his people. ^15Six days shall work be done, but on the seventh day is a sabbath of solemn rest, holy to Jehovah: whosoever doeth any work on the sabbath day, he shall surely be put to death. ^16Wherefore the children of Israel shall keep the sabbath, to observe the sabbath throughout their generations, for a perpetual covenant. ^17It is a sign between me and the children of Israel for ever: for in six days Jehovah made heaven and earth, and on the seventh day he rested, and was refreshed.

^18And he gave unto Moses, when he had made an end of communing with him upon mount Sinai, the two tables of the testimony, tables of stone, written with the finger of God.

Exodus 32

32

^1And when the people saw that Moses delayed to come down from the mount, the people gathered themselves together unto Aaron, and said unto him, Up, make us gods, which shall go before us; for as for this Moses, the man that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we know not what is become of him. ^2And Aaron said unto them, Break off the golden rings, which are in the ears of your wives, of your sons, and of your daughters, and bring them unto me. ^3And all the people brake off the golden rings which were in their ears, and brought them unto Aaron. ^4And he received it at their hand, and fashioned it with a graving tool, and made it a molten calf: and they said, These are thy gods, O Israel, which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. ^5And when Aaron saw this, he built an altar before it; and Aaron made proclamation, and said, To-morrow shall be a feast to Jehovah. ^6And they rose up early on the morrow, and offered burnt-offerings, and brought peace-offerings; and the people sat down to eat and to drink, and rose up to play.

^7And Jehovah spake unto Moses, Go, get thee down; for thy people, that thou broughtest up out of the land of Egypt, have corrupted themselves: ^8they have turned aside quickly out of the way which I commanded them: they have made them a molten calf, and have worshipped it, and have sacrificed unto it, and said, These are thy gods, O Israel, which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. ^9And Jehovah said unto Moses, I have seen this people, and, behold, it is a stiffnecked people: ^10now therefore let me alone, that my wrath may wax hot against them, and that I may consume them: and I will make of thee a great nation. ^11And Moses besought Jehovah his God, and said, Jehovah, why doth thy wrath wax hot against thy people, that thou hast brought forth out of the land of Egypt with great power and with a mighty hand? ^12Wherefore should the Egyptians speak, saying, For evil did he bring them forth, to slay them in the mountains, and to consume them from the face of the earth? Turn from thy fierce wrath, and repent of this evil against thy people. ^13Remember Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, thy servants, to whom thou swarest by thine own self, and saidst unto them, I will multiply your seed as the stars of heaven, and all this land that I have spoken of will I give unto your seed, and they shall inherit it for ever. ^14And Jehovah repented of the evil which he said he would do unto his people.

^15And Moses turned, and went down from the mount, with the two tables of the testimony in his hand; tables that were written on both their sides; on the one side and on the other were they written. ^16And the tables were the work of God, and the writing was the writing of God, graven upon the tables. ^17And when Joshua heard the noise of the people as they shouted, he said unto Moses, There is a noise of war in the camp. ^18And he said, It is not the voice of them that shout for mastery, neither is it the voice of them that cry for being overcome; but the noise of them that sing do I hear. ^19And it came to pass, as soon as he came nigh unto the camp, that he saw the calf and the dancing: and Moses' anger waxed hot, and he cast the tables out of his hands, and brake them beneath the mount. ^20And he took the calf which they had made, and burnt it with fire, and ground it to powder, and strewed it upon the water, and made the children of Israel drink of it.

^21And Moses said unto Aaron, What did this people unto thee, that thou hast brought a great sin upon them? ^22And Aaron said, Let not the anger of my lord wax hot: thou knowest the people, that they are set on evil. ^23For they said unto me, Make us gods, which shall go before us; for as for this Moses, the man that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, we know not what is become of him. ^24And I said unto them, Whosoever hath any gold, let them break it off: so they gave it me; and I cast it into the fire, and there came out this calf.

^25And when Moses saw that the people were broken loose, (for Aaron had let them loose for a derision among their enemies,) ^26then Moses stood in the gate of the camp, and said, Whoso is on Jehovah's side, let him come unto me. And all the sons of Levi gathered themselves together unto him. ^27And he said unto them, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, Put ye every man his sword upon his thigh, and go to and fro from gate to gate throughout the camp, and slay every man his brother, and every man his companion, and every man his neighbor. ^28And the sons of Levi did according to the word of Moses: and there fell of the people that day about three thousand men. ^29And Moses said, Consecrate yourselves to-day to Jehovah, yea, every man against his son, and against his brother; that he may bestow upon you a blessing this day.

^30And it came to pass on the morrow, that Moses said unto the people, Ye have sinned a great sin: and now I will go up unto Jehovah; peradventure I shall make atonement for your sin. ^31And Moses returned unto Jehovah, and said, Oh, this people have sinned a great sin, and have made them gods of gold. ^32Yet now, if thou wilt forgive their sin-; and if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of thy book which thou hast written. ^33And Jehovah said unto Moses, Whosoever hath sinned against me, him will I blot out of my book. ^34And now go, lead the people unto the place of which I have spoken unto thee: behold, mine angel shall go before thee; nevertheless in the day when I visit, I will visit their sin upon them. ^35And Jehovah smote the people, because they made the calf, which Aaron made.

Exodus 33

33

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, Depart, go up hence, thou and the people that thou hast brought up out of the land of Egypt, unto the land of which I sware unto Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, saying, Unto thy seed will I give it: ^2and I will send an angel before thee; and I will drive out the Canaanite, the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite: ^3unto a land flowing with milk and honey: for I will not go up in the midst of thee, for thou art a stiffnecked people, lest I consume thee in the way. ^4And when the people heard these evil tidings, they mourned: and no man did put on him his ornaments. ^5And Jehovah said unto Moses, Say unto the children of Israel, Ye are a stiffnecked people; if I go up into the midst of thee for one moment, I shall consume thee: therefore now put off thy ornaments from thee, that I may know what to do unto thee. ^6And the children of Israel stripped themselves of their ornaments from mount Horeb onward.

^7Now Moses used to take the tent and to pitch it without the camp, afar off from the camp; and he called it, The tent of meeting. And it came to pass, that every one that sought Jehovah went out unto the tent of meeting, which was without the camp. ^8And it came to pass, when Moses went out unto the Tent, that all the people rose up, and stood, every man at his tent door, and looked after Moses, until he was gone into the Tent. ^9And it came to pass, when Moses entered into the Tent, the pillar of cloud descended, and stood at the door of the Tent: and Jehovah spake with Moses. ^10And all the people saw the pillar of cloud stand at the door of the Tent: and all the people rose up and worshipped, every man at his tent door. ^11And Jehovah spake unto Moses face to face, as a man speaketh unto his friend. And he turned again into the camp: but his minister Joshua, the son of Nun, a young man, departed not out of the Tent.

^12And Moses said unto Jehovah, See, thou sayest unto me, Bring up this people: and thou hast not let me know whom thou wilt send with me. Yet thou hast said, I know thee by name, and thou hast also found favor in my sight. ^13Now therefore, I pray thee, if I have found favor in thy sight, show me now thy ways, that I may know thee, to the end that I may find favor in thy sight: and consider that this nation is thy people. ^14And he said, My presence shall go with thee, and I will give thee rest. ^15And he said unto him, If thy presence go not with me, carry us not up hence. ^16For wherein now shall it be known that I have found favor in thy sight, I and thy people? is it not in that thou goest with us, so that we are separated, I and thy people, from all the people that are upon the face of the earth?

^17And Jehovah said unto Moses, I will do this thing also that thou hast spoken; for thou hast found favor in my sight, and I know thee by name. ^18And he said, Show me, I pray thee, thy glory. ^19And he said, I will make all my goodness pass before thee, and will proclaim the name of Jehovah before thee; and I will be gracious to whom I will be gracious, and will show mercy on whom I will show mercy. ^20And he said, Thou canst not see my face; for man shall not see me and live. ^21and Jehovah said, Behold, there is a place by me, and thou shalt stand upon the rock: ^22and it shall come to pass, while my glory passeth by, that I will put thee in a cleft of the rock, and will cover thee with my hand until I have passed by: ^23and I will take away my hand, and thou shalt see my back; but my face shall not be seen.

Exodus 34

34

^1And Jehovah said unto Moses, Hew thee two tables of stone like unto the first: and I will write upon the tables the words that were on the first tables, which thou brakest. ^2And be ready by the morning, and come up in the morning unto mount Sinai, and present thyself there to me on the top of the mount. ^3And no man shall come up with thee; neither let any man be seen throughout all the mount; neither let the flocks nor herds feed before that mount. ^4And he hewed two tables of stone like unto the first; and Moses rose up early in the morning, and went up unto mount Sinai, as Jehovah had commanded him, and took in his hand two tables of stone. ^5And Jehovah descended in the cloud, and stood with him there, and proclaimed the name of Jehovah. ^6And Jehovah passed by before him, and proclaimed, Jehovah, Jehovah, a God merciful and gracious, slow to anger, and abundant in lovingkindness and truth, ^7keeping lovingkindness for thousands, forgiving iniquity and transgression and sin; and that will by no means clear the guilty, visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children, and upon the children's children, upon the third and upon the fourth generation. ^8And Moses made haste, and bowed his head toward the earth, and worshipped. ^9And he said, If now I have found favor in thy sight, O Lord, let the Lord, I pray thee, go in the midst of us; for it is a stiffnecked people; and pardon our iniquity and our sin, and take us for thine inheritance.

^10And he said, Behold, I make a covenant: before all thy people I will do marvels, such as have not been wrought in all the earth, nor in any nation; and all the people among which thou art shall see the work of Jehovah; for it is a terrible thing that I do with thee. ^11Observe thou that which I command thee this day: behold, I drive out before thee the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite. ^12Take heed to thyself, lest thou make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land whither thou goest, lest it be for a snare in the midst of thee: ^13but ye shall break down their altars, and dash in pieces their pillars, and ye shall cut down their Asherim; ^14for thou shalt worship no other god: for Jehovah, whose name is Jealous, is a jealous God: ^15lest thou make a covenant with the inhabitants of the land, and they play the harlot after their gods, and sacrifice unto their gods, and one call thee and thou eat of his sacrifice; ^16and thou take of their daughters unto thy sons, and their daughters play the harlot after their gods, and make thy sons play the harlot after their gods. ^17Thou shalt make thee no molten gods.

^18The feast of unleavened bread shalt thou keep. Seven days thou shalt eat unleavened bread, as I commanded thee, at the time appointed in the month Abib; for in the month Abib thou camest out from Egypt. ^19All that openeth the womb is mine; and all thy cattle that is male, the firstlings of cow and sheep. ^20And the firstling of an ass thou shalt redeem with a lamb: and if thou wilt not redeem it, then thou shalt break its neck. All the first-born of thy sons thou shalt redeem. And none shall appear before me empty.

^21Six days thou shalt work, but on the seventh day thou shalt rest: in plowing time and in harvest thou shalt rest. ^22And thou shalt observe the feast of weeks, even of the first-fruits of wheat harvest, and the feast of ingathering at the year's end. ^23Three times in the year shall all thy males appear before the Lord Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^24For I will cast out nations before thee, and enlarge thy borders: neither shall any man desire thy land, when thou goest up to appear before Jehovah thy God three times in the year.

^25Thou shalt not offer the blood of my sacrifice with leavened bread; neither shall the sacrifice of the feast of the passover be left unto the morning. ^26The first of the first-fruits of thy ground thou shalt bring unto the house of Jehovah thy God. Thou shalt not boil a kid in its mother's milk. ^27And Jehovah said unto Moses, Write thou these words: for after the tenor of these words I have made a covenant with thee and with Israel. ^28And he was there with Jehovah forty days and forty nights; he did neither eat bread, nor drink water. And he wrote upon the tables the words of the covenant, the ten commandments.

^29And it came to pass, when Moses came down from mount Sinai with the two tables of the testimony in Moses' hand, when he came down from the mount, that Moses knew not that the skin of his face shone by reason of his speaking with him. ^30And when Aaron and all the children of Israel saw Moses, behold, the skin of his face shone; and they were afraid to come nigh him. ^31And Moses called unto them; and Aaron and all the rulers of the congregation returned unto him: and Moses spake to them. ^32And afterward all the children of Israel came nigh: and he gave them in commandment all that Jehovah had spoken with him in mount Sinai. ^33And when Moses had done speaking with them, he put a veil on his face. ^34But when Moses went in before Jehovah to speak with him, he took the veil off, until he came out; and he came out, and spake unto the children of Israel that which he was commanded. ^35And the children of Israel saw the face of Moses, that the skin of Moses' face shone: and Moses put the veil upon his face again, until he went in to speak with him.

Exodus 35

35

^1And Moses assembled all the congregation of the children of Israel, and said unto them, These are the words which Jehovah hath commanded, that ye should do them. ^2Six days shall work be done; but on the seventh day there shall be to you a holy day, a sabbath of solemn rest to Jehovah: whosoever doeth any work therein shall be put to death. ^3Ye shall kindle no fire throughout your habitations upon the sabbath day.

^4And Moses spake unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, saying, This is the thing which Jehovah commanded, saying, ^5Take ye from among you an offering unto Jehovah; whosoever is of a willing heart, let him bring it, Jehovah's offering: gold, and silver, and brass, ^6and blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen, and goats' hair, ^7and rams' skins dyed red, and sealskins, and acacia wood, ^8and oil for the light, and spices for the anointing oil, and for the sweet incense, ^9and onyx stones, and stones to be set, for the ephod, and for the breastplate.

^10And let every wise-hearted man among you come, and make all that Jehovah hath commanded: ^11the tabernacle, its tent, and its covering, its clasps, and its boards, its bars, its pillars, and its sockets; ^12the ark, and the staves thereof, the mercy-seat, and the veil of the screen; ^13the table, and its staves, and all its vessels, and the showbread; ^14the candlestick also for the light, and its vessels, and its lamps, and the oil for the light; ^15and the altar of incense, and its staves, and the anointing oil, and the sweet incense, and the screen for the door, at the door of the tabernacle; ^16the altar of burnt-offering, with its grating of brass, it staves, and all its vessels, the laver and its base; ^17the hangings of the court, the pillars thereof, and their sockets, and the screen for the gate of the court; ^18the pins of the tabernacle, and the pins of the court, and their cords; ^19the finely wrought garments, for ministering in the holy place, the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, to minister in the priest's office.

^20And all the congregation of the children of Israel departed from the presence of Moses. ^21And they came, every one whose heart stirred him up, and every one whom his spirit made willing, and brought Jehovah's offering, for the work of the tent of meeting, and for all the service thereof, and for the holy garments. ^22And they came, both men and women, as many as were willing-hearted, and brought brooches, and ear-rings, and signet-rings, and armlets, all jewels of gold; even every man that offered an offering of gold unto Jehovah. ^23And every man, with whom was found blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linen, and goats' hair, and rams' skins dyed red, and sealskins, brought them. ^24Every one that did offer an offering of silver and brass brought Jehovah's offering; and every man, with whom was found acacia wood for any work of the service, brought it. ^25And all the women that were wise-hearted did spin with their hands, and brought that which they had spun, the blue, and the purple, the scarlet, and the fine linen. ^26And all the women whose heart stirred them up in wisdom spun the goats' hair. ^27And the rulers brought the onyx stones, and the stones to be set, for the ephod, and for the breastplate; ^28and the spice, and the oil; for the light, and for the anointing oil, and for the sweet incense. ^29The children of Israel brought a freewill-offering unto Jehovah; every man and woman, whose heart made them willing to bring for all the work, which Jehovah had commanded to be made by Moses.

^30And Moses said unto the children of Israel, See, Jehovah hath called by name Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah. ^31And he hath filled him with the Spirit of God, in wisdom, in understanding, and in knowledge, and in all manner of workmanship; ^32and to devise skilful works, to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, ^33and in cutting of stones for setting, and in carving of wood, to work in all manner of skilful workmanship. ^34And he hath put in his heart that he may teach, both he, and Oholiab, the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan. ^35Them hath he filled with wisdom of heart, to work all manner of workmanship, of the engraver, and of the skilful workman, and of the embroiderer, in blue, and in purple, in scarlet, and in fine linen, and of the weaver, even of them that do any workmanship, and of those that devise skilful works.

Exodus 36

36

^1And Bezalel and Oholiab shall work, and every wise-hearted man, in whom Jehovah hath put wisdom and understanding to know how to work all the work for the service of the sanctuary, according to all that Jehovah hath commanded.

^2And Moses called Bezalel and Oholiab, and every wise-hearted man, in whose heart Jehovah had put wisdom, even every one whose heart stirred him up to come unto the work to do it: ^3and they received of Moses all the offering which the children of Israel had brought for the work of the service of the sanctuary, wherewith to make it. And they brought yet unto him freewill-offerings every morning. ^4And all the wise men, that wrought all the work of the sanctuary, came every man from his work which they wrought. ^5And they spake unto Moses, saying, The people bring much more than enough for the service of the work which Jehovah commanded to make. ^6And Moses gave commandment, and they caused it to be proclaimed throughout the camp, saying, Let neither man nor woman make any more work for the offering of the sanctuary. So the people were restrained from bringing. ^7For the stuff they had was sufficient for all the work to make it, and too much.

^8And all the wise-hearted men among them that wrought the work made the tabernacle with ten curtains; of fine twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, with cherubim, the work of the skilful workman, Bezalel made them. ^9The length of each curtain was eight and twenty cubits, and the breadth of each curtain four cubits: all the curtains had one measure. ^10And he coupled five curtains one to another: and the other five curtains he coupled one to another. ^11And he made loops of blue upon the edge of the one curtain from the selvedge in the coupling: likewise he made in the edge of the curtain that was outmost in the second coupling. ^12Fifty loops made he in the one curtain, and fifty loops made he in the edge of the curtain that was in the second coupling: the loops were opposite one to another. ^13And he made fifty clasps of gold, and coupled the curtains one to another with the clasps: so the tabernacle was one.

^14And he made curtains of goats' hair for a tent over the tabernacle: eleven curtains he made them. ^15The length of each curtain was thirty cubits, and four cubits the breadth of each curtain: the eleven curtains had one measure. ^16And he coupled five curtains by themselves, and six curtains by themselves. ^17And he made fifty loops on the edge of the curtain that was outmost in the coupling, and fifty loops made he upon the edge of the curtain which was outmost in the second coupling. ^18And he made fifty clasps of brass to couple the tent together, that it might be one. ^19And he made a covering for the tent of rams' skins dyed red, and a covering of sealskins above.

^20And he made the boards for the tabernacle, of acacia wood, standing up. ^21Ten cubits was the length of a board, and a cubit and a half the breadth of each board. ^22Each board had two tenons, joined one to another: thus did he make for all the boards of the tabernacle. ^23And he made the boards for the tabernacle: twenty boards for the south side southward. ^24And he made forty sockets of silver under the twenty boards; two sockets under one board for its two tenons, and two sockets under another board for its two tenons. ^25And for the second side of the tabernacle, on the north side, he made twenty boards, ^26and their forty sockets of silver; two sockets under one board, and two sockets under another board. ^27And for the hinder part of the tabernacle westward he made six boards. ^28And two boards made he for the corners of the tabernacle in the hinder part. ^29And they were double beneath; and in like manner they were entire unto the top thereof unto one ring: thus he did to both of them in the two corners. ^30And there were eight boards, and their sockets of silver, sixteen sockets; under every board two sockets.

^31And he made bars of acacia wood; five for the boards of the one side of the tabernacle, ^32and five bars for the boards of the other side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the tabernacle for the hinder part westward. ^33And he made the middle bar to pass through in the midst of the boards from the one end to the other. ^34And he overlaid the boards with gold, and made their rings of gold for places for the bars, and overlaid the bars with gold.

^35And he made the veil of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen: with cherubim, the work of the skilful workman, made he it. ^36And he made thereunto four pillars of acacia, and overlaid them with gold: their hooks were of gold; And he cast for them four sockets of silver. ^37And he made a screen for the door of the Tent, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen, the work of the embroiderer; ^38and the five pillars of it with their hooks: and he overlaid their capitals and their fillets with gold; and their five sockets were of brass.

Exodus 37

37

^1And Bezalel made the ark of acacia wood: two cubits and a half was the length of it, and a cubit and a half the breadth of it, and a cubit and a half the height of it: ^2and he overlaid it with pure gold within and without, and made a crown of gold to it round about. ^3And he cast for it four rings of gold, in the four feet thereof; even two rings on the one side of it, and two rings on the other side of it. ^4And he made staves of acacia wood, and overlaid them with gold. ^5And he put the staves into the rings on the sides of the ark, to bear the ark. ^6And he made a mercy-seat of pure gold: two cubits and a half was the length thereof, and a cubit and a half the breadth thereof. ^7And he made two cherubim of gold; of beaten work made he them, at the two ends of the mercy-seat; ^8one cherub at the one end, and one cherub at the other end: of one piece with the mercy-seat made he the cherubim at the two ends thereof. ^9And the cherubim spread out their wings on high, covering the mercy-seat with their wings, with their faces one to another; toward the mercy-seat were the faces of the cherubim.

^10And he made the table of acacia wood: two cubits was the length thereof, and a cubit the breadth thereof, and a cubit and a half the height thereof: ^11and he overlaid it with pure gold, and made thereto a crown of gold round about. ^12And he made unto it a border of a handbreadth round about, and made a golden crown to the border thereof round about. ^13And he cast for it four rings of gold, and put the rings in the four corners that were on the four feet thereof. ^14Close by the border were the rings, the places for the staves to bear the table. ^15And he made the staves of acacia wood, and overlaid them with gold, to bear the table. ^16And he made the vessels which were upon the table, the dishes thereof, and the spoons thereof, and the bowls thereof, and the flagons thereof, wherewith to pour out, of pure gold.

^17And he made the candlestick of pure gold: of beaten work made he the candlestick, even its base, and its shaft; its cups, it knops, and its flowers, were of one piece with it: ^18and there were six branches going out of the sides thereof; three branches of the candlestick out of the one side thereof, and three branches of the candlestick out of the other side thereof: ^19three cups made like almond-blossoms in one branch, a knop and a flower, and three cups made like almond-blossoms in the other branch, a knop and a flower: so for the six branches going out of the candlestick. ^20And in the candlestick were four cups made like almond-blossoms, the knops thereof, and the flowers thereof; ^21and a knop under two branches of one piece with it, and a knop under two branches of one piece with it, and a knop under two branches of one piece with it, for the six branches going out of it. ^22Their knops and their branches were of one piece with it: the whole of it was one beaten work of pure gold. ^23And he made the lamps thereof, seven, and the snuffers thereof, and the snuffdishes thereof, of pure gold. ^24Of a talent of pure gold made he it, and all the vessels thereof.

^25And he made the altar of incense of acacia wood: a cubit was the length thereof, and a cubit the breadth thereof, foursquare; and two cubits was the height thereof; the horns thereof were of one piece with it. ^26And he overlaid it with pure gold, the top thereof, and the sides thereof round about, and the horns of it: and he made unto it a crown of gold round about. ^27And he made for it two golden rings under the crown thereof, upon the two ribs thereof, upon the two sides of it, for places for staves wherewith to bear it. ^28And he made the staves of acacia wood, and overlaid them with gold. ^29And he made the holy anointing oil, and the pure incense of sweet spices, after the art of the perfumer.

Exodus 38

38

^1And he made the altar of burnt-offering of acacia wood: five cubits was the length thereof, and five cubits the breadth thereof, foursquare; and three cubits the height thereof. ^2And he made the horns thereof upon the four corners of it; the horns thereof were of one piece with it: and he overlaid it with brass. ^3And he made all the vessels of the altar, the pots, and the shovels, and the basins, the flesh-hooks, and the firepans: all the vessels thereof made he of brass. ^4And he made for the altar a grating of network of brass, under the ledge round it beneath, reaching halfway up. ^5And he cast four rings for the four ends of the grating of brass, to be places for the staves. ^6And he made the staves of acacia wood, and overlaid them with brass. ^7And he put the staves into the rings on the sides of the altar, wherewith to bear it; he made it hollow with planks.

^8And he made the laver of brass, and the base thereof of brass, of the mirrors of the ministering women that ministered at the door of the tent of meeting.

^9And he made the court: for the south side southward the hangings of the court were of fine twined linen, a hundred cubits; ^10their pillars were twenty, and their sockets twenty, of brass; the hooks of the pillars and their fillets were of silver. ^11And for the north side a hundred cubits, their pillars twenty, and their sockets twenty, of brass; the hooks of the pillars, and their fillets, of silver. ^12And for the west side were hangings of fifty cubits, their pillars ten, and their sockets ten; the hooks of the pillars, and their fillets, of silver. ^13And for the east side eastward fifty cubits. ^14The hangings for the one side of the gate were fifteen cubits; their pillars three, and their sockets three; ^15and so for the other side: on this hand and that hand by the gate of the court were hangings of fifteen cubits; their pillars three, and their sockets three. ^16All the hangings of the court round about were of fine twined linen. ^17And the sockets for the pillars were of brass; the hooks of the pillars, and their fillets, of silver; and the overlaying of their capitals, of silver; and all the pillars of the court were filleted with silver. ^18And the screen for the gate of the court was the work of the embroiderer, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen: and twenty cubits was the length, and the height in the breadth was five cubits, answerable to the hangings of the court. ^19And their pillars were four, and their sockets four, of brass; their hooks of silver, and the overlaying of their capitals, and their fillets, of silver. ^20And all the pins of the tabernacle, and of the court round about, were of brass.

^21This is the sum of the things for the tabernacle, even the tabernacle of the testimony, as they were counted, according to the commandment of Moses, for the service of the Levites, by the hand of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the priest. ^22And Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, of the tribe of Judah, made all that Jehovah commanded Moses. ^23And with him was Oholiab, the son of Ahisamach, of the tribe of Dan, an engraver, and a skilful workman, and an embroiderer in blue, and in purple, and in scarlet, and in fine linen.

^24All the gold that was used for the work in all the work of the sanctuary, even the gold of the offering, was twenty and nine talents, and seven hundred and thirty shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary. ^25And the silver of them that were numbered of the congregation was a hundred talents, and a thousand seven hundred and threescore and fifteen shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary: ^26a beka a head, that is, half a shekel, after the shekel of the sanctuary, for every one that passed over to them that were numbered, from twenty years old and upward, for six hundred thousand and three thousand and five hundred and fifty men. ^27And the hundred talents of silver were for casting the sockets of the sanctuary, and the sockets of the veil; a hundred sockets for the hundred talents, a talent for a socket. ^28And of the thousand seven hundred seventy and five shekels he made hooks for the pillars, and overlaid their capitals, and made fillets for them. ^29And the brass of the offering was seventy talents, and two thousand and four hundred shekels. ^30And therewith he made the sockets to the door of the tent of meeting, and the brazen altar, and the brazen grating for it, and all the vessels of the altar, ^31and the sockets of the court round about, and the sockets of the gate of the court, and all the pins of the tabernacle, and all the pins of the court round about.

Exodus 39

39

^1And of the blue, and purple, and scarlet, they made finely wrought garments, for ministering in the holy place, and made the holy garments for Aaron; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^2And he made the ephod of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen. ^3And they did beat the gold into thin plates, and cut it into wires, to work it in the blue, and in the purple, and in the scarlet, and in the fine linen, the work of the skilful workman. ^4They made shoulder-pieces for it, joined together; at the two ends was it joined together. ^5And the skilfully woven band, that was upon it, wherewith to gird it on, was of the same piece and like the work thereof; of gold, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^6And they wrought the onyx stones, inclosed in settings of gold, graven with the engravings of a signet, according to the names of the children of Israel. ^7And he put them on the shoulder-pieces of the ephod, to be stones of memorial for the children of Israel; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^8And he made the breastplate, the work of the skilful workman, like the work of the ephod; of gold, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined linen. ^9It was foursquare; they made the breastplate double: a span was the length thereof, and a span the breadth thereof, being double. ^10And they set in it four rows of stones. A row of sardius, topaz, and carbuncle was the first row; ^11and the second row, an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond; ^12and the third row, a jacinth, an agate, and an amethyst; ^13and the fourth row, a beryl, an onyx, and a jaspar: they were inclosed in inclosings of gold in their settings. ^14And the stones were according to the names of the children of Israel, twelve, according to their names; like the engravings of a signet, every one according to his name, for the twelve tribes. ^15And they made upon the breastplate chains like cords, of wreathen work of pure gold. ^16And they made two settings of gold, and two gold rings, and put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate. ^17And they put the two wreathen chains of gold in the two rings at the ends of the breastplate. ^18And the other two ends of the two wreathen chains they put on the two settings, and put them on the shoulder-pieces of the ephod, in the forepart thereof. ^19And they made two rings of gold, and put them upon the two ends of the breastplate, upon the edge thereof, which was toward the side of the ephod inward. ^20And they made two rings of gold, and put them on the two shoulder-pieces of the ephod underneath, in the forepart thereof, close by the coupling thereof, above the skilfully woven band of the ephod. ^21And they did bind the breastplate by the rings thereof unto the rings of the ephod with a lace of blue, that it might be upon the skilfully woven band of the ephod, and that the breastplate might not be loosed from the ephod; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^22And he made the robe of the ephod of woven work, all of blue. ^23And the hole of the robe in the midst thereof, as the hole of a coat of mail, with a binding round about the hole of it, that it should not be rent. ^24And they made upon the skirts of the robe pomegranates of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen. ^25And they made bells of pure gold, and put the bells between the pomegranates upon the skirts of the robe round about, between the pomegranates; ^26a bell and a pomegranate, a bell and a pomegranate, upon the skirts of the robe round about, to minister in; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^27And they made the coats of fine linen of woven work for Aaron, and for his sons, ^28and the mitre of fine linen, and the goodly head-tires of fine linen, and the linen breeches of fine twined linen, ^29and the girdle of fine twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, the work of the embroiderer; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^30And they made the plate of the holy crown of pure gold, and wrote upon it a writing, like the engravings of a signet, HOLY TO JEHOVAH. ^31And they tied unto it a lace of blue, to fasten it upon the mitre above; as Jehovah commanded Moses.

^32Thus was finished all the work of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting: and the children of Israel did according to all that Jehovah commanded Moses; so did they. ^33And they brought the tabernacle unto Moses, the Tent, and all its furniture, its clasps, its boards, it bars, and its pillars, and it sockets; ^34and the covering of rams' skins dyed red, and the covering of sealskins, and the veil of the screen; ^35the ark of the testimony, and the staves thereof, and the mercy-seat; ^36the table, all the vessels thereof, and the showbread; ^37the pure candlestick, the lamps thereof, even the lamps to be set in order, and all the vessels thereof, and the oil for the light; ^38and the golden altar, and the anointing oil, and the sweet incense, and the screen for the door of the Tent; ^39the brazen altar, and its grating of brass, its staves, and all its vessels, the laver and its base; ^40the hangings of the court, its pillars, and its sockets, and the screen for the gate of the court, the cords thereof, and the pins thereof, and all the instruments of the service of the tabernacle, for the tent of meeting; ^41the finely wrought garments for ministering in the holy place, and the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, to minister in the priest's office. ^42According to all that Jehovah commanded Moses, so the children of Israel did all the work. ^43And Moses saw all the work, and, behold, they had done it; as Jehovah had commanded, even so had they done it: and Moses blessed them.

Exodus 40

40

^1And Jehovah spake unto Moses, saying, ^2On the first day of the first month shalt thou rear up the tabernacle of the tent of meeting. ^3And thou shalt put therein the ark of the testimony, and thou shalt screen the ark with the veil. ^4And thou shalt bring in the table, and set in order the things that are upon it; and thou shalt bring in the candlestick, and light the lamps thereof. ^5And thou shalt set the golden altar for incense before the ark of the testimony, and put the screen of the door to the tabernacle. ^6And thou shalt set the altar of burnt-offering before the door of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting. ^7And thou shalt set the laver between the tent of meeting and the altar, and shalt put water therein. ^8And thou shalt set up the court round about, and hang up the screen of the gate of the court. ^9And thou shalt take the anointing oil, and anoint the tabernacle, and all that is therein, and shalt hallow it, and all the furniture thereof: and it shall be holy. ^10And thou shalt anoint the altar of burnt-offering, and all its vessels, and sanctify the altar: and the altar shall be most holy. ^11And thou shalt anoint the laver and its base, and sanctify it. ^12And thou shalt bring Aaron and his sons unto the door of the tent of meeting, and shalt wash them with water. ^13And thou shalt put upon Aaron the holy garments; and thou shalt anoint him, and sanctify him, that he may minister unto me in the priest's office. ^14And thou shalt bring his sons, and put coats upon them; ^15and thou shalt anoint them, as thou didst anoint their father, that they may minister unto me in the priest's office: and their anointing shall be to them for an everlasting priesthood throughout their generations. ^16Thus did Moses: according to all that Jehovah commanded him, so did he.

^17And it came to pass in the first month in the second year, on the first day of the month, that the tabernacle was reared up. ^18And Moses reared up the tabernacle, and laid its sockets, and set up the boards thereof, and put in the bars thereof, and reared up its pillars. ^19And he spread the tent over the tabernacle, and put the covering of the tent above upon it; as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^20And he took and put the testimony into the ark, and set the staves on the ark, and put the mercy-seat above upon the ark: ^21and he brought the ark into the tabernacle, and set up the veil of the screen, and screened the ark of the testimony; as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^22And he put the table in the tent of meeting, upon the side of the tabernacle northward, without the veil. ^23And he set the bread in order upon it before Jehovah; as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^24And he put the candlestick in the tent of meeting, over against the table, on the side of the tabernacle southward. ^25And he lighted the lamps before Jehovah; as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^26And he put the golden altar in the tent of meeting before the veil: ^27and he burnt thereon incense of sweet spices; as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^28And he put the screen of the door to the tabernacle. ^29And he set the altar of burnt-offering at the door of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting, and offered upon it the burnt-offering and the meal-offering; as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^30And he set the laver between the tent of meeting and the altar, and put water therein, wherewith to wash. ^31And Moses and Aaron and his sons washed their hands and their feet thereat; ^32when they went into the tent of meeting, and when they came near unto the altar, they washed; as Jehovah commanded Moses. ^33And he reared up the court round about the tabernacle and the altar, and set up the screen of the gate of the court. So Moses finished the work.

^34Then the cloud covered the tent of meeting, and the glory of Jehovah filled the tabernacle. ^35And Moses was not able to enter into the tent of meeting, because the cloud abode thereon, and the glory of Jehovah filled the tabernacle. ^36And when the cloud was taken up from over the tabernacle, the children of Israel went onward, throughout all their journeys: ^37but if the cloud was not taken up, then they journeyed not till the day that it was taken up. ^38For the cloud of Jehovah was upon the tabernacle by day, and there was fire therein by night, in the sight of all the house of Israel, throughout all their journeys.

Ezekiel 2

2

^1And he said unto me, Son of man, stand upon thy feet, and I will speak with thee. ^2And the Spirit entered into me when he spake unto me, and set me upon my feet; and I heard him that spake unto me. ^3And he said unto me, Son of man, I send thee to the children of Israel, to nations that are rebellious, which have rebelled against me: they and their fathers have transgressed against me even unto this very day. ^4And the children are impudent and stiffhearted: I do sent thee unto them; and thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah. ^5And they, whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear, (for they are a rebellious house,) yet shall know that there hath been a prophet among them. ^6And thou, son of man, be not afraid of them, neither be afraid of their words, though briers and thorns are with thee, and thou dost dwell among scorpions: be not afraid of their words, nor be dismayed at their looks, though they are a rebellious house. ^7And thou shalt speak my words unto them, whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear; for they are most rebellious. ^8But thou, son of man, hear what I say unto thee; be not thou rebellious like that rebellious house: open thy mouth, and eat that which I give thee. ^9And when I looked, behold, a hand was put forth unto me; and, lo, a roll of a book was therein; ^10And he spread it before me: and it was written within and without; and there were written therein lamentations, and mourning, and woe.

Ezekiel 3

3

^1And he said unto me, Son of man, eat that which thou findest; eat this roll, and go, speak unto the house of Israel. ^2So I opened my mouth, and he caused me to eat the roll. ^3And he said unto me, Son of man, cause thy belly to eat, and fill thy bowels with this roll that I give thee. Then did I eat it; and it was in my mouth as honey for sweetness. ^4And he said unto me, Son of man, go, get thee unto the house of Israel, and speak with my words unto them. ^5For thou art not sent to a people of a strange speech and of a hard language, but to the house of Israel; ^6not to many peoples of a strange speech and of a hard language, whose words thou canst not understand. Surely, if I sent thee to them, they would hearken unto thee. ^7But the house of Israel will not hearken unto thee; for they will not hearken unto me: for all the house of Israel are of hard forehead and of a stiff heart. ^8Behold, I have made thy face hard against their faces, and thy forehead hard against their foreheads. ^9As an adamant harder than flint have I made thy forehead: fear them not, neither be dismayed at their looks, though they are a rebellious house. ^10Moreover he said unto me, Son of man, all my words that I shall speak unto thee receive in thy heart, and hear with thine ears. ^11And go, get thee to them of the captivity, unto the children of thy people, and speak unto them, and tell them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah; whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear. ^12Then the Spirit lifted me up, and I heard behind me the voice of a great rushing, saying, Blessed be the glory of Jehovah from his place. ^13And I heard the noise of the wings of the living creatures as they touched one another, and the noise of the wheels beside them, even the noise of a great rushing. ^14So the Spirit lifted me up, and took me away; and I went in bitterness, in the heat of my spirit; and the hand of Jehovah was strong upon me. ^15Then I came to them of the captivity at Tel-abib, that dwelt by the river Chebar, and to where they dwelt; and I sat there overwhelmed among them seven days. ^16And it came to pass at the end of seven days, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^17Son of man, I have made thee a watchman unto the house of Israel: therefore hear the word at my mouth, and give them warning from me. ^18When I say unto the wicked, Thou shalt surely die; and thou givest him not warning, nor speakest to warn the wicked from his wicked way, to save his life; the same wicked man shall die in his iniquity; but his blood will I require at thy hand. ^19Yet if thou warn the wicked, and he turn not from his wickedness, nor from his wicked way, he shall die in his iniquity; but thou hast delivered thy soul. ^20Again, when a righteous man doth turn from his righteousness, and commit iniquity, and I lay a stumblingblock before him, he shall die: because thou hast not given him warning, he shall die in his sin, and his righteous deeds which he hath done shall not be remembered; but his blood will I require at thy hand. ^21Nevertheless if thou warn the righteous man, that the righteous sin not, and he doth not sin, he shall surely live, because he took warning; and thou hast delivered thy soul. ^22And the hand of Jehovah was there upon me; and he said unto me, Arise, go forth into the plain, and I will there talk with thee. ^23Then I arose, and went forth into the plain: and, behold, the glory of Jehovah stood there, as the glory which I saw by the river Chebar; and I fell on my face. ^24Then the Spirit entered into me, and set me upon my feet; and he spake with me, and said unto me, Go, shut thyself within thy house. ^25But thou, son of man, behold, they shall lay bands upon thee, and shall bind thee with them, and thou shalt not go out among them: ^26and I will make thy tongue cleave to the roof of thy mouth, that thou shalt be dumb, and shalt not be to them a reprover; for they are a rebellious house. ^27But when I speak with thee, I will open thy mouth, and thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: He that heareth, let him hear; and he that forbeareth, let him forbear: for they are a rebellious house.

Ezekiel 4

4

^1Thou also, son of man, take thee a tile, and lay it before thee, and portray upon it a city, even Jerusalem: ^2and lay siege against it, and build forts against it, and cast up a mound against it; set camps also against it, and plant battering rams against it round about. ^3And take thou unto thee an iron pan, and set it for a wall of iron between thee and the city: and set thy face toward it, and it shall be besieged, and thou shalt lay siege against it. This shall be a sign to the house of Israel. ^4Moreover lie thou upon thy left side, and lay the iniquity of the house of Israel upon it; according to the number of the days that thou shalt lie upon it, thou shalt bear their iniquity. ^5For I have appointed the years of their iniquity to be unto thee a number of days, even three hundred and ninety days: so shalt thou bear the iniquity of the house of Israel. ^6And again, when thou hast accomplished these, thou shalt lie on thy right side, and shalt bear the iniquity of the house of Judah: forty days, each day for a year, have I appointed it unto thee. ^7And thou shalt set thy face toward the siege of Jerusalem, with thine arm uncovered; and thou shalt prophesy against it. ^8And, behold, I lay bands upon thee, and thou shalt not turn thee from one side to the other, till thou hast accomplished the days of thy siege. ^9Take thou also unto thee wheat, and barley, and beans, and lentils, and millet, and spelt, and put them in one vessel, and make thee bread thereof; according to the number of the days that thou shalt lie upon thy side, even three hundred and ninety days, shalt thou eat thereof. ^10And thy food which thou shalt eat shall be by weight, twenty shekels a day: from time to time shalt thou eat it. ^11And thou shalt drink water by measure, the sixth part of a hin: from time to time shalt thou drink. ^12And thou shalt eat it as barley cakes, and thou shalt bake it in their sight with dung that cometh out of man. ^13And Jehovah said, Even thus shall the children of Israel eat their bread unclean, among the nations whither I will drive them. ^14Then said I, Ah Lord Jehovah! behold, my soul hath not been polluted; for from my youth up even till now have I not eaten of that which dieth of itself, or is torn of beasts; neither came there abominable flesh into my mouth. ^15Then he said unto me, See, I have given thee cow's dung for man's dung, and thou shalt prepare thy bread thereon. ^16Moreover he said unto me, Son of man, behold, I will break the staff of bread in Jerusalem: and they shall eat bread by weight, and with fearfulness; and they shall drink water by measure, and in dismay: ^17that they may want bread and water, and be dismayed one with another, and pine away in their iniquity.

Ezekiel 5

5

^1And thou, son of man, take thee a sharp sword; as a barber's razor shalt thou take it unto thee, and shalt cause it to pass upon thy head and upon thy beard: then take thee balances to weigh, and divide the hair. ^2A third part shalt thou burn in the fire in the midst of the city, when the days of the siege are fulfilled; and thou shalt take a third part, and smite with the sword round about it; and a third part thou shalt scatter to the wind, and I will draw out a sword after them. ^3And thou shalt take thereof a few in number, and bind them in thy skirts. ^4And of these again shalt thou take, and cast them into the midst of the fire, and burn them in the fire; therefrom shall a fire come forth into all the house of Israel. ^5Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: This is Jerusalem; I have set her in the midst of the nations, and countries are round about her. ^6And she hath rebelled against mine ordinances in doing wickedness more than the nations, and against my statutes more than the countries that are round about her; for they have rejected mine ordinances, and as for my statutes, they have not walked in them. ^7Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because ye are turbulent more than the nations that are round about you, and have not walked in my statutes, neither have kept mine ordinances, neither have done after the ordinances of the nations that are round about you; ^8therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I, even I, am against thee; and I will execute judgments in the midst of thee in the sight of the nations. ^9And I will do in thee that which I have not done, and whereunto I will not do any more the like, because of all thine abominations. ^10Therefore the fathers shall eat the sons in the midst of thee, and the sons shall eat their fathers; and I will execute judgments on thee; and the whole remnant of thee will I scatter unto all the winds. ^11Wherefore, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, surely, because thou hast defiled my sanctuary with all thy detestable things, and with all thine abominations, therefore will I also diminish thee; neither shall mine eye spare, and I also will have no pity. ^12A third part of thee shall die with the pestilence, and with famine shall they be consumed in the midst of thee; and a third part shall fall by the sword round about thee; and a third part I will scatter unto all the winds, and will draw out a sword after them. ^13Thus shall mine anger be accomplished, and I will cause my wrath toward them to rest, and I shall be comforted; and they shall know that I, Jehovah, have spoken in my zeal, when I have accomplished my wrath upon them. ^14Moreover I will make thee a desolation and a reproach among the nations that are round about thee, in the sight of all that pass by. ^15So it shall be a reproach and a taunt, an instruction and an astonishment, unto the nations that are round about thee, when I shall execute judgments on thee in anger and in wrath, and in wrathful rebukes; (I, Jehovah, have spoken it;) ^16when I shall send upon them the evil arrows of famine, that are for destruction, which I will send to destroy you: and I will increase the famine upon you, and will break your staff of bread; ^17and I will send upon you famine and evil beasts, and they shall bereave thee; and pestilence and blood shall pass through thee; and I will bring the sword upon thee: I, Jehovah, have spoken it.

Ezekiel 6

6

^1And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, set thy face toward the mountains of Israel, and prophesy unto them, ^3and say, Ye mountains of Israel, hear the word of the Lord Jehovah: Thus saith the Lord Jehovah to the mountains and to the hills, to the watercourses and to the valleys: Behold, I, even I, will bring a sword upon you, and I will destroy your high places. ^4And your altars shall become desolate, and your sun-images shall be broken; and I will cast down your slain men before your idols. ^5And I will lay the dead bodies of the children of Israel before their idols; and I will scatter your bones round about your altars. ^6In all your dwelling-places the cities shall be laid waste, and the high places shall be desolate; that your altars may be laid waste and made desolate, and your idols may be broken and cease, and your sun-images may be hewn down, and your works may be abolished. ^7And the slain shall fall in the midst of you, and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^8Yet will I leave a remnant, in that ye shall have some that escape the sword among the nations, when ye shall be scattered through the countries. ^9And those of you that escape shall remember me among the nations whither they shall be carried captive, how that I have been broken with their lewd heart, which hath departed from me, and with their eyes, which play the harlot after their idols: and they shall loathe themselves in their own sight for the evils which they have committed in all their abominations. ^10And they shall know that I am Jehovah: I have not said in vain that I would do this evil unto them. ^11Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Smite with thy hand, and stamp with thy foot, and say, Alas! because of all the evil abominations of the house of Israel; for they shall fall by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence. ^12He that is far off shall die of the pestilence; and he that is near shall fall by the sword; and he that remaineth and is besieged shall die by the famine: thus will I accomplish my wrath upon them. ^13And ye shall know that I am Jehovah, when their slain men shall be among their idols round about their altars, upon every high hill, on all the tops of the mountains, and under every green tree, and under every thick oak, the places where they offered sweet savor to all their idols. ^14And I will stretch out my hand upon them, and make the land desolate and waste, from the wilderness toward Diblah, throughout all their habitations: and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 7

7

^1Moreover the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2And thou, son of man, thus saith the Lord Jehovah unto the land of Israel, An end: the end is come upon the four corners of the land. ^3Now is the end upon thee, and I will send mine anger upon thee, and will judge thee according to thy ways; and I will bring upon thee all thine abominations. ^4And mine eye shall not spare thee, neither will I have pity; but I will bring thy ways upon thee, and thine abominations shall be in the midst of thee: and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^5Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: An evil, an only evil; behold, it cometh. ^6An end is come, the end is come; it awaketh against thee; behold, it cometh. ^7Thy doom is come unto thee, O inhabitant of the land: the time is come, the day is near, a day of tumult, and not of joyful shouting, upon the mountains. ^8Now will I shortly pour out my wrath upon thee, and accomplish mine anger against thee, and will judge thee according to thy ways; and I will bring upon thee all thine abominations. ^9And mine eye shall not spare, neither will I have pity: I will bring upon thee according to thy ways; and thine abominations shall be in the midst of thee; and ye shall know that I, Jehovah, do smite. ^10Behold, the day, behold, it cometh: thy doom is gone forth; the rod hath blossomed, pride hath budded. ^11Violence is risen up into a rod of wickedness; none of them shall remain, nor of their multitude, nor of their wealth: neither shall there be eminency among them. ^12The time is come, the day draweth near: let not the buyer rejoice, nor the seller mourn; for wrath is upon all the multitude thereof. ^13For the seller shall not return to that which is sold, although they be yet alive: for the vision is touching the whole multitude thereof, none shall return; neither shall any strengthen himself in the iniquity of his life. ^14They have blown the trumpet, and have made all ready; but none goeth to the battle; for my wrath is upon all the multitude thereof. ^15The sword is without, and the pestilence and the famine within: he that is in the field shall die with the sword: and he that is in the city, famine and pestilence shall devour him. ^16But those of them that escape shall escape, and shall be on the mountains like doves of the valleys, all of them moaning, every one in his iniquity. ^17All hands shall be feeble, and all knees shall be weak as water. ^18They shall also gird themselves with sackcloth, and horror shall cover them; and shame shall be upon all faces, and baldness upon all their heads. ^19They shall cast their silver in the streets, and their gold shall be as an unclean thing; their silver and their gold shall not be able to deliver them in the day of the wrath of Jehovah: they shall not satisfy their souls, neither fill their bowels; because it hath been the stumblingblock of their iniquity. ^20As for the beauty of his ornament, he set it in majesty; but they made the images of their abominations and their detestable things therein: therefore have I made it unto them as an unclean thing. ^21And I will give it into the hands of the strangers for a prey, and to the wicked of the earth for a spoil; and they shall profane it. ^22My face will I turn also from them, and they shall profane my secret place; and robbers shall enter into it, and profane it. ^23Make the chain; for the land is full of bloody crimes, and the city is full of violence. ^24Wherefore I will bring the worst of the nations, and they shall possess their houses: I will also make the pride of the strong to cease; and their holy places shall be profaned. ^25Destruction cometh; and they shall seek peace, and there shall be none. ^26Mischief shall come upon mischief, and rumor shall be upon rumor; and they shall seek a vision of the prophet; but the law shall perish from the priest, and counsel from the elders. ^27The king shall mourn, and the prince shall be clothed with desolation, and the hands of the people of the land shall be troubled: I will do unto them after their way, and according to their deserts will I judge them; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 8

8

^1And it came to pass in the sixth year, in the sixth month, in the fifth day of the month, as I sat in my house, and the elders of Judah sat before me, that the hand of the Lord Jehovah fell there upon me. ^2Then I beheld, and, lo, a likeness as the appearance of fire; from the appearance of his loins and downward, fire; and from his loins and upward, as the appearance of brightness, as it were glowing metal. ^3And he put forth the form of a hand, and took me by a lock of my head; and the Spirit lifted me up between earth and heaven, and brought me in the visions of God to Jerusalem, to the door of the gate of the inner court that looketh toward the north; where was the seat of the image of jealousy, which provoketh to jealousy. ^4And, behold, the glory of the God of Israel was there, according to the appearance that I saw in the plain. ^5Then said he unto me, Son of man, lift up thine eyes now the way toward the north. So I lifted up mine eyes the way toward the north, and behold, northward of the gate of the altar this image of jealousy in the entry. ^6And he said unto me, Son of man, seest thou what they do? even the great abominations that the house of Israel do commit here, that I should go far off from my sanctuary? but thou shalt again see yet other great abominations. ^7And he brought me to the door of the court; and when I looked, behold, a hole in the wall. ^8Then said he unto me, Son of man, dig now in the wall: and when I had digged in the wall, behold, a door. ^9And he said unto me, Go in, and see the wicked abominations that they do here. ^10So I went in and saw; and behold, every form of creeping things, and abominable beasts, and all the idols of the house of Israel, portrayed upon the wall round about. ^11And there stood before them seventy men of the elders of the house of Israel; and in the midst of them stood Jaazaniah the son of Shaphan, every man with his censer in his hand; and the odor of the cloud of incense went up. ^12Then said he unto me, Son of man, hast thou seen what the elders of the house of Israel do in the dark, every man in his chambers of imagery? for they say, Jehovah seeth us not; Jehovah hath forsaken the land. ^13He said also unto me, Thou shalt again see yet other great abominations which they do. ^14Then he brought me to the door of the gate of Jehovah's house which was toward the north; and behold, there sat the women weeping for Tammuz. ^15Then said he unto me, Hast thou seen this, O son of man? thou shalt again see yet greater abominations than these. ^16And he brought me into the inner court of Jehovah's house; and behold, at the door of the temple of Jehovah, between the porch and the altar, were about five and twenty men, with their backs toward the temple of Jehovah, and their faces toward the east; and they were worshipping the sun toward the east. ^17Then he said unto me, Hast thou seen this, O son of man? Is it a light thing to the house of Judah that they commit the abominations which they commit here? for they have filled the land with violence, and have turned again to provoke me to anger: and, lo, they put the branch to their nose. ^18Therefore will I also deal in wrath; mine eye shall not spare, neither will I have pity; and though they cry in mine ears with a loud voice, yet will I not hear them.

Ezekiel 9

9

^1Then he cried in mine ears with a loud voice, saying, Cause ye them that have charge over the city to draw near, every man with his destroying weapon in his hand. ^2And behold, six men came from the way of the upper gate, which lieth toward the north, every man with his slaughter weapon in his hand; and one man in the midst of them clothed in linen, with a writer's inkhorn by his side. And they went in, and stood beside the brazen altar. ^3And the glory of the God of Israel was gone up from the cherub, whereupon it was, to the threshold of the house: and he called to the man clothed in linen, who had the writer's inkhorn by his side. ^4And Jehovah said unto him, Go through the midst of the city, through the midst of Jerusalem, and set a mark upon the foreheads of the men that sigh and that cry over all the abominations that are done in the midst thereof. ^5And to the others he said in my hearing, Go ye through the city after him, and smite: let not your eye spare, neither have ye pity; ^6slay utterly the old man, the young man and the virgin, and little children and women; but come not near any man upon whom is the mark: and begin at my sanctuary. Then they began at the old men that were before the house. ^7And he said unto them, Defile the house, and fill the courts with the slain: go ye forth. And they went forth, and smote in the city. ^8And it came to pass, while they were smiting, and I was left, that I fell upon my face, and cried, and said, Ah Lord Jehovah! wilt thou destroy all the residue of Israel in thy pouring out of thy wrath upon Jerusalem? ^9Then said he unto me, The iniquity of the house of Israel and Judah is exceeding great, and the land is full of blood, and the city full of wrestling of judgment: for they say, Jehovah hath forsaken the land, and Jehovah seeth not. ^10And as for me also, mine eye shall not spare, neither will I have pity, but I will bring their way upon their head. ^11And behold, the man clothed in linen, who had the inkhorn by his side, reported the matter, saying, I have done as thou hast commanded me.

Ezekiel 10

10

^1Then I looked, and behold, in the firmament that was over the head of the cherubim there appeared above them as it were a sapphire stone, as the appearance of the likeness of a throne. ^2And he spake unto the man clothed in linen, and said, Go in between the whirling wheels, even under the cherub, and fill both thy hands with coals of fire from between the cherubim, and scatter them over the city. And he went in in my sight. ^3Now the cherubim stood on the right side of the house, when the man went in; and the cloud filled the inner court. ^4And the glory of Jehovah mounted up from the cherub, and stood over the threshold of the house; and the house was filled with the cloud, and the court was full of the brightness of Jehovah's glory. ^5And the sound of the wings of the cherubim was heard even to the outer court, as the voice of God Almighty when he speaketh. ^6And it came to pass, when he commanded the man clothed in linen, saying, Take fire from between the whirling wheels, from between the cherubim, that he went in, and stood beside a wheel. ^7And the cherub stretched forth his hand from between the cherubim unto the fire that was between the cherubim, and took thereof, and put it into the hands of him that was clothed in linen, who took it and went out. ^8And there appeared in the cherubim the form of a man's hand under their wings. ^9And I looked, and behold, four wheels beside the cherubim, one wheel beside one cherub, and another wheel beside another cherub; and the appearance of the wheels was like unto a beryl stone. ^10And as for their appearance, they four had one likeness, as if a wheel have been within a wheel. ^11When they went, they went in their four directions: they turned not as they went, but to the place whither the head looked they followed it; they turned not as they went. ^12And their whole body, and their backs, and their hands, and their wings, and the wheels, were full of eyes round about, even the wheels that they four had. ^13As for the wheels, they were called in my hearing, the whirling wheels. ^14And every one had four faces: the first face was the face of the cherub, and the second face was the face of a man, and the third face the face of a lion, and the fourth the face of an eagle. ^15And the cherubim mounted up: this is the living creature that I saw by the river Chebar. ^16And when the cherubim went, the wheels went beside them; and when the cherubim lifted up their wings to mount up from the earth, the wheels also turned not from beside them. ^17When they stood, these stood; and when they mounted up, these mounted up with them: for the spirit of the living creature was in them. ^18And the glory of Jehovah went forth from over the threshold of the house, and stood over the cherubim. ^19And the cherubim lifted up their wings, and mounted up from the earth in my sight when they went forth, and the wheels beside them: and they stood at the door of the east gate of Jehovah's house; and the glory of the God of Israel was over them above. ^20This is the living creature that I saw under the God of Israel by the river Chebar; and I knew that they were cherubim. ^21Every one had four faces, and every one four wings; and the likeness of the hands of a man was under their wings. ^22And as for the likeness of their faces, they were the faces which I saw by the river Chebar, their appearances and themselves; they went every one straight forward.

Ezekiel 11

11

^1Moreover the Spirit lifted me up, and brought me unto the east gate of Jehovah's house, which looketh eastward: and behold, at the door of the gate five and twenty men; and I saw in the midst of them Jaazaniah the son of Azzur, and Pelatiah the son of Benaiah, princes of the people. ^2And he said unto me, Son of man, these are the men that devise iniquity, and that give wicked counsel in this city; ^3that say, The time is not near to build houses: this city is the caldron, and we are the flesh. ^4Therefore prophesy against them, prophesy, O son of man. ^5And the Spirit of Jehovah fell upon me, and he said unto me, Speak, Thus saith Jehovah: Thus have ye said, O house of Israel; for I know the things that come into your mind. ^6Ye have multiplied your slain in this city, and ye have filled the streets thereof with the slain. ^7Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Your slain whom ye have laid in the midst of it, they are the flesh, and this city is the caldron; but ye shall be brought forth out of the midst of it. ^8Ye have feared the sword; and I will bring the sword upon you, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^9And I will bring you forth out of the midst thereof, and deliver you into the hands of strangers, and will execute judgments among you. ^10Ye shall fall by the sword; I will judge you in the border of Israel; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^11This city shall not be your caldron, neither shall ye be the flesh in the midst thereof; I will judge you in the border of Israel; ^12and ye shall know that I am Jehovah: for ye have not walked in my statutes, neither have ye executed mine ordinances, but have done after the ordinances of the nations that are round about you. ^13And it came to pass, when I prophesied, that Pelatiah the son of Benaiah died. Then fell I down upon my face, and cried with a loud voice, and said, Ah Lord Jehovah! wilt thou make a full end of the remnant of Israel? ^14And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^15Son of man, thy brethren, even thy brethren, the men of thy kindred, and all the house of Israel, all of them, are they unto whom the inhabitants of Jerusalem have said, Get you far from Jehovah; unto us is this land given for a possession. ^16Therefore say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Whereas I have removed them far off among the nations, and whereas I have scattered them among the countries, yet will I be to them a sanctuary for a little while in the countries where they are come. ^17Therefore say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will gather you from the peoples, and assemble you out of the countries where ye have been scattered, and I will give you the land of Israel. ^18And they shall come thither, and they shall take away all the detestable things thereof and all the abominations thereof from thence. ^19And I will give them one heart, and I will put a new spirit within you; and I will take the stony heart out of their flesh, and will give them a heart of flesh; ^20that they may walk in my statutes, and keep mine ordinances, and do them: and they shall be my people, and I will be their God. ^21But as for them whose heart walketh after the heart of their detestable things and their abominations, I will bring their way upon their own heads, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^22Then did the cherubim lift up their wings, and the wheels were beside them; and the glory of the God of Israel was over them above. ^23And the glory of Jehovah went up from the midst of the city, and stood upon the mountain which is on the east side of the city. ^24And the Spirit lifted me up, and brought me in the vision by the Spirit of God into Chaldea, to them of the captivity. So the vision that I had seen went up from me. ^25Then I spake unto them of the captivity all the things that Jehovah had showed me.

Ezekiel 12

12

^1The word of Jehovah also came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, thou dwellest in the midst of the rebellious house, that have eyes to see, and see not, that have ears to hear, and hear not; for they are a rebellious house. ^3Therefore, thou son of man, prepare thee stuff for removing, and remove by day in their sight; and thou shalt remove from thy place to another place in their sight: it may be they will consider, though they are a rebellious house. ^4And thou shalt bring forth thy stuff by day in their sight, as stuff for removing; and thou shalt go forth thyself at even in their sight, as when men go forth into exile. ^5Dig thou through the wall in their sight, and carry out thereby. ^6In their sight shalt thou bear it upon thy shoulder, and carry it forth in the dark; thou shalt cover thy face, that thou see not the land: for I have set thee for a sign unto the house of Israel. ^7And I did so as I was commanded: I brought forth my stuff by day, as stuff for removing, and in the even I digged through the wall with my hand; I brought it forth in the dark, and bare it upon my shoulder in their sight. ^8And in the morning came the word of Jehovah unto me, saying, ^9Son of man, hath not the house of Israel, the rebellious house, said unto thee, What doest thou? ^10Say thou unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: This burden concerneth the prince in Jerusalem, and all the house of Israel among whom they are. ^11Say, I am your sign: like as I have done, so shall it be done unto them; they shall go into exile, into captivity. ^12And the prince that is among them shall bear upon his shoulder in the dark, and shall go forth: they shall dig through the wall to carry out thereby: he shall cover his face, because he shall not see the land with his eyes. ^13My net also will I spread upon him, and he shall be taken in my snare; and I will bring him to Babylon to the land of the Chaldeans; yet shall he not see it, though he shall die there. ^14And I will scatter toward every wind all that are round about him to help him, and all his bands; and I will draw out the sword after them. ^15And they shall know that I am Jehovah, when I shall disperse them among the nations, and scatter them through the countries. ^16But I will leave a few men of them from the sword, from the famine, and from the pestilence; that they may declare all their abominations among the nations whither they come; and they shall know that I am Jehovah. ^17Moreover the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, ^18Son of man, eat thy bread with quaking, and drink thy water with trembling and with fearfulness; ^19and say unto the people of the land, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah concerning the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and the land of Israel: They shall eat their bread with fearfulness, and drink their water in dismay, that her land may be desolate, and despoiled of all that is therein, because of the violence of all them that dwell therein. ^20And the cities that are inhabited shall be laid waste, and the land shall be a desolation; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^21And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^22Son of man, what is this proverb that ye have in the land of Israel, saying, The days are prolonged, and every vision faileth? ^23Tell them therefore, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will make this proverb to cease, and they shall no more use it as a proverb in Israel; but say unto them, The days are at hand, and the fulfilment of every vision. ^24For there shall be no more any false vision nor flattering divination within the house of Israel. ^25For I am Jehovah; I will speak, and the word that I shall speak shall be performed; it shall be no more deferred: for in your days, O rebellious house, will I speak the word, and will perform it, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^26Again the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, ^27Son of man, behold, they of the house of Israel say, The vision that he seeth is for many day to come, and he prophesieth of times that are far off. ^28Therefore say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: There shall none of my words be deferred any more, but the word which I shall speak shall be performed, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 13

13

^1And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, prophesy against the prophets of Israel that prophesy, and say thou unto them that prophesy out of their own heart, Hear ye the word of Jehovah: ^3Thus saith the Lord Jehovah, Woe unto the foolish prophets, that follow their own spirit, and have seen nothing! ^4O Israel, thy prophets have been like foxes in the waste places. ^5Ye have not gone up into the gaps, neither built up the wall for the house of Israel, to stand in the battle in the day of Jehovah. ^6They have seen falsehood and lying divination, that say, Jehovah saith; but Jehovah hath not sent them: and they have made men to hope that the word would be confirmed. ^7Have ye not seen a false vision, and have ye not spoken a lying divination, in that ye say, Jehovah saith; albeit I have not spoken? ^8Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because ye have spoken falsehood, and seen lies, therefore, behold, I am against you, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^9And my hand shall be against the prophets that see false visions, and that divine lies: they shall not be in the council of my people, neither shall they be written in the writing of the house of Israel, neither shall they enter into the land of Israel; and ye shall know that I am the Lord Jehovah. ^10Because, even because they have seduced my people, saying, Peace; and there is no peace; and when one buildeth up a wall, behold, they daub it with untempered mortar: ^11say unto them that daub it with untempered mortar, that it shall fall: there shall be an overflowing shower; and ye, O great hailstones, shall fall; and a stormy wind shall rend it. ^12Lo, when the wall is fallen, shall it not be said unto you, Where is the daubing wherewith ye have daubed it? ^13Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will even rend it with a stormy wind in my wrath; and there shall be an overflowing shower in mine anger, and great hailstones in wrath to consume it. ^14So will I break down the wall that ye have daubed with untempered mortar, and bring it down to the ground, so that the foundation thereof shall be uncovered; and it shall fall, and ye shall be consumed in the midst thereof: and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^15Thus will I accomplish my wrath upon the wall, and upon them that have daubed it with untempered mortar; and I will say unto you, The wall is no more, neither they that daubed it; ^16to wit, the prophets of Israel that prophesy concerning Jerusalem, and that see visions of peace for her, and there is no peace, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^17And thou, son of man, set thy face against the daughters of thy people, that prophesy out of their own heart; and prophesy thou against them, ^18and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Woe to the women that sew pillows upon all elbows, and make kerchiefs for the head of persons of every stature to hunt souls! Will ye hunt the souls of my people, and save souls alive for yourselves? ^19And ye have profaned me among my people for handfuls of barley and for pieces of bread, to slay the souls that should not die, and to save the souls alive that should not live, by your lying to my people that hearken unto lies. ^20Wherefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against your pillows, wherewith ye there hunt the souls to make them fly, and I will tear them from your arms; and I will let the souls go, even the souls that ye hunt to make them fly. ^21Your kerchiefs also will I tear, and deliver my people out of your hand, and they shall be no more in your hand to be hunted; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^22Because with lies ye have grieved the heart of the righteous, whom I have not made sad; and strengthened the hands of the wicked, that he should not return from his wicked way, and be saved alive: ^23Therefore ye shall no more see false visions, nor divine divinations: and I will deliver my people out of your hand; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 14

14

^1Then came certain of the elders of Israel unto me, and sat before me. ^2And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^3Son of man, these men have taken their idols into their heart, and put the stumblingblock of their iniquity before their face: should I be inquired of at all by them? ^4Therefore speak unto them, and say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Every man of the house of Israel that taketh his idols into his heart, and putteth the stumblingblock of his iniquity before his face, and cometh to the prophet; I Jehovah will answer him therein according to the multitude of his idols; ^5that I may take the house of Israel in their own heart, because they are all estranged from me through their idols. ^6Therefore say unto the house of Israel, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Return ye, and turn yourselves from your idols; and turn away your faces from all your abominations. ^7For every one of the house of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn in Israel, that separateth himself from me, and taketh his idols into his heart, and putteth the stumblingblock of his iniquity before his face, and cometh to the prophet to inquire for himself of me; I Jehovah will answer him by myself: ^8and I will set my face against that man, and will make him an astonishment, for a sign and a proverb, and I will cut him off from the midst of my people; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^9And if the prophet be deceived and speak a word, I, Jehovah, have deceived that prophet, and I will stretch out my hand upon him, and will destroy him from the midst of my people Israel. ^10And they shall bear their iniquity: the iniquity of the prophet shall be even as the iniquity of him that seeketh unto him; ^11that the house of Israel may go no more astray from me, neither defile themselves any more with all their transgressions; but that they may be my people, and I may be their God, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^12And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^13Son of man, when a land sinneth against me by committing a trespass, and I stretch out my hand upon it, and break the staff of the bread thereof, and send famine upon it, and cut off from it man and beast; ^14though these three men, Noah, Daniel, and Job, were in it, they should deliver but their own souls by their righteousness, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^15If I cause evil beasts to pass through the land, and they ravage it, and it be made desolate, so that no man may pass through because of the beasts; ^16though these three men were in it, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, they should deliver neither sons nor daughters; they only should be delivered, but the land should be desolate. ^17Or if I bring a sword upon that land, and say, Sword, go through the land; so that I cut off from it man and beast; ^18though these three men were in it, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, they should deliver neither sons nor daughters, but they only should be delivered themselves. ^19Or if I send a pestilence into that land, and pour out my wrath upon it in blood, to cut off from it man and beast; ^20though Noah, Daniel, and Job, were in it, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, they should deliver neither son nor daughter; they should but deliver their own souls by their righteousness. ^21For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: How much more when I send my four sore judgments upon Jerusalem, the sword, and the famine, and the evil beasts, and the pestilence, to cut off from it man and beast! ^22Yet, behold, therein shall be left a remnant that shall be carried forth, both sons and daughters: behold, they shall come forth unto you, and ye shall see their way and their doings; and ye shall be comforted concerning the evil that I have brought upon Jerusalem, even concerning all that I have brought upon it. ^23And they shall comfort you, when ye see their way and their doings; and ye shall know that I have not done without cause all that I have done in it, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 16

16

^1Again the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, cause Jerusalem to know her abominations; ^3and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah unto Jerusalem: Thy birth and thy nativity is of the land of the Canaanite; the Amorite was thy father, and thy mother was a Hittite. ^4And as for thy nativity, in the day thou wast born thy navel was not cut, neither wast thou washed in water to cleanse thee; thou wast not salted at all, nor swaddled at all. ^5No eye pitied thee, to do any of these things unto thee, to have compassion upon thee; but thou wast cast out in the open field, for that thy person was abhorred, in the day that thou wast born. ^6And when I passed by thee, and saw thee weltering in thy blood, I said unto thee, Though thou art in thy blood, live; yea, I said unto thee, Though thou art in thy blood, live. ^7I caused thee to multiply as that which groweth in the field, and thou didst increase and wax great, and thou attainedst to excellent ornament; thy breasts were fashioned, and thy hair was grown; yet thou wast naked and bare. ^8Now when I passed by thee, and looked upon thee, behold, thy time was the time of love; and I spread my skirt over thee, and covered thy nakedness: yea, I sware unto thee, and entered into a covenant with thee, saith the Lord Jehovah, and thou becamest mine. ^9Then washed I thee with water; yea, I thoroughly washed away thy blood from thee, and I anointed thee with oil. ^10I clothed thee also with broidered work, and shod thee with sealskin, and I girded thee about with fine linen, and covered thee with silk. ^11And I decked thee with ornaments, and I put bracelets upon thy hands, and a chain on thy neck. ^12And I put a ring upon thy nose, and ear-rings in thine ears, and a beautiful crown upon thy head. ^13Thus wast thou decked with gold and silver; and thy raiment was of fine linen, and silk, and broidered work; thou didst eat fine flour, and honey, and oil; and thou wast exceeding beautiful, and thou didst prosper unto royal estate. ^14And thy renown went forth among the nations for thy beauty; for it was perfect, through my majesty which I had put upon thee, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^15But thou didst trust in thy beauty, and playedst the harlot because of thy renown, and pouredst out thy whoredoms on every one that passed by; his it was. ^16And thou didst take of thy garments, and madest for thee high places decked with divers colors, and playedst the harlot upon them: the like things shall not come, neither shall it be so. ^17Thou didst also take thy fair jewels of my gold and of my silver, which I had given thee, and madest for thee images of men, and didst play the harlot with them; ^18and thou tookest thy broidered garments, and coveredst them, and didst set mine oil and mine incense before them. ^19My bread also which I gave thee, fine flour, and oil, and honey, wherewith I fed thee, thou didst even set it before them for a sweet savor; and thus it was, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^20Moreover thou hast taken thy sons and thy daughters, whom thou hast borne unto me, and these hast thou sacrificed unto them to be devoured. Were thy whoredoms a small matter, ^21that thou hast slain my children, and delivered them up, in causing them to pass through the fire unto them? ^22And in all thine abominations and thy whoredoms thou hast not remembered the days of thy youth, when thou wast naked and bare, and wast weltering in thy blood. ^23And it is come to pass after all thy wickedness, (woe, woe unto thee! saith the Lord Jehovah,) ^24that thou hast built unto thee a vaulted place, and hast made thee a lofty place in every street. ^25Thou hast built thy lofty place at the head of every way, and hast made thy beauty an abomination, and hast opened thy feet to every one that passed by, and multiplied thy whoredom. ^26Thou hast also committed fornication with the Egyptians, thy neighbors, great of flesh; and hast multiplied thy whoredom, to provoke me to anger. ^27Behold therefore, I have stretched out my hand over thee, and have diminished thine ordinary food, and delivered thee unto the will of them that hate thee, the daughters of the Philistines, that are ashamed of thy lewd way. ^28Thou hast played the harlot also with the Assyrians, because thou wast insatiable; yea, thou hast played the harlot with them, and yet thou wast not satisfied. ^29Thou hast moreover multiplied thy whoredom unto the land of traffic, unto Chaldea; and yet thou wast not satisfied herewith. ^30How weak is thy heart, saith the Lord Jehovah, seeing thou doest all these things, the work of an impudent harlot; ^31in that thou buildest thy vaulted place at the head of every way, and makest thy lofty place in every street, and hast not been as a harlot, in that thou scornest hire. ^32A wife that committeth adultery! that taketh strangers instead of her husband! ^33They give gifts to all harlots; but thou givest thy gifts to all thy lovers, and bribest them, that they may come unto thee on every side for thy whoredoms. ^34And thou art different from other women in thy whoredoms, in that none followeth thee to play the harlot; and whereas thou givest hire, and no hire is given unto thee, therefore thou art different. ^35Wherefore, O harlot, hear the word of Jehovah: ^36Thus saith the Lord Jehovah, Because thy filthiness was poured out, and thy nakedness uncovered through thy whoredoms with thy lovers; and because of all the idols of thy abominations, and for the blood of thy children, that thou didst give unto them; ^37therefore behold, I will gather all thy lovers, with whom thou hast taken pleasure, and all them that thou hast loved, with all them that thou hast hated; I will even gather them against thee on every side, and will uncover thy nakedness unto them, that they may see all thy nakedness. ^38And I will judge thee, as women that break wedlock and shed blood are judged; and I will bring upon thee the blood of wrath and jealousy. ^39I will also give thee into their hand, and they shall throw down thy vaulted place, and break down thy lofty places; and they shall strip thee of thy clothes, and take thy fair jewels; and they shall leave thee naked and bare. ^40They shall also bring up a company against thee, and they shall stone thee with stones, and thrust thee through with their swords. ^41And they shall burn thy houses with fire, and execute judgments upon thee in the sight of many women; and I will cause thee to cease from playing the harlot, and thou shalt also give no hire any more. ^42So will I cause my wrath toward thee to rest, and my jealousy shall depart from thee, and I will be quiet, and will be no more angry. ^43Because thou hast not remembered the days of thy youth, but hast raged against me in all these things; therefore, behold, I also will bring thy way upon thy head, saith the Lord Jehovah: and thou shalt not commit this lewdness with all thine abominations. ^44Behold, every one that useth proverbs shall use this proverb against thee, saying, As is the mother, so is her daughter. ^45Thou art the daughter of thy mother, that loatheth her husband and her children; and thou art the sister of thy sisters, who loathed their husbands and their children: your mother was a Hittite, and your father an Amorite. ^46And thine elder sister is Samaria, that dwelleth at thy left hand, she and her daughters; and thy younger sister, that dwelleth at thy right hand, is Sodom and her daughters. ^47Yet hast thou not walked in their ways, nor done after their abominations; but, as if that were a very little thing, thou wast more corrupt than they in all thy ways. ^48As I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, Sodom thy sister hath not done, she nor her daughters, as thou hast done, thou and thy daughters. ^49Behold, this was the iniquity of thy sister Sodom: pride, fulness of bread, and prosperous ease was in her and in her daughters; neither did she strengthen the hand of the poor and needy. ^50And they were haughty, and committed abomination before me: therefore I took them away as I saw good. ^51Neither hath Samaria committed half of thy sins; but thou hast multiplied thine abominations more than they, and hast justified thy sisters by all thine abominations which thou hast done. ^52Thou also, bear thou thine own shame, in that thou hast given judgment for thy sisters; through thy sins that thou hast committed more abominable than they, they are more righteous that thou: yea, be thou also confounded, and bear thy shame, in that thou hast justified thy sisters. ^53And I will turn again their captivity, the captivity of Sodom and her daughters, and the captivity of Samaria and her daughters, and the captivity of thy captives in the midst of them; ^54that thou mayest bear thine own shame, and mayest be ashamed because of all that thou hast done, in that thou art a comfort unto them. ^55And thy sisters, Sodom and her daughters, shall return to their former estate; and Samaria and her daughters shall return to their former estate; and thou and thy daughters shall return to your former estate. ^56For thy sister Sodom was not mentioned by thy mouth in the day of thy pride, ^57before thy wickedness was uncovered, as at the time of the reproach of the daughters of Syria, and of all that are round about her, the daughters of the Philistines, that do despite unto thee round about. ^58Thou hast borne thy lewdness and thine abominations, saith Jehovah. ^59For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will also deal with thee as thou hast done, who hast despised the oath in breaking the covenant. ^60Nevertheless I will remember my covenant with thee in the days of thy youth, and I will establish unto thee an everlasting covenant. ^61Then shalt thou remember thy ways, and be ashamed, when thou shalt receive thy sisters, thine elder sisters and thy younger; and I will give them unto thee for daughters, but not by thy covenant. ^62And I will establish my covenant with thee; and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah; ^63that thou mayest remember, and be confounded, and never open thy mouth any more, because of thy shame, when I have forgiven thee all that thou hast done, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 17

17

^1And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, put forth a riddle, and speak a parable unto the house of Israel; ^3and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: A great eagle with great wings and long pinions, full of feathers, which had divers colors, came unto Lebanon, and took the top of the cedar: ^4he cropped off the topmost of the young twigs thereof, and carried it unto a land of traffic; he set it in a city of merchants. ^5He took also of the seed of the land, and planted it in a fruitful soil; he placed it beside many waters; he set it as a willow-tree. ^6And it grew, and became a spreading vine of low stature, whose branches turned toward him, and the roots thereof were under him: so it became a vine, and brought forth branches, and shot forth sprigs. ^7There was also another great eagle with great wings and many feathers: and, behold, this vine did bend its roots toward him, and shot forth its branches toward him, from the beds of its plantation, that he might water it. ^8It was planted in a good soil by many waters, that it might bring forth branches, and that it might bear fruit, that it might be a goodly vine. ^9Say thou, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Shall it prosper? shall he not pull up the roots thereof, and cut off the fruit thereof, that it may wither; that all its fresh springing leaves may wither? and not by a strong arm or much people can it be raised from the roots thereof. ^10Yea, behold, being planted, shall it prosper? shall it not utterly wither, when the east wind toucheth it? it shall wither in the beds where it grew. ^11Moreover the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^12Say now to the rebellious house, Know ye not what these things mean? tell them, Behold, the king of Babylon came to Jerusalem, and took the king thereof, and the princes thereof, and brought them to him to Babylon: ^13and he took of the seed royal, and made a covenant with him; he also brought him under an oath, and took away the mighty of the land; ^14that the kingdom might be base, that it might not lift itself up, but that by keeping his covenant it might stand. ^15But he rebelled against him in sending his ambassadors into Egypt, that they might give him horses and much people. Shall he prosper? shall he escape that doeth such things? shall he break the covenant, and yet escape? ^16As I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, surely in the place where the king dwelleth that made him king, whose oath he despised, and whose covenant he brake, even with him in the midst of Babylon he shall die. ^17Neither shall Pharaoh with his mighty army and great company help him in the war, when they cast up mounds and build forts, to cut off many persons. ^18For he hath despised the oath by breaking the covenant; and behold, he had given his hand, and yet hath done all these things; he shall not escape. ^19Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: As I live, surely mine oath that he hath despised, and my covenant that he hath broken, I will even bring it upon his own head. ^20And I will spread my net upon him, and he shall be taken in my snare, and I will bring him to Babylon, and will enter into judgment with him there for his trespass that he hath trespassed against me. ^21And all his fugitives in all his bands shall fall by the sword, and they that remain shall be scattered toward every wind: and ye shall know that I, Jehovah, have spoken it. ^22Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will also take of the lofty top of the cedar, and will set it; I will crop off from the topmost of its young twigs a tender one, and I will plant it upon a high and lofty mountain: ^23in the mountain of the height of Israel will I plant it; and it shall bring forth boughs, and bear fruit, and be a goodly cedar: and under it shall dwell all birds of every wing; in the shade of the branches thereof shall they dwell. ^24And all the trees of the field shall know that I, Jehovah, have brought down the high tree, have exalted the low tree, have dried up the green tree, and have made the dry tree to flourish; I, Jehovah, have spoken and have done it.

Ezekiel 18

18

^1The word of Jehovah came unto me again, saying, ^2What mean ye, that ye use this proverb concerning the land of Israel, saying, The fathers have eaten sour grapes, and the children's teeth are set on edge? ^3As I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, ye shall not have occasion any more to use this proverb in Israel. ^4Behold, all souls are mine; as the soul of the father, so also the soul of the son is mine: the soul that sinneth, it shall die. ^5But if a man be just, and do that which is lawful and right, ^6and hath not eaten upon the mountains, neither hath lifted up his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel, neither hath defiled his neighbor's wife, neither hath come near to a woman in her impurity, ^7and hath not wronged any, but hath restored to the debtor his pledge, hath taken nought by robbery, hath given his bread to the hungry, and hath covered the naked with a garment; ^8he that hath not given forth upon interest, neither hath taken any increase, that hath withdrawn his hand from iniquity, hath executed true justice between man and man, ^9hath walked in my statutes, and hath kept mine ordinances, to deal truly; he is just, he shall surely live, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^10If he beget a son that is a robber, a shedder of blood, and that doeth any one of these things, ^11and that doeth not any of those duties, but even hath eaten upon the mountains, and defiled his neighbor's wife, ^12hath wronged the poor and needy, hath taken by robbery, hath not restored the pledge, and hath lifted up his eyes to the idols, hath committed abomination, ^13hath given forth upon interest, and hath taken increase; shall he then live? he shall not live: he hath done all these abominations; he shall surely die; his blood shall be upon him. ^14Now, lo, if he beget a son, that seeth all his father's sins, which he hath done, and feareth, and doeth not such like; ^15that hath not eaten upon the mountains, neither hath lifted up his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel, hath not defiled his neighbor's wife, ^16neither hath wronged any, hath not taken aught to pledge, neither hath taken by robbery, but hath given his bread to the hungry, and hath covered the naked with a garment; ^17that hath withdrawn his hand from the poor, that hath not received interest nor increase, hath executed mine ordinances, hath walked in my statutes; he shall not die for the iniquity of his father, he shall surely live. ^18As for his father, because he cruelly oppressed, robbed his brother, and did that which is not good among his people, behold, he shall die in his iniquity. ^19Yet say ye, Wherefore doth not the son bear the iniquity of the father? when the son hath done that which is lawful and right, and hath kept all my statutes, and hath done them, he shall surely live. ^20The soul that sinneth, it shall die: the son shall not bear the iniquity of the father, neither shall the father bear the iniquity of the son; the righteousness of the righteous shall be upon him, and the wickedness of the wicked shall be upon him. ^21But if the wicked turn from all his sins that he hath committed, and keep all my statutes, and do that which is lawful and right, he shall surely live, he shall not die. ^22None of his transgressions that he hath committed shall be remembered against him: in his righteousness that he hath done he shall live. ^23Have I any pleasure in the death of the wicked? saith the Lord Jehovah; and not rather that he should return from his way, and live? ^24But when the righteous turneth away from his righteousness, and committeth iniquity, and doeth according to all the abominations that the wicked man doeth, shall he live? None of his righteous deeds that he hath done shall be remembered: in his trespass that he hath trespassed, and in his sin that he hath sinned, in them shall he die. ^25Yet ye say, The way of the Lord is not equal. Hear now, O house of Israel: Is not my way equal? are not your ways unequal? ^26When the righteous man turneth away from his righteousness, and committeth iniquity, and dieth therein; in his iniquity that he hath done shall he die. ^27Again, when the wicked man turneth away from his wickedness that he hath committed, and doeth that which is lawful and right, he shall save his soul alive. ^28Because he considereth, and turneth away from all his transgressions that he hath committed, he shall surely live, he shall not die. ^29Yet saith the house of Israel, The way of the Lord is not equal. O house of Israel, are not my ways equal? are not your ways unequal? ^30Therefore I will judge you, O house of Israel, every one according to his ways, saith the Lord Jehovah. Return ye, and turn yourselves from all your transgressions; so iniquity shall not be your ruin. ^31Cast away from you all your transgressions, wherein ye have transgressed; and make you a new heart and a new spirit: for why will ye die, O house of Israel? ^32For I have no pleasure in the death of him that dieth, saith the Lord Jehovah: wherefore turn yourselves, and live.

Ezekiel 19

19

^1Moreover, take thou up a lamentation for the princes of Israel, ^2and say, What was thy mother? A lioness: she couched among lions, in the midst of the young lions she nourished her whelps. ^3And she brought up one of her whelps: he became a young lion, and he learned to catch the prey; he devoured men. ^4The nations also heard of him; he was taken in their pit; and they brought him with hooks unto the land of Egypt. ^5Now when she saw that she had waited, and her hope was lost, then she took another of her whelps, and made him a young lion. ^6And he went up and down among the lions; he became a young lion, and he learned to catch the prey; he devoured men. ^7And he knew their palaces, and laid waste their cities; and the land was desolate, and the fulness thereof, because of the noise of his roaring. ^8Then the nations set against him on every side from the provinces; and they spread their net over him; he was taken in their pit. ^9And they put him in a cage with hooks, and brought him to the king of Babylon; they brought him into strongholds, that his voice should no more be heard upon the mountains of Israel. ^10Thy mother was like a vine, in thy blood, planted by the waters: it was fruitful and full of branches by reason of many waters. ^11And it had strong rods for the sceptres of them that bare rule, and their stature was exalted among the thick boughs, and they were seen in their height with the multitude of their branches. ^12But it was plucked up in fury, it was cast down to the ground, and the east wind dried up its fruit: its strong rods were broken off and withered; the fire consumed them. ^13And now it is planted in the wilderness, in a dry and thirsty land. ^14And fire is gone out of the rods of its branches, it hath devoured its fruit, so that there is in it no strong rod to be a sceptre to rule. This is a lamentation, and shall be for a lamentation.

Ezekiel 21

21

^1And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, set thy face toward Jerusalem, and drop thy word toward the sanctuaries, and prophesy against the land of Israel; ^3and say to the land of Israel, Thus saith Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, and will draw forth my sword out of its sheath, and will cut off from thee the righteous and the wicked. ^4Seeing then that I will cut off from thee the righteous and the wicked, therefore shall my sword go forth out of its sheath against all flesh from the south to the north: ^5and all flesh shall know that I, Jehovah, have drawn forth my sword out of its sheath; it shall not return any more. ^6Sigh therefore, thou son of man; with the breaking of thy loins and with bitterness shalt thou sigh before their eyes. ^7And it shall be, when they say unto thee, Wherefore sighest thou? that thou shalt say, Because of the tidings, for it cometh; and every heart shall melt, and all hands shall be feeble, and every spirit shall faint, and all knees shall be weak as water: behold, it cometh, and it shall be done, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^8And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^9Son of man, prophesy, and say, Thus saith Jehovah: Say, A sword, a sword, it is sharpened, and also furbished; ^10it is sharpened that it may make a slaughter; it is furbished that it may be as lightning: shall we then make mirth? the rod of my son, it contemneth every tree. ^11And it is given to be furbished, that it may be handled: the sword, it is sharpened, yea, it is furbished, to give it into the hand of the slayer. ^12Cry and wail, son of man; for it is upon my people, it is upon all the princes of Israel: they are delivered over to the sword with my people; smite therefore upon thy thigh. ^13For there is a trial; and what if even the rod that contemneth shall be no more? saith the Lord Jehovah. ^14Thou therefore, son of man, prophesy, and smite thy hands together; and let the sword be doubled the third time, the sword of the deadly wounded: it is the sword of the great one that is deadly wounded, which entereth into their chambers. ^15I have set the threatening sword against all their gates, that their heart may melt, and their stumblings be multiplied: ah! it is made as lightning, it is pointed for slaughter. ^16Gather thee together, go to the right, set thyself in array, go to the left, whithersoever thy face is set. ^17I will also smite my hands together, and I will cause my wrath to rest: I, Jehovah, have spoken it. ^18The word of Jehovah came unto me again, saying, ^19Also, thou son of man, appoint thee two ways, that the sword of the king of Babylon may come; they twain shall come forth out of one land: and mark out a place, mark it out at the head of the way to the city. ^20Thou shalt appoint a way for the sword to come to Rabbah of the children of Ammon, and to Judah in Jerusalem the fortified. ^21For the king of Babylon stood at the parting of the way, at the head of the two ways, to use divination: he shook the arrows to and fro, he consulted the teraphim, he looked in the liver. ^22In his right hand was the divination for Jerusalem, to set battering rams, to open the mouth in the slaughter, to lift up the voice with shouting, to set battering rams against the gates, to cast up mounds, to build forts. ^23And it shall be unto them as a false divination in their sight, who have sworn oaths unto them; but he bringeth iniquity to remembrance, that they may be taken. ^24Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because ye have made your iniquity to be remembered, in that your transgressions are uncovered, so that in all your doings your sins do appear; because that ye are come to remembrance, ye shall be taken with the hand. ^25And thou, O deadly wounded wicked one, the prince of Israel, whose day is come, in the time of the iniquity of the end, ^26thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Remove the mitre, and take off the crown; this shall be no more the same; exalt that which is low, and abase that which is high. ^27I will overturn, overturn, overturn it: this also shall be no more, until he come whose right it is; and I will give it him. ^28And thou, son of man, prophesy, and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah concerning the children of Ammon, and concerning their reproach; and say thou, A sword, a sword is drawn, for the slaughter it is furbished, to cause it to devour, that it may be as lightning; ^29while they see for thee false visions, while they divine lies unto thee, to lay thee upon the necks of the wicked that are deadly wounded, whose day is come in the time of the iniquity of the end. ^30Cause it to return into its sheath. In the place where thou wast created, in the land of thy birth, will I judge thee. ^31And I will pour out mine indignation upon thee; I will blow upon thee with the fire of my wrath; and I will deliver thee into the hand of brutish men, skilful to destroy. ^32Thou shalt be for fuel to the fire; thy blood shall be in the midst of the land; thou shalt be no more remembered: for I, Jehovah, have spoken it.

Ezekiel 22

22

^1Moreover the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2And thou, son of man, wilt thou judge, wilt thou judge the bloody city? then cause her to know all her abominations. ^3And thou shalt say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: A city that sheddeth blood in the midst of her, that her time may come, and that maketh idols against herself to defile her! ^4Thou art become guilty in thy blood that thou hast shed, and art defiled in thine idols which thou hast made; and thou hast caused thy days to draw near, and art come even unto thy years: therefore have I made thee a reproach unto the nations, and a mocking to all the countries. ^5Those that are near, and those that are far from thee, shall mock thee, thou infamous one and full of tumult. ^6Behold, the princes of Israel, every one according to his power, have been in thee to shed blood. ^7In thee have they set light by father and mother; in the midst of thee have they dealt by oppression with the sojourner; in thee have they wronged the fatherless and the widow. ^8Thou hast despised my holy things, and hast profaned my sabbaths. ^9Slanderous men have been in thee to shed blood; and in thee they have eaten upon the mountains: in the midst of thee they have committed lewdness. ^10In thee have they uncovered their fathers' nakedness; in thee have they humbled her that was unclean in her impurity. ^11And one hath committed abomination with his neighbor's wife; and another hath lewdly defiled his daughter-in-law; and another in thee hath humbled his sister, his father's daughter. ^12In thee have they taken bribes to shed blood; thou hast taken interest and increase, and thou hast greedily gained of thy neighbors by oppression, and hast forgotten me, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^13Behold, therefore, I have smitten my hand at thy dishonest gain which thou hast made, and at thy blood which hath been in the midst of thee. ^14Can thy heart endure, or can thy hands be strong, in the days that I shall deal with thee? I, Jehovah, have spoken it, and will do it. ^15And I will scatter thee among the nations, and disperse thee through the countries; and I will consume thy filthiness out of thee. ^16And thou shalt be profaned in thyself, in the sight of the nations; and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah. ^17And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^18Son of man, the house of Israel is become dross unto me: all of them are brass and tin and iron and lead, in the midst of the furnace; they are the dross of silver. ^19Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because ye are all become dross, therefore, behold, I will gather you into the midst of Jerusalem. ^20As they gather silver and brass and iron and lead and tin into the midst of the furnace, to blow the fire upon it, to melt it; so will I gather you in mine anger and in my wrath, and I will lay you there, and melt you. ^21Yea, I will gather you, and blow upon you with the fire of my wrath, and ye shall be melted in the midst thereof. ^22As silver is melted in the midst of the furnace, so shall ye be melted in the midst thereof; and ye shall know that I, Jehovah, have poured out my wrath upon you. ^23And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^24Son of man, say unto her, Thou art a land that is not cleansed, nor rained upon in the day of indignation. ^25There is a conspiracy of her prophets in the midst thereof, like a roaring lion ravening the prey: they have devoured souls; they take treasure and precious things; they have made her widows many in the midst thereof. ^26Her priests have done violence to my law, and have profaned my holy things: they have made no distinction between the holy and the common, neither have they caused men to discern between the unclean and the clean, and have hid their eyes from my sabbaths, and I am profaned among them. ^27Her princes in the midst thereof are like wolves ravening the prey, to shed blood, and to destroy souls, that they may get dishonest gain. ^28And her prophets have daubed for them with untempered mortar, seeing false visions, and divining lies unto them, saying, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah, when Jehovah hath not spoken. ^29The people of the land have used oppression, and exercised robbery; yea, they have vexed the poor and needy, and have oppressed the sojourner wrongfully. ^30And I sought for a man among them, that should build up the wall, and stand in the gap before me for the land, that I should not destroy it; but I found none. ^31Therefore have I poured out mine indignation upon them; I have consumed them with the fire of my wrath: their own way have I brought upon their heads, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 23

23

^1The word of Jehovah came again unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, there were two women, the daughters of one mother: ^3and they played the harlot in Egypt; they played the harlot in their youth; there were their breasts pressed, and there was handled the bosom of their virginity. ^4And the names of them were Oholah the elder, and Oholibah her sister: and they became mine, and they bare sons and daughters. And as for their names, Samaria is Oholah, and Jerusalem Oholibah. ^5And Oholah played the harlot when she was mine; and she doted on her lovers, on the Assyrians her neighbors, ^6who were clothed with blue, governors and rulers, all of them desirable young men, horsemen riding upon horses. ^7And she bestowed her whoredoms upon them, the choicest men of Assyria all of them; and on whomsoever she doted, with all their idols she defiled herself. ^8Neither hath she left her whoredoms since the days of Egypt; for in her youth they lay with her, and they handled the bosom of her virginity; and they poured out their whoredom upon her. ^9Wherefore I delivered her into the hand of her lovers, into the hand of the Assyrians, upon whom she doted. ^10These uncovered her nakedness; they took her sons and her daughters; and her they slew with the sword: and she became a byword among women; for they executed judgments upon her. ^11And her sister Oholibah saw this, yet was she more corrupt in her doting than she, and in her whoredoms which were more than the whoredoms of her sister. ^12She doted upon the Assyrians, governors and rulers, her neighbors, clothed most gorgeously, horsemen riding upon horses, all of them desirable young men. ^13And I saw that she was defiled; they both took one way. ^14And she increased her whoredoms; for she saw men portrayed upon the wall, the images of the Chaldeans portrayed with vermilion, ^15girded with girdles upon their loins, with flowing turbans upon their heads, all of them princes to look upon, after the likeness of the Babylonians in Chaldea, the land of their nativity. ^16And as soon as she saw them she doted upon them, and sent messengers unto them into Chaldea. ^17And the Babylonians came to her into the bed of love, and they defiled her with their whoredom, and she was polluted with them, and her soul was alienated from them. ^18So she uncovered her whoredoms, and uncovered her nakedness: then my soul was alienated from her, like as my soul was alienated from her sister. ^19Yet she multiplied her whoredoms, remembering the days of her youth, wherein she had played the harlot in the land of Egypt. ^20And she doted upon their paramours, whose flesh is as the flesh of asses, and whose issue is like the issue of horses. ^21Thus thou calledst to remembrance the lewdness of thy youth, in the handling of thy bosom by the Egyptians for the breasts of thy youth. ^22Therefore, O Oholibah, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will raise up thy lovers against thee, from whom thy soul is alienated, and I will bring them against thee on every side: ^23the Babylonians and all the Chaldeans, Pekod and Shoa and Koa, and all the Assyrians with them; desirable young men, governors and rulers all of them, princes and men of renown, all of them riding upon horses. ^24And they shall come against thee with weapons, chariots, and wagons, and with a company of peoples; they shall set themselves against thee with buckler and shield and helmet round about; and I will commit the judgment unto them, and they shall judge thee according to their judgments. ^25And I will set my jealousy against thee, and they shall deal with thee in fury; they shall take away thy nose and thine ears; and thy residue shall fall by the sword: they shall take thy sons and thy daughters; and thy residue shall be devoured by the fire. ^26They shall also strip thee of thy clothes, and take away thy fair jewels. ^27Thus will I make thy lewdness to cease from thee, and thy whoredom brought from the land of Egypt; so that thou shalt not lift up thine eyes unto them, nor remember Egypt any more. ^28For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will deliver thee into the hand of them whom thou hatest, into the hand of them from whom thy soul is alienated; ^29and they shall deal with thee in hatred, and shall take away all thy labor, and shall leave thee naked and bare; and the nakedness of thy whoredoms shall be uncovered, both thy lewdness and thy whoredoms. ^30These things shall be done unto thee, for that thou hast played the harlot after the nations, and because thou art polluted with their idols. ^31Thou hast walked in the way of thy sister; therefore will I give her cup into thy hand. ^32Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Thou shalt drink of thy sister's cup, which is deep and large; thou shalt be laughed to scorn and had in derision; it containeth much. ^33Thou shalt be filled with drunkenness and sorrow, with the cup of astonishment and desolation, with the cup of thy sister Samaria. ^34Thou shalt even drink it and drain it out, and thou shalt gnaw the sherds thereof, and shalt tear thy breasts; for I have spoken it, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^35Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because thou hast forgotten me, and cast me behind thy back, therefore bear thou also thy lewdness and thy whoredoms. ^36Jehovah said moreover unto me: Son of man, wilt thou judge Oholah and Oholibah? then declare unto them their abominations. ^37For they have committed adultery, and blood is in their hands; and with their idols have they committed adultery; and they have also caused their sons, whom they bare unto me, to pass through the fire unto them to be devoured. ^38Moreover this they have done unto me: they have defiled my sanctuary in the same day, and have profaned my sabbaths. ^39For when they had slain their children to their idols, then they came the same day into my sanctuary to profane it; and, lo, thus have they done in the midst of my house. ^40And furthermore ye have sent for men that come from far, unto whom a messenger was sent, and, lo, they came; for whom thou didst wash thyself, paint thine eyes, and deck thyself with ornaments, ^41and sit upon a stately bed, with a table prepared before it, whereupon thou didst set mine incense and mine oil. ^42And the voice of a multitude being at ease was with her: and with men of the common sort were brought drunkards from the wilderness; and they put bracelets upon the hands of them twain, and beautiful crowns upon their heads. ^43Then said I of her that was old in adulteries, Now will they play the harlot with her, and she with them. ^44And they went in unto her, as they go in unto a harlot: so went they in unto Oholah and unto Oholibah, the lewd women. ^45And righteous men, they shall judge them with the judgment of adulteresses, and with the judgment of women that shed blood; because they are adulteresses, and blood is in their hands. ^46For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will bring up a company against them, and will give them to be tossed to and fro and robbed. ^47And the company shall stone them with stones, and despatch them with their swords; they shall slay their sons and their daughters, and burn up their houses with fire. ^48Thus will I cause lewdness to cease out of the land, that all women may be taught not to do after your lewdness. ^49And they shall recompense your lewdness upon you, and ye shall bear the sins of your idols; and ye shall know that I am the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 24

24

^1Again, in the ninth year, in the tenth month, in the tenth day of the month, the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, write thee the name of the day, even of this selfsame day: the king of Babylon drew close unto Jerusalem this selfsame day. ^3And utter a parable unto the rebellious house, and say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah, Set on the caldron, set it on, and also pour water into it: ^4gather the pieces thereof into it, even every good piece, the thigh, and the shoulder; fill it with the choice bones. ^5Take the choice of the flock, and also a pile of wood for the bones under the caldron; make it boil well; yea, let the bones thereof be boiled in the midst of it. ^6Wherefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Woe to the bloody city, to the caldron whose rust is therein, and whose rust is not gone out of it! take out of it piece after piece; No lot is fallen upon it. ^7For her blood is in the midst of her; she set it upon the bare rock; she poured it not upon the ground, to cover it with dust. ^8That it may cause wrath to come up to take vengeance, I have set her blood upon the bare rock, that it should not be covered. ^9Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Woe to the bloody city! I also will make the pile great. ^10Heap on the wood, make the fire hot, boil well the flesh, and make thick the broth, and let the bones be burned. ^11Then set it empty upon the coals thereof, that it may be hot, and the brass thereof may burn, and that the filthiness of it may be molten in it, that the rust of it may be consumed. ^12She hath wearied herself with toil; yet her great rust goeth not forth out of her; her rust goeth not forth by fire. ^13In thy filthiness is lewdness: because I have cleansed thee and thou wast not cleansed, thou shalt not be cleansed from thy filthiness any more, till I have caused my wrath toward thee to rest. ^14I, Jehovah, have spoken it: it shall come to pass, and I will do it: I will not go back, neither will I spare, neither will I repent; according to thy ways, and according to thy doings, shall they judge thee, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^15Also the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^16Son of man, behold, I take away from thee the desire of thine eyes with a stroke: yet thou shalt neither mourn nor weep, neither shall thy tears run down. ^17Sigh, but not aloud, make no mourning for the dead; bind thy headtire upon thee, and put thy shoes upon thy feet, and cover not thy lips, and eat not the bread of men. ^18So I spake unto the people in the morning; and at even my wife died; and I did in the morning as I was commanded. ^19And the people said unto me, Wilt thou not tell us what these things are to us, that thou doest so? ^20Then I said unto them, The word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^21Speak unto the house of Israel, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will profane my sanctuary, the pride of your power, the desire of your eyes, and that which your soul pitieth; and your sons and your daughters whom ye have left behind shall fall by the sword. ^22And ye shall do as I have done: ye shall not cover your lips, nor eat the bread of men. ^23And your tires shall be upon your heads, and your shoes upon your feet: ye shall not mourn nor weep; but ye shall pine away in your iniquities, and moan one toward another. ^24Thus shall Ezekiel be unto you a sign; according to all that he hath done shall ye do: when this cometh, then shall ye know that I am the Lord Jehovah. ^25And thou, son of man, shall it not be in the day when I take from them their strength, the joy of their glory, the desire of their eyes, and that whereupon they set their heart, their sons and their daughters, ^26that in that day he that escapeth shall come unto thee, to cause thee to hear it with thine ears? ^27In that day shall thy mouth be opened to him that is escaped, and thou shalt speak, and be no more dumb: so shalt thou be a sign unto them; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 25

25

^1And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, set thy face toward the children of Ammon, and prophesy against them: ^3and say unto the children of Ammon, Hear the word of the Lord Jehovah: Thus saith the Lord Jehovah, Because thou saidst, Aha, against my sanctuary, when it was profaned; and against the land of Israel, when it was made desolate; and against the house of Judah, when they went into captivity: ^4therefore, behold, I will deliver thee to the children of the east for a possession, and they shall set their encampments in thee, and make their dwellings in thee; they shall eat thy fruit, and they shall drink thy milk. ^5And I will make Rabbah a stable for camels, and the children of Ammon a couching-place for flocks: and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^6For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because thou hast clapped thy hands, and stamped with the feet, and rejoiced with all the despite of thy soul against the land of Israel; ^7therefore, behold, I have stretched out my hand upon thee, and will deliver thee for a spoil to the nations; and I will cut thee off from the peoples, and I will cause thee to perish out of the countries: I will destroy thee; and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah. ^8Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because that Moab and Seir do say, Behold, the house of Judah is like unto all the nations; ^9therefore, behold, I will open the side of Moab from the cities, from his cities which are on his frontiers, the glory of the country, Beth-jeshimoth, Baal-meon, and Kiriathaim, ^10unto the children of the east, to go against the children of Ammon; and I will give them for a possession, that the children of Ammon may not be remembered among the nations. ^11and I will execute judgments upon Moab; and they shall know that I am Jehovah. ^12Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because that Edom hath dealt against the house of Judah by taking vengeance, and hath greatly offended, and revenged himself upon them; ^13therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah, I will stretch out my hand upon Edom, and will cut off man and beast from it; and I will make it desolate from Teman; even unto Dedan shall they fall by the sword. ^14And I will lay my vengeance upon Edom by the hand of my people Israel; and they shall do in Edom according to mine anger and according to my wrath; and they shall know my vengeance, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^15Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because the Philistines have dealt by revenge, and have taken vengeance with despite of soul to destroy with perpetual enmity; ^16therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah, Behold, I will stretch out my hand upon the Philistines, and I will cut off the Cherethites, and destroy the remnant of the sea coast. ^17And I will execute great vengeance upon them with wrathful rebukes; and they shall know that I am Jehovah, when I shall lay my vengeance upon them.

Ezekiel 26

26

^1And it came to pass in the eleventh year, in the first day of the month, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, because that Tyre hath said against Jerusalem, Aha, she is broken that was the gate of the peoples; she is turned unto me; I shall be replenished, now that she is laid waste: ^3therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah, Behold, I am against thee, O Tyre, and will cause many nations to come up against thee, as the sea causeth its waves to come up. ^4And they shall destroy the walls of Tyre, and break down her towers: I will also scrape her dust from her, and make her a bare rock. ^5She shall be a place for the spreading of nets in the midst of the sea; for I have spoken it, saith the Lord Jehovah; and she shall become a spoil to the nations. ^6And her daughters that are in the field shall be slain with the sword: and they shall know that I am Jehovah. ^7For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will bring upon Tyre Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, king of kings, from the north, with horses, and with chariots, and with horsemen, and a company, and much people. ^8He shall slay with the sword thy daughters in the field; and he shall make forts against thee, and cast up a mound against thee, and raise up the buckler against thee. ^9And he shall set his battering engines against thy walls, and with his axes he shall break down thy towers. ^10By reason of the abundance of his horses their dust shall cover thee: thy walls shall shake at the noise of the horsemen, and of the wagons, and of the chariots, when he shall enter into thy gates, as men enter into a city wherein is made a breach. ^11With the hoofs of his horses shall he tread down all thy streets; he shall slay thy people with the sword; and the pillars of thy strength shall go down to the ground. ^12And they shall make a spoil of thy riches, and make a prey of thy merchandise; and they shall break down thy walls, and destroy thy pleasant houses; and they shall lay thy stones and thy timber and thy dust in the midst of the waters. ^13And I will cause the noise of thy songs to cease; and the sound of thy harps shall be no more heard. ^14And I will make thee a bare rock; thou shalt be a place for the spreading of nets; thou shalt be built no more: for I Jehovah have spoken it, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^15Thus saith the Lord Jehovah to Tyre: shall not the isles shake at the sound of thy fall, when the wounded groan, when the slaughter is made in the midst of thee? ^16Then all the princes of the sea shall come down from their thrones, and lay aside their robes, and strip off their broidered garments: they shall clothe themselves with trembling; they shall sit upon the ground, and shall tremble every moment, and be astonished at thee. ^17And they shall take up a lamentation over thee, and say to thee, How art thou destroyed, that wast inhabited by seafaring men, the renowned city, that was strong in the sea, she and her inhabitants, that caused their terror to be on all that dwelt there! ^18Now shall the isles tremble in the day of thy fall; yea, the isles that are in the sea shall be dismayed at thy departure. ^19For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: When I shall make thee a desolate city, like the cities that are not inhabited; when I shall bring up the deep upon thee, and the great waters shall cover thee; ^20then will I bring thee down with them that descend into the pit, to the people of old time, and will make thee to dwell in the nether parts of the earth, in the places that are desolate of old, with them that go down to the pit, that thou be not inhabited; and I will set glory in the land of the living: ^21I will make thee a terror, and thou shalt no more have any being; though thou be sought for, yet shalt thou never be found again, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 27

27

^1The word of Jehovah came again unto me, saying, ^2And thou, son of man, take up a lamentation over Tyre; ^3and say unto Tyre, O thou that dwellest at the entry of the sea, that art the merchant of the peoples unto many isles, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Thou, O Tyre, hast said, I am perfect in beauty. ^4Thy borders are in the heart of the seas; thy builders have perfected thy beauty. ^5They have made all thy planks of fir-trees from Senir; they have taken a cedar from Lebanon to make a mast for thee. ^6Of the oaks of Bashan have they made thine oars; they have made thy benches of ivory inlaid in boxwood, from the isles of Kittim. ^7Of fine linen with broidered work from Egypt was thy sail, that it might be to thee for an ensign; blue and purple from the isles of Elishah was thine awning. ^8The inhabitants of Sidon and Arvad were thy rowers: thy wise men, O Tyre, were in thee, they were thy pilots. ^9The old men of Gebal and the wise men thereof were in thee thy calkers: all the ships of the sea with their mariners were in thee to deal in thy merchandise. ^10Persia and Lud and Put were in thine army, thy men of war: they hanged the shield and helmet in thee; they set forth thy comeliness. ^11The men of Arvad with thine army were upon thy walls round about, and valorous men were in thy towers; they hanged their shields upon thy walls round about; they have perfected thy beauty. ^12Tarshish was thy merchant by reason of the multitude of all kinds of riches; with silver, iron, tin, and lead, they traded for thy wares. ^13Javan, Tubal, and Meshech, they were thy traffickers; they traded the persons of men and vessels of brass for thy merchandise. ^14They of the house of Togarmah traded for thy wares with horses and war-horses and mules. ^15The men of Dedan were thy traffickers; many isles were the mart of thy hand: they brought thee in exchange horns of ivory and ebony. ^16Syria was thy merchant by reason of the multitude of thy handiworks: they traded for thy wares with emeralds, purple, and broidered work, and fine linen, and coral, and rubies. ^17Judah, and the land of Israel, they were thy traffickers: they traded for thy merchandise wheat of Minnith, and pannag, and honey, and oil, and balm. ^18Damascus was thy merchant for the multitude of thy handiworks, by reason of the multitude of all kinds of riches, with the wine of Helbon, and white wool. ^19Vedan and Javan traded with yarn for thy wares: bright iron, cassia, and calamus, were among thy merchandise. ^20Dedan was thy trafficker in precious cloths for riding. ^21Arabia, and all the princes of Kedar, they were the merchants of thy hand; in lambs, and rams, and goats, in these were they thy merchants. ^22The traffickers of Sheba and Raamah, they were thy traffickers; they traded for thy wares with the chief of all spices, and with all precious stones, and gold. ^23Haran and Canneh and Eden, the traffickers of Sheba, Asshur and Chilmad, were thy traffickers. ^24These were thy traffickers in choice wares, in wrappings of blue and broidered work, and in chests of rich apparel, bound with cords and made of cedar, among thy merchandise. ^25The ships of Tarshish were thy caravans for thy merchandise: and thou wast replenished, and made very glorious in the heart of the seas. ^26Thy rowers have brought thee into great waters: the east wind hath broken thee in the heart of the seas. ^27Thy riches, and thy wares, thy merchandise, thy mariners, and thy pilots, thy calkers, and the dealers in thy merchandise, and all thy men of war, that are in thee, with all thy company which is in the midst of thee, shall fall into the heart of the seas in the day of thy ruin. ^28At the sound of the cry of thy pilots the suburbs shall shake. ^29And all that handled the oar, the mariners, and all the pilots of the sea, shall come down from their ships; they shall stand upon the land, ^30and shall cause their voice to be heard over thee, and shall cry bitterly, and shall cast up dust upon their heads, they shall wallow themselves in the ashes: ^31and they shall make themselves bald for thee, and gird them with sackcloth, and they shall weep for thee in bitterness of soul with bitter mourning. ^32And in their wailing they shall take up a lamentation for thee, and lament over thee, saying, Who is there like Tyre, like her that is brought to silence in the midst of the sea? ^33When thy wares went forth out of the seas, thou filledst many peoples; thou didst enrich the kings of the earth with the multitude of thy riches and of thy merchandise. ^34In the time that thou wast broken by the seas in the depths of the waters, thy merchandise and all thy company did fall in the midst of thee. ^35All the inhabitants of the isles are astonished at thee, and their kings are horribly afraid; they are troubled in their countenance. ^36The merchants among the peoples hiss at thee; thou art become a terror, and thou shalt nevermore have any being.

Ezekiel 28

28

^1The word of Jehovah came again unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, say unto the prince of Tyre, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because thy heart is lifted up, and thou hast said, I am a god, I sit in the seat of God, in the midst of the seas; yet thou art man, and not God, though thou didst set thy heart as the heart of God;- ^3behold, thou art wiser than Daniel; there is no secret that is hidden from thee; ^4by thy wisdom and by thine understanding thou hast gotten thee riches, and hast gotten gold and silver into thy treasures; ^5by thy great wisdom and by thy traffic hast thou increased thy riches, and thy heart is lifted up because of thy riches;- ^6therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because thou hast set thy heart as the heart of God, ^7therefore, behold, I will bring strangers upon thee, the terrible of the nations; and they shall draw their swords against the beauty of thy wisdom, and they shall defile thy brightness. ^8They shall bring thee down to the pit; and thou shalt die the death of them that are slain, in the heart of the seas. ^9Wilt thou yet say before him that slayeth thee, I am God? but thou art man, and not God, in the hand of him that woundeth thee. ^10Thou shalt die the death of the uncircumcised by the hand of strangers: for I have spoken it, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^11Moreover the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^12Son of man, take up a lamentation over the king of Tyre, and say unto him, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Thou sealest up the sum, full of wisdom, and perfect in beauty. ^13Thou wast in Eden, the garden of God; every precious stone was thy covering, the sardius, the topaz, and the diamond, the beryl, the onyx, and the jasper, the sapphire, the emerald, and the carbuncle, and gold: the workmanship of thy tabrets and of thy pipes was in thee; in the day that thou wast created they were prepared. ^14Thou wast the anointed cherub that covereth: and I set thee, so that thou wast upon the holy mountain of God; thou hast walked up and down in the midst of the stones of fire. ^15Thou wast perfect in thy ways from the day that thou wast created, till unrighteousness was found in thee. ^16By the abundance of thy traffic they filled the midst of thee with violence, and thou hast sinned: therefore have I cast thee as profane out of the mountain of God; and I have destroyed thee, O covering cherub, from the midst of the stones of fire. ^17Thy heart was lifted up because of thy beauty; thou hast corrupted thy wisdom by reason of thy brightness: I have cast thee to the ground; I have laid thee before kings, that they may behold thee. ^18By the multitude of thine iniquities, in the unrighteousness of thy traffic, thou hast profaned thy sanctuaries; therefore have I brought forth a fire from the midst of thee; it hath devoured thee, and I have turned thee to ashes upon the earth in the sight of all them that behold thee. ^19All they that know thee among the peoples shall be astonished at thee: thou art become a terror, and thou shalt nevermore have any being. ^20And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^21Son of man, set thy face toward Sidon, and prophesy against it, ^22and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, O Sidon; and I will be glorified in the midst of thee; and they shall know that I am Jehovah, when I shall have executed judgments in her, and shall be sanctified in her. ^23For I will send pestilence into her, and blood into her streets; and the wounded shall fall in the midst of her, with the sword upon her on every side; and they shall know that I am Jehovah. ^24And there shall be no more a pricking brier unto the house of Israel, nor a hurting thorn of any that are round about them, that did despite unto them; and they shall know that I am the Lord Jehovah. ^25Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: When I shall have gathered the house of Israel from the peoples among whom they are scattered, and shall be sanctified in them in the sight of the nations, then shall they dwell in their own land which I gave to my servant Jacob. ^26And they shall dwell securely therein; yea, they shall build houses, and plant vineyards, and shall dwell securely, when I have executed judgments upon all those that do them despite round about them; and they shall know that I am Jehovah their God.

Ezekiel 29

29

^1In the tenth year, in the tenth month, in the twelfth day of the month, the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, set thy face against Pharaoh king of Egypt, and prophesy against him, and against all Egypt; ^3speak, and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, Pharaoh king of Egypt, the great monster that lieth in the midst of his rivers, that hath said, My river is mine own, and I have made it for myself. ^4And I will put hooks in thy jaws, and I will cause the fish of thy rivers to stick unto thy scales; and I will bring thee up out of the midst of thy rivers, with all the fish of thy rivers which stick unto thy scales. ^5And I will cast thee forth into the wilderness, thee and all the fish of thy rivers: thou shalt fall upon the open field; thou shalt not be brought together, nor gathered; I have given thee for food to the beasts of the earth and to the birds of the heavens. ^6And all the inhabitants of Egypt shall know that I am Jehovah, because they have been a staff of reed to the house of Israel. ^7When they took hold of thee by thy hand, thou didst break, and didst rend all their shoulders; and when they leaned upon thee, thou brakest, and madest all their loins to be at a stand. ^8Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will bring a sword upon thee, and will cut off from thee man and beast. ^9And the land of Egypt shall be a desolation and a waste; and they shall know that I am Jehovah. Because he hath said, The river is mine, and I have made it; ^10therefore, behold, I am against thee, and against thy rivers, and I will make the land of Egypt an utter waste and desolation, from the tower of Seveneh even unto the border of Ethiopia. ^11No foot of man shall pass through it, nor foot of beast shall pass through it, neither shall it be inhabited forty years. ^12And I will make the land of Egypt a desolation in the midst of the countries that are desolate; and her cities among the cities that are laid waste shall be a desolation forty years; and I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations, and will disperse them through the countries. ^13For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: At the end of forty years will I gather the Egyptians from the peoples whither they were scattered; ^14and I will bring back the captivity of Egypt, and will cause them to return into the land of Pathros, into the land of their birth; and they shall be there a base kingdom. ^15It shall be the basest of the kingdoms; neither shall it any more lift itself up above the nations: and I will diminish them, that they shall no more rule over the nations. ^16And it shall be no more the confidence of the house of Israel, bringing iniquity to remembrance, when they turn to look after them: and they shall know that I am the Lord Jehovah. ^17And it came to pass in the seven and twentieth year, in the first month, in the first day of the month, the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^18Son of man, Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon caused his army to serve a great service against Tyre: every head was made bald, and every shoulder was worn; yet had he no wages, nor his army, from Tyre, for the service that he had served against it. ^19Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will give the land of Egypt unto Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon; and he shall carry off her multitude, and take her spoil, and take her prey; and it shall be the wages for his army. ^20I have given him the land of Egypt as his recompense for which he served, because they wrought for me, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^21In that day will I cause a horn to bud forth unto the house of Israel, and I will give thee the opening of the mouth in the midst of them; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 30

30

^1The word of Jehovah came again unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, prophesy, and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Wail ye, Alas for the day! ^3For the day is near, even the day of Jehovah is near; it shall be a day of clouds, a time of the nations. ^4And a sword shall come upon Egypt, and anguish shall be in Ethiopia, when the slain shall fall in Egypt; and they shall take away her multitude, and her foundations shall be broken down. ^5Ethiopia, and Put, and Lud, and all the mingled people, and Cub, and the children of the land that is in league, shall fall with them by the sword. ^6Thus saith Jehovah: They also that uphold Egypt shall fall; and the pride of her power shall come down: from the tower of Seveneh shall they fall in it by the sword, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^7And they shall be desolate in the midst of the countries that are desolate; and her cities shall be in the midst of the cities that are wasted. ^8And they shall know at I am Jehovah, when I have set a fire in Egypt, and all her helpers are destroyed. ^9In that day shall messengers go forth from before me in ships to make the careless Ethiopians afraid; and there shall be anguish upon them, as in the day of Egypt; for, lo, it cometh. ^10Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will also make the multitude of Egypt to cease, by the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon. ^11He and his people with him, the terrible of the nations, shall be brought in to destroy the land; and they shall draw their swords against Egypt, and fill the land with the slain. ^12And I will make the rivers dry, and will sell the land into the hand of evil men; and I will make the land desolate, and all that is therein, by the hand of strangers: I, Jehovah, have spoken it. ^13Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will also destroy the idols, and I will cause the images to cease from Memphis; and there shall be no more a prince from the land of Egypt: and I will put a fear in the land of Egypt. ^14And I will make Pathros desolate, and will set a fire in Zoan, and will execute judgments upon No. ^15And I will pour my wrath upon Sin, the stronghold of Egypt; and I will cut off the multitude of No. ^16And I will set a fire in Egypt: Sin shall be in great anguish, and No shall be broken up; and Memphis shall have adversaries in the day-time. ^17The young men of Aven and of Pibeseth shall fall by the sword; and these cities shall go into captivity. ^18At Tehaphnehes also the day shall withdraw itself, when I shall break there the yokes of Egypt, and the pride of her power shall cease in her: as for her, a cloud shall cover her, and her daughters shall go into captivity. ^19Thus will I execute judgments upon Egypt; and they shall know that I am Jehovah. ^20And it came to pass in the eleventh year, in the first month, in the seventh day of the month, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^21Son of man, I have broken the arm of Pharaoh king of Egypt; and, lo, it hath not been bound up, to apply healing medicines, to put a bandage to bind it, that it be strong to hold the sword. ^22Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against Pharaoh king of Egypt, and will break his arms, the strong arm, and that which was broken; and I will cause the sword to fall out of his hand. ^23And I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations, and will disperse them through the countries. ^24And I will strengthen the arms of the king of Babylon, and put my sword in his hand: but I will break the arms of Pharaoh, and he shall groan before him with the groanings of a deadly wounded man. ^25And I will hold up the arms of the king of Babylon; and the arms of Pharaoh shall fall down; and they shall know that I am Jehovah, when I shall put my sword into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shall stretch it out upon the land of Egypt. ^26And I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations, and disperse them through the countries; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 31

31

^1And it came to pass in the eleventh year, in the third month, in the first day of the month, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, say unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, and to his multitude: Whom art thou like in thy greatness? ^3Behold, the Assyrian was a cedar in Lebanon with fair branches, and with a forest-like shade, and of high stature; and its top was among the thick boughs. ^4The waters nourished it, the deep made it to grow: the rivers thereof ran round about its plantation; and it sent out its channels unto all the trees of the field. ^5Therefore its stature was exalted above all the trees of the field; and its boughs were multiplied, and its branches became long by reason of many waters, when it shot them forth. ^6All the birds of the heavens made their nests in its boughs; and under its branches did all the beasts of the field bring forth their young; and under its shadow dwelt all great nations. ^7Thus was it fair in its greatness, in the length of its branches; for its root was by many waters. ^8The cedars in the garden of God could not hide it; the fir-trees were not like its boughs, and the plane-trees were not as its branches; nor was any tree in the garden of God like unto it in its beauty. ^9I made it fair by the multitude of its branches, so that all the trees of Eden, that were in the garden of God, envied it. ^10Therefore thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because thou art exalted in stature, and he hath set his top among the thick boughs, and his heart is lifted up in his height; ^11I will even deliver him into the hand of the mighty one of the nations; he shall surely deal with him; I have driven him out for his wickedness. ^12And strangers, the terrible of the nations, have cut him off, and have left him: upon the mountains and in all the valleys his branches are fallen, and his boughs are broken by all the watercourses of the land; and all the peoples of the earth are gone down from his shadow, and have left him. ^13Upon his ruin all the birds of the heavens shall dwell, and all the beasts of the field shall be upon his branches; ^14to the end that none of all the trees by the waters exalt themselves in their stature, neither set their top among the thick boughs, nor that their mighty ones stand up on their height, even all that drink water: for they are all delivered unto death, to the nether parts of the earth, in the midst of the children of men, with them that go down to the pit. ^15Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: In the day when he went down to Sheol I caused a mourning: I covered the deep for him, and I restrained the rivers thereof; and the great waters were stayed; and I caused Lebanon to mourn for him, and all the trees of the field fainted for him. ^16I made the nations to shake at the sound of his fall, when I cast him down to Sheol with them that descend into the pit; and all the trees of Eden, the choice and best of Lebanon, all that drink water, were comforted in the nether parts of the earth. ^17They also went down into Sheol with him unto them that are slain by the sword; yea, they that were his arm, that dwelt under his shadow in the midst of the nations. ^18To whom art thou thus like in glory and in greatness among the trees of Eden? yet shalt thou be brought down with the trees of Eden unto the nether parts of the earth: thou shalt lie in the midst of the uncircumcised, with them that are slain by the sword. This is Pharaoh and all his multitude, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 32

32

^1And it came to pass in the twelfth year, in the twelfth month, in the first day of the month, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, take up a lamentation over Pharaoh king of Egypt, and say unto him, Thou wast likened unto a young lion of the nations: yet art thou as a monster in the seas; and thou didst break forth with thy rivers, and troubledst the waters with thy feet, and fouledst their rivers. ^3Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I will spread out my net upon thee with a company of many peoples; and they shall bring thee up in my net. ^4And I will leave thee upon the land, I will cast thee forth upon the open field, and will cause all the birds of the heavens to settle upon thee, and I will satisfy the beasts of the whole earth with thee. ^5And I will lay thy flesh upon the mountains, and fill the valleys with thy height. ^6I will also water with thy blood the land wherein thou swimmest, even to the mountains; and the watercourses shall be full of thee. ^7And when I shall extinguish thee, I will cover the heavens, and make the stars thereof dark; I will cover the sun with a cloud, and the moon shall not give its light. ^8All the bright lights of heaven will I make dark over thee, and set darkness upon thy land, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^9I will also vex the hearts of many peoples, when I shall bring thy destruction among the nations, into the countries which thou hast not known. ^10Yea, I will make many peoples amazed at thee, and their kings shall be horribly afraid for thee, when I shall brandish my sword before them; and they shall tremble at every moment, every man for his own life, in the day of thy fall. ^11For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: The sword of the king of Babylon shall come upon thee. ^12By the swords of the mighty will I cause thy multitude to fall; the terrible of the nations are they all: and they shall bring to nought the pride of Egypt, and all the multitude thereof shall be destroyed. ^13I will destroy also all the beasts thereof from beside many waters; neither shall the foot of man trouble them any more, nor the hoofs of beasts trouble them. ^14Then will I make their waters clear, and cause their rivers to run like oil, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^15When I shall make the land of Egypt desolate and waste, a land destitute of that whereof it was full, when I shall smite all them that dwell therein, then shall they know that I am Jehovah. ^16This is the lamentation wherewith they shall lament; the daughters of the nations shall lament therewith; over Egypt, and over all her multitude, shall they lament therewith, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^17It came to pass also in the twelfth year, in the fifteenth day of the month, that the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^18Son of man, wail for the multitude of Egypt, and cast them down, even her, and the daughters of the famous nations, unto the nether parts of the earth, with them that go down into the pit. ^19Whom dost thou pass in beauty? go down, and be thou laid with the uncircumcised. ^20They shall fall in the midst of them that are slain by the sword: she is delivered to the sword; draw her away and all her multitudes. ^21The strong among the mighty shall speak to him out of the midst of Sheol with them that help him: they are gone down, they lie still, even the uncircumcised, slain by the sword. ^22Asshur is there and all her company; her graves are round about her; all of them slain, fallen by the sword; ^23whose graves are set in the uttermost parts of the pit, and her company is round about her grave; all of them slain, fallen by the sword, who caused terror in the land of the living. ^24There is Elam and all her multitude round about her grave; all of them slain, fallen by the sword, who are gone down uncircumcised into the nether parts of the earth, who caused their terror in the land of the living, and have borne their shame with them that go down to the pit. ^25They have set her a bed in the midst of the slain with all her multitude; her graves are round about her; all of them uncircumcised, slain by the sword; for their terror was caused in the land of the living, and they have borne their shame with them that go down to the pit: he is put in the midst of them that are slain. ^26There is Meshech, Tubal, and all their multitude; their graves are round about them; all of them uncircumcised, slain by the sword; for they caused their terror in the land of the living. ^27And they shall not lie with the mighty that are fallen of the uncircumcised, that are gone down to Sheol with their weapons of war, and have laid their swords under their heads, and their iniquities are upon their bones; for they were the terror of the mighty in the land of the living. ^28But thou shalt be broken in the midst of the uncircumcised, and shalt lie with them that are slain by the sword. ^29There is Edom, her kings and all her princes, who in their might are laid with them that are slain by the sword: they shall lie with the uncircumcised, and with them that go down to the pit. ^30There are the princes of the north, all of them, and all the Sidonians, who are gone down with the slain; in the terror which they caused by their might they are put to shame; and they lie uncircumcised with them that are slain by the sword, and bear their shame with them that go down to the pit. ^31Pharaoh shall see them, and shall be comforted over all his multitude, even Pharaoh and all his army, slain by the sword, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^32For I have put his terror in the land of the living; and he shall be laid in the midst of the uncircumcised, with them that are slain by the sword, even Pharaoh and all his multitude, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 33

33

^1And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, speak to the children of thy people, and say unto them, When I bring the sword upon a land, and the people of the land take a man from among them, and set him for their watchman; ^3if, when he seeth the sword come upon the land, he blow the trumpet, and warn the people; ^4then whosoever heareth the sound of the trumpet, and taketh not warning, if the sword come, and take him away, his blood shall be upon his own head. ^5He heard the sound of the trumpet, and took not warning; his blood shall be upon him; whereas if he had taken warning, he would have delivered his soul. ^6But if the watchman see the sword come, and blow not the trumpet, and the people be not warned, and the sword come, and take any person from among them; he is taken away in his iniquity, but his blood will I require at the watchman's hand. ^7So thou, son of man, I have set thee a watchman unto the house of Israel; therefore hear the word at my mouth, and give them warning from me. ^8When I say unto the wicked, O wicked man, thou shalt surely die, and thou dost not speak to warn the wicked from his way; that wicked man shall die in his iniquity, but his blood will I require at thy hand. ^9Nevertheless, if thou warn the wicked of his way to turn from it, and he turn not from his way; he shall die in his iniquity, but thou hast delivered thy soul. ^10And thou, son of man, say unto the house of Israel: Thus ye speak, saying, Our transgressions and our sins are upon us, and we pine away in them; how then can we live? ^11Say unto them, As I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, I have no pleasure in the death of the wicked; but that the wicked turn from his way and live: turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways; for why will ye die, O house of Israel? ^12And thou, son of man, say unto the children of thy people, The righteousness of the righteous shall not deliver him in the day of his transgression; and as for the wickedness of the wicked, he shall not fall thereby in the day that he turneth from his wickedness; neither shall he that is righteous be able to live thereby in the day that he sinneth. ^13When I say to the righteous, that he shall surely live; if he trust to his righteousness, and commit iniquity, none of his righteous deeds shall be remembered; but in his iniquity that he hath committed, therein shall he die. ^14Again, when I say unto the wicked, Thou shalt surely die; if he turn from his sin, and do that which is lawful and right; ^15if the wicked restore the pledge, give again that which he had taken by robbery, walk in the statutes of life, committing no iniquity; he shall surely live, he shall not die. ^16None of his sins that he hath committed shall be remembered against him: he hath done that which is lawful and right; he shall surely live. ^17Yet the children of thy people say, The way of the Lord is not equal: but as for them, their way is not equal. ^18When the righteous turneth from his righteousness, and committeth iniquity, he shall even die therein. ^19And when the wicked turneth from his wickedness, and doeth that which is lawful and right, he shall live thereby. ^20Yet ye say, The way of the Lord is not equal. O house of Israel, I will judge you every one after his ways. ^21And it came to pass in the twelfth year of our captivity, in the tenth month, in the fifth day of the month, that one that had escaped out of Jerusalem came unto me, saying, The city is smitten. ^22Now the hand of Jehovah had been upon me in the evening, before he that was escaped came; and he had opened my mouth, until he came to me in the morning; and my mouth was opened, and I was no more dumb. ^23And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^24Son of man, they that inhabit those waste places in the land of Israel speak, saying, Abraham was one, and he inherited the land: but we are many; the land is given us for inheritance. ^25Wherefore say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Ye eat with the blood, and lift up your eyes unto your idols, and shed blood: and shall ye possess the land? ^26Ye stand upon your sword, ye work abomination, and ye defile every one his neighbor's wife: and shall ye possess the land? ^27Thus shalt thou say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: As I live, surely they that are in the waste places shall fall by the sword; and him that is in the open field will I give to the beasts to be devoured; and they that are in the strongholds and in the caves shall die of the pestilence. ^28And I will make the land a desolation and an astonishment; and the pride of her power shall cease; and the mountains of Israel shall be desolate, so that none shall pass through. ^29Then shall they know that I am Jehovah, when I have made the land a desolation and an astonishment, because of all their abominations which they have committed. ^30And as for thee, son of man, the children of thy people talk of thee by the walls and in the doors of the houses, and speak one to another, every one to his brother, saying, Come, I pray you, and hear what is the word that cometh forth from Jehovah. ^31And they come unto thee as the people cometh, and they sit before thee as my people, and they hear thy words, but do them not; for with their mouth they show much love, but their heart goeth after their gain. ^32And, lo, thou art unto them as a very lovely song of one that hath a pleasant voice, and can play well on an instrument; for they hear thy words, but they do them not. ^33And when this cometh to pass, (behold, it cometh,) then shall they know that a prophet hath been among them.

Ezekiel 34

34

^1And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, prophesy against the shepherds of Israel, prophesy, and say unto them, even to the shepherds, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Woe unto the shepherds of Israel that do feed themselves! should not the shepherds feed the sheep? ^3Ye eat the fat, and ye clothe you with the wool, ye kill the fatlings; but ye feed not the sheep. ^4The diseased have ye not strengthened, neither have ye healed that which was sick, neither have ye bound up that which was broken, neither have ye brought back that which was driven away, neither have ye sought that which was lost; but with force and with rigor have ye ruled over them. ^5And they were scattered, because there was no shepherd; and they became food to all the beasts of the field, and were scattered. ^6My sheep wandered through all the mountains, and upon every high hill: yea, my sheep were scattered upon all the face of the earth; and there was none that did search or seek after them. ^7Therefore, ye shepherds, hear the word of Jehovah: ^8As I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, surely forasmuch as my sheep became a prey, and my sheep became food to all the beasts of the field, because there was no shepherd, neither did my shepherds search for my sheep, but the shepherds fed themselves, and fed not my sheep; ^9therefore, ye shepherds, hear the word of Jehovah: ^10Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against the shepherds; and I will require my sheep at their hand, and cause them to cease from feeding the sheep; neither shall the shepherds feed themselves any more; and I will deliver my sheep from their mouth, that they may not be food for them. ^11For thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I myself, even I, will search for my sheep, and will seek them out. ^12As a shepherd seeketh out his flock in the day that he is among his sheep that are scattered abroad, so will I seek out my sheep; and I will deliver them out of all places whither they have been scattered in the cloudy and dark day. ^13And I will bring them out from the peoples, and gather them from the countries, and will bring them into their own land; and I will feed them upon the mountains of Israel, by the watercourses, and in all the inhabited places of the country. ^14I will feed them with good pasture; and upon the mountains of the height of Israel shall their fold be: there shall they lie down in a good fold; and on fat pasture shall they feed upon the mountains of Israel. ^15I myself will be the shepherd of my sheep, and I will cause them to lie down, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^16I will seek that which was lost, and will bring back that which was driven away, and will bind up that which was broken, and will strengthen that which was sick: but the fat and the strong I will destroy; I will feed them in justice. ^17And as for you, O my flock, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I judge between sheep and sheep, the rams and the he-goats. ^18Seemeth it a small thing unto you to have fed upon the good pasture, but ye must tread down with your feet the residue of your pasture? and to have drunk of the clear waters, but ye must foul the residue with your feet? ^19And as for my sheep, they eat that which ye have trodden with your feet, and they drink that which ye have fouled with your feet. ^20Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah unto them: Behold, I, even I, will judge between the fat sheep and the lean sheep. ^21Because ye thrust with side and with shoulder, and push all the diseased with your horns, till ye have scattered them abroad; ^22therefore will I save my flock, and they shall no more be a prey; and I will judge between sheep and sheep. ^23And I will set up one shepherd over them, and he shall feed them, even my servant David; he shall feed them, and he shall be their shepherd. ^24And I, Jehovah, will be their God, and my servant David prince among them; I, Jehovah, have spoken it. ^25And I will make with them a covenant of peace, and will cause evil beasts to cease out of the land; and they shall dwell securely in the wilderness, and sleep in the woods. ^26And I will make them and the places round about my hill a blessing; and I will cause the shower to come down in its season; there shall be showers of blessing. ^27And the tree of the field shall yield its fruit, and the earth shall yield its increase, and they shall be secure in their land; and they shall know that I am Jehovah, when I have broken the bars of their yoke, and have delivered them out of the hand of those that made bondmen of them. ^28And they shall no more be a prey to the nations, neither shall the beasts of the earth devour them; but they shall dwell securely, and none shall make them afraid. ^29And I will raise up unto them a plantation for renown, and they shall be no more consumed with famine in the land, neither bear the shame of the nations any more. ^30And they shall know that I, Jehovah, their God am with them, and that they, the house of Israel, are my people, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^31And ye my sheep, the sheep of my pasture, are men, and I am your God, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 35

35

^1Moreover the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, set thy face against mount Seir, and prophesy against it, ^3and say unto it, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, O mount Seir, and I will stretch out my hand against thee, and I will make thee a desolation and an astonishment. ^4I will lay thy cities waste, and thou shalt be desolate; and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah. ^5Because thou hast had a perpetual enmity, and hast given over the children of Israel to the power of the sword in the time of their calamity, in the time of the iniquity of the end; ^6therefore, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, I will prepare thee unto blood, and blood shall pursue thee: since thou hast not hated blood, therefore blood shall pursue thee. ^7Thus will I make mount Seir an astonishment and a desolation; and I will cut off from it him that passeth through and him that returneth. ^8And I will fill its mountains with its slain: in thy hills and in thy valleys and in all thy watercourses shall they fall that are slain with the sword. ^9I will make thee a perpetual desolation, and thy cities shall not be inhabited; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^10Because thou hast said, These two nations and these two countries shall be mine, and we will possess it; whereas Jehovah was there: ^11therefore, as I live, saith the Lord Jehovah, I will do according to thine anger, and according to thine envy which thou hast showed out of thy hatred against them; and I will make myself known among them, when I shall judge thee. ^12And thou shalt know that I, Jehovah, have heard all thy revilings which thou hast spoken against the mountains of Israel, saying, They are laid desolate, they are given us to devour. ^13And ye have magnified yourselves against me with your mouth, and have multiplied your words against me: I have heard it. ^14Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: When the whole earth rejoiceth, I will make thee desolate. ^15As thou didst rejoice over the inheritance of the house of Israel, because it was desolate, so will I do unto thee: thou shalt be desolate, O mount Seir, and all Edom, even all of it; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 36

36

^1And thou, son of man, prophesy unto the mountains of Israel, and say, Ye mountains of Israel, hear the word of Jehovah. ^2Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because the enemy hath said against you, Aha! and, The ancient high places are ours in possession; ^3therefore prophesy, and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because, even because they have made you desolate, and swallowed you up on every side, that ye might be a possession unto the residue of the nations, and ye are taken up in the lips of talkers, and the evil report of the people; ^4therefore, ye mountains of Israel, hear the word of the Lord Jehovah: Thus saith the Lord Jehovah to the mountains and to the hills, to the watercourses and to the valleys, to the desolate wastes and to the cities that are forsaken, which are become a prey and derision to the residue of the nations that are round about; ^5therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Surely in the fire of my jealousy have I spoken against the residue of the nations, and against all Edom, that have appointed my land unto themselves for a possession with the joy of all their heart, with despite of soul, to cast it out for a prey. ^6Therefore prophesy concerning the land of Israel, and say unto the mountains and to the hills, to the watercourses and to the valleys, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I have spoken in my jealousy and in my wrath, because ye have borne the shame of the nations: ^7therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I have sworn, saying, Surely the nations that are round about you, they shall bear their shame. ^8But ye, O mountains of Israel, ye shall shoot forth your branches, and yield your fruit to my people Israel; for they are at hand to come. ^9For, behold, I am for you, and I will turn into you, and ye shall be tilled and sown; ^10and I will multiply men upon you, all the house of Israel, even all of it; and the cities shall be inhabited, and the waste places shall be builded; ^11and I will multiply upon you man and beast; and they shall increase and be fruitful; and I will cause you to be inhabited after your former estate, and will do better unto you than at your beginnings: and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^12Yea, I will cause men to walk upon you, even my people Israel; and they shall possess thee, and thou shalt be their inheritance, and thou shalt no more henceforth bereave them of children. ^13Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Because they say unto you, Thou land art a devourer of men, and hast been a bereaver of thy nation; ^14therefore thou shalt devour men no more, neither bereave thy nation any more, saith the Lord Jehovah; ^15neither will I let thee hear any more the shame of the nations, neither shalt thou bear the reproach of the peoples any more, neither shalt thou cause thy nation to stumble any more, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^16Moreover the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^17Son of man, when the house of Israel dwelt in their own land, they defiled it by their way and by their doings: their way before me was as the uncleanness of a woman in her impurity. ^18Wherefore I poured out my wrath upon them for the blood which they had poured out upon the land, and because they had defiled it with their idols; ^19and I scattered them among the nations, and they were dispersed through the countries: according to their way and according to their doings I judged them. ^20And when they came unto the nations, whither they went, they profaned my holy name; in that men said of them, These are the people of Jehovah, and are gone forth out of his land. ^21But I had regard for my holy name, which the house of Israel had profaned among the nations, whither they went. ^22Therefore say unto the house of Israel, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: I do not this for your sake, O house of Israel, but for my holy name, which ye have profaned among the nations, whither ye went. ^23And I will sanctify my great name, which hath been profaned among the nations, which ye have profaned in the midst of them; and the nations shall know that I am Jehovah, saith the Lord Jehovah, when I shall be sanctified in you before their eyes. ^24For I will take you from among the nations, and gather you out of all the countries, and will bring you into your own land. ^25And I will sprinkle clean water upon you, and ye shall be clean: from all your filthiness, and from all your idols, will I cleanse you. ^26A new heart also will I give you, and a new spirit will I put within you; and I will take away the stony heart out of your flesh, and I will give you a heart of flesh. ^27And I will put my Spirit within you, and cause you to walk in my statutes, and ye shall keep mine ordinances, and do them. ^28And ye shall dwell in the land that I gave to your fathers; and ye shall be my people, and I will be your God. ^29And I will save you from all your uncleannesses: and I will call for the grain, and will multiply it, and lay no famine upon you. ^30And I will multiply the fruit of the tree, and the increase of the field, that ye may receive no more the reproach of famine among the nations. ^31Then shall ye remember your evil ways, and your doings that were not good; and ye shall loathe yourselves in your own sight for your iniquities and for your abominations. ^32Nor for your sake do I this, saith the Lord Jehovah, be it known unto you: be ashamed and confounded for your ways, O house of Israel. ^33Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: In the day that I cleanse you from all your iniquities, I will cause the cities to be inhabited, and the waste places shall be builded. ^34And the land that was desolate shall be tilled, whereas it was a desolation in the sight of all that passed by. ^35And they shall say, This land that was desolate is become like the garden of Eden; and the waste and desolate and ruined cities are fortified and inhabited. ^36Then the nations that are left round about you shall know that I, Jehovah, have builded the ruined places, and planted that which was desolate: I, Jehovah, have spoken it, and I will do it. ^37Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: For this, moreover, will I be inquired of by the house of Israel, to do it for them: I will increase them with men like a flock. ^38As the flock for sacrifice, as the flock of Jerusalem in her appointed feasts, so shall the waste cities be filled with flocks of men; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 37

37

^1The hand of Jehovah was upon me, and he brought me out in the Spirit of Jehovah, and set me down in the midst of the valley; and it was full of bones. ^2And he caused me to pass by them round about: and, behold, there were very many in the open valley; and, lo, they were very dry. ^3And he said unto me, Son of man, can these bones live? And I answered, O Lord Jehovah, thou knowest. ^4Again he said unto me, Prophesy over these bones, and say unto them, O ye dry bones, hear the word of Jehovah. ^5Thus saith the Lord Jehovah unto these bones: Behold, I will cause breath to enter into you, and ye shall live. ^6And I will lay sinews upon you, and will bring up flesh upon you, and cover you with skin, and put breath in you, and ye shall live; and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^7So I prophesied as I was commanded: and as I prophesied, there was a noise, and, behold, an earthquake; and the bones came together, bone to its bone. ^8And I beheld, and, lo, there were sinews upon them, and flesh came up, and skin covered them above; but there was no breath in them. ^9Then said he unto me, Prophesy unto the wind, prophesy, son of man, and say to the wind, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Come from the four winds, O breath, and breathe upon these slain, that they may live. ^10So I prophesied as he commanded me, and the breath came into them, and they lived, and stood up upon their feet, an exceeding great army. ^11Then he said unto me, Son of man, these bones are the whole house of Israel: behold, they say, Our bones are dried up, and our hope is lost; we are clean cut off. ^12Therefore prophesy, and say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will open your graves, and cause you to come up out of your graves, O my people; and I will bring you into the land of Israel. ^13And ye shall know that I am Jehovah, when I have opened your graves, and caused you to come up out of your graves, O my people. ^14And I will put my Spirit in you, and ye shall live, and I will place you in your own land: and ye shall know that I, Jehovah, have spoken it and performed it, saith Jehovah. ^15The word of Jehovah came again unto me, saying, ^16And thou, son of man, take thee one stick, and write upon it, For Judah, and for the children of Israel his companions: then take another stick, and write upon it, For Joseph, the stick of Ephraim, and for all the house of Israel his companions: ^17and join them for thee one to another into one stick, that they may become one in thy hand. ^18And when the children of thy people shall speak unto thee, saying, Wilt thou not show us what thou meanest by these? ^19say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will take the stick of Joseph, which is in the hand of Ephraim, and the tribes of Israel his companions; and I will put them with it, even with the stick of Judah, and make them one stick, and they shall be one in my hand. ^20And the sticks whereon thou writest shall be in thy hand before their eyes. ^21And say unto them, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I will take the children of Israel from among the nations, whither they are gone, and will gather them on every side, and bring them into their own land: ^22and I will make them one nation in the land, upon the mountains of Israel; and one king shall be king to them all; and they shall be no more two nations, neither shall they be divided into two kingdoms any more at all; ^23neither shall they defile themselves any more with their idols, nor with their detestable things, nor with any of their transgressions; but I will save them out of all their dwelling-places, wherein they have sinned, and will cleanse them: so shall they be my people, and I will be their God. ^24And my servant David shall be king over them; and they all shall have one shepherd: they shall also walk in mine ordinances, and observe my statutes, and do them. ^25And they shall dwell in the land that I have given unto Jacob my servant, wherein your fathers dwelt; and they shall dwell therein, they, and their children, and their children's children, for ever: and David my servant shall be their prince for ever. ^26Moreover I will make a covenant of peace with them; it shall be an everlasting covenant with them; and I will place them, and multiply them, and will set my sanctuary in the midst of them for evermore. ^27My tabernacle also shall be with them; and I will be their God, and they shall be my people. ^28And the nations shall know that I am Jehovah that sanctifieth Israel, when my sanctuary shall be in the midst of them for evermore.

Ezekiel 38

38

^1And the word of Jehovah came unto me, saying, ^2Son of man, set thy face toward Gog, of the land of Magog, the prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal, and prophesy against him, ^3and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, O Gog, prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal: ^4and I will turn thee about, and put hooks into thy jaws, and I will bring thee forth, and all thine army, horses and horsemen, all of them clothed in full armor, a great company with buckler and shield, all of them handling swords; ^5Persia, Cush, and Put with them, all of them with shield and helmet; ^6Gomer, and all his hordes; the house of Togarmah in the uttermost parts of the north, and all his hordes; even many peoples with thee. ^7Be thou prepared, yea, prepare thyself, thou, and all thy companies that are assembled unto thee, and be thou a guard unto them. ^8After many days thou shalt be visited: in the latter years thou shalt come into the land that is brought back from the sword, that is gathered out of many peoples, upon the mountains of Israel, which have been a continual waste; but it is brought forth out of the peoples, and they shall dwell securely, all of them. ^9And thou shalt ascend, thou shalt come like a storm, thou shalt be like a cloud to cover the land, thou, and all thy hordes, and many peoples with thee. ^10Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: It shall come to pass in that day, that things shall come into thy mind, and thou shalt devise an evil device: ^11and thou shalt say, I will go up to the land of unwalled villages; I will go to them that are at rest, that dwell securely, all of them dwelling without walls, and having neither bars nor gates; ^12to take the spoil and to take the prey; to turn thy hand against the waste places that are now inhabited, and against the people that are gathered out of the nations, that have gotten cattle and goods, that dwell in the middle of the earth. ^13Sheba, and Dedan, and the merchants of Tarshish, with all the young lions thereof, shall say unto thee, Art thou come to take the spoil? hast thou assembled thy company to take the prey? to carry away silver and gold, to take away cattle and goods, to take great spoil? ^14Therefore, son of man, prophesy, and say unto Gog, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: In that day when my people Israel dwelleth securely, shalt thou not know it? ^15And thou shalt come from thy place out of the uttermost parts of the north, thou, and many peoples with thee, all of them riding upon horses, a great company and a mighty army; ^16and thou shalt come up against my people Israel, as a cloud to cover the land: it shall come to pass in the latter days, that I will bring thee against my land, that the nations may know me, when I shall be sanctified in thee, O Gog, before their eyes. ^17Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Art thou he of whom I spake in old time by my servants the prophets of Israel, that prophesied in those days for many years that I would bring thee against them? ^18And it shall come to pass in that day, when Gog shall come against the land of Israel, saith the Lord Jehovah, that my wrath shall come up into my nostrils. ^19For in my jealousy and in the fire of my wrath have I spoken, Surely in that day there shall be a great shaking in the land of Israel; ^20so that the fishes of the sea, and the birds of the heavens, and the beasts of the field, and all creeping things that creep upon the earth, and all the men that are upon the face of the earth, shall shake at my presence, and the mountains shall be thrown down, and the steep places shall fall, and every wall shall fall to the ground. ^21And I will call for a sword against him unto all my mountains, saith the Lord Jehovah: every man's sword shall be against his brother. ^22And with pestilence and with blood will I enter into judgment with him; and I will rain upon him, and upon his hordes, and upon the many peoples that are with him, an overflowing shower, and great hailstones, fire, and brimstone. ^23And I will magnify myself, and sanctify myself, and I will make myself known in the eyes of many nations; and they shall know that I am Jehovah.

Ezekiel 39

39

^1And thou, son of man, prophesy against Gog, and say, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Behold, I am against thee, O Gog, prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal: ^2and I will turn thee about, and will lead thee on, and will cause thee to come up from the uttermost parts of the north; and I will bring thee upon the mountains of Israel; ^3and I will smite thy bow out of thy left hand, and will cause thine arrows to fall out of thy right hand. ^4Thou shalt fall upon the mountains of Israel, thou, and all thy hordes, and the peoples that are with thee: I will give thee unto the ravenous birds of every sort, and to the beasts of the field to be devoured. ^5Thou shalt fall upon the open field; for I have spoken it, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^6And I will send a fire on Magog, and on them that dwell securely in the isles; and they shall know that I am Jehovah. ^7And my holy name will I make known in the midst of my people Israel; neither will I suffer my holy name to be profaned any more: and the nations shall know that I am Jehovah, the Holy One in Israel. ^8Behold, it cometh, and it shall be done, saith the Lord Jehovah; this is the day whereof I have spoken. ^9And they that dwell in the cities of Israel shall go forth, and shall make fires of the weapons and burn them, both the shields and the bucklers, the bows and the arrows, and the handstaves, and the spears, and they shall make fires of them seven years; ^10so that they shall take no wood out of the field, neither cut down any out of the forests; for they shall make fires of the weapons; and they shall plunder those that plundered them, and rob those that robbed them, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^11And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will give unto Gog a place for burial in Israel, the valley of them that pass through on the east of the sea; and it shall stop them that pass through: and there shall they bury Gog and all his multitude; and they shall call it The valley of Hamon-gog. ^12And seven months shall the house of Israel be burying them, that they may cleanse the land. ^13Yea, all the people of the land shall bury them; and it shall be to them a renown in the day that I shall be glorified, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^14And they shall set apart men of continual employment, that shall pass through the land, and, with them that pass through, those that bury them that remain upon the face of the land, to cleanse it: after the end of seven months shall they search. ^15And they that pass through the land shall pass through; and when any seeth a man's bone, then shall he set up a sign by it, till the buriers have buried it in the valley of Hamon-gog. ^16And Hamonah shall also be the name of a city. Thus shall they cleanse the land. ^17And thou, son of man, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Speak unto the birds of every sort, and to every beast of the field, Assemble yourselves, and come; gather yourselves on every side to my sacrifice that I do sacrifice for you, even a great sacrifice upon the mountains of Israel, that ye may eat flesh and drink blood. ^18Ye shall eat the flesh of the mighty, and drink the blood of the princes of the earth, of rams, of lambs, and of goats, of bullocks, all of them fatlings of Bashan. ^19And ye shall eat fat till ye be full, and drink blood till ye be drunken, of my sacrifice which I have sacrificed for you. ^20And ye shall be filled at my table with horses and chariots, with mighty men, and with all men of war, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^21And I will set my glory among the nations; and all the nations shall see my judgment that I have executed, and my hand that I have laid upon them. ^22So the house of Israel shall know that I am Jehovah their God, from that day and forward. ^23And the nations shall know that the house of Israel went into captivity for their iniquity; because they trespassed against me, and I hid my face from them: so I gave them into the hand of their adversaries, and they fell all of them by the sword. ^24According to their uncleanness and according to their transgressions did I unto them; and I hid my face from them. ^25Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Now will I bring back the captivity of Jacob, and have mercy upon the whole house of Israel; and I will be jealous for my holy name. ^26And they shall bear their shame, and all their trespasses whereby they have trespassed against me, when they shall dwell securely in their land, and none shall make them afraid; ^27when I have brought them back from the peoples, and gathered them out of their enemies' lands, and am sanctified in them in the sight of many nations. ^28And they shall know that I am Jehovah their God, in that I caused them to go into captivity among the nations, and have gathered them unto their own land; and I will leave none of them any more there; ^29neither will I hide my face any more from them; for I have poured out my Spirit upon the house of Israel, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 41

41

^1And he brought me to the temple, and measured the posts, six cubits broad on the one side, and six cubits broad on the other side, which was the breadth of the tabernacle. ^2And the breadth of the entrance was ten cubits; and the sides of the entrance were five cubits on the one side, and five cubits on the other side: and he measured the length thereof, forty cubits, and the breadth, twenty cubits. ^3Then went he inward, and measured each post of the entrance, two cubits; and the entrance, six cubits; and the breadth of the entrance, seven cubits. ^4And he measured the length thereof, twenty cubits, and the breadth, twenty cubits, before the temple: and he said unto me, This is the most holy place. ^5Then he measured the wall of the house, six cubits; and the breadth of every side-chamber, four cubits, round about the house on every side. ^6And the side-chambers were in three stories, one over another, and thirty in order; and they entered into the wall which belonged to the house for the side-chambers round about, that they might have hold therein, and not have hold in the wall of the house. ^7And the side-chambers were broader as they encompassed the house higher and higher; for the encompassing of the house went higher and higher round about the house: therefore the breadth of the house continued upward; and so one went up from the lowest chamber to the highest by the middle chamber. ^8I saw also that the house had a raised basement round about: the foundations of the side-chambers were a full reed of six great cubits. ^9The thickness of the wall, which was for the side-chambers, on the outside, was five cubits: and that which was left was the place of the side-chambers that belonged to the house. ^10And between the chambers was a breadth of twenty cubits round about the house on every side. ^11And the doors of the side-chambers were toward the place that was left, one door toward the north, and another door toward the south: and the breadth of the place that was left was five cubits round about. ^12And the building that was before the separate place at the side toward the west was seventy cubits broad; and the wall of the building was five cubits thick round about, and the length thereof ninety cubits. ^13So he measured the house, a hundred cubits long; and the separate place, and the building, with the walls thereof, a hundred cubits long; ^14also the breadth of the face of the house, and of the separate place toward the east, a hundred cubits. ^15And he measured the length of the building before the separate place which was at the back thereof, and the galleries thereof on the one side and on the other side, a hundred cubits; and the inner temple, and the porches of the court; ^16the thresholds, and the closed windows, and the galleries round about on their three stories, over against the threshold, ceiled with wood round about, and from the ground up to the windows, (now the windows were covered), ^17to the space above the door, even unto the inner house, and without, and by all the wall round about within and without, by measure. ^18And it was made with cherubim and palm-trees; and a palm-tree was between cherub and cherub, and every cherub had two faces; ^19so that there was the face of a man toward the palm-tree on the one side, and the face of a young lion toward the palm-tree on the other side. thus was it made through all the house round about: ^20from the ground unto above the door were cherubim and palm-trees made: thus was the wall of the temple. ^21As for the temple, the door-posts were squared; and as for the face of the sanctuary, the appearance thereof was as the appearance of the temple. ^22The altar was of wood, three cubits high, and the length thereof two cubits; and the corners thereof, and the length thereof, and the walls thereof, were of wood: and he said unto me, This is the table that is before Jehovah. ^23And the temple and the sanctuary had two doors. ^24And the doors had two leaves apiece, two turning leaves: two leaves for the one door, and two leaves for the other. ^25And there were made on them, on the doors of the temple, cherubim and palm-trees, like as were made upon the walls; and there was a threshold of wood upon the face of the porch without. ^26And there were closed windows and palm-trees on the one side and on the other side, on the sides of the porch: thus were the side-chambers of the house, and the thresholds.

Ezekiel 42

42

^1Then he brought me forth into the outer court, the way toward the north: and he brought me into the chamber that was over against the separate place, and which was over against the building toward the north. ^2Before the length of a hundred cubits was the north door, and the breadth was fifty cubits. ^3Over against the twenty cubits which belonged to the inner court, and over against the pavement which belonged to the outer court, was gallery against gallery in the third story. ^4And before the chambers was a walk of ten cubits' breadth inward, a way of one cubit; and their doors were toward the north. ^5Now the upper chambers were shorter; for the galleries took away from these, more than from the lower and the middlemost, in the building. ^6For they were in three stories, and they had not pillars as the pillars of the courts: therefore the uppermost was straitened more than the lowest and the middlemost from the ground. ^7And the wall that was without by the side of the chambers, toward the outer court before the chambers, the length thereof was fifty cubits. ^8For the length of the chambers that were in the outer court was fifty cubits: and, lo, before the temple were a hundred cubits. ^9And from under these chambers was the entry on the east side, as one goeth into them from the outer court. ^10In the thickness of the wall of the court toward the east, before the separate place, and before the building, there were chambers. ^11And the way before them was like the appearance of the way of the chambers which were toward the north; according to their length so was their breadth: and all their egresses were both according to their fashions, and according to their doors. ^12And according to the doors of the chambers that were toward the south was a door at the head of the way, even the way directly before the wall toward the east, as one entereth into them. ^13Then said he unto me, The north chambers and the south chambers, which are before the separate place, they are the holy chambers, where the priests that are near unto Jehovah shall eat the most holy things: there shall they lay the most holy things, and the meal-offering, and the sin-offering, and the trespass-offering; for the place is holy. ^14When the priests enter in, then shall they not go out of the holy place into the outer court, but there they shall lay their garments wherein they minister; for they are holy: and they shall put on other garments, and shall approach to that which pertaineth to the people. ^15Now when he had made an end of measuring the inner house, he brought me forth by the way of the gate whose prospect is toward the east, and measured it round about. ^16He measured on the east side with the measuring reed five hundred reeds, with the measuring reed round about. ^17He measured on the north side five hundred reeds with the measuring reed round about. ^18He measured on the south side five hundred reeds with the measuring reed. ^19He turned about to the west side, and measured five hundred reeds with the measuring reed. ^20He measured it on the four sides: it had a wall round about, the length five hundred, and the breadth five hundred, to make a separation between that which was holy and that which was common.

Ezekiel 43

43

^1Afterward he brought me to the gate, even the gate that looketh toward the east. ^2And, behold, the glory of the God of Israel came from the way of the east: and his voice was like the sound of many waters; and the earth shined with his glory. ^3And it was according to the appearance of the vision which I saw, even according to the vision that I saw when I came to destroy the city; and the visions were like the vision that I saw by the river Chebar; and I fell upon my face. ^4And the glory of Jehovah came into the house by the way of the gate whose prospect is toward the east. ^5And the Spirit took me up, and brought me into the inner court; and, behold, the glory of Jehovah filled the house. ^6And I heard one speaking unto me out of the house; and a man stood by me. ^7And he said unto me, Son of man, this is the place of my throne, and the place of the soles of my feet, where I will dwell in the midst of the children of Israel for ever. And the house of Israel shall no more defile my holy name, neither they, nor their kings, by their whoredom, and by the dead bodies of their kings in their high places; ^8in their setting of their threshold by my threshold, and their door-post beside my door-post, and there was but the wall between me and them; and they have defiled my holy name by their abominations which they have committed: wherefore I have consumed them in mine anger. ^9Now let them put away their whoredom, and the dead bodies of their kings, far from me; and I will dwell in the midst of them for ever. ^10Thou, son of man, show the house to the house of Israel, that they may be ashamed of their iniquities; and let them measure the pattern. ^11And if they be ashamed of all that they have done, make known unto them the form of the house, and the fashion thereof, and the egresses thereof, and the entrances thereof, and all the forms thereof, and all the ordinances thereof, and all the forms thereof, and all the laws thereof; and write it in their sight; that they may keep the whole form thereof, and all the ordinances thereof, and do them. ^12This is the law of the house: upon the top of the mountain the whole limit thereof round about shall be most holy. Behold, this is the law of the house. ^13And these are the measures of the altar by cubits (the cubit is a cubit and a handbreadth): the bottom shall be a cubit, and the breadth a cubit, and the border thereof by the edge thereof round about a span; and this shall be the base of the altar. ^14And from the bottom upon the ground to the lower ledge shall be two cubits, and the breadth one cubit; and from the lesser ledge to the greater ledge shall be four cubits, and the breadth a cubit. ^15And the upper altar shall be four cubits; and from the altar hearth and upward there shall be four horns. ^16And the altar hearth shall be twelve cubits long by twelve broad, square in the four sides thereof. ^17And the ledge shall be fourteen cubits long by fourteen broad in the four sides thereof; and the border about it shall be half a cubit; and the bottom thereof shall be a cubit round about; and the steps thereof shall look toward the east. ^18And he said unto me, Son of man, thus saith the Lord Jehovah: These are the ordinances of the altar in the day when they shall make it, to offer burnt-offerings thereon, and to sprinkle blood thereon. ^19Thou shalt give to the priests the Levites that are of the seed of Zadok, who are near unto me, to minister unto me, saith the Lord Jehovah, a young bullock for a sin-offering. ^20And thou shalt take of the blood thereof, and put it on the four horns of it, and on the four corners of the ledge, and upon the border round about: thus shalt thou cleanse it and make atonement for it. ^21Thou shalt also take the bullock of the sin-offering, and it shall be burnt in the appointed place of the house, without the sanctuary. ^22And on the second day thou shalt offer a he-goat without blemish for a sin-offering; and they shall cleanse the altar, as they did cleanse it with the bullock. ^23When thou hast made an end of cleansing it, thou shalt offer a young bullock without blemish, and a ram out of the flock without blemish. ^24And thou shalt bring them near before Jehovah, and the priests shall cast salt upon them, and they shall offer them up for a burnt-offering unto Jehovah. ^25Seven days shalt thou prepare every day a goat for a sin-offering: they shall also prepare a young bullock, and a ram out of the flock, without blemish. ^26Seven days shall they make atonement for the altar and purify it; so shall they consecrate it. ^27And when they have accomplished the days, it shall be that upon the eighth day, and forward, the priests shall make your burnt-offerings upon the altar, and your peace-offerings; and I will accept you, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 44

44

^1Then he brought me back by the way of the outer gate of the sanctuary, which looketh toward the east; and it was shut. ^2And Jehovah said unto me, This gate shall be shut; it shall not be opened, neither shall any man enter in by it; for Jehovah, the God of Israel, hath entered in by it; therefore it shall be shut. ^3As for the prince, he shall sit therein as prince to eat bread before Jehovah; he shall enter by the way of the porch of the gate, and shall go out by the way of the same. ^4Then he brought me by the way of the north gate before the house; and I looked, and, behold, the glory of Jehovah filled the house of Jehovah: and I fell upon my face. ^5And Jehovah said unto me, Son of man, mark well, and behold with thine eyes, and hear with thine ears all that I say unto thee concerning all the ordinances of the house of Jehovah, and all the laws thereof; and mark well the entrance of the house, with every egress of the sanctuary. ^6And thou shalt say to the rebellious, even to the house of Israel, Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: O ye house of Israel, let it suffice you of all your abominations, ^7in that ye have brought in foreigners, uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, to be in my sanctuary, to profane it, even my house, when ye offer my bread, the fat and the blood, and they have broken my covenant, to add unto all your abominations. ^8And ye have not kept the charge of my holy things; but ye have set keepers of my charge in my sanctuary for yourselves. ^9Thus saith the Lord Jehovah, No foreigner, uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, shall enter into my sanctuary, of any foreigners that are among the children of Israel. ^10But the Levites that went far from me, when Israel went astray, that went astray from me after their idols, they shall bear their iniquity. ^11Yet they shall be ministers in my sanctuary, having oversight at the gates of the house, and ministering in the house: they shall slay the burnt-offering and the sacrifice for the people, and they shall stand before them to minister unto them. ^12Because they ministered unto them before their idols, and became a stumblingblock of iniquity unto the house of Israel; therefore have I lifted up my hand against them, saith the Lord Jehovah, and they shall bear their iniquity. ^13And they shall not come near unto me, to execute the office of priest unto me, nor to come near to any of my holy things, unto the things that are most holy; but they shall bear their shame, and their abominations which they have committed. ^14Yet will I make them keepers of the charge of the house, for all the service thereof, and for all that shall be done therein. ^15But the priests the Levites, the sons of Zadok, that kept the charge of my sanctuary when the children of Israel went astray from me, they shall come near to me to minister unto me; and they shall stand before me to offer unto me the fat and the blood, saith the Lord Jehovah: ^16they shall enter into my sanctuary, and they shall come near to my table, to minister unto me, and they shall keep my charge. ^17And it shall be that, when they enter in at the gates of the inner court, they shall be clothed with linen garments; and no wool shall come upon them, while they minister in the gates of the inner court, and within. ^18They shall have linen tires upon their heads, and shall have linen breeches upon their loins; they shall not gird themselves with anything that causeth sweat. ^19And when they go forth into the outer court, even into the outer court to the people, they shall put off their garments wherein they minister, and lay them in the holy chambers; and they shall put on other garments, that they sanctify not the people with their garments. ^20Neither shall they shave their heads, nor suffer their locks to grow long; they shall only cut off the hair of their heads. ^21Neither shall any of the priests drink wine, when they enter into the inner court. ^22Neither shall they take for their wives a widow, nor her that is put away; but they shall take virgins of the seed of the house of Israel, or a widow that is the widow of a priest. ^23And they shall teach my people the difference between the holy and the common, and cause them to discern between the unclean and the clean. ^24And in a controversy they shall stand to judge; according to mine ordinances shall they judge it: and they shall keep my laws and my statutes in all my appointed feasts; and they shall hallow my sabbaths. ^25And they shall go in to no dead person to defile themselves; but for father, or for mother, or for son, or for daughter, for brother, or for sister that hath had no husband, they may defile themselves. ^26And after he is cleansed, they shall reckon unto him seven days. ^27And in the day that he goeth into the sanctuary, into the inner court, to minister in the sanctuary, he shall offer his sin-offering, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^28And they shall have an inheritance: I am their inheritance; and ye shall give them no possession in Israel; I am their possession. ^29They shall eat the meal-offering, and the sin-offering, and the trespass-offering; and every devoted thing in Israel shall be theirs. ^30And the first of all the first-fruits of every thing, and every oblation of everything, of all your oblations, shall be for the priest: ye shall also give unto the priests the first of your dough, to cause a blessing to rest on thy house. ^31The priests shall not eat of anything that dieth of itself, or is torn, whether it be bird or beast.

Ezekiel 45

45

^1Moreover, when ye shall divide by lot the land for inheritance, ye shall offer an oblation unto Jehovah, a holy portion of the land; the length shall be the length of five and twenty thousand reeds, and the breadth shall be ten thousand: it shall be holy in all the border thereof round about. ^2Of this there shall be for the holy place five hundred in length by five hundred in breadth, square round about; and fifty cubits for the suburbs thereof round about. ^3And of this measure shalt thou measure a length of five and twenty thousand, and a breadth of ten thousand: and in it shall be the sanctuary, which is most holy. ^4It is a holy portion of the land; it shall be for the priests, the ministers of the sanctuary, that come near to minister unto Jehovah; and it shall be a place for their houses, and a holy place for the sanctuary. ^5And five and twenty thousand in length, and ten thousand in breadth, shall be unto the Levites, the ministers of the house, for a possession unto themselves, for twenty chambers. ^6And ye shall appoint the possession of the city five thousand broad, and five and twenty thousand long, side by side with the oblation of the holy portion: it shall be for the whole house of Israel. ^7And whatsoever is for the prince shall be on the one side and on the other side of the holy oblation and of the possession of the city, in front of the holy oblation and in front of the possession of the city, on the west side westward, and on the east side eastward; and in length answerable unto one of the portions, from the west border unto the east border. ^8In the land it shall be to him for a possession in Israel: and my princes shall no more oppress my people; but they shall give the land to the house of Israel according to their tribes. ^9Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Let it suffice you, O princes of Israel: remove violence and spoil, and execute justice and righteousness; take away your exactions from my people, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^10Ye shall have just balances, and a just ephah, and a just bath. ^11The ephah and the bath shall be of one measure, that the bath may contain the tenth part of a homer, and the ephah the tenth part of a homer: the measure thereof shall be after the homer. ^12And the shekel shall be twenty gerahs; twenty shekels, five and twenty shekels, fifteen shekels, shall be your maneh. ^13This is the oblation that ye shall offer: the sixth part of an ephah from a homer of wheat; and ye shall give the sixth part of an ephah from a homer of barley; ^14and the set portion of oil, of the bath of oil, the tenth part of a bath out of the cor, which is ten baths, even a homer; (for ten baths are a homer;) ^15and one lamb of the flock, out of two hundred, from the well-watered pastures of Israel; -for a meal-offering, and for a burnt-offering, and for peace-offerings, to make atonement for them, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^16All the people of the land shall give unto this oblation for the prince in Israel. ^17And it shall be the prince's part to give the burnt-offerings, and the meal-offerings, and the drink-offerings, in the feasts, and on the new moons, and on the sabbaths, in all the appointed feasts of the house of Israel: he shall prepare the sin-offering, and the meal-offering, and the burnt-offering, and the peace-offerings, to make atonement for the house of Israel. ^18Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: In the first month, in the first day of the month, thou shalt take a young bullock without blemish; and thou shalt cleanse the sanctuary. ^19And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin-offering, and put it upon the door-posts of the house, and upon the four corners of the ledge of the altar, and upon the posts of the gate of the inner court. ^20And so thou shalt do on the seventh day of the month for every one that erreth, and for him that is simple: so shall ye make atonement for the house. ^21In the first month, in the fourteenth day of the month, ye shall have the passover, a feast of seven days; unleavened bread shall be eaten. ^22And upon that day shall the prince prepare for himself and for all the people of the land a bullock for a sin-offering. ^23And the seven days of the feast he shall prepare a burnt-offering to Jehovah, seven bullocks and seven rams without blemish daily the seven days; and a he-goat daily for a sin-offering. ^24And he shall prepare a meal-offering, an ephah for a bullock, and an ephah for a ram, and a hin of oil to an ephah. ^25In the seventh month, in the fifteenth day of the month, in the feast, shall he do the like the seven days; according to the sin-offering, according to the burnt-offering, and according to the meal-offering, and according to the oil.

Ezekiel 46

46

^1Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: The gate of the inner court that looketh toward the east shall be shut the six working days; but on the sabbath day it shall be opened, and on the day of the new moon it shall be opened. ^2And the prince shall enter by the way of the porch of the gate without, and shall stand by the post of the gate; and the priests shall prepare his burnt-offering and his peace-offerings, and he shall worship at the threshold of the gate: then he shall go forth; but the gate shall not be shut until the evening. ^3And the people of the land shall worship at the door of that gate before Jehovah on the sabbaths and on the new moons. ^4And the burnt-offering that the prince shall offer unto Jehovah shall be on the sabbath day six lambs without blemish and a ram without blemish; ^5and the meal-offering shall be an ephah for the ram, and the meal-offering for the lambs as he is able to give, and a hin of oil to an ephah. ^6And on the day of the new moon it shall be a young bullock without blemish, and six lambs, and a ram; they shall be without blemish: ^7and he shall prepare a meal-offering, an ephah for the bullock, and an ephah for the ram, and for the lambs according as he is able, and a hin of oil to an ephah. ^8And when the prince shall enter, he shall go in by the way of the porch of the gate, and he shall go forth by the way thereof. ^9But when the people of the land shall come before Jehovah in the appointed feasts, he that entereth by the way of the north gate to worship shall go forth by the way of the south gate; and he that entereth by the way of the south gate shall go forth by the way of the north gate: he shall not return by the way of the gate whereby he came in, but shall go forth straight before him. ^10And the prince, when they go in, shall go in in the midst of them; and when they go forth, they shall go forth together. ^11And in the feasts and in the solemnities the meal-offering shall be an ephah for a bullock, and an ephah for a ram, and for the lambs as he is able to give, and a hin of oil to an ephah. ^12And when the prince shall prepare a freewill-offering, a burnt-offering or peace-offerings as a freewill-offering unto Jehovah, one shall open for him the gate that looketh toward the east; and he shall prepare his burnt-offering and his peace-offerings, as he doth on the sabbath day: then he shall go forth; and after his going forth one shall shut the gate. ^13And thou shalt prepare a lamb a year old without blemish for a burnt-offering unto Jehovah daily: morning by morning shalt thou prepare it. ^14And thou shalt prepare a meal-offering with it morning by morning, the sixth part of an ephah, and the third part of a hin of oil, to moisten the fine flour; a meal-offering unto Jehovah continually by a perpetual ordinance. ^15Thus shall they prepare the lamb, and the meal-offering, and the oil, morning by morning, for a continual burnt-offering. ^16Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: If the prince give a gift unto any of his sons, it is his inheritance, it shall belong to his sons; it is their possession by inheritance. ^17But if he give of his inheritance a gift to one of his servants, it shall be his to the year of liberty; then it shall return to the prince; but as for his inheritance, it shall be for his sons. ^18Moreover the prince shall not take of the people's inheritance, to thrust them out of their possession; he shall give inheritance to his sons out of his own possession, that my people be not scattered every man from his possession. ^19Then he brought me through the entry, which was at the side of the gate, into the holy chambers for the priests, which looked toward the north: and, behold, there was a place on the hinder part westward. ^20And he said unto me, This is the place where the priests shall boil the trespass-offering and the sin-offering, and where they shall bake the meal-offering; that they bring them not forth into the outer court, to sanctify the people. ^21Then he brought me forth into the outer court, and caused me to pass by the four corners of the court; and, behold, in every corner of the court there was a court. ^22In the four corners of the court there were courts inclosed, forty cubits long and thirty broad: these four in the corners were of one measure. ^23And there was a wall round about in them, round about the four, and boiling-places were made under the walls round about. ^24Then said he unto me, These are the boiling-houses, where the ministers of the house shall boil the sacrifice of the people.

Ezekiel 47

47

^1And he brought me back unto the door of the house; and, behold, waters issued out from under the threshold of the house eastward; (for the forefront of the house was toward the east;) and the waters came down from under, from the right side of the house, on the south of the altar. ^2Then he brought me out by the way of the gate northward, and led me round by the way without unto the outer gate, by the way of the gate that looketh toward the east; and, behold, there ran out waters on the right side. ^3When the man went forth eastward with the line in his hand, he measured a thousand cubits, and he caused me to pass through the waters, waters that were to the ankles. ^4Again he measured a thousand, and caused me to pass through the waters, waters that were to the knees. Again he measured a thousand, and caused me to pass through the waters, waters that were to the loins. ^5Afterward he measured a thousand; and it was a river that I could not pass through; for the waters were risen, waters to swim in, a river that could not be passed through. ^6And he said unto me, Son of man, hast thou seen this? Then he brought me, and caused me to return to the bank of the river. ^7Now when I had returned, behold, upon the bank of the river were very many trees on the one side and on the other. ^8Then said he unto me, These waters issue forth toward the eastern region, and shall go down into the Arabah; and they shall go toward the sea; into the sea shall the waters go which were made to issue forth; and the waters shall be healed. ^9And it shall come to pass, that every living creature which swarmeth, in every place whither the rivers come, shall live; and there shall be a very great multitude of fish; for these waters are come thither, and the waters of the sea shall be healed, and everything shall live whithersoever the river cometh. ^10And it shall come to pass, that fishers shall stand by it: from En-gedi even unto En-eglaim shall be a place for the spreading of nets; their fish shall be after their kinds, as the fish of the great sea, exceeding many. ^11But the miry places thereof, and the marshes thereof, shall not be healed; they shall be given up to salt. ^12And by the river upon the bank thereof, on this side and on that side, shall grow every tree for food, whose leaf shall not whither, neither shall the fruit thereof fail: it shall bring forth new fruit every month, because the waters thereof issue out of the sanctuary; and the fruit thereof shall be for food, and the leaf thereof for healing. ^13Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: This shall be the border, whereby ye shall divide the land for inheritance according to the twelve tribes of Israel: Joseph shall have two portions. ^14And ye shall inherit it, one as well as another; for I sware to give it unto your fathers: and this land shall fall unto you for inheritance. ^15And this shall be the border of the land: On the north side, from the great sea, by the way of Hethlon, unto the entrance of Zedad; ^16Hamath, Berothah, Sibraim, which is between the border of Damascus and the border of Hamath; Hazer-hatticon, which is by the border of Hauran. ^17And the border from the sea, shall be Hazar-enon at the border of Damascus; and on the north northward is the border of Hamath. This is the north side. ^18And the east side, between Hauran and Damascus and Gilead, and the land of Israel, shall be the Jordan; from the north border unto the east sea shall ye measure. This is the east side. ^19And the south side southward shall be from Tamar as far as the waters of Meriboth-kadesh, to the brook of Egypt, unto the great sea. This is the south side southward. ^20And the west side shall be the great sea, from the south border as far as over against the entrance of Hamath. This is the west side. ^21So shall ye divide this land unto you according to the tribes of Israel. ^22And it shall come to pass, that ye shall divide it by lot for an inheritance unto you and to the strangers that sojourn among you, who shall beget children among you; and they shall be unto you as the home-born among the children of Israel; they shall have inheritance with you among the tribes of Israel. ^23And it shall come to pass, that in what tribe the stranger sojourneth, there shall ye give him his inheritance, saith the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 48

48

^1Now these are the names of the tribes: From the north end, beside the way of Hethlon to the entrance of Hamath, Hazar-enan at the border of Damascus, northward beside Hamath, (and they shall have their sides east and west,) Dan, one portion. ^2And by the border of Dan, from the east side unto the west side, Asher, one portion. ^3And by the border of Asher, from the east side even unto the west side, Naphtali, one portion. ^4And by the border of Naphtali, from the east side unto the west side, Manasseh, one portion. ^5And by the border of Manasseh, from the east side unto the west side, Ephraim, one portion. ^6And by the border of Ephraim, from the east side even unto the west side, Reuben, one portion. ^7And by the border of Reuben, from the east side unto the west side, Judah, one portion. ^8And by the border of Judah, from the east side unto the west side, shall be the oblation which ye shall offer, five and twenty thousand reeds in breadth, and in length as one of the portions, from the east side unto the west side: and the sanctuary shall be in the midst of it. ^9The oblation that ye shall offer unto Jehovah shall be five and twenty thousand reeds in length, and ten thousand in breadth. ^10And for these, even for the priests, shall be the holy oblation: toward the north five and twenty thousand in length, and toward the west ten thousand in breadth, and toward the east ten thousand in breadth, and toward the south five and twenty thousand in length: and the sanctuary of Jehovah shall be in the midst thereof. ^11It shall be for the priests that are sanctified of the sons of Zadok, that have kept my charge, that went not astray when the children of Israel went astray, as the Levites went astray. ^12And it shall be unto them an oblation from the oblation of the land, a thing most holy, by the border of the Levites. ^13And answerable unto the border of the priests, the Levites shall have five and twenty thousand in length, and ten thousand in breadth: all the length shall be five and twenty thousand, and the breadth ten thousand. ^14And they shall sell none of it, nor exchange it, nor shall the first-fruits of the land be alienated; for it is holy unto Jehovah. ^15And the five thousand that are left in the breadth, in front of the five and twenty thousand, shall be for common use, for the city, for dwelling and for suburbs; and the city shall be in the midst thereof. ^16And these shall be the measures thereof: the north side four thousand and five hundred, and the south side four thousand and five hundred, and on the east side four thousand and five hundred, and the west side four thousand and five hundred. ^17And the city shall have suburbs: toward the north two hundred and fifty, and toward the south two hundred and fifty, and toward the east two hundred and fifty, and toward the west two hundred and fifty. ^18And the residue in the length, answerable unto the holy oblation, shall be ten thousand eastward, and ten thousand westward; and it shall be answerable unto the holy oblation; and the increase thereof shall be for food unto them that labor in the city. ^19And they that labor in the city, out of all the tribes of Israel, shall till it. ^20All the oblation shall be five and twenty thousand by five and twenty thousand: ye shall offer the holy oblation four-square, with the possession of the city. ^21And the residue shall be for the prince, on the one side and on the other of the holy oblation and of the possession of the city; in front of the five and twenty thousand of the oblation toward the east border, and westward in front of the five and twenty thousand toward the west border, answerable unto the portions, it shall be for the prince: and the holy oblation and the sanctuary of the house shall be in the midst thereof. ^22Moreover from the possession of the Levites, and from the possession of the city, being in the midst of that which is the prince's, between the border of Judah and the border of Benjamin, it shall be for the prince. ^23And as for the rest of the tribes: from the east side unto the west side, Benjamin, one portion. ^24And by the border of Benjamin, from the east side unto the west side, Simeon, one portion. ^25And by the border of Simeon, from the east side unto the west side, Issachar, one portion. ^26And by the border of Issachar, from the east side unto the west side, Zebulun, one portion. ^27And by the border of Zebulun, from the east side unto the west side, Gad, one portion. ^28And by the border of Gad, at the south side southward, the border shall be even from Tamar unto the waters of Meribath-kadesh, to the brook of Egypt, unto the great sea. ^29This is the land which ye shall divide by lot unto the tribes of Israel for inheritance, and these are their several portions, saith the Lord Jehovah. ^30And these are the egresses of the city: On the north side four thousand and five hundred reeds by measure; ^31and the gates of the city shall be after the names of the tribes of Israel, three gates northward: the gate of Reuben, one; the gate of Judah, one; the gate of Levi, one. ^32And at the east side four thousand and five hundred reeds, and three gates: even the gate of Joseph, one; the gate of Benjamin, one; the gate of Dan, one. ^33And at the south side four thousand and five hundred reeds by measure, and three gates: the gate of Simeon, one; the gate of Issachar, one; the gate of Zebulun, one. ^34At the west side four thousand and five hundred reeds, with their three gates: the gate of Gad, one; the gate of Asher, one; the gate of Naphtali, one. ^35It shall be eighteen thousand reeds round about: and the name of the city from that day shall be, Jehovah is there.

Ezra 2

2

^1Now these are the children of the province, that went up out of the captivity of those that had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away unto Babylon, and that returned unto Jerusalem and Judah, every one unto his city; ^2who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Seraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispar, Bigvai, Rehum, Baanah. The number of the men of the people of Israel: ^3The children of Parosh, two thousand a hundred seventy and two. ^4The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two. ^5The children of Arah, seven hundred seventy and five. ^6The children of Pahath-moab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve. ^7The children of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. ^8The children of Zattu, nine hundred forty and five. ^9The children of Zaccai, seven hundred and threescore. ^10The children of Bani, six hundred forty and two. ^11The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty and three. ^12The children of Azgad, a thousand two hundred twenty and two. ^13The children of Adonikam, six hundred sixty and six. ^14The children of Bigvai, two thousand fifty and six. ^15The children of Adin, four hundred fifty and four. ^16The children of Ater, of Hezekiah, ninety and eight. ^17The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty and three. ^18The children of Jorah, a hundred and twelve. ^19The children of Hashum, two hundred twenty and three. ^20The children of Gibbar, ninety and five. ^21The children of Beth-lehem, a hundred twenty and three. ^22The men of Netophah, fifty and six. ^23The men of Anathoth, a hundred twenty and eight. ^24The children of Azmaveth, forty and two. ^25The children of Kiriath-arim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty and three. ^26The children of Ramah and Geba, six hundred twenty and one. ^27The men of Michmas, a hundred twenty and two. ^28The men of Beth-el and Ai, two hundred twenty and three. ^29The children of Nebo, fifty and two. ^30The children of Magbish, a hundred fifty and six. ^31The children of the other Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four. ^32The children of Harim, three hundred and twenty. ^33The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and five. ^34The children of Jericho, three hundred forty and five. ^35The children of Senaah, three thousand and six hundred and thirty. ^36The priests: the children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three. ^37The children of Immer, a thousand fifty and two. ^38The children of Pashhur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven. ^39The children of Harim, a thousand and seventeen. ^40The Levites: the children of Jeshua and Kadmiel, of the children of Hodaviah, seventy and four. ^41The singers: the children of Asaph, a hundred twenty and eight. ^42The children of the porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, in all a hundred thirty and nine. ^43The Nethinim: the children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth, ^44the children of Keros, the children of Siaha, the children of Padon, ^45the children of Lebanah, the children of Hagabah, the children of Akkub, ^46the children of Hagab, the children of Shamlai, the children of Hanan, ^47the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar, the children of Reaiah, ^48the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, the children of Gazzam, ^49the children of Uzza, the children of Paseah, the children of Besai, ^50the children of Asnah, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephisim, ^51the children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur, ^52the children of Bazluth, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha, ^53the children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Temah, ^54the children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha. ^55The children of Solomon's servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Hassophereth, the children of Peruda, ^56the children of Jaalah, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel, ^57the children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth-hazzebaim, the children of Ami. ^58All the Nethinim, and the children of Solomon's servants, were three hundred ninety and two. ^59And these were they that went up from Tel-melah, Tel-harsha, Cherub, Addan, and Immer; but they could not show their fathers' houses, and their seed, whether they were of Israel: ^60the children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred fifty and two. ^61And of the children of the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children of Hakkoz, the children of Barzillai, who took a wife of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called after their name. ^62These sought their register among those that were reckoned by genealogy, but they were not found: therefore were they deemed polluted and put from the priesthood. ^63And the governor said unto them, that they should not eat of the most holy things, till there stood up a priest with Urim and with Thummim. ^64The whole assembly together was forty and two thousand three hundred and threescore, ^65besides their men-servants and their maid-servants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and they had two hundred singing men and singing women. ^66Their horses were seven hundred thirty and six; their mules, two hundred forty and five; ^67their camels, four hundred thirty and five; their asses, six thousand seven hundred and twenty. ^68And some of the heads of fathers' houses, when they came to the house of Jehovah which is in Jerusalem, offered willingly for the house of God to set it up in its place: ^69they gave after their ability into the treasury of the work threescore and one thousand darics of gold, and five thousand pounds of silver, and one hundred priests' garments. ^70So the priests, and the Levites, and some of the people, and the singers, and the porters, and the Nethinim, dwelt in their cities, and all Israel in their cities.

Ezra 3

3

^1And when the seventh month was come, and the children of Israel were in the cities, the people gathered themselves together as one man to Jerusalem. ^2Then stood up Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and his brethren the priests, and Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and his brethren, and builded the altar of the God of Israel, to offer burnt-offerings thereon, as it is written in the law of Moses the man of God. ^3And they set the altar upon its base; for fear was upon them because of the peoples of the countries: and they offered burnt-offerings thereon unto Jehovah, even burnt-offerings morning and evening. ^4And they kept the feast of tabernacles, as it is written, and offered the daily burnt-offerings by number, according to the ordinance, as the duty of every day required; ^5and afterward the continual burnt-offering, and the offerings of the new moons, and of all the set feasts of Jehovah that were consecrated, and of every one that willingly offered a freewill-offering unto Jehovah. ^6From the first day of the seventh month began they to offer burnt-offerings unto Jehovah: but the foundation of the temple of Jehovah was not yet laid. ^7They gave money also unto the masons, and to the carpenters; and food, and drink, and oil, unto them of Sidon, and to them of Tyre, to bring cedar-trees from Lebanon to the sea, unto Joppa, according to the grant that they had of Cyrus king of Persia. ^8Now in the second year of their coming unto the house of God at Jerusalem, in the second month, began Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and the rest of their brethren the priests and the Levites, and all they that were come out of the captivity unto Jerusalem, and appointed the Levites, from twenty years old and upward, to have the oversight of the work of the house of Jehovah. ^9Then stood Jeshua with his sons and his brethren, Kadmiel and his sons, the sons of Judah, together, to have the oversight of the workmen in the house of God: the sons of Henadad, with their sons and their brethren the Levites. ^10And when the builders laid the foundation of the temple of Jehovah, they set the priests in their apparel with trumpets, and the Levites the sons of Asaph with cymbals, to praise Jehovah, after the order of David king of Israel. ^11And they sang one to another in praising and giving thanks unto Jehovah, saying, For he is good, for his lovingkindness endureth for ever toward Israel. And all the people shouted with a great shout, when they praised Jehovah, because the foundation of the house of Jehovah was laid. ^12But many of the priests and Levites and heads of fathers' houses, the old men that had seen the first house, when the foundation of this house was laid before their eyes, wept with a loud voice; and many shouted aloud for joy: ^13so that the people could not discern the noise of the shout of joy from the noise of the weeping of the people; for the people shouted with a loud shout, and the noise was heard afar off.

Ezra 4

4

^1Now when the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin heard that the children of the captivity were building a temple unto Jehovah, the God of Israel; ^2then they drew near to Zerubbabel, and to the heads of fathers' houses, and said unto them, Let us build with you; for we seek your God, as ye do; and we sacrifice unto him since the days of Esar-haddon king of Assyria, who brought us up hither. ^3But Zerubbabel, and Jeshua, and the rest of the heads of fathers' houses of Israel, said unto them, Ye have nothing to do with us in building a house unto our God; but we ourselves together will build unto Jehovah, the God of Israel, as king Cyrus the king of Persia hath commanded us. ^4Then the people of the land weakened the hands of the people of Judah, and troubled them in building, ^5and hired counsellors against them, to frustrate their purpose, all the days of Cyrus king of Persia, even until the reign of Darius king of Persia. ^6And in the reign of Ahasuerus, in the beginning of his reign, wrote they an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem. ^7And in the days of Artaxerxes wrote Bishlam, Mithredath, Tabeel, and the rest of his companions, unto Artaxerxes king of Persia; and the writing of the letter was written in the Syrian character, and set forth in the Syrian tongue. ^8Rehum the chancellor and Shimshai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to Artaxerxes the king in this sort: ^9then wrote Rehum the chancellor, and Shimshai the scribe, and the rest of their companions, the Dinaites, and the Apharsathchites, the Tarpelites, the Apharsites, the Archevites, the Babylonians, the Shushanchites, the Dehaites, the Elamites, ^10and the rest of the nations whom the great and noble Osnappar brought over, and set in the city of Samaria, and in the rest of the country beyond the River, and so forth. ^11This is the copy of the letter that they sent unto Artaxerxes the king: Thy servants the men beyond the River, and so forth. ^12Be it known unto the king, that the Jews that came up from thee are come to us unto Jerusalem; they are building the rebellious and the bad city, and have finished the walls, and repaired the foundations. ^13Be it known now unto the king, that, if this city be builded, and the walls finished, they will not pay tribute, custom, or toll, and in the end it will be hurtful unto the kings. ^14Now because we eat the salt of the palace, and it is not meet for us to see the king's dishonor, therefore have we sent and certified the king; ^15that search may be made in the book of the records of thy fathers: so shalt thou find in the book of the records, and know that this city is a rebellious city, and hurtful unto kings and provinces, and that they have moved sedition within the same of old time; for which cause was this city laid waste. ^16We certify the king that, if this city be builded, and the walls finished, by this means thou shalt have no portion beyond the River. ^17Then sent the king an answer unto Rehum the chancellor, and to Shimshai the scribe, and to the rest of their companions that dwell in Samaria, and in the rest of the country beyond the River: Peace, and so forth. ^18The letter which ye sent unto us hath been plainly read before me. ^19And I decreed, and search hath been made, and it is found that this city of old time hath made insurrection against kings, and that rebellion and sedition have been made therein. ^20There have been mighty kings also over Jerusalem, who have ruled over all the country beyond the River; and tribute, custom, and toll, was paid unto them. ^21Make ye now a decree to cause these men to cease, and that this city be not builded, until a decree shall be made by me. ^22And take heed that ye be not slack herein: why should damage grow to the hurt of the kings? ^23Then when the copy of king Artaxerxes' letter was read before Rehum, and Shimshai the scribe, and their companions, they went in haste to Jerusalem unto the Jews, and made them to cease by force and power. ^24Then ceased the work of the house of God which is at Jerusalem; and it ceased until the second year of the reign of Darius king of Persia.

Ezra 5

5

^1Now the prophets, Haggai the prophet, and Zechariah the son of Iddo, prophesied unto the Jews that were in Judah and Jerusalem; in the name of the God of Israel prophesied they unto them. ^2Then rose up Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and began to build the house of God which is at Jerusalem; and with them were the prophets of God, helping them. ^3At the same time came to them Tattenai, the governor beyond the River, and Shethar-bozenai, and their companions, and said thus unto them, Who gave you a decree to build this house, and to finish this wall? ^4Then we told them after this manner, what the names of the men were that were making this building. ^5But the eye of their God was upon the elders of the Jews, and they did not make them cease, till the matter should come to Darius, and then answer should be returned by letter concerning it. ^6The copy of the letter that Tattenai, the governor beyond the River, and Shethar-bozenai, and his companions the Apharsachites, who were beyond the River, sent unto Darius the king; ^7they sent a letter unto him, wherein was written thus: Unto Darius the king, all peace. ^8Be it known unto the king, that we went into the province of Judah, to the house of the great God, which is builded with great stones, and timber is laid in the walls; and this work goeth on with diligence and prospereth in their hands. ^9Then asked we those elders, and said unto them thus, Who gave you a decree to build this house, and to finish this wall? ^10We asked them their names also, to certify thee, that we might write the names of the men that were at the head of them. ^11And thus they returned us answer, saying, We are the servants of the God of heaven and earth, and are building the house that was builded these many years ago, which a great king of Israel builded and finished. ^12But after that our fathers had provoked the God of heaven unto wrath, he gave them into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, the Chaldean, who destroyed this house, and carried the people away into Babylon. ^13But in the first year of Cyrus king of Babylon, Cyrus the king made a decree to build this house of God. ^14And the gold and silver vessels also of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the temple that was in Jerusalem, and brought into the temple of Babylon, those did Cyrus the king take out of the temple of Babylon, and they were delivered unto one whose name was Sheshbazzar, whom he had made governor; ^15and he said unto him, Take these vessels, go, put them in the temple that is in Jerusalem, and let the house of God be builded in its place. ^16Then came the same Sheshbazzar, and laid the foundations of the house of God which is in Jerusalem: and since that time even until now hath it been in building, and yet it is not completed. ^17Now therefore, if it seem good to the king, let there be search made in the king's treasure-house, which is there at Babylon, whether it be so, that a decree was made of Cyrus the king to build this house of God at Jerusalem; and let the king send his pleasure to us concerning this matter.

Ezra 6

6

^1Then Darius the king made a decree, and search was made in the house of the archives, where the treasures were laid up in Babylon. ^2And there was found at Achmetha, in the palace that is in the province of Media, a roll, and therein was thus written for a record: ^3In the first year of Cyrus the king, Cyrus the king made a decree: Concerning the house of God at Jerusalem, let the house be builded, the place where they offer sacrifices, and let the foundations thereof be strongly laid; the height thereof threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof threescore cubits; ^4with three courses of great stones, and a course of new timber: and let the expenses be given out of the king's house. ^5And also let the gold and silver vessels of the house of God, which Nebuchadnezzar took forth out of the temple which is at Jerusalem, and brought unto Babylon, be restored, and brought again unto the temple which is at Jerusalem, every one to its place; and thou shalt put them in the house of God. ^6Now therefore, Tattenai, governor beyond the River, Shethar-bozenai, and your companions the Apharsachites, who are beyond the River, be ye far from thence: ^7let the work of this house of God alone; let the governor of the Jews and the elders of the Jews build this house of God in its place. ^8Moreover I make a decree what ye shall do to these elders of the Jews for the building of this house of God: that of the king's goods, even of the tribute beyond the River, expenses be given with all diligence unto these men, that they be not hindered. ^9And that which they have need of, both young bullocks, and rams, and lambs, for burnt-offerings to the God of heaven; also wheat, salt, wine, and oil, according to the word of the priests that are at Jerusalem, let it be given them day by day without fail; ^10that they may offer sacrifices of sweet savor unto the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the king, and of his sons. ^11Also I have made a decree, that whosoever shall alter this word, let a beam be pulled out from his house, and let him be lifted up and fastened thereon; and let his house be made a dunghill for this: ^12and the God that hath caused his name to dwell there overthrow all kings and peoples that shall put forth their hand to alter the same, to destroy this house of God which is at Jerusalem. I Darius have made a decree; let it be done with all diligence. ^13Then Tattenai, the governor beyond the River, Shethar-bozenai, and their companions, because that Darius the king had sent, did accordingly with all diligence. ^14And the elders of the Jews builded and prospered, through the prophesying of Haggai the prophet and Zechariah the son of Iddo. And they builded and finished it, according to the commandment of the God of Israel, and according to the decree of Cyrus, and Darius, and Artaxerxes king of Persia. ^15And this house was finished on the third day of the month Adar, which was in the sixth year of the reign of Darius the king. ^16And the children of Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the rest of the children of the captivity, kept the dedication of this house of God with joy. ^17And they offered at the dedication of this house of God a hundred bullocks, two hundred rams, four hundred lambs; and for a sin-offering for all Israel, twelve he-goats, according to the number of the tribes of Israel. ^18And they set the priests in their divisions, and the Levites in their courses, for the service of God, which is at Jerusalem; as it is written in the book of Moses. ^19And the children of the captivity kept the passover upon the fourteenth day of the first month. ^20For the priests and the Levites had purified themselves together; all of them were pure: and they killed the passover for all the children of the captivity, and for their brethren the priests, and for themselves. ^21And the children of Israel that were come again out of the captivity, and all such as had separated themselves unto them from the filthiness of the nations of the land, to seek Jehovah, the God of Israel, did eat, ^22and kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with joy: for Jehovah had made them joyful, and had turned the heart of the king of Assyria unto them, to strengthen their hands in the work of the house of God, the God of Israel.

Ezra 7

7

^1Now after these things, in the reign of Artaxerxes king of Persia, Ezra the son of Seraiah, the son of Azariah, the son of Hilkiah, ^2the son of Shallum, the son of Zadok, the son of Ahitub, ^3the son of Amariah, the son of Azariah, the son of Meraioth, ^4the son of Zerahiah, the son of Uzzi, the son of Bukki, ^5the son of Abishua, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the chief priest; ^6this Ezra went up from Babylon: and he was a ready scribe in the law of Moses, which Jehovah, the God of Israel, had given; and the king granted him all his request, according to the hand of Jehovah his God upon him. ^7And there went up some of the children of Israel, and of the priests, and the Levites, and the singers, and the porters, and the Nethinim, unto Jerusalem, in the seventh year of Artaxerxes the king. ^8And he came to Jerusalem in the fifth month, which was in the seventh year of the king. ^9For upon the first day of the first month began he to go up from Babylon; and on the first day of the fifth month came he to Jerusalem, according to the good hand of his God upon him. ^10For Ezra had set his heart to seek the law of Jehovah, and to do it, and to teach in Israel statutes and ordinances. ^11Now this is the copy of the letter that the king Artaxerxes gave unto Ezra the priest, the scribe, even the scribe of the words of the commandments of Jehovah, and of his statutes to Israel: ^12Artaxerxes, king of kings, unto Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the God of heaven, perfect and so forth. ^13I make a decree, that all they of the people of Israel, and their priests and the Levites, in my realm, that are minded of their own free will to go to Jerusalem, go with thee. ^14Forasmuch as thou art sent of the king and his seven counsellors, to inquire concerning Judah and Jerusalem, according to the law of thy God which is in thy hand, ^15and to carry the silver and gold, which the king and his counsellors have freely offered unto the God of Israel, whose habitation is in Jerusalem, ^16and all the silver and gold that thou shalt find in all the province of Babylon, with the freewill-offering of the people, and of the priests, offering willingly for the house of their God which is in Jerusalem; ^17therefore thou shalt with all diligence buy with this money bullocks, rams, lambs, with their meal-offerings and their drink-offerings, and shalt offer them upon the altar of the house of your God which is in Jerusalem. ^18And whatsoever shall seem good to thee and to thy brethren to do with the rest of the silver and the gold, that do ye after the will of your God. ^19And the vessels that are given thee for the service of the house of thy God, deliver thou before the God of Jerusalem. ^20And whatsoever more shall be needful for the house of thy God, which thou shalt have occasion to bestow, bestow it out of the king's treasure-house. ^21And I, even I Artaxerxes the king, do make a decree to all the treasurers that are beyond the River, that whatsoever Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the God of heaven, shall require of you, it be done with all diligence, ^22unto a hundred talents of silver, and to a hundred measures of wheat, and to a hundred baths of wine, and to a hundred baths of oil, and salt without prescribing how much. ^23Whatsoever is commanded by the God of heaven, let it be done exactly for the house of the God of heaven; for why should there be wrath against the realm of the king and his sons? ^24Also we certify you, that touching any of the priests and Levites, the singers, porters, Nethinim, or servants of this house of God, it shall not be lawful to impose tribute, custom, or toll, upon them. ^25And thou, Ezra, after the wisdom of thy God that is in thy hand, appoint magistrates and judges, who may judge all the people that are beyond the River, all such as know the laws of thy God; and teach ye him that knoweth them not. ^26And whosoever will not do the law of thy God, and the law of the king, let judgment be executed upon him with all diligence, whether it be unto death, or to banishment, or to confiscation of goods, or to imprisonment. ^27Blessed be Jehovah, the God of our fathers, who hath put such a thing as this in the king's heart, to beautify the house of Jehovah which is in Jerusalem; ^28and hath extended lovingkindness unto me before the king, and his counsellors, and before all the king's mighty princes. And I was strengthened according to the hand of Jehovah my God upon me, and I gathered together out of Israel chief men to go up with me.

Ezra 8

8

^1Now these are the heads of their fathers' houses, and this is the genealogy of them that went up with me from Babylon, in the reign of Artaxerxes the king: ^2Of the sons of Phinehas, Gershom. Of the sons of Ithamar, Daniel. Of the sons of David, Hattush. ^3Of the sons of Shecaniah, of the sons of Parosh, Zechariah; and with him were reckoned by genealogy of the males a hundred and fifty. ^4Of the sons of Pahath-moab, Eliehoenai the son of Zerahiah; and with him two hundred males. ^5Of the sons of Shecaniah, the son of Jahaziel; and with him three hundred males. ^6And of the sons of Adin, Ebed the son of Jonathan; and with him fifty males. ^7And of the sons of Elam, Jeshaiah the son of Athaliah; and with him seventy males. ^8And of the sons of Shephatiah, Zebadiah the son of Michael; and with him fourscore males. ^9Of the sons of Joab, Obadiah the son of Jehiel; and with him two hundred and eighteen males. ^10And of the sons of Shelomith, the son of Josiphiah; and with him a hundred and threescore males. ^11And of the sons of Bebai, Zechariah the son of Bebai; and with him twenty and eight males. ^12And of the sons of Azgad, Johanan the son of Hakkatan; and with him a hundred and ten males. ^13And of the sons of Adonikam, that were the last; and these are their names: Eliphelet, Jeuel, and Shemaiah; and with them threescore males. ^14And of the sons of Bigvai, Uthai and Zabbud; and with them seventy males. ^15And I gathered them together to the river that runneth to Ahava; and there we encamped three days: and I viewed the people, and the priests, and found there none of the sons of Levi. ^16Then sent I for Eliezer, for Ariel, for Shemaiah, and for Elnathan, and for Jarib, and for Elnathan, and for Nathan, and for Zechariah, and for Meshullam, chief men; also for Joiarib, and for Elnathan, who were teachers. ^17And I sent them forth unto Iddo the chief at the place Casiphia; and I told them what they should say unto Iddo, and his brethren the Nethinim, at the place Casiphia, that they should bring unto us ministers for the house of our God. ^18And according to the good hand of our God upon us they brought us a man of discretion, of the sons of Mahli, the son of Levi, the son of Israel; and Sherebiah, with his sons and his brethren, eighteen; ^19and Hashabiah, and with him Jeshaiah of the sons of Merari, his brethren and their sons, twenty; ^20and of the Nethinim, whom David and the princes had given for the service of the Levites, two hundred and twenty Nethinim: all of them were mentioned by name. ^21Then I proclaimed a fast there, at the river Ahava, that we might humble ourselves before our God, to seek of him a straight way for us, and for our little ones, and for all our substance. ^22For I was ashamed to ask of the king a band of soldiers and horsemen to help us against the enemy in the way, because we had spoken unto the king, saying, The hand of our God is upon all them that seek him, for good; but his power and his wrath is against all them that forsake him. ^23So we fasted and besought our God for this: and he was entreated of us. ^24Then I set apart twelve of the chiefs of the priests, even Sherebiah, Hashabiah, and ten of their brethren with them, ^25and weighed unto them the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, even the offering for the house of our God, which the king, and his counsellors, and his princes, and all Israel there present, had offered: ^26I weighed into their hand six hundred and fifty talents of silver, and silver vessels a hundred talents; of gold a hundred talents; ^27and twenty bowls of gold, of a thousand darics; and two vessels of fine bright brass, precious as gold. ^28And I said unto them, Ye are holy unto Jehovah, and the vessels are holy; and the silver and the gold are a freewill-offering unto Jehovah, the God of your fathers. ^29Watch ye, and keep them, until ye weigh them before the chiefs of the priests and the Levites, and the princes of the fathers' houses of Israel, at Jerusalem, in the chambers of the house of Jehovah. ^30So the priests and the Levites received the weight of the silver and the gold, and the vessels, to bring them to Jerusalem unto the house of our God. ^31Then we departed from the river Ahava on the twelfth day of the first month, to go unto Jerusalem: and the hand of our God was upon us, and he delivered us from the hand of the enemy and the lier-in-wait by the way. ^32And we came to Jerusalem, and abode there three days. ^33And on the fourth day the silver and the gold and the vessels were weighed in the house of our God into the hand of Meremoth the son of Uriah the priest; and with him was Eleazar the son of Phinehas; and with them was Jozabad the son of Jeshua, and Noadiah the son of Binnui, the Levite; ^34the whole by number and by weight: and all the weight was written at that time. ^35The children of the captivity, that were come out of exile, offered burnt-offerings unto the God of Israel, twelve bullocks for all Israel, ninety and six rams, seventy and seven lambs, twelve he-goats for a sin-offering: all this was a burnt-offering unto Jehovah. ^36And they delivered the king's commissions unto the king's satraps, and to the governors beyond the River: and they furthered the people and the house of God.

Ezra 9

9

^1Now when these things were done, the princes drew near unto me, saying, The people of Israel, and the priests and the Levites, have not separated themselves from the peoples of the lands, doing according to their abominations, even of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Jebusites, the Ammonites, the Moabites, the Egyptians, and the Amorites. ^2For they have taken of their daughters for themselves and for their sons, so that the holy seed have mingled themselves with the peoples of the lands: yea, the hand of the princes and rulers hath been chief in this trespass. ^3And when I heard this thing, I rent my garment and my robe, and plucked off the hair of my head and of my beard, and sat down confounded. ^4Then were assembled unto me every one that trembled at the words of the God of Israel, because of the trespass of them of the captivity; and I sat confounded until the evening oblation. ^5And at the evening oblation I arose up from my humiliation, even with my garment and my robe rent; and I fell upon my knees, and spread out my hands unto Jehovah my God; ^6and I said, O my God, I am ashamed and blush to lift up my face to thee, my God; for our iniquities are increased over our head, and our guiltiness is grown up unto the heavens. ^7Since the days of our fathers we have been exceeding guilty unto this day; and for our iniquities have we, our kings, and our priests, been delivered into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to captivity, and to plunder, and to confusion of face, as it is this day. ^8And now for a little moment grace hath been showed from Jehovah our God, to leave us a remnant to escape, and to give us a nail in his holy place, that our God may lighten our eyes, and give us a little reviving in our bondage. ^9For we are bondmen; yet our God hath not forsaken us in our bondage, but hath extended lovingkindness unto us in the sight of the kings of Persia, to give us a reviving, to set up the house of our God, and to repair the ruins thereof, and to give us a wall in Judah and in Jerusalem. ^10And now, O our God, what shall we say after this? for we have forsaken thy commandments, ^11which thou hast commanded by thy servants the prophets, saying, The land, unto which ye go to possess it, is an unclean land through the uncleanness of the peoples of the lands, through their abominations, which have filled it from one end to another with their filthiness: ^12now therefore give not your daughters unto their sons, neither take their daughters unto your sons, nor seek their peace or their prosperity for ever; that ye may be strong, and eat the good of the land, and leave it for an inheritance to your children for ever. ^13And after all that is come upon us for our evil deeds, and for our great guilt, seeing that thou our God hast punished us less than our iniquities deserve, and hast given us such a remnant, ^14shall we again break thy commandments, and join in affinity with the peoples that do these abominations? wouldest not thou be angry with us till thou hadst consumed us, so that there should be no remnant, nor any to escape? ^15O Jehovah, the God of Israel, thou art righteous; for we are left a remnant that is escaped, as it is this day: behold, we are before thee in our guiltiness; for none can stand before thee because of this.

Ezra 10

10

^1Now while Ezra prayed and made confession, weeping and casting himself down before the house of God, there was gathered together unto him out of Israel a very great assembly of men and women and children; for the people wept very sore. ^2And Shecaniah the son of Jehiel, one of the sons of Elam, answered and said unto Ezra, We have trespassed against our God, and have married foreign women of the peoples of the land: yet now there is hope for Israel concerning this thing. ^3Now therefore let us make a covenant with our God to put away all the wives, and such as are born of them, according to the counsel of my lord, and of those that tremble at the commandment of our God; and let it be done according to the law. ^4Arise; for the matter belongeth unto thee, and we are with thee: be of good courage, and do it. ^5Then arose Ezra, and made the chiefs of the priests, the Levites, and all Israel, to swear that they would do according to this word. So they sware. ^6Then Ezra rose up from before the house of God, and went into the chamber of Jehohanan the son of Eliashib: and when he came thither, he did eat no bread, nor drink water; for he mourned because of the trespass of them of the captivity. ^7And they made proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem unto all the children of the captivity, that they should gather themselves together unto Jerusalem; ^8and that whosoever came not within three days, according to the counsel of the princes and the elders, all his substance should be forfeited, and himself separated from the assembly of the captivity. ^9Then all the men of Judah and Benjamin gathered themselves together unto Jerusalem within the three days; it was the ninth month, on the twentieth day of the month: and all the people sat in the broad place before the house of God, trembling because of this matter, and for the great rain. ^10And Ezra the priest stood up, and said unto them, Ye have trespassed, and have married foreign women, to increase the guilt of Israel. ^11Now therefore make confession unto Jehovah, the God of your fathers, and do his pleasure; and separate yourselves from the peoples of the land, and from the foreign women. ^12Then all the assembly answered and said with a loud voice, As thou hast said concerning us, so must we do. ^13But the people are many, and it is a time of much rain, and we are not able to stand without: neither is this a work of one day or two; for we have greatly transgressed in this matter. ^14Let now our princes be appointed for all the assembly, and let all them that are in our cities that have married foreign women come at appointed times, and with them the elders of every city, and the judges thereof, until the fierce wrath of our God be turned from us, until this matter be despatched. ^15Only Jonathan the son of Asahel and Jahzeiah the son of Tikvah stood up against this matter: and Meshullam and Shabbethai the Levite helped them. ^16And the children of the captivity did so. And Ezra the priest, with certain heads of fathers' houses, after their fathers' houses, and all of them by their names, were set apart; and they sat down in the first day of the tenth month to examine the matter. ^17And they made an end with all the men that had married foreign women by the first day of the first month. ^18And among the sons of the priests there were found that had married foreign women: namely, of the sons of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and his brethren, Maaseiah, and Eliezer, and Jarib, and Gedaliah. ^19And they gave their hand that they would put away their wives; and being guilty, they offered a ram of the flock for their guilt. ^20And of the sons of Immer: Hanani and Zebadiah. ^21And of the sons of Harim: Maaseiah, and Elijah, and Shemaiah, and Jehiel, and Uzziah. ^22And of the sons of Pashhur: Elioenai, Maaseiah, Ishmael, Nethanel, Jozabad, and Elasah. ^23And of the Levites: Jozabad, and Shimei, and Kelaiah (the same is Kelita), Pethahiah, Judah, and Eliezer. ^24And of the singers: Eliashib. And of the porters: Shallum, and Telem, and Uri. ^25And of Israel: Of the sons of Parosh: Ramiah, and Izziah, and Malchijah, and Mijamin, and Eleazar, and Malchijah, and Benaiah. ^26And of the sons of Elam: Mattaniah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, and Abdi, and Jeremoth, and Elijah. ^27And of the sons of Zattu: Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, and Jeremoth, and Zabad, and Aziza. ^28And of the sons of Bebai: Jehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, Athlai. ^29And of the sons of Bani: Meshullam, Malluch, and Adaiah, Jashub, and Sheal, Jeremoth. ^30And of the sons of Pahath-moab: Adna, and Chelal, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattaniah, Bezalel, and Binnui, and Manasseh. ^31And of the sons of Harim: Eliezer, Isshijah, Malchijah, Shemaiah, Shimeon, ^32Benjamin, Malluch, Shemariah. ^33Of the sons of Hashum: Mattenai, Mattattah, Zabad, Eliphelet, Jeremai, Manasseh, Shimei. ^34Of the sons of Bani: Maadai, Amram, and Uel, ^35Benaiah, Bedeiah, Cheluhi, ^36Vaniah, Meremoth, Eliashib, ^37Mattaniah, Mattenai, and Jaasu, ^38and Bani, and Binnui, Shimei, ^39and Shelemiah, and Nathan, and Adaiah, ^40Machnadebai, Shashai, Sharai, ^41Azarel, and Shelemiah, Shemariah, ^42Shallum, Amariah, Joseph. ^43Of the sons of Nebo: Jeiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Iddo, and Joel, Benaiah. ^44All these had taken foreign wives; and some of them had wives by whom they had children.

Galatians 2

2

^1Then after the space of fourteen years I went up again to Jerusalem with Barnabas, taking Titus also with me. ^2And I went up by revelation; and I laid before them the gospel which I preach among the Gentiles but privately before them who were of repute, lest by any means I should be running, or had run, in vain. ^3But not even Titus who was with me, being a Greek, was compelled to be circumcised: ^4and that because of the false brethren privily brought in, who came in privily to spy out our liberty which we have in Christ Jesus, that they might bring us into bondage: ^5to whom we gave place in the way of subjection, no, not for an hour; that the truth of the gospel might continue with you. ^6But from those who were reputed to be somewhat (whatsoever they were, it maketh no matter to me: God accepteth not man's person)-- they, I say, who were of repute imparted nothing to me: ^7but contrariwise, when they saw that I had been intrusted with the gospel of the uncircumcision, even as Peter with the gospel of the circumcision ^8(for he that wrought for Peter unto the apostleship of the circumcision wrought for me also unto the Gentiles); ^9and when they perceived the grace that was given unto me, James and Cephas and John, they who were reputed to be pillars, gave to me and Barnabas the right hands of fellowship, that we should go unto the Gentiles, and they unto the circumcision; ^10only they would that we should remember the poor; which very thing I was also zealous to do. ^11But when Cephas came to Antioch, I resisted him to the face, because he stood condemned. ^12For before that certain came from James, he ate with the Gentiles; but when they came, he drew back and separated himself, fearing them that were of the circumcision. ^13And the rest of the Jews dissembled likewise with him; insomuch that even Barnabas was carried away with their dissimulation. ^14But when I saw that they walked not uprightly according to the truth of the gospel, I said unto Cephas before them all, If thou, being a Jew, livest as do the Gentiles, and not as do the Jews, how compellest thou the Gentiles to live as do the Jews? ^15We being Jews by nature, and not sinners of the Gentiles, ^16yet knowing that a man is not justified by the works of the law but through faith in Jesus Christ, even we believed on Christ Jesus, that we might be justified by faith in Christ, and not by the works of the law: because by the works of the law shall no flesh be justified. ^17But if, while we sought to be justified in Christ, we ourselves also were found sinners, is Christ a minister of sin? God forbid. ^18For if I build up again those things which I destroyed, I prove myself a transgressor. ^19For I through the law died unto the law, that I might live unto God. ^20I have been crucified with Christ; and it is no longer I that live, but Christ living in me: and that life which I now live in the flesh I live in faith, the faith which is in the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himself up for me. ^21I do not make void the grace of God: for if righteousness is through the law, then Christ died for nought.

Galatians 3

3

^1O foolish Galatians, who did bewitch you, before whose eyes Jesus Christ was openly set forth crucified? ^2This only would I learn from you. Received ye the Spirit by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith? ^3Are ye so foolish? having begun in the Spirit, are ye now perfected in the flesh? ^4Did ye suffer so many things in vain? if it be indeed in vain. ^5He therefore that supplieth to you the Spirit, and worketh miracles among you, doeth he it by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith? ^6Even as Abraham believed God, and it was reckoned unto him for righteousness. ^7Know therefore that they that are of faith, the same are sons of Abraham. ^8And the span, foreseeing that God would justify the Gentiles by faith, preached the gospel beforehand unto Abraham, saying, In thee shall all the nations be blessed. ^9So then they that are of faith are blessed with the faithful Abraham. ^10For as many as are of the works of the law are under a curse: for it is written, Cursed is every one who continueth not in all things that are written in the book of the law, to do them. ^11Now that no man is justified by the law before God, is evident: for, The righteous shall live by faith; ^12and the law is not of faith; but, He that doeth them shall live in them. ^13Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law, having become a curse for us; for it is written, Cursed is every one that hangeth on a tree: ^14that upon the Gentiles might come the blessing of Abraham in Christ Jesus; that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith. ^15Brethren, I speak after the manner of men: Though it be but a man's covenant, yet when it hath been confirmed, no one maketh it void, or addeth thereto. ^16Now to Abraham were the promises spoken, and to his seed. He saith not, And to seeds, as of many; but as of one, And to thy seed, which is Christ. ^17Now this I say: A covenant confirmed beforehand by God, the law, which came four hundred and thirty years after, doth not disannul, so as to make the promise of none effect. ^18For if the inheritance is of the law, it is no more of promise: but God hath granted it to Abraham by promise. ^19What then is the law? It was added because of transgressions, till the seed should come to whom the promise hath been made; and it was ordained through angels by the hand of a mediator. ^20Now a mediator is not a mediator of one; but God is one. ^21Is the law then against the promises of God? God forbid: for if there had been a law given which could make alive, verily righteousness would have been of the law. ^22But the spans shut up all things under sin, that the promise by faith in Jesus Christ might be given to them that believe. ^23But before faith came, we were kept in ward under the law, shut up unto the faith which should afterwards be revealed. ^24So that the law is become our tutor to bring us unto Christ, that we might be justified by faith. ^25But now faith that is come, we are no longer under a tutor. ^26For ye are all sons of God, through faith, in Christ Jesus. ^27For as many of you as were baptized into Christ did put on Christ. ^28There can be neither Jew nor Greek, there can be neither bond nor free, there can be no male and female; for ye all are one man in Christ Jesus. ^29And if ye are Christ's, then are ye Abraham's seed, heirs according to promise.

Galatians 4

4

^1But I say that so long as the heir is a child, he differeth nothing from a bondservant though he is lord of all; ^2but is under guardians and stewards until the day appointed of the father. ^3So we also, when we were children, were held in bondage under the rudiments of the world: ^4but when the fulness of the time came, God sent forth his Son, born of a woman, born under the law, ^5that he might redeem them that were under the law, that we might receive the adoption of sons. ^6And because ye are sons, God sent forth the Spirit of his Son into our hearts, crying, Abba, Father. ^7So that thou art no longer a bondservant, but a son; and if a son, then an heir through God. ^8Howbeit at that time, not knowing God, ye were in bondage to them that by nature are no gods: ^9but now that ye have come to know God, or rather to be known by God, how turn ye back again to the weak and beggarly rudiments, whereunto ye desire to be in bondage over again? ^10Ye observe days, and months, and seasons, and years. ^11I am afraid of you, lest by any means I have bestowed labor upon you in vain. ^12I beseech you, brethren, become as I am, for I also am become as ye are. Ye did me no wrong: ^13but ye know that because of an infirmity of the flesh I preached the gospel unto you the first time: ^14and that which was a temptation to you in my flesh ye despised not, nor rejected; but ye received me as an angel of God, even as Christ Jesus. ^15Where then is that gratulation of yourselves? for I bear you witness, that, if possible, ye would have plucked out your eyes and given them to me. ^16So then am I become your enemy, by telling you the truth? ^17They zealously seek you in no good way; nay, they desire to shut you out, that ye may seek them. ^18But it is good to be zealously sought in a good matter at all times, and not only when I am present with you. ^19My little children, of whom I am again in travail until Christ be formed in you-- ^20but I could wish to be present with you now, and to change my tone; for I am perplexed about you. ^21Tell me, ye that desire to be under the law, do ye not hear the law? ^22For it is written, that Abraham had two sons, one by the handmaid, and one by the freewoman. ^23Howbeit the son by the handmaid is born after the flesh; but the son by the freewoman is born through promise. ^24Which things contain an allegory: for these women are two covenants; one from mount Sinai, bearing children unto bondage, which is Hagar. ^25Now this Hagar is mount Sinai in Arabia and answereth to the Jerusalem that now is: for she is in bondage with her children. ^26But the Jerusalem that is above is free, which is our mother. ^27For it is written,

Rejoice, thou barren that bearest not;

Break forth and cry, thou that travailest not:

For more are the children of the desolate than of her that hath the husband.

^28Now we, brethren, as Isaac was, are children of promise. ^29But as then he that was born after the flesh persecuted him that was born after the Spirit, so also it is now. ^30Howbeit what saith the span? Cast out the handmaid and her son: for the son of the handmaid shall not inherit with the son of the freewoman. ^31Wherefore, brethren, we are not children of a handmaid, but of the freewoman.

Galatians 5

5

^1For freedom did Christ set us free: stand fast therefore, and be not entangled again in a yoke of bondage. ^2Behold, I Paul say unto you, that, if ye receive circumcision, Christ will profit you nothing. ^3Yea, I testify again to every man that receiveth circumcision, that he is a debtor to do the whole law. ^4Ye are severed from Christ, ye would be justified by the law; ye are fallen away from grace. ^5For we through the Spirit by faith wait for the hope of righteousness. ^6For in Christ Jesus neither circumcision availeth anything, nor uncircumcision; but faith working through love. ^7Ye were running well; who hindered you that ye should not obey the truth? ^8This persuasion came not of him that calleth you. ^9A little leaven leaveneth the whole lump. ^10I have confidence to you-ward in the Lord, that ye will be none otherwise minded: but he that troubleth you shall bear his judgment, whosoever he be. ^11But I, brethren, if I still preach circumcision, why am I still persecuted? then hath the stumbling-block of the cross been done away. ^12I would that they that unsettle you would even go beyond circumcision. ^13For ye, brethren, were called for freedom; only use not your freedom for an occasion to the flesh, but through love be servants one to another. ^14For the whole law is fulfilled in one word, even in this: Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. ^15But if ye bite and devour one another, take heed that ye be not consumed one of another. ^16But I say, walk by the Spirit, and ye shall not fulfil the lust of the flesh. ^17For the flesh lusteth against the Spirit, and the Spirit against the flesh; for these are contrary the one to the other; that ye may not do the things that ye would. ^18But if ye are led by the Spirit, ye are not under the law. ^19Now the works of the flesh are manifest, which are these: fornication, uncleanness, lasciviousness, ^20idolatry, sorcery, enmities, strife, jealousies, wraths, factions, divisions, parties, ^21envyings, drunkenness, revellings, and such like; of which I forewarn you, even as I did forewarn you, that they who practise such things shall not inherit the kingdom of God. ^22But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, longsuffering, kindness, goodness, faithfulness, ^23meekness, self-control; against such there is no law. ^24And they that are of Christ Jesus have crucified the flesh with the passions and the lusts thereof. ^25If we live by the Spirit, by the Spirit let us also walk. ^26Let us not become vainglorious, provoking one another, envying one another.

Galatians 6

6

^1Brethren, even if a man be overtaken in any trespass, ye who are spiritual, restore such a one in a spirit of gentleness; looking to thyself, lest thou also be tempted. ^2Bear ye one another's burdens, and so fulfil the law of Christ. ^3For if a man thinketh himself to be something when he is nothing, he deceiveth himself. ^4But let each man prove his own work, and then shall he have his glorying in regard of himself alone, and not of his neighbor. ^5For each man shall bear his own burden. ^6But let him that is taught in the word communicate unto him that teacheth in all good things. ^7Be not deceived; God is not mocked: for whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap. ^8For he that soweth unto his own flesh shall of the flesh reap corruption; but he that soweth unto the Spirit shall of the Spirit reap eternal life. ^9And let us not be weary in well-doing: for in due season we shall reap, if we faint not. ^10So then, as we have opportunity, let us work that which is good toward all men, and especially toward them that are of the household of the faith. ^11See with how large letters I write unto you with mine own hand. ^12As many as desire to make a fair show in the flesh, they compel you to be circumcised; only that they may not be persecuted for the cross of Christ. ^13For not even they who receive circumcision do themselves keep the law; but they desire to have you circumcised, that they may glory in your flesh. ^14But far be it from me to glory, save in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, through which the world hath been crucified unto me, and I unto the world. ^15For neither is circumcision anything, nor uncircumcision, but a new creature. ^16And as many as shall walk by this rule, peace be upon them, and mercy, and upon the Israel of God. ^17Henceforth, let no man trouble me; for I bear branded on my body the marks of Jesus. ^18The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit, brethren. Amen.

Genesis 2

2

^1And the heavens and the earth were finished, and all the host of them. ^2And on the seventh day God finished his work which he had made; and he rested on the seventh day from all his work which he had made. ^3And God blessed the seventh day, and hallowed it; because that in it he rested from all his work which God had created and made.

^4These are the generations of the heavens and of the earth when they were created, in the day that Jehovah God made earth and heaven. ^5And no plant of the field was yet in the earth, and no herb of the field had yet sprung up; for Jehovah God had not caused it to rain upon the earth: and there was not a man to till the ground; ^6but there went up a mist from the earth, and watered the whole face of the ground. ^7And Jehovah God formed man of the dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man became a living soul. ^8And Jehovah God planted a garden eastward, in Eden; and there he put the man whom he had formed. ^9And out of the ground made Jehovah God to grow every tree that is pleasant to the sight, and good for food; the tree of life also in the midst of the garden, and the tree of the knowledge of good and evil. ^10And a river went out of Eden to water the garden; and from thence it was parted, and became four heads. ^11The name of the first is Pishon: that is it which compasseth the whole land of Havilah, where there is gold; ^12and the gold of that land is good: there is bdellium and the onyx stone. ^13And the name of the second river is Gihon: the same is it that compasseth the whole land of Cush. ^14And the name of the third river is Hiddekel: that is it which goeth in front of Assyria. And the fourth river is the Euphrates. ^15And Jehovah God took the man, and put him into the garden of Eden to dress it and to keep it. ^16And Jehovah God commanded the man, saying, Of every tree of the garden thou mayest freely eat: ^17but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, thou shalt not eat of it: for in the day that thou eatest thereof thou shalt surely die.

^18And Jehovah God said, It is not good that the man should be alone; I will make him a help meet for him. ^19And out of the ground Jehovah God formed every beast of the field, and every bird of the heavens; and brought them unto the man to see what he would call them: and whatsoever the man called every living creature, that was the name thereof. ^20And the man gave names to all cattle, and to the birds of the heavens, and to every beast of the field; but for man there was not found a help meet for him. ^21And Jehovah God caused a deep sleep to fall upon the man, and he slept; and he took one of his ribs, and closed up the flesh instead thereof: ^22and the rib, which Jehovah God had taken from the man, made he a woman, and brought her unto the man. ^23And the man said, This is now bone of my bones, and flesh of my flesh: she shall be called Woman, because she was taken out of Man. ^24Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother, and shall cleave unto his wife: and they shall be one flesh. ^25And they were both naked, the man and his wife, and were not ashamed.

Genesis 3

3

^1Now the serpent was more subtle than any beast of the field which Jehovah God had made. And he said unto the woman, Yea, hath God said, Ye shall not eat of any tree of the garden? ^2And the woman said unto the serpent, Of the fruit of the trees of the garden we may eat: ^3but of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the garden, God hath said, Ye shall not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die. ^4And the serpent said unto the woman, Ye shall not surely die: ^5for God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes shall be opened, and ye shall be as God, knowing good and evil. ^6And when the woman saw that the tree was good for food, and that it was a delight to the eyes, and that the tree was to be desired to make one wise, she took of the fruit thereof, and did eat; and she gave also unto her husband with her, and he did eat. ^7And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked; and they sewed fig-leaves together, and made themselves aprons. ^8And they heard the voice of Jehovah God walking in the garden in the cool of the day: and the man and his wife hid themselves from the presence of Jehovah God amongst the trees of the garden.

^9And Jehovah God called unto the man, and said unto him, Where art thou? ^10And he said, I heard thy voice in the garden, and I was afraid, because I was naked; and I hid myself. ^11And he said, Who told thee that thou wast naked? Hast thou eaten of the tree, whereof I commanded thee that thou shouldest not eat? ^12And the man said, The woman whom thou gavest to be with me, she gave me of the tree, and I did eat. ^13And Jehovah God said unto the woman, What is this thou hast done? And the woman said, The serpent beguiled me, and I did eat. ^14And Jehovah God said unto the serpent, Because thou hast done this, cursed art thou above all cattle, and above every beast of the field; upon thy belly shalt thou go, and dust shalt thou eat all the days of thy life: ^15and I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy seed and her seed: he shall bruise thy head, and thou shalt bruise his heel. ^16Unto the woman he said, I will greatly multiply thy pain and thy conception; in pain thou shalt bring forth children; and thy desire shall be to thy husband, and he shall rule over thee. ^17And unto Adam he said, Because thou hast hearkened unto the voice of thy wife, and hast eaten of the tree, of which I commanded thee, saying, Thou shalt not eat of it: cursed is the ground for thy sake; in toil shalt thou eat of it all the days of thy life; ^18thorns also and thistles shall it bring forth to thee; and thou shalt eat the herb of the field; ^19in the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground; for out of it wast thou taken: for dust thou art, and unto dust shalt thou return. ^20And the man called his wife's name Eve; because she was the mother of all living. ^21And Jehovah God made for Adam and for his wife coats of skins, and clothed them.

^22And Jehovah God said, Behold, the man is become as one of us, to know good and evil; and now, lest he put forth his hand, and take also of the tree of life, and eat, and live for ever- ^23therefore Jehovah God sent him forth from the garden of Eden, to till the ground from whence he was taken. ^24So he drove out the man; and he placed at the east of the garden of Eden the Cherubim, and the flame of a sword which turned every way, to keep the way of the tree of life.

Genesis 4

4

^1And the man knew Eve his wife; and she conceived, and bare Cain, and said, I have gotten a man with the help of Jehovah. ^2And again she bare his brother Abel. And Abel was a keeper of sheep, but Cain was a tiller of the ground. ^3And in process of time it came to pass, that Cain brought of the fruit of the ground an offering unto Jehovah. ^4And Abel, he also brought of the firstlings of his flock and of the fat thereof. And Jehovah had respect unto Abel and to his offering: ^5but unto Cain and to his offering he had not respect. And Cain was very wroth, and his countenance fell. ^6And Jehovah said unto Cain, Why art thou wroth? and why is thy countenance fallen? ^7If thou doest well, shall it not be lifted up? and if thou doest not well, sin coucheth at the door: and unto thee shall be its desire, but do thou rule over it. ^8And Cain told Abel his brother. And it came to pass, when they were in the field, that Cain rose up against Abel his brother, and slew him.

^9And Jehovah said unto Cain, Where is Abel thy brother? And he said, I know not: am I my brother's keeper? ^10And he said, What hast thou done? the voice of thy brother's blood crieth unto me from the ground. ^11And now cursed art thou from the ground, which hath opened its mouth to receive thy brother's blood from thy hand; ^12when thou tillest the ground, it shall not henceforth yield unto thee its strength; a fugitive and a wanderer shalt thou be in the earth. ^13And Cain said unto Jehovah, My punishment is greater than I can bear. ^14Behold, thou hast driven me out this day from the face of the ground; and from thy face shall I be hid; and I shall be a fugitive and a wanderer in the earth; and it will come to pass, that whosoever findeth me will slay me. ^15And Jehovah said unto him, Therefore whosoever slayeth Cain, vengeance shall be taken on him sevenfold. And Jehovah appointed a sign for Cain, lest any finding him should smite him.

^16And Cain went out from the presence of Jehovah, and dwelt in the land of Nod, on the east of Eden. ^17And Cain knew his wife; and she conceived, and bare Enoch: and he builded a city, and called the name of the city, after the name of his son, Enoch. ^18And unto Enoch was born Irad: and Irad begat Mehujael: and Mehujael begat Methushael; and Methushael begat Lamech. ^19And Lamech took unto him two wives: the name of the one was Adah, and the name of the other Zillah. ^20And Adah bare Jabal: he was the father of such as dwell in tents and have cattle. ^21And his brother's name was Jubal: he was the father of all such as handle the harp and pipe. ^22And Zillah, she also bare Tubal-cain, the forger of every cutting instrument of brass and iron: and the sister of Tubal-cain was Naamah. ^23And Lamech said unto his wives:

Adah and Zillah, hear my voice;

Ye wives of Lamech, hearken unto my speech:

For I have slain a man for wounding me,

And a young man for bruising me:

^24If Cain shall be avenged sevenfold,

Truly Lamech seventy and sevenfold.

^25And Adam knew his wife again; and she bare a son, and called his name Seth. For, said she, God hath appointed me another seed instead of Abel; for Cain slew him. ^26And to Seth, to him also there was born a son; and he called his name Enosh. Then began men to call upon the name of Jehovah.

Genesis 6

6

^1And it came to pass, when men began to multiply on the face of the ground, and daughters were born unto them, ^2that the sons of God saw the daughters of men that they were fair; and they took them wives of all that they chose. ^3And Jehovah said, My spirit shall not strive with man for ever, for that he also is flesh: yet shall his days be a hundred and twenty years. ^4The Nephilim were in the earth in those days, and also after that, when the sons of God came unto the daughters of men, and they bare children to them: the same were the mighty men that were of old, the men of renown.

^5And Jehovah saw that the wickedness of man was great in the earth, and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually. ^6And it repented Jehovah that he had made man on the earth, and it grieved him at his heart. ^7And Jehovah said, I will destroy man whom I have created from the face of the ground; both man, and beast, and creeping things, and birds of the heavens; for it repenteth me that I have made them. ^8But Noah found favor in the eyes of Jehovah.

^9These are the generations of Noah. Noah was a righteous man, and perfect in his generations: Noah walked with God. ^10And Noah begat three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth. ^11And the earth was corrupt before God, and the earth was filled with violence. ^12And God saw the earth, and, behold, it was corrupt; for all flesh had corrupted their way upon the earth.

^13And God said unto Noah, The end of all flesh is come before me; for the earth is filled with violence through them; and, behold, I will destroy them with the earth. ^14Make thee an ark of gopher wood; rooms shalt thou make in the ark, and shalt pitch it within and without with pitch. ^15And this is how thou shalt make it: the length of the ark three hundred cubits, the breadth of it fifty cubits, and the height of it thirty cubits. ^16A light shalt thou make to the ark, and to a cubit shalt thou finish it upward; and the door of the ark shalt thou set in the side thereof; with lower, second, and third stories shalt thou make it. ^17And I, behold, I do bring the flood of waters upon this earth, to destroy all flesh, wherein is the breath of life, from under heaven; everything that is in the earth shall die. ^18But I will establish my covenant with thee; and thou shalt come into the ark, thou, and thy sons, and thy wife, and thy sons' wives with thee. ^19And of every living thing of all flesh, two of every sort shalt thou bring into the ark, to keep them alive with thee; they shall be male and female. ^20Of the birds after their kind, and of the cattle after their kind, of every creeping thing of the ground after its kind, two of every sort shall come unto thee, to keep them alive. ^21And take thou unto thee of all food that is eaten, and gather it to thee; and it shall be for food for thee, and for them. ^22Thus did Noah; according to all that God commanded him, so did he.

Genesis 7

7

^1And Jehovah said unto Noah, Come thou and all thy house into the ark; for thee have I seen righteous before me in this generation. ^2Of every clean beast thou shalt take to thee seven and seven, the male and his female; and of the beasts that are not clean two, the male and his female: ^3of the birds also of the heavens, seven and seven, male and female, to keep seed alive upon the face of all the earth. ^4For yet seven days, and I will cause it to rain upon the earth forty days and forty nights; and every living thing that I have made will I destroy from off the face of the ground. ^5And Noah did according unto all that Jehovah commanded him.

^6And Noah was six hundred years old when the flood of waters was upon the earth. ^7And Noah went in, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons' wives with him, into the ark, because of the waters of the flood. ^8Of clean beasts, and of beasts that are not clean, and of birds, and of everything that creepeth upon the ground, ^9there went in two and two unto Noah into the ark, male and female, as God commanded Noah. ^10And it came to pass after the seven days, that the waters of the flood were upon the earth. ^11In the six hundredth year of Noah's life, in the second month, on the seventeenth day of the month, on the same day were all the fountains of the great deep broken up, and the windows of heaven were opened. ^12And the rain was upon the earth forty days and forty nights.

^13In the selfsame day entered Noah, and Shem, and Ham, and Japheth, the sons of Noah, and Noah's wife, and the three wives of his sons with them, into the ark; ^14they, and every beast after its kind, and all the cattle after their kind, and every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth after its kind, and every bird after its kind, every bird of every sort. ^15And they went in unto Noah into the ark, two and two of all flesh wherein is the breath of life. ^16And they that went in, went in male and female of all flesh, as God commanded him: and Jehovah shut him in. ^17And the flood was forty days upon the earth; and the waters increased, and bare up the ark, and it was lifted up above the earth. ^18And the waters prevailed, and increased greatly upon the earth; and the ark went upon the face of the waters. ^19And the waters prevailed exceedingly upon the earth; and all the high mountains that were under the whole heaven were covered. ^20Fifteen cubits upward did the waters prevail; and the mountains were covered. ^21And all flesh died that moved upon the earth, both birds, and cattle, and beasts, and every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth, and every man: ^22all in whose nostrils was the breath of the spirit of life, of all that was on the dry land, died. ^23And every living thing was destroyed that was upon the face of the ground, both man, and cattle, and creeping things, and birds of the heavens; and they were destroyed from the earth: and Noah only was left, and they that were with him in the ark. ^24And the waters prevailed upon the earth a hundred and fifty days.

Genesis 8

8

^1And God remembered Noah, and all the beasts, and all the cattle that were with him in the ark: and God made a wind to pass over the earth, and the waters assuaged; ^2the fountains also of the deep and the windows of heaven were stopped, and the rain from heaven was restrained; ^3and the waters returned from off the earth continually: and after the end of a hundred and fifty days the waters decreased. ^4And the ark rested in the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, upon the mountains of Ararat. ^5And the waters decreased continually until the tenth month: in the tenth month, on the first day of the month, were the tops of the mountains seen.

^6And it came to pass at the end of forty days, that Noah opened the window of the ark which he had made: ^7and he sent forth a raven, and it went forth to and fro, until the waters were dried up from off the earth. ^8And he sent forth a dove from him, to see if the waters were abated from off the face of the ground; ^9but the dove found no rest for the sole of her foot, and she returned unto him to the ark; for the waters were on the face of the whole earth: and he put forth his hand, and took her, and brought her in unto him into the ark. ^10And he stayed yet other seven days; and again he sent forth the dove out of the ark; ^11and the dove came in to him at eventide; and, lo, in her mouth an olive-leaf plucked off: so Noah knew that the waters were abated from off the earth. ^12And he stayed yet other seven days, and sent forth the dove; and she returned not again unto him any more.

^13And it came to pass in the six hundred and first year, in the first month, the first day of the month, the waters were dried up from off the earth: and Noah removed the covering of the ark, and looked, and, behold, the face of the ground was dried. ^14And in the second month, on the seven and twentieth day of the month, was the earth dry. ^15And God spake unto Noah, saying, ^16Go forth from the ark, thou, and thy wife, and thy sons, and thy sons' wives with thee. ^17Bring forth with thee every living thing that is with thee of all flesh, both birds, and cattle, and every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth; that they may breed abundantly in the earth, and be fruitful, and multiply upon the earth. ^18And Noah went forth, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons' wives with him: ^19every beast, every creeping thing, and every bird, whatsoever moveth upon the earth, after their families, went forth out of the ark.

^20And Noah builded an altar unto Jehovah, and took of every clean beast, and of every clean bird, and offered burnt-offerings on the altar. ^21And Jehovah smelled the sweet savor; and Jehovah said in his heart, I will not again curse the ground any more for man's sake, for that the imagination of man's heart is evil from his youth; neither will I again smite any more everything living, as I have done. ^22While the earth remaineth, seedtime and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night shall not cease.

Genesis 9

9

^1And God blessed Noah and his sons, and said unto them, Be fruitful, and multiply, and replenish the earth. ^2And the fear of you and the dread of you shall be upon every beast of the earth, and upon every bird of the heavens; With all wherewith the ground teemeth, and all the fishes of the sea, into your hand are they delivered. ^3Every moving thing that liveth shall be food for you; As the green herb have I given you all. ^4But flesh with the life thereof, which is the blood thereof, shall ye not eat. ^5And surely your blood, the blood of your lives, will I require; At the hand of every beast will I require it. And at the hand of man, even at the hand of every man's brother, will I require the life of man. ^6Whoso sheddeth man's blood, by man shall his blood be shed: For in the image of God made he man. ^7And you, be ye fruitful, and multiply; Bring forth abundantly in the earth, and multiply therein.

^8And God spake unto Noah, and to his sons with him, saying, ^9And I, behold, I establish my covenant with you, and with your seed after you; ^10and with every living creature that is with you, the birds, the cattle, and every beast of the earth with you. Of all that go out of the ark, even every beast of the earth. ^11And I will establish my covenant with you; neither shall all flesh be cut off any more by the waters of the flood; neither shall there any more be a flood to destroy the earth. ^12And God said, This is the token of the covenant which I make between me and you and every living creature that is with you, for perpetual generations: ^13I do set my bow in the cloud, and it shall be for a token of a covenant between me and the earth. ^14And it shall come to pass, when I bring a cloud over the earth, that the bow shall be seen in the cloud, ^15and I will remember my covenant, which is between me and you and every living creature of all flesh; and the waters shall no more become a flood to destroy all flesh. ^16And the bow shall be in the cloud; and I will look upon it, that I may remember the everlasting covenant between God and every living creature of all flesh that is upon the earth. ^17And God said unto Noah, This is the token of the covenant which I have established between me and all flesh that is upon the earth.

^18And the sons of Noah, that went forth from the ark, were Shem, and Ham, and Japheth: and Ham is the father of Canaan. ^19These three were the sons of Noah: and of these was the whole earth overspread.

^20And Noah began to be a husbandman, and planted a vineyard: ^21and he drank of the wine, and was drunken. And he was uncovered within his tent. ^22And Ham, the father of Canaan, saw the nakedness of his father, and told his two brethren without. ^23And Shem and Japheth took a garment, and laid it upon both their shoulders, and went backward, and covered the nakedness of their father. And their faces were backward, and they saw not their father's nakedness. ^24And Noah awoke from his wine, and knew what his youngest son had done unto him. ^25And he said,

Cursed be Canaan;

A servant of servants shall he be unto his brethren.

^26And he said,

Blessed be Jehovah, the God of Shem;

And let Canaan be his servant.

^27God enlarge Japheth,

And let him dwell in the tents of Shem;

And let Canaan be his servant.

^28And Noah lived after the flood three hundred and fifty years. ^29And all the days of Noah were nine hundred and fifty years: And he died.

Genesis 11

11

^1And the whole earth was of one language and of one speech. ^2And it came to pass, as they journeyed east, that they found a plain in the land of Shinar; and they dwelt there. ^3And they said one to another, Come, let us make brick, and burn them thoroughly. And they had brick for stone, and slime had they for mortar. ^4And they said, Come, let us build us a city, and a tower, whose top may reach unto heaven, and let us make us a name; lest we be scattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth. ^5And Jehovah came down to see the city and the tower, which the children of men builded. ^6And Jehovah said, Behold, they are one people, and they have all one language; and this is what they begin to do: and now nothing will be withholden from them, which they purpose to do. ^7Come, let us go down, and there confound their language, that they may not understand one another's speech. ^8So Jehovah scattered them abroad from thence upon the face of all the earth: and they left off building the city. ^9Therefore was the name of it called Babel; because Jehovah did there confound the language of all the earth: and from thence did Jehovah scatter them abroad upon the face of all the earth.

^10These are the generations of Shem. Shem was a hundred years old, and begat Arpachshad two years after the flood. ^11and Shem lived after he begat Arpachshad five hundred years, and begat sons and daughters.

^12And Arpachshad lived five and thirty years, and begat Shelah. ^13and Arpachshad lived after he begat Shelah four hundred and three years, and begat sons and daughters.

^14And Shelah lived thirty years, and begat Eber: ^15and Shelah lived after he begat Eber four hundred and three years, and begat sons and daughters.

^16And Eber lived four and thirty years, and begat Peleg: ^17and Eber lived after he begat Peleg four hundred and thirty years, and begat sons and daughters.

^18And Peleg lived thirty years, and begat Reu: ^19and Peleg lived after he begat Reu two hundred and nine years, and begat sons and daughters.

^20And Reu lived two and thirty years, and begat Serug: ^21and Reu lived after he begat Serug two hundred and seven years, and begat sons and daughters.

^22And Serug lived thirty years, and begat Nahor: ^23and Serug lived after he begat Nahor two hundred years, and begat sons and daughters.

^24And Nahor lived nine and twenty years, and begat Terah: ^25and Nahor lived after he begat Terah a hundred and nineteen years, and begat sons and daughters.

^26And Terah lived seventy years, and begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran.

^27Now these are the generations of Terah. Terah begat Abram, Nahor, and Haran. And Haran begat Lot. ^28And Haran died before his father Terah in the land of his nativity, in Ur of the Chaldees. ^29And Abram and Nahor took them wives: The name of Abram's wife was Sarai; and the name of Nahor's wife, Milcah, the daughter of Haran, the father of Milcah, and the father of Iscah. ^30And Sarai was barren; She had no child. ^31And Terah took Abram his son, and Lot the son of Haran, his son's son, and Sarai his daughter-in-law, his son Abram's wife; and they went forth with them from Ur of the Chaldees, to go into the land of Canaan; and they came unto Haran, and dwelt there. ^32And the days of Terah were two hundred and five years: and Terah died in Haran.

Genesis 12

12

^1Now Jehovah said unto Abram, Get thee out of thy country, and from thy kindred, and from thy father's house, unto the land that I will show thee: ^2and I will make of thee a great nation, and I will bless thee, and make they name great; and be thou a blessing; ^3and I will bless them that bless thee, and him that curseth thee will I curse: and in thee shall all the families of the earth be blessed. ^4So Abram went, as Jehovah had spoken unto him; and Lot went with him: and Abram was seventy and five years old when he departed out of Haran. ^5And Abram took Sarai his wife, and Lot his brother's son, and all their substance that they had gathered, and the souls that they had gotten in Haran; and they went forth to go into the land of Canaan; and into the land of Canaan they came. ^6And Abram passed through the land unto the place of Shechem, unto the oak of Moreh. And the Canaanite was then in the land. ^7And Jehovah appeared unto Abram, and said, Unto thy seed will I give this land: and there builded he an altar unto Jehovah, who appeared unto him. ^8And he removed from thence unto the mountain on the east of Beth-el, and pitched his tent, having Beth-el on the west, and Ai on the east: and there he builded an altar unto Jehovah, and called upon the name of Jehovah. ^9And Abram journeyed, going on still toward the South.

^10And there was a famine in the land: and Abram went down into Egypt to sojourn there; for the famine was sore in the land. ^11And it came to pass, when he was come near to enter into Egypt, that he said unto Sarai his wife, Behold now, I know that thou art a fair woman to look upon: ^12and it will come to pass, when the Egyptians shall see thee, that they will say, This is his wife: and they will kill me, but they will save thee alive. ^13Say, I pray thee, thou art my sister; that it may be well with me for thy sake, and that my soul may live because of thee. ^14And it came to pass, that, when Abram was come into Egypt, the Egyptians beheld the woman that she was very fair. ^15And the princes of Pharaoh saw her, and praised her to Pharaoh: and the woman was taken into Pharaoh's house. ^16And he dealt well with Abram for her sake: and he had sheep, and oxen, and he-asses, and men-servants, and maid-servants, and she-asses, and camels. ^17And Jehovah plagued Pharaoh and his house with great plagues because of Sarai, Abram's wife. ^18And Pharaoh called Abram, and said, What is this that thou hast done unto me? why didst thou not tell me that she was thy wife? ^19why saidst thou, She is my sister, so that I took her to be my wife? now therefore behold thy wife, take her, and go thy way. ^20And Pharaoh gave men charge concerning him: and they brought him on the way, and his wife, and all that he had.

Genesis 13

13

^1And Abram went up out of Egypt, he, and his wife, and all that he had, and Lot with him, into the South. ^2And Abram was very rich in cattle, in silver, and in gold. ^3And he went on his journeys from the South even to Beth-el, unto the place where his tent had been at the beginning, between Beth-el and Ai, ^4unto the place of the altar, which he had made there at the first: and there Abram called on the name of Jehovah. ^5And Lot also, who went with Abram, had flocks, and herds, and tents. ^6And the land was not able to bear them, that they might dwell together: for their substance was great, so that they could not dwell together. ^7And there was a strife between the herdsmen of Abram's cattle and the herdsmen of Lot's cattle: and the Canaanite and the Perizzite dwelt then in the land. ^8And Abram said unto Lot, Let there be no strife, I pray thee, between me and thee, and between my herdsmen and thy herdsmen; for we are brethren. ^9Is not the whole land before thee? separate thyself, I pray thee, from me. If thou wilt take the left hand, then I will go to the right. Or if thou take the right hand, then I will go to the left. ^10And Lot lifted up his eyes, and beheld all the Plain of the Jordan, that it was well watered every where, before Jehovah destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah, like the garden of Jehovah, like the land of Egypt, as thou goest unto Zoar. ^11So Lot chose him all the Plain of the Jordan; and Lot journeyed east: and they separated themselves the one from the other. ^12Abram dwelt in the land of Canaan, and Lot dwelt in the cities of the Plain, and moved his tent as far as Sodom. ^13Now the men of Sodom were wicked and sinners against Jehovah exceedingly.

^14And Jehovah said unto Abram, after that Lot was separated from him, Lift up now thine eyes, and look from the place where thou art, northward and southward and eastward and westward: ^15for all the land which thou seest, to thee will I give it, and to thy seed for ever. ^16And I will make thy seed as the dust of the earth: So that if a man can number the dust of the earth, then may thy seed also be numbered. ^17Arise, walk through the land in the length of it and in the breadth of it; for unto thee will I give it. ^18And Abram moved his tent, and came and dwelt by the oaks of Mamre, which are in Hebron, and built there an altar unto Jehovah.

Genesis 14

14

^1And it came to pass in the days of Amraphel king of Shinar, Arioch king of Ellasar, Chedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of Goiim, ^2that they made war with Bera king of Sodom, and with Birsha king of Gomorrah, Shinab king of Admah, and Shemeber king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (the same is Zoar). ^3All these joined together in the vale of Siddim (the same is the Salt Sea). ^4Twelve years they served Chedorlaomer, and in the thirteenth year they rebelled. ^5And in the fourteenth year came Chedorlaomer, and the kings that were with him, and smote the Rephaim in Ashteroth-karnaim, and the Zuzim in Ham, and the Emim in Shaveh-kiriathaim, ^6and the Horites in their mount Seir, unto Elparan, which is by the wilderness. ^7And they returned, and came to En-mishpat (the same is Kadesh), and smote all the country of the Amalekites, and also the Amorites, that dwelt in Hazazon-tamar. ^8And there went out the king of Sodom, and the king of Gomorrah, and the king of Admah, and the king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (the same is Zoar); and they set the battle in array against them in the vale of Siddim; ^9against Chedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of Goiim, and Amraphel king of Shinar, and Arioch king of Ellasar; four kings against the five. ^10Now the vale of Siddim was full of slime pits; and the kings of Sodom and Gomorrah fled, and they fell there, and they that remained fled to the mountain. ^11And they took all the goods of Sodom and Gomorrah, and all their victuals, and went their way. ^12And they took Lot, Abram's brother's son, who dwelt in Sodom, and his goods, and departed.

^13And there came one that had escaped, and told Abram the Hebrew: now he dwelt by the oaks of Mamre, the Amorite, brother of Eshcol, and brother of Aner; and these were confederate with Abram. ^14And when Abram heard that his brother was taken captive, he led forth his trained men, born in his house, three hundred and eighteen, and pursued as far as Dan. ^15And he divided himself against them by night, he and his servants, and smote them, and pursued them unto Hobah, which is on the left hand of Damascus. ^16And he brought back all the goods, and also brought back his brother Lot, and his goods, and the women also, and the people.

^17And the king of Sodom went out to meet him, after his return from the slaughter of Chedorlaomer and the kings that were with him, at the vale of Shaveh (the same is the King's Vale). ^18And Melchizedek king of Salem brought forth bread and wine: and he was priest of God Most High. ^19And he blessed him, and said, Blessed be Abram of God Most High, possessor of heaven and earth: ^20and blessed be God Most High, who hath delivered thine enemies into thy hand. And he gave him a tenth of all. ^21And the king of Sodom said unto Abram, Give me the persons, and take the goods to thyself. ^22And Abram said to the king of Sodom, I have lifted up my hand unto Jehovah, God Most High, possessor of heaven and earth, ^23that I will not take a thread nor a shoe-latchet nor aught that is thine, lest thou shouldest say, I have made Abram rich: ^24save only that which the young men have eaten, and the portion of the men that went with me, Aner, Eshcol, and Mamre. Let them take their portion.

Genesis 15

15

^1After these things the word of Jehovah came unto Abram in a vision, saying, Fear not, Abram: I am thy shield, and thy exceeding great reward. ^2And Abram said, O Lord Jehovah, what wilt thou give me, seeing I go childless, and he that shall be possessor of my house is Eliezer of Damascus? ^3And Abram said, Behold, to me thou hast given no seed: and, lo, one born in my house is mine heir. ^4And, behold, the word of Jehovah came unto him, saying, This man shall not be thine heir; But he that shall come forth out of thine own bowels shall be thine heir. ^5And he brought him forth abroad, and said, Look now toward heaven, and number the stars, if thou be able to number them: and he said unto him, So shall thy seed be. ^6And he believed in Jehovah; and he reckoned it to him for righteousness. ^7And he said unto him, I am Jehovah that brought thee out of Ur of the Chaldees, to give thee this land to inherit it. ^8And he said, O Lord Jehovah, whereby shall I know that I shall inherit it? ^9And he said unto him, Take me a heifer three years old, and a she-goat three years old, and a ram three years old, and a turtle-dove, and a young pigeon. ^10And he took him all these, and divided them in the midst, and laid each half over against the other: but the birds divided he not. ^11And the birds of prey came down upon the carcasses, and Abram drove them away.

^12And when the sun was going down, a deep sleep fell upon Abram; and, lo, a horror of great darkness fell upon him. ^13And he said unto Abram, Know of a surety that thy seed shall be sojourners in a land that is not theirs, and shall serve them; and they shall afflict them four hundred years; ^14and also that nation, whom they shall serve, will I judge: and afterward shall they come out with great substance. ^15But thou shalt go to thy fathers in peace; thou shalt be buried in a good old age. ^16And in the fourth generation they shall come hither again; for the iniquity of the Amorite is not yet full. ^17And it came to pass, that, when the sun went down, and it was dark, behold, a smoking furnace, and a flaming torch that passed between these pieces. ^18In that day Jehovah made a covenant with Abram, saying, Unto thy seed have I given this land, from the river of Egypt unto the great river, the river Euphrates: ^19the Kenite, and the Kenizzite, and the Kadmonite, ^20and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Rephaim, ^21and the Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Girgashite, and the Jebusite.

Genesis 16

16

^1Now Sarai, Abram's wife, bare him no children: and she had a handmaid, an Egyptian, whose name was Hagar. ^2And Sarai said unto Abram, Behold now, Jehovah hath restrained me from bearing; go in, I pray thee, unto my handmaid; it may be that I shall obtain children by her. And Abram hearkened to the voice of Sarai. ^3And Sarai, Abram's wife, took Hagar the Egyptian, her handmaid, after Abram had dwelt ten years in the land of Canaan, and gave her to Abram her husband to be his wife. ^4And he went in unto Hagar, and she conceived: and when she saw that she had conceived, her mistress was despised in her eyes. ^5And Sarai said unto Abram, My wrong be upon thee: I gave my handmaid into they bosom; and when she saw that she had conceived, I was despised in her eyes: Jehovah judge between me and thee. ^6But Abram said unto Sarai, Behold, thy maid is in thy hand; do to her that which is good in thine eyes. And Sarai dealt hardly with her, and she fled from her face.

^7And the angel of Jehovah found her by a fountain of water in the wilderness, by the fountain in the way to Shur. ^8And he said, Hagar, Sarai's handmaid, whence camest thou? and whither goest thou? And she said, I am fleeing from the face of my mistress Sarai. ^9And the angel of Jehovah said unto her, Return to thy mistress, and submit thyself under her hands. ^10And the angel of Jehovah said unto her, I will greatly multiply thy seed, that it shall not be numbered for multitude. ^11And the angel of Jehovah said unto her, Behold, thou art with child, and shalt bear a son; and thou shalt call his name Ishmael, because Jehovah hath heard thy affliction. ^12And he shall be as a wild ass among men; his hand shall be against every man, and every man's hand against him; and he shall dwell over against all his brethren. ^13And she called the name of Jehovah that spake unto her, Thou art a God that seeth: for she said, Have I even here looked after him that seeth me? ^14Wherefore the well was called Beer-lahai-roi; behold, it is between Kadesh and Bered.

^15And Hagar bare Abram a son: and Abram called the name of his son, whom Hagar bare, Ishmael. ^16And Abram was fourscore and six years old, when Hagar bare Ishmael to Abram.

Genesis 17

17

^1And when Abram was ninety years old and nine, Jehovah appeared to Abram, and said unto him, I am God Almighty; walk before me, and be thou perfect. ^2And I will make my covenant between me and thee, and will multiply thee exceedingly. ^3And Abram fell on his face: and God talked with him, saying, ^4As for me, behold, my covenant is with thee, and thou shalt be the father of a multitude of nations. ^5Neither shall thy name any more be called Abram, but thy name shall be Abraham; for the father of a multitude of nations have I made thee. ^6And I will make thee exceeding fruitful, and I will make nations of thee, and kings shall come out of thee. ^7And I will establish my covenant between me and thee and thy seed after thee throughout their generations for an everlasting covenant, to be a God unto thee and to thy seed after thee. ^8And I will give unto thee, and to thy seed after thee, the land of thy sojournings, all the land of Canaan, for an everlasting possession; and I will be their God.

^9And God said unto Abraham, And as for thee, thou shalt keep my covenant, thou, and thy seed after thee throughout their generations. ^10This is my covenant, which ye shall keep, between me and you and thy seed after thee: every male among you shall be circumcised. ^11And ye shall be circumcised in the flesh of your foreskin; and it shall be a token of a covenant betwixt me and you. ^12And he that is eight days old shall be circumcised among you, every male throughout your generations, he that is born in the house, or bought with money of any foreigner that is not of thy seed. ^13He that is born in thy house, and he that is bought with thy money, must needs be circumcised: and my covenant shall be in your flesh for an everlasting covenant. ^14And the uncircumcised male who is not circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin, that soul shall be cut off from his people; he hath broken my covenant.

^15And God said unto Abraham, As for Sarai thy wife, thou shalt not call her name Sarai, but Sarah shall her name be. ^16And I will bless her, and moreover I will give thee a son of her: yea, I will bless her, and she shall be a mother of nations; kings of peoples shall be of her. ^17Then Abraham fell upon his face, and laughed, and said in his heart, Shall a child be born unto him that is a hundred years old? and shall Sarah, that is ninety years old, bear? ^18And Abraham said unto God, Oh that Ishmael might live before thee! ^19And God said, Nay, but Sarah thy wife shall bear thee a son; and thou shalt call his name Isaac: and I will establish my covenant with him for an everlasting covenant for his seed after him. ^20And as for Ishmael, I have heard thee: behold, I have blessed him, and will make him fruitful, and will multiply him exceedingly; twelve princes shall he beget, and I will make him a great nation. ^21But my covenant will I establish with Isaac, whom Sarah shall bear unto thee at this set time in the next year.

^22And he left off talking with him, and God went up from Abraham. ^23And Abraham took Ishmael his son, and all that were born in his house, and all that were bought with his money, every male among the men of Abraham's house, and circumcised the flesh of their foreskin in the selfsame day, as God had said unto him. ^24And Abraham was ninety years old and nine, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin. ^25And Ishmael his son was thirteen years old, when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin. ^26In the selfsame day was Abraham circumcised, and Ishmael his son. ^27And all the men of his house, those born in the house, and those bought with money of a foreigner, were circumcised with him.

Genesis 18

18

^1And Jehovah appeared unto him by the oaks of Mamre, as he sat in the tent door in the heat of the day; ^2and he lifted up his eyes and looked, and, lo, three men stood over against him: and when he saw them, he ran to meet them from the tent door, and bowed himself to the earth, ^3and said, My lord, if now I have found favor in thy sight, pass not away, I pray thee, from thy servant: ^4let now a little water be fetched, and wash your feet, and rest yourselves under the tree: ^5and I will fetch a morsel of bread, and strengthen ye your heart; after that ye shall pass on: forasmuch as ye are come to your servant. And they said, So do, as thou hast said. ^6And Abraham hastened into the tent unto Sarah, and said, Make ready quickly three measures of fine meal, knead it, and make cakes. ^7And Abraham ran unto the herd, and fetched a calf tender and good, and gave it unto the servant; and he hasted to dress it. ^8And he took butter, and milk, and the calf which he had dressed, and set it before them; and he stood by them under the tree, and they did eat.

^9And they said unto him, Where is Sarah thy wife? And he said, Behold, in the tent. ^10And he said, I will certainly return unto thee when the season cometh round; and, lo, Sarah thy wife shall have a son. And Sarah heard in the tent door, which was behind him. ^11Now Abraham and Sarah were old, and well stricken in age; it had ceased to be with Sarah after the manner of women. ^12And Sarah laughed within herself, saying, After I am waxed old shall I have pleasure, my lord being old also? ^13And Jehovah said unto Abraham, Wherefore did Sarah laugh, saying, Shall I of a surety bear a child, who am old? ^14Is anything too hard for Jehovah? At the set time I will return unto thee, when the season cometh round, and Sarah shall have a son. ^15Then Sarah denied, saying, I laughed not; for she was afraid. And he said, Nay; but thou didst laugh.

^16And the men rose up from thence, and looked toward Sodom: and Abraham went with them to bring them on the way. ^17And Jehovah said, Shall I hide from Abraham that which I do; ^18seeing that Abraham had surely become a great and mighty nation, and all the nations of the earth shall be blessed in him? ^19For I have known him, to the end that he may command his children and his household after him, that they may keep the way of Jehovah, to do righteousness and justice; to the end that Jehovah may bring upon Abraham that which he hath spoken of him. ^20And Jehovah said, Because the cry of Sodom and Gomorrah is great, and because their sin is very grievous; ^21I will go down now, and see whether they have done altogether according to the cry of it, which is come unto me; and if not, I will know.

^22And the men turned from thence, and went toward Sodom: but Abraham stood yet before Jehovah. ^23And Abraham drew near, and said, Wilt thou consume the righteous with the wicked? ^24Peradventure there are fifty righteous within the city: wilt thou consume and not spare the place for the fifty righteous that are therein? ^25That be far from thee to do after this manner, to slay the righteous with the wicked, that so the righteous should be as the wicked; that be far from thee: shall not the Judge of all the earth do right? ^26And Jehovah said, If I find in Sodom fifty righteous within the city, then I will spare all the place for their sake. ^27And Abraham answered and said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord, who am but dust and ashes: ^28peradventure there shall lack five of the fifty righteous: wilt thou destroy all the city for lack of five? And he said, I will not destroy it, if I find there forty and five. ^29And he spake unto him yet again, and said, Peradventure there shall be forty found there. And he said, I will not do it for the forty's sake. ^30And he said, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speak: peradventure there shall thirty be found there. And he said, I will not do it, if I find thirty there. ^31And he said, Behold now, I have taken upon me to speak unto the Lord: peradventure there shall be twenty found there. And he said, I will not destroy it for the twenty's sake. ^32And he said, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speak yet but this once: peradventure ten shall be found there. And he said, I will not destroy it for the ten's sake. ^33And Jehovah went his way, as soon as he had left off communing with Abraham: and Abraham returned unto his place.

Genesis 19

19

^1And the two angels came to Sodom at even; and Lot sat in the gate of Sodom: and Lot saw them, and rose up to meet them; and he bowed himself with his face to the earth; ^2and he said, Behold now, my lords, turn aside, I pray you, into your servant's house, and tarry all night, and wash your feet, and ye shall rise up early, and go on your way. And they said, Nay; but we will abide in the street all night. ^3And he urged them greatly; and they turned in unto him, and entered into his house; and he made them a feast, and did bake unleavened bread, and they did eat. ^4But before they lay down, the men of the city, even the men of Sodom, compassed the house round, both young and old, all the people from every quarter; ^5and they called unto Lot, and said unto him, Where are the men that came in to thee this night? bring them out unto us, that we may know them. ^6And Lot went out unto them to the door, and shut the door after him. ^7And he said, I pray you, my brethren, do not so wickedly. ^8Behold now, I have two daughters that have not known man; let me, I pray you, bring them out unto you, and do ye to them as is good in your eyes: only unto these men do nothing, forasmuch as they are come under the shadow of my roof. ^9And they said, Stand back. And they said, This one fellow came in to sojourn, and he will needs be a judge: now will we deal worse with thee, than with them. And they pressed sore upon the man, even Lot, and drew near to break the door. ^10But the men put forth their hand, and brought Lot into the house to them, and shut to the door. ^11And they smote the men that were at the door of the house with blindness, both small and great, so that they wearied themselves to find the door.

^12And the men said unto Lot, Hast thou here any besides? son-in-law, and thy sons, and thy daughters, and whomsoever thou hast in the city, bring them out of the place: ^13for we will destroy this place, because the cry of them is waxed great before Jehovah: and Jehovah hath sent us to destroy it. ^14And Lot went out, and spake unto his sons-in-law, who married his daughters, and said, Up, get you out of this place; for Jehovah will destroy the city. But he seemed unto his sons-in-law as one that mocked. ^15And when the morning arose, then the angels hastened Lot, saying, Arise, take thy wife, and thy two daughters that are here, lest thou be consumed in the iniquity of the city. ^16But he lingered; and the men laid hold upon his hand, and upon the hand of his wife, and upon the hand of his two daughters, Jehovah being merciful unto him; and they brought him forth, and set him without the city. ^17And it came to pass, when they had brought them forth abroad, that he said, Escape for thy life; look not behind thee, neither stay thou in all the Plain; escape to the mountain, lest thou be consumed. ^18And Lot said unto them, Oh, not so, my lord: ^19behold now, thy servant hath found favor in thy sight, and thou hast magnified thy lovingkindness, which thou hast showed unto me in saving my life; and I cannot escape to the mountain, lest evil overtake me, and I die: ^20behold now, this city is near to flee unto, and it is a little one. Oh let me escape thither (is it not a little one?), and my soul shall live. ^21And he said unto him, See, I have accepted thee concerning this thing also, that I will not overthrow the city of which thou hast spoken. ^22Haste thee, escape thither; for I cannot do anything till thou be come thither. Therefore the name of the city was called Zoar.

^23The sun was risen upon the earth when Lot came unto Zoar. ^24Then Jehovah rained upon Sodom and upon Gomorrah brimstone and fire from Jehovah out of heaven; ^25and he overthrew those cities, and all the Plain, and all the inhabitants of the cities, and that which grew upon the ground. ^26But his wife looked back from behind him, and she became a pillar of salt. ^27And Abraham gat up early in the morning to the place where he had stood before Jehovah: ^28and he looked toward Sodom and Gomorrah, and toward all the land of the Plain, and beheld, and, lo, the smoke of the land went up as the smoke of a furnace.

^29And it came to pass, when God destroyed the cities of the Plain, that God remembered Abraham, and sent Lot out of the midst of the overthrow, when he overthrew the cities in which Lot dwelt.

^30And Lot went up out of Zoar, and dwelt in the mountain, and his two daughters with him; for he feared to dwell in Zoar: and he dwelt in a cave, he and his two daughters. ^31And the first-born said unto the younger, Our father is old, and there is not a man in the earth to come in unto us after the manner of all the earth: ^32come, let us make our father drink wine, and we will lie with him, that we may preserve seed of our father. ^33And they made their father drink wine that night: and the first-born went in, and lay with her father; and he knew not when she lay down, nor when she arose. ^34And it came to pass on the morrow, that the first-born said unto the younger, Behold, I lay yesternight with my father: let us make him drink wine this night also; and go thou in, and lie with him, that we may preserve seed of our father. ^35And they made their father drink wine that night also: and the younger arose, and lay with him; and he knew not when she lay down, nor when she arose. ^36Thus were both the daughters of Lot with child by their father. ^37And the first-born bare a son, and called his name Moab: the same is the father of the Moabites unto this day. ^38And the younger, she also bare a son, and called his name Ben-ammi: the same is the father of the children of Ammon unto this day.

Genesis 20

20

^1And Abraham journeyed from thence toward the land of the South, and dwelt between Kadesh and Shur. And he sojourned in Gerar. ^2And Abraham said of Sarah his wife, She is my sister. And Abimelech king of Gerar sent, and took Sarah. ^3But God came to Abimelech in a dream of the night, and said to him, Behold, thou art but a dead man, because of the woman whom thou hast taken. For she is a man's wife. ^4Now Abimelech had not come near her. And he said, Lord, wilt thou slay even a righteous nation? ^5Said he not himself unto me, She is my sister? And she, even she herself said, He is my brother. In the integrity of my heart and the innocency of my hands have I done this. ^6And God said unto him in the dream, Yea, I know that in the integrity of thy heart thou has done this, and I also withheld thee from sinning against me. Therefore suffered I thee not to touch her. ^7Now therefore restore the man's wife. For he is a prophet, and he shall pray for thee, and thou shalt live. And if thou restore her not, know thou that thou shalt surely die, thou, and all that are thine.

^8And Abimelech rose early in the morning, and called all his servants, and told all these things in their ear. And the men were sore afraid. ^9Then Abimelech called Abraham, and said unto him, What hast thou done unto us? And wherein have I sinned against thee, that thou hast brought on me and on my kingdom a great sin? Thou hast done deeds unto me that ought not to be done. ^10And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What sawest thou, that thou hast done this thing? ^11And Abraham said, Because I thought, Surely the fear of God is not in this place. And they will slay me for my wife's sake. ^12And moreover she is indeed my sister, the daughter of my father, but not the daughter of my mother; and she became my wife: ^13and it came to pass, when God caused me to wander from my father's house, that I said unto her, This is thy kindness which thou shalt show unto me. At every place whither we shall come, say of me, He is my brother. ^14And Abimelech took sheep and oxen, and men-servants and women-servants, and gave them unto Abraham, and restored him Sarah his wife. ^15And Abimelech said, Behold, my land is before thee. Dwell where it pleaseth thee. ^16And unto Sarah he said, Behold, I have given thy brother a thousand pieces of silver. Behold, it is for thee a covering of the eyes to all that are with thee. And in respect of all thou art righted. ^17And Abraham prayed unto God. And God healed Abimelech, and his wife, and his maid-servants. And they bare children. ^18For Jehovah had fast closed up all the wombs of the house of Abimelech, because of Sarah, Abraham's wife.

Genesis 21

21

^1And Jehovah visited Sarah as he had said, and Jehovah did unto Sarah as he had spoken. ^2And Sarah conceived, and bare Abraham a son in his old age, at the set time of which God had spoken to him. ^3And Abraham called the name of his son that was born unto him, whom Sarah bare to him, Isaac. ^4And Abraham circumcised his son Isaac when he was eight days old, as God had commanded him. ^5And Abraham was a hundred years old, when his son Isaac was born unto him. ^6And Sarah said, God hath made me to laugh. Every one that heareth will laugh with me. ^7And she said, Who would have said unto Abraham, that Sarah should give children suck? For I have borne him a son in his old age.

^8And the child grew, and was weaned. And Abraham made a great feast on the day that Isaac was weaned. ^9And Sarah saw the son of Hagar the Egyptian, whom she had borne unto Abraham, mocking. ^10Wherefore she said unto Abraham, Cast out this handmaid and her son. For the son of this handmaid shall not be heir with my son, even with Isaac. ^11And the thing was very grievous in Abraham's sight on account of his son. ^12And God said unto Abraham, Let it not be grievous in thy sight because of the lad, and because of thy handmaid. In all that Sarah saith unto thee, hearken unto her voice. For in Isaac shall thy seed be called. ^13And also of the son of the handmaid will I make a nation, because he is thy seed. ^14And Abraham rose up early in the morning, and took bread and a bottle of water, and gave it unto Hagar, putting it on her shoulder, and gave her the child, and sent her away. And she departed, and wandered in the wilderness of Beer-sheba. ^15And the water in the bottle was spent, and she cast the child under one of the shrubs. ^16And she went, and sat her down over against him a good way off, as it were a bowshot. For she said, Let me not look upon the death of the child. And she sat over against him, and lifted up her voice, and wept. ^17And God heard the voice of the lad. And the angel of God called to Hagar out of heaven, and said unto her, What aileth thee, Hagar? Fear not. For God hath heard the voice of the lad where he is. ^18Arise, lift up the lad, and hold him in thy hand. For I will make him a great nation. ^19And God opened her eyes, and she saw a well of water. And she went, and filled the bottle with water, and gave the lad drink. ^20And God was with the lad, and he grew. And he dwelt in the wilderness, and became, as he grew up, an archer. ^21And he dwelt in the wilderness of Paran. And his mother took him a wife out of the land of Egypt.

^22And it came to pass at that time, that Abimelech and Phicol the captain of his host spake unto Abraham, saying, God is with thee in all that thou doest. ^23Now therefore swear unto me here by God that thou wilt not deal falsely with me, nor with my son, nor with my son's son. But according to the kindness that I have done unto thee, thou shalt do unto me, and to the land wherein thou hast sojourned. ^24And Abraham said, I will swear. ^25And Abraham reproved Abimelech because of the well of water, which Abimelech's servants had violently taken away. ^26And Abimelech said, I know not who hath done this thing. Neither didst thou tell me, neither yet heard I of it, but to-day. ^27And Abraham took sheep and oxen, and gave them unto Abimelech. And they two made a covenant. ^28And Abraham set seven ewe lambs of the flock by themselves. ^29And Abimelech said unto Abraham, What mean these seven ewe lambs which thou hast set by themselves? ^30And he said, These seven ewe lambs shalt thou take of my hand, that it may be a witness unto me, that I have digged this well. ^31Wherefore he called that place Beer-sheba. Because there they sware both of them. ^32So they made a covenant at Beer-sheba. And Abimelech rose up, and Phicol the captain of his host, and they returned into the land of the Philistines. ^33And Abraham planted a tamarisk tree in Beer-sheba, and called there on the name of Jehovah, the Everlasting God. ^34And Abraham sojourned in the land of the Philistines many days.

Genesis 22

22

^1And it came to pass after these things, that God did prove Abraham, and said unto him, Abraham. And he said, Here am I. ^2And he said, Take now thy son, thine only son, whom thou lovest, even Isaac, and get thee into the land of Moriah. And offer him there for a burnt-offering upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of. ^3And Abraham rose early in the morning, and saddled his ass, and took two of his young men with him, and Isaac his son. And he clave the wood for the burnt-offering, and rose up, and went unto the place of which God had told him. ^4On the third day Abraham lifted up his eyes, and saw the place afar off. ^5And Abraham said unto his young men, Abide ye here with the ass, and I and the lad will go yonder; and we will worship, and come again to you. ^6And Abraham took the wood of the burnt-offering, and laid it upon Isaac his son. And he took in his hand the fire and the knife. And they went both of them together. ^7And Isaac spake unto Abraham his father, and said, My father. And he said, Here am I, my son. And he said, Behold, the fire and the wood. But where is the lamb for a burnt-offering? ^8And Abraham said, God will provide himself the lamb for a burnt-offering, my son. So they went both of them together.

^9And they came to the place which God had told him of. And Abraham built the altar there, and laid the wood in order, and bound Isaac his son, and laid him on the altar, upon the wood. ^10And Abraham stretched forth his hand, and took the knife to slay his son. ^11And the angel of Jehovah called unto him out of heaven, and said, Abraham, Abraham. And he said, Here I am. ^12And he said, Lay not thy hand upon the lad, neither do thou anything unto him. For now I know that thou fearest God, seeing thou hast not withheld thy son, thine only son, from me. ^13And Abraham lifted up his eyes, and looked, and behold, behind him a ram caught in the thicket by his horns. And Abraham went and took the ram, and offered him up for a burnt-offering in the stead of his son. ^14And Abraham called the name of that place Jehovah-jireh. As it is said to this day, In the mount of Jehovah it shall be provided. ^15And the angel of Jehovah called unto Abraham a second time out of heaven, ^16and said, By myself have I sworn, saith Jehovah, because thou hast done this thing, and hast not withheld thy son, thine only son, ^17that in blessing I will bless thee, and in multiplying I will multiply thy seed as the stars of the heavens, and as the sand which is upon the seashore. And thy seed shall possess the gate of his enemies. ^18And in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth be blessed. Because thou hast obeyed my voice. ^19So Abraham returned unto his young men, and they rose up and went together to Beer-sheba. And Abraham dwelt at Beer-sheba.

^20And it came to pass after these things, that it was told Abraham, saying, Behold, Milcah, she also hath borne children unto they brother Nahor. ^21Uz his first-born, and Buz his brother, and Kemuel the father of Aram. ^22And Chesed, and Hazo, and Pildash, and Jidlaph, and Bethuel. ^23And Bethuel begat Rebekah. These eight did Milcah bear to Nahor, Abraham's brother. ^24And his concubine, whose name was Reumah, she also bare Tebah, and Gaham, and Tahash, and Maacah.

Genesis 23

23

^1And the life of Sarah was a hundred and seven and twenty years. These were the years of the life of Sarah. ^2And Sarah died in Kiriath-arba (the same is Hebron), in the land of Canaan. And Abraham came to mourn for Sarah, and to weep for her. ^3And Abraham rose up from before his dead, and spake unto the children of Heth, saying, ^4I am a stranger and a sojourner with you. Give me a possession of a burying-place with you, that I may bury my dead out of my sight. ^5And the children of Heth answered Abraham, saying unto him, ^6Hear us, my lord. Thou art a prince of God among us. In the choice of our sepulchres bury thy dead. None of us shall withhold from thee his sepulchre, but that thou mayest bury thy dead. ^7And Abraham rose up, and bowed himself to the people of the land, even to the children of Heth. ^8And he communed with them, saying, If it be your mind that I should bury my dead out of my sight, hear me, and entreat for me to Ephron the son of Zohar, ^9that he may give me the cave of Machpelah, which he hath, which is in the end of his field. For the full price let him give it to me in the midst of you for a possession of a burying-place. ^10Now Ephron was sitting in the midst of the children of Heth. And Ephron the Hittite answered Abraham in the audience of the children of Heth, even of all that went in at the gate of his city, saying, ^11Nay, my lord, hear me. The field give I thee, and the cave that is therein, I give it thee. In the presence of the children of my people give I it thee. Bury thy dead. ^12And Abraham bowed himself down before the people of the land. ^13And he spake unto Ephron in the audience of the people of the land, saying, But if thou wilt, I pray thee, hear me. I will give the price of the field. Take it of me, and I will bury my dead there. ^14And Ephron answered Abraham, saying unto him, ^15My lord, hearken unto me. A piece of land worth four hundred shekels of silver, what is that betwixt me and thee? Bury therefore thy dead. ^16And Abraham hearkened unto Ephron. And Abraham weighed to Ephron the silver which he had named in the audience of the children of Heth, four hundred shekels of silver, current money with the merchant.

^17So the field of Ephron, which was in Machpelah, which was before Mamre, the field, and the cave which was therein, and all the trees that were in the field, that were in all the border thereof round about, were made sure ^18unto Abraham for a possession in the presence of the children of Heth, before all that went in at the gate of his city. ^19And after this, Abraham buried Sarah his wife in the cave of the field of Machpelah before Mamre (the same is Hebron), in the land of Canaan. ^20And the field, and the cave that is therein, were made sure unto Abraham for a possession of a burying-place by the children of Heth.

Genesis 24

24

^1And Abraham was old, and well stricken in age. And Jehovah had blessed Abraham in all things. ^2And Abraham said unto his servant, the elder of his house, that ruled over all that he had, Put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh. ^3And I will make thee swear by Jehovah, the God of heaven and the God of the earth, that thou wilt not take a wife for my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, among whom I dwell. ^4But thou shalt go unto my country, and to my kindred, and take a wife for my son Isaac. ^5And the servant said unto him, Peradventure the woman will not be willing to follow me unto this land. Must I needs bring thy son again unto the land from whence thou camest? ^6And Abraham said unto him, Beware thou that thou bring not my son thither again. ^7Jehovah, the God of heaven, who took me from my father's house, and from the land of my nativity, and who spake unto me, and who sware unto me, saying, Unto thy seed will I give this land. He will send his angel before thee, and thou shalt take a wife for my son from thence. ^8And if the woman be not willing to follow thee, then thou shalt be clear from this my oath. Only thou shalt not bring my son thither again. ^9And the servant put his hand under the thigh of Abraham his master, and sware to him concerning this matter.

^10And the servant took ten camels, of the camels of his master, and departed, having all goodly things of his master's in his hand. And he arose, and went to Mesopotamia, unto the city of Nahor. ^11And he made the camels to kneel down without the city by the well of water at the time of evening, the time that women go out to draw water. ^12And he said, O Jehovah, the God of my master Abraham, send me, I pray thee, good speed this day, and show kindness unto my master Abraham. ^13Behold, I am standing by the fountain of water. And the daughters of the men of the city are coming out to draw water. ^14And let it come to pass, that the damsel to whom I shall say, Let down thy pitcher, I pray thee, that I may drink. And she shall say, Drink, and I will give thy camels drink also. Let the same be she that thou hast appointed for thy servant Isaac. And thereby shall I know that thou hast showed kindness unto my master. ^15And it came to pass, before he had done speaking, that, behold, Rebekah came out, who was born to Bethuel the son of Milcah, the wife of Nahor, Abraham's brother, with her pitcher upon her shoulder. ^16And the damsel was very fair to look upon, a virgin, neither had any man known her. And she went down to the fountain, and filled her pitcher, and came up. ^17And the servant ran to meet her, and said, Give me to drink, I pray thee, a little water from thy pitcher. ^18And she said, Drink, my lord. And she hasted, and let down her pitcher upon her hand, and gave him drink. ^19And when she had done giving him drink, she said, I will draw for thy camels also, until they have done drinking. ^20And she hasted, and emptied her pitcher into the trough, and ran again unto the well to draw, and drew for all his camels. ^21And the man looked stedfastly on her, holding his peace, to know whether Jehovah had made his journey prosperous or not. ^22And it came to pass, as the camels had done drinking, that the man took a golden ring of half a shekel weight, and two bracelets for her hands of ten shekels weight of gold, ^23and said, Whose daughter art thou? Tell me, I pray thee. Is there room in thy father's house for us to lodge in? ^24And she said unto him, I am the daughter of Bethuel the son of Milcah, whom she bare unto Nahor. ^25She said moreover unto him, We have both straw and provender enough, and room to lodge in. ^26And the man bowed his head, and worshipped Jehovah. ^27And he said, Blessed be Jehovah, the God of my master Abraham, who hath not forsaken his lovingkindness and his truth toward my master. As for me, Jehovah hath led me in the way to the house of my master's brethren.

^28And the damsel ran, and told her mother's house according to these words. ^29And Rebekah had a brother, and his name was Laban: and Laban ran out unto the man, unto the fountain. ^30And it came to pass, when he saw the ring, and the bracelets upon his sister's hands, and when he heard the words of Rebekah his sister, saying, Thus spake the man unto me. That he came unto the man. And, behold, he was standing by the camels at the fountain. ^31And he said, Come in, thou blessed of Jehovah. Wherefore standest thou without? For I have prepared the house, and room for the camels. ^32And the man came into the house, and he ungirded the camels. And he gave straw and provender for the camels, and water to wash his feet and the feet of the men that were with him. ^33And there was set food before him to eat. But he said, I will not eat, until I have told mine errand. And he said, Speak on. ^34And he said, I am Abraham's servant. ^35And Jehovah hath blessed my master greatly. And he is become great. And he hath given him flocks and herds, and silver and gold, and men-servants and maid-servants, and camels and asses. ^36And Sarah my master's wife bare a son to my master when she was old. And unto him hath he given all that he hath. ^37And my master made me swear, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife for my son of the daughters of the Canaanites, in whose land I dwell. ^38But thou shalt go unto my father's house, and to my kindred, and take a wife for my son. ^39And I said unto my master, Peradventure the woman will not follow me. ^40And he said unto me, Jehovah, before whom I walk, will send his angel with thee, and prosper thy way. And thou shalt take a wife for my son of my kindred, and of my father's house. ^41Then shalt thou be clear from my oath, when thou comest to my kindred. And if they give her not to thee, thou shalt be clear from my oath. ^42And I came this day unto the fountain, and said, O Jehovah, the God of my master Abraham, if now thou do prosper my way which I go. ^43Behold, I am standing by the fountain of water. And let it come to pass, that the maiden that cometh forth to draw, to whom I shall say, Give me, I pray thee, a little water from thy pitcher to drink. ^44And she shall say to me, Both drink thou, and I will also draw for thy camels. Let the same be the woman whom Jehovah hath appointed for my master's son. ^45And before I had done speaking in my heart, behold, Rebekah came forth with her pitcher on her shoulder. And she went down unto the fountain, and drew. And I said unto her, Let me drink, I pray thee. ^46And she made haste, and let down her pitcher from her shoulder, and said, Drink, and I will give thy camels drink also. So I drank, and she made the camels drink also. ^47And I asked her, and said, Whose daughter art thou? And she said, The daughter of Bethuel, Nahor's son, whom Milcah bare unto him. And I put the ring upon her nose, and the bracelets upon her hands. ^48And I bowed my head, and worshipped Jehovah, and blessed Jehovah, the God of my master Abraham, who had led me in the right way to take my master's brother's daughter for his son. ^49And now if ye will deal kindly and truly with my master, tell me. And if not, tell me. That I may turn to the right hand, or to the left.

^50Then Laban and Bethuel answered and said, The thing proceedeth from Jehovah. We cannot speak unto thee bad or good. ^51Behold, Rebekah is before thee, take her, and go, and let her be thy master's son's wife, as Jehovah hath spoken. ^52And it came to pass, that, when Abraham's servant heard their words, he bowed himself down to the earth unto Jehovah. ^53And the servant brought forth jewels of silver, and jewels of gold, and raiment, and gave them to Rebekah. He gave also to her brother and to her mother precious things. ^54And they did eat and drink, he and the men that were with him, and tarried all night. And they rose up in the morning, and he said, Send me away unto my master. ^55And her brother and her mother said, Let the damsel abide with us a few days, at the least ten. After that she shall go. ^56And he said unto them, Hinder me not, seeing Jehovah hath prospered my way. Send me away that I may go to my master. ^57And they said, We will call the damsel, and inquire at her mouth. ^58And they called Rebekah, and said unto her, Wilt thou go with this man? And she said, I will go. ^59And they sent away Rebekah their sister, and her nurse, and Abraham's servant, and his men. ^60And they blessed Rebekah, and said unto her, Our sister, be thou the mother of thousands of ten thousands, and let thy seed possess the gate of those that hate them.

^61And Rebekah arose, and her damsels, and they rode upon the camels, and followed the man. And the servant took Rebekah, and went his way. ^62And Isaac came from the way of Beer-lahai-roi. For he dwelt in the land of the South. ^63And Isaac went out to meditate in the field at the eventide. And he lifted up his eyes, and saw, and, behold, there were camels coming. ^64And Rebekah lifted up her eyes, and when she saw Isaac, she alighted from the camel. ^65And she said unto the servant, What man is this that walketh in the field to meet us? And the servant said, It is my master. And she took her veil, and covered herself. ^66And the servant told Isaac all the things that he had done. ^67And Isaac brought her into his mother Sarah's tent, and took Rebekah, and she became his wife. And he loved her. And Isaac was comforted after his mother's death.

Genesis 25

25

^1And Abraham took another wife, and her name was Keturah. ^2And she bare him Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. ^3And Jokshan begat Sheba, and Dedan. And the sons of Dedan were Asshurim, and Letushim, and Leummim. ^4And the sons of Midian: Ephah, and Epher, and Hanoch, and Abida, and Eldaah. All these were the children of Keturah. ^5And Abraham gave all that he had unto Isaac. ^6But unto the sons of the concubines, that Abraham had, Abraham gave gifts. And he sent them away from Isaac his son, while he yet lived, eastward, unto the east country. ^7And these are the days of the years of Abraham's life which he lived, a hundred threescore and fifteen years. ^8And Abraham gave up the ghost, and died in a good old age, an old man, and full of years, and was gathered to his people. ^9And Isaac and Ishmael his sons buried him in the cave of Machpelah, in the field of Ephron the son of Zohar the Hittite, which is before Mamre. ^10The field which Abraham purchased of the children of Heth. There was Abraham buried, and Sarah his wife. ^11And it came to pass after the death of Abraham, that God blessed Isaac his son. And Isaac dwelt by Beer-lahai-roi.

^12Now these are the generations of Ishmael, Abraham's son, whom Hagar the Egyptian, Sarah's handmaid, bare unto Abraham. ^13And these are the names of the sons of Ishmael, by their names, according to their generations: the first-born of Ishmael, Nebaioth, and Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam, ^14and Mishma, and Dumah, and Massa, ^15Hadad, and Tema, Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah. ^16These are the sons of Ishmael, and these are their names, by their villages, and by their encampments. Twelve princes according to their nations. ^17And these are the years of the life of Ishmael, a hundred and thirty and seven years. And he gave up the ghost and died, and was gathered unto his people. ^18And they dwelt from Havilah unto Shur that is before Egypt, as thou goest toward Assyria. He abode over against all his brethren.

^19And these are the generations of Isaac, Abraham's son. Abraham begat Isaac. ^20And Isaac was forty years old when he took Rebekah, the daughter of Bethuel the Syrian of Paddan-aram, the sister of Laban the Syrian, to be his wife. ^21And Isaac entreated Jehovah for his wife, because she was barren. And Jehovah was entreated of him, and Rebekah his wife conceived. ^22And the children struggled together within her. And she said, If it be so, wherefore do I live? And she went to inquire of Jehovah. ^23And Jehovah said unto her,

Two nations are in thy womb,

And two peoples shall be separated from thy bowels.

And the one people shall be stronger than the other people.

And the elder shall serve the younger.

^24And when her days to be delivered were fulfilled, behold, there were twins in her womb. ^25And the first came forth red, all over like a hairy garment. And they called his name Esau. ^26And after that came forth his brother, and his hand had hold on Esau's heel. And his name was called Jacob. And Isaac was threescore years old when she bare them.

^27And the boys grew. And Esau was a skilful hunter, a man of the field. And Jacob was a quiet man, dwelling in tents. ^28Now Isaac loved Esau, because he did eat of his venison. And Rebekah loved Jacob. ^29And Jacob boiled pottage. And Esau came in from the field, and he was faint. ^30And Esau said to Jacob, Feed me, I pray thee, with that same red pottage. For I am faint. Therefore was his name called Edom. ^31And Jacob said, Sell me first thy birthright. ^32And Esau said, Behold, I am about to die. And what profit shall the birthright do to me? ^33And Jacob said, Swear to me first. And he sware unto him. And he sold his birthright unto Jacob. ^34And Jacob gave Esau bread and pottage of lentils. And he did eat and drink, and rose up, and went his way. So Esau despised his birthright.

Genesis 26

26

^1And there was a famine in the land, besides the first famine that was in the days of Abraham. And Isaac went unto Abimelech king of the Philistines, unto Gerar. ^2And Jehovah appeared unto him, and said, Go not down into Egypt. Dwell in the land which I shall tell thee of. ^3Sojourn in this land, and I will be with thee, and will bless thee. For unto thee, and unto thy seed, I will give all these lands, and I will establish the oath which I sware unto Abraham thy father. ^4And I will multiply thy seed as the stars of heaven, and will give unto thy seed all these lands. And in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth be blessed. ^5Because that Abraham obeyed my voice, and kept my charge, my commandments, my statutes, and my laws. ^6And Isaac dwelt in Gerar. ^7And the men of the place asked him of his wife. And he said, She is my sister. For he feared to say, My wife. Lest, said he, the men of the place should kill me for Rebekah. Because she was fair to look upon. ^8And it came to pass, when he had been there a long time, that Abimelech king of the Philistines looked out at a window, and saw, and, behold, Isaac was sporting with Rebekah his wife. ^9And Abimelech called Isaac, and said, Behold, of a surety she is thy wife. And how saidst thou, She is my sister? And Isaac said unto him, Because I said, Lest I die because of her. ^10And Abimelech said, What is this thou hast done unto us? One of the people might easily have lain with thy wife, and thou wouldest have brought guiltiness upon us. ^11And Abimelech charged all the people, saying, He that toucheth this man or his wife shall surely be put to death.

^12And Isaac sowed in that land, and found in the same year a hundredfold. And Jehovah blessed him. ^13And the man waxed great, and grew more and more until he became very great. ^14And he had possessions of flocks, and possessions of herds, and a great household. And the Philistines envied him. ^15Now all the wells which his father's servants had digged in the days of Abraham his father, the Philistines had stopped, and filled with earth. ^16And Abimelech said unto Isaac, Go from us. For thou art much mightier than we. ^17And Isaac departed thence, and encamped in the valley of Gerar, and dwelt there.

^18And Isaac digged again the wells of water, which they had digged in the days of Abraham his father. For the Philistines had stopped them after the death of Abraham. And he called their names after the names by which his father had called them. ^19And Isaac's servants digged in the valley, and found there a well of springing water. ^20And the herdsmen of Gerar strove with Isaac's herdsmen, saying, The water is ours. And he called the name of the well Esek, because they contended with him. ^21And they digged another well, and they strove for that also. And he called the name of it Sitnah. ^22And he removed from thence, and digged another well. And for that they strove not. And he called the name of it Rehoboth. And he said, For now Jehovah hath made room for us, and we shall be fruitful in the land.

^23And he went up from thence to Beer-sheba. ^24And Jehovah appeared unto him the same night, and said, I am the God of Abraham thy father. Fear not, for I am with thee, and will bless thee, and multiply thy seed for my servant Abraham's sake. ^25And he builded an altar there, and called upon the name of Jehovah, and pitched his tent there. And there Isaac's servants digged a well.

^26Then Abimelech went to him from Gerar, and Ahuzzath his friend, and Phicol the captain of his host. ^27And Isaac said unto them, Wherefore are ye come unto me, seeing ye hate me, and have sent me away from you? ^28And they said, We saw plainly that Jehovah was with thee. And we said, Let there now be an oath betwixt us, even betwixt us and thee, and let us make a covenant with thee, ^29that thou wilt do us no hurt, as we have not touched thee, and as we have done unto thee nothing but good, and have sent thee away in peace. Thou art now the blessed of Jehovah. ^30And he made them a feast, and they did eat and drink. ^31And they rose up betimes in the morning, and sware one to another. And Isaac sent them away, and they departed from him in peace. ^32And it came to pass the same day, that Isaac's servants came, and told him concerning the well which they had digged, and said unto him, We have found water. ^33And he called it Shibah. Therefore the name of the city is Beer-sheba unto this day.

^34And when Esau was forty years old he took to wife Judith the daughter of Beeri the Hittite, and Basemath the daughter of Elon the Hittite. ^35And they were a grief of mind unto Isaac and to Rebekah.

Genesis 27

27

^1And it came to pass, that when Isaac was old, and his eyes were dim, so that he could not see, he called Esau his elder son, and said unto him, My son. And he said unto him, Here am I. ^2And he said, Behold now, I am old, I know not the day of my death. ^3Now therefore take, I pray thee, thy weapons, thy quiver and thy bow, and go out to the field, and take me venison. ^4And make me savory food, such as I love, and bring it to me, that I may eat. That my soul may bless thee before I die.

^5And Rebekah heard when Isaac spake to Esau his son. And Esau went to the field to hunt for venison, and to bring it. ^6And Rebekah spake unto Jacob her son, saying, Behold, I heard thy father speak unto Esau thy brother, saying, ^7Bring me venison, and make me savory food, that I may eat, and bless thee before Jehovah before my death. ^8Now therefore, my son, obey my voice according to that which I command thee. ^9Go now to the flock, and fetch me from thence two good kids of the goats. And I will make them savory food for thy father, such as he loveth. ^10And thou shalt bring it to thy father, that he may eat, so that he may bless thee before his death. ^11And Jacob said to Rebekah his mother, Behold, Esau my brother is a hairy man, and I am a smooth man. ^12My father peradventure will feel me, and I shall seem to him as a deceiver. And I shall bring a curse upon me, and not a blessing. ^13And his mother said unto him, Upon me be thy curse, my son. Only obey my voice, and go fetch me them. ^14And he went, and fetched, and brought them to his mother. And his mother made savory food, such as his father loved. ^15And Rebekah took the goodly garments of Esau her elder son, which were with her in the house, and put them upon Jacob her younger son. ^16And she put the skins of the kids of the goats upon his hands, and upon the smooth of his neck. ^17And she gave the savory food and the bread, which she had prepared, into the hand of her son Jacob.

^18And he came unto his father, and said, My father. And he said, Here am I. Who art thou, my son? ^19And Jacob said unto his father, I am Esau thy first-born; I have done according as thou badest me: arise, I pray thee, sit and eat of my venison, that thy soul may bless me. ^20And Isaac said unto his son, How is it that thou hast found it so quickly, my son? And he said, Because Jehovah thy God sent me good speed. ^21And Isaac said unto Jacob, Come near, I pray thee, that I may feel thee, my son, whether thou be my very son Esau or not. ^22And Jacob went near unto Isaac his father. And he felt him, and said, The voice is Jacob's voice, but the hands are the hands of Esau. ^23And he discerned him not, because his hands were hairy, as his brother Esau's hands. So he blessed him. ^24And he said, Art thou my very son Esau? And he said, I am. ^25And he said, Bring it near to me, and I will eat of my son's venison, that my soul may bless thee. And he brought it near to him, and he did eat. And he brought him wine, and he drank. ^26And his father Isaac said unto him, Come near now, and kiss me, my son. ^27And he came near, and kissed him. And he smelled the smell of his raiment, and blessed him, and said,

See, the smell of my son

Is as the smell of a field which Jehovah hath blessed.

^28And God give thee of the dew of heaven,

And of the fatness of the earth,

And plenty of grain and new wine.

^29Let peoples serve thee,

And nations bow down to thee.

Be lord over thy brethren,

And let thy mother's sons bow down to thee.

Cursed be every one that curseth thee,

And blessed be every one that blesseth thee.

^30And it came to pass, as soon as Isaac had made an end of blessing Jacob, and Jacob was yet scarce gone out from the presence of Isaac his father, that Esau his brother came in from his hunting. ^31And he also made savory food, and brought it unto his father. And he said unto his father, Let my father arise, and eat of his son's venison, that thy soul may bless me. ^32And Isaac his father said unto him, Who art thou? And he said, I am thy son, thy first-born, Esau. ^33And Isaac trembled very exceedingly, and said, Who then is he that hath taken venison, and brought it me, and I have eaten of all before thou camest, and have blessed him? Yea, and he shall be blessed. ^34When Esau heard the words of his father, he cried with an exceeding great and bitter cry, and said unto his father, Bless me, even me also, O my father. ^35And he said, Thy brother came with guile, and hath taken away thy blessing. ^36And he said, Is not he rightly name Jacob? for he hath supplanted me these two time. He took away my birthright. And, behold, now he hath taken away my blessing. And he said, Hast thou not reserved a blessing for me? ^37And Isaac answered and said unto Esau, Behold, I have made him thy lord, and all his brethren have I given to him for servants. And with grain and new wine have I sustained him. And what then shall I do for thee, my son? ^38And Esau said unto his father, Hast thou but one blessing, my father? Bless me, even me also, O my father. And Esau lifted up his voice, and wept. ^39And Isaac his father answered and said unto him,

Behold, of the fatness of the earth shall be thy dwelling,

And of the dew of heaven from above.

^40And by thy sword shalt thou live, and thou shalt serve thy brother.

And it shall come to pass, when thou shalt break loose,

That thou shalt shake his yoke from off thy neck.

^41And Esau hated Jacob because of the blessing wherewith his father blessed him. And Esau said in his heart, The days of mourning for my father are at hand. Then will I slay my brother Jacob. ^42And the words of Esau her elder son were told to Rebekah. And she sent and called Jacob her younger son, and said unto him, Behold, thy brother Esau, as touching thee, doth comfort himself, purposing to kill thee. ^43Now therefore, my son, obey my voice. And arise, flee thou to Laban my brother to Haran. ^44And tarry with him a few days, until thy brother's fury turn away. ^45Until thy brother's anger turn away from thee, and he forget that which thou hast done to him. Then I will send, and fetch thee from thence. Why should I be bereaved of you both in one day?

^46And Rebekah said to Isaac, I am weary of my life because of the daughters of Heth. If Jacob take a wife of the daughters of Heth, such as these, of the daughters of the land, what good shall my life do me?

Genesis 28

28

^1And Isaac called Jacob, and blessed him, and charged him, and said unto him, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan. ^2Arise, go to Paddan-aram, to the house of Bethuel thy mother's father. And take thee a wife from thence of the daughters of Laban thy mother's brother. ^3And God Almighty bless thee, and make thee fruitful, and multiply thee, that thou mayest be a company of peoples. ^4And give thee the blessing of Abraham, to thee, and to thy seed with thee. That thou mayest inherit the land of thy sojournings, which God gave unto Abraham. ^5And Isaac sent away Jacob. And he went to Paddan-aram unto Laban, son of Bethuel the Syrian, the brother of Rebekah, Jacob's and Esau's mother.

^6Now Esau saw that Isaac had blessed Jacob and sent him away to Paddan-aram, to take him a wife from thence. And that as he blessed him he gave him a charge, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters of Canaan. ^7And that Jacob obeyed his father and his mother, and was gone to Paddan-aram. ^8And Esau saw that the daughters of Canaan pleased not Isaac his father. ^9And Esau went unto Ishmael, and took, besides the wives that he had, Mahalath the daughter of Ishmael Abraham's son, the sister of Nebaioth, to be his wife.

^10And Jacob went out from Beer-sheba, and went toward Haran. ^11And he lighted upon a certain place, and tarried there all night, because the sun was set. And he took one of the stones of the place, and put it under his head, and lay down in that place to sleep. ^12And he dreamed. And behold, a ladder set up on the earth, and the top of it reached to heaven. And behold, the angels of God ascending and descending on it. ^13And, behold, Jehovah stood above it, and said, I am Jehovah, the God of Abraham thy father, and the God of Isaac. The land whereon thou liest, to thee will I give it, and to thy seed. ^14And thy seed shall be as the dust of the earth, and thou shalt spread abroad to the west, and to the east, and to the north, and to the south. And in thee and in thy seed shall all the families of the earth be blessed. ^15And, behold, I am with thee, and will keep thee, whithersoever thou goest, and will bring thee again into this land. For I will not leave thee, until I have done that which I have spoken to thee of. ^16And Jacob awaked out of his sleep, and he said, Surely Jehovah is in this place. And I knew it not. ^17And he was afraid, and said, How dreadful is this place! This is none other than the house of God, and this is the gate of heaven.

^18And Jacob rose up early in the morning, and took the stone that he had put under his head, and set it up for a pillar, and poured oil upon the top of it. ^19And he called the name of that place Beth-el. But the name of the city was Luz at the first. ^20And Jacob vowed a vow, saying, If God will be with me, and will keep me in this way that I go, and will give me bread to eat, and raiment to put on, ^21so that I come again to my father's house in peace, and Jehovah will be my God, ^22then this stone, which I have set up for a pillar, shall be God's house. And of all that thou shalt give me I will surely give the tenth unto thee.

Genesis 29

29

^1Then Jacob went on his journey, and came to the land of the children of the east. ^2And he looked, and behold, a well in the field, and, lo, three flocks of sheep lying there by it. For out of that well they watered the flocks. And the stone upon the well's mouth was great. ^3And thither were all the flocks gathered. And they rolled the stone from the well's mouth, and watered the sheep, and put the stone again upon the well's mouth in its place. ^4And Jacob said unto them, My brethren, whence are ye? And they said, Of Haran are we. ^5And he said unto them, Know ye Laban the son of Nahor? And they said, We know him. ^6And he said unto them, Is it well with him? And they said, It is well. And, behold, Rachel his daughter cometh with the sheep. ^7And he said, Lo, it is yet high day, neither is it time that the cattle should be gathered together. Water ye the sheep, and go and feed them. ^8And they said, We cannot, until all the flocks be gathered together, and they roll the stone from the well's mouth. Then we water the sheep. ^9While he was yet speaking with them, Rachel came with her father's sheep. For she kept them. ^10And it came to pass, when Jacob saw Rachel the daughter of Laban his mother's brother, and the sheep of Laban his mother's brother, that Jacob went near, and rolled the stone from the well's mouth, and watered the flock of Laban his mother's brother. ^11And Jacob kissed Rachel, and lifted up his voice, and wept. ^12And Jacob told Rachel that he was her father's brother, and that he was Rebekah's son. And she ran and told her father.

^13And it came to pass, when Laban heard the tidings of Jacob his sister's son, that he ran to meet him, and embraced him, and kissed him, and brought him to his house. And he told Laban all these things. ^14And Laban said to him, Surely thou art my bone and my flesh. And he abode with him the space of a month. ^15And Laban said unto Jacob, Because thou art my brother, shouldest thou therefore serve me for nought? Tell me, what shall thy wages be? ^16And Laban had two daughters. The name of the elder was Leah, and the name of the younger was Rachel. ^17And Leah's eyes were tender. But Rachel was beautiful and well favored. ^18And Jacob loved Rachel. And he said, I will serve thee seven years for Rachel thy younger daughter. ^19And Laban said, It is better that I give her to thee, than that I should give her to another man. Abide with me. ^20And Jacob served seven years for Rachel. And they seemed unto him but a few days, for the love he had to her.

^21And Jacob said unto Laban, Give me my wife, for my days are fulfilled, that I may go in unto her. ^22And Laban gathered together all the men of the place, and made a feast. ^23And it came to pass in the evening, that he took Leah his daughter, and brought her to him. And he went in unto her. ^24And Laban gave Zilpah his handmaid unto his daughter Leah for a handmaid. ^25And it came to pass in the morning that, behold, it was Leah. And he said to Laban, What is this thou hast done unto me? Did not I serve with thee for Rachel? Wherefore then hast thou beguiled me? ^26And Laban said, It is not so done in our place, to give the younger before the first-born. ^27Fulfil the week of this one, and we will give thee the other also for the service which thou shalt serve with me yet seven other years. ^28And Jacob did so, and fulfilled her week. And he gave him Rachel his daughter to wife. ^29And Laban gave to Rachel his daughter Bilhah his handmaid to be her handmaid. ^30And he went in also unto Rachel, and he loved also Rachel more than Leah, and served with him yet seven other years.

^31And Jehovah saw that Leah was hated, and he opened her womb. But Rachel was barren. ^32And Leah conceived, and bare a son, and she called his name Reuben. For she said, Because Jehovah hath looked upon my affliction. For now my husband will love me. ^33And she conceived again, and bare a son: and said, Because Jehovah hath heard that I am hated, he hath therefore given me this son also. And she called his name Simeon. ^34And she conceived again, and bare a son. And said, Now this time will my husband be joined unto me, because I have borne him three sons. Therefore was his name called Levi. ^35And she conceived again, and bare a son. And she said, This time will I praise Jehovah. Therefore she called his name Judah. And she left off bearing.

Genesis 30

30

^1And when Rachel saw that she bare Jacob no children, Rachel envied her sister; and she said unto Jacob, Give me children, or else I die. ^2And Jacob's anger was kindled against Rachel: and he said, Am I in God's stead, who hath withheld from thee the fruit of the womb? ^3And she said, Behold, my maid Bilhah, go in unto her; that she may bear upon my knees, and I also may obtain children by her. ^4And she gave him Bilhah her handmaid to wife: and Jacob went in unto her. ^5And Bilhah conceived, and bare Jacob a son. ^6And Rachel said, God hath judged me, and hath also heard my voice, and hath given me a son: therefore called she his name Dan. ^7And Bilhah Rachel's handmaid conceived again, and bare Jacob a second son. ^8And Rachel said, With mighty wrestlings have I wrestled with my sister, and have prevailed: and she called his name Naphtali.

^9When Leah saw that she had left off bearing, she took Zilpah her handmaid, and gave her to Jacob to wife. ^10And Zilpah Leah's handmaid bare Jacob a son. ^11And Leah said, Fortunate! and she called his name Gad. ^12And Zilpah Leah's handmaid bare Jacob a second son. ^13And Leah said, Happy am I! for the daughters will call me happy: and she called his name Asher.

^14And Reuben went in the days of wheat harvest, and found mandrakes in the field, and brought them unto his mother Leah. Then Rachel said to Leah, Give me, I pray thee, of thy son's mandrakes. ^15And she said unto her, Is it a small matter that thou hast taken away my husband? and wouldest thou take away my son's mandrakes also? And Rachel said, Therefore he shall lie with thee to-night for thy son's mandrakes. ^16And Jacob came from the field in the evening, and Leah went out to meet him, and said, Thou must come in unto me; for I have surely hired thee with my son's mandrakes. And he lay with her that night. ^17And God hearkened unto Leah, and she conceived, and bare Jacob a fifth son. ^18And Leah said, God hath given me my hire, because I gave my handmaid to my husband: and she called his name Issachar. ^19And Leah conceived again, and bare a sixth son to Jacob. ^20And Leah said, God hath endowed me with a good dowry; now will my husband dwell with me, because I have borne him six sons: and she called his name Zebulun. ^21And afterwards she bare a daughter, and called her name Dinah. ^22And God remembered Rachel, and God hearkened to her, and opened her womb. ^23And she conceived, and bare a son: and said, God hath taken away my reproach: ^24and she called his name Joseph, saying, Jehovah add to me another son.

^25And it came to pass, when Rachel had borne Joseph, that Jacob said unto Laban, Send me away, that I may go unto mine own place, and to my country. ^26Give me my wives and my children for whom I have served thee, and let me go: for thou knowest my service wherewith I have served thee. ^27And Laban said unto him, If now I have found favor in thine eyes, tarry: for I have divined that Jehovah hath blessed me for thy sake. ^28And he said, Appoint me thy wages, and I will give it. ^29And he said unto him, Thou knowest how I have served thee, and how thy cattle have fared with me. ^30For it was little which thou hadst before I came, and it hath increased unto a multitude; and Jehovah hath blessed thee whithersoever I turned: and now when shall I provide for mine own house also? ^31And he said, What shall I give thee? And Jacob said, Thou shalt not give me aught: if thou wilt do this thing for me, I will again feed thy flock and keep it. ^32I will pass through all thy flock to-day, removing from thence every speckled and spotted one, and every black one among the sheep, and the spotted and speckled among the goats: and of such shall be my hire. ^33So shall my righteousness answer for me hereafter, when thou shalt come concerning my hire that is before thee: every one that is not speckled and spotted among the goats, and black among the sheep, that if found with me, shall be counted stolen. ^34And Laban said, Behold, I would it might be according to thy word. ^35And he removed that day the he-goats that were ringstreaked and spotted, and all the she-goats that were speckled and spotted, every one that had white in it, and all the black ones among the sheep, and gave them into the hand of his sons; ^36and he set three days' journey betwixt himself and Jacob: and Jacob fed the rest of Laban's flocks.

^37And Jacob took him rods of fresh poplar, and of the almond and of the plane-tree. And peeled white streaks in them, and made the white appear which was in the rods. ^38And he set the rods which he had peeled over against the flocks in the gutters in the watering-troughs where the flocks came to drink; and they conceived when they came to drink. ^39And the flocks conceived before the rods, and the flocks brought forth ringstreaked, speckled, and spotted. ^40And Jacob separated the lambs, and set the faces of the flocks toward the ringstreaked and all the black in the flock of Laban: and he put his own droves apart, and put them not unto Laban's flock. ^41And it came to pass, whensoever the stronger of the flock did conceive, that Jacob laid the rods before the eyes of the flock in the gutters, that they might conceive among the rods; ^42but when the flock were feeble, he put them not in: so the feebler were Laban's, and the stronger Jacob's. ^43And the man increased exceedingly, and had large flocks, and maid-servants and men-servants, and camels and asses.

Genesis 31

31

^1And he heard the words of Laban's sons, saying, Jacob hath taken away all that was our father's; and of that which was our father's hath he gotten all this glory. ^2And Jacob beheld the countenance of Laban, and, behold, it was not toward him as beforetime. ^3And Jehovah said unto Jacob, Return unto the land of thy fathers, and to thy kindred; and I will be with thee. ^4And Jacob sent and called Rachel and Leah to the field unto his flock, ^5and said unto them, I see your father's countenance, that it is not toward me as beforetime; but the God of my father hath been with me. ^6And ye know that will all my power I have served your father. ^7And your father hath deceived me, and changed my wages ten times; but God suffered him not to hurt me. ^8If he said thus, The speckled shall be thy wages; then all the flock bare speckled: and if he said thus, The ringstreaked shall be thy wages; then bare all the flock ringstreaked. ^9Thus God hath taken away the cattle of your father, and given them to me. ^10And it came to pass at the time that the flock conceive, that I lifted up mine eyes, and saw in a dream, and, behold, the he-goats which leaped upon the flock were ringstreaked, speckled, and grizzled. ^11And the angel of God said unto me in the dream, Jacob: and I said, Here am I. ^12And he said, Lift up now thine eyes, and see, all the he-goats which leap upon the flock are ringstreaked, speckled, and grizzled: for I have seen all that Laban doeth unto thee. ^13I am the God of Beth-el, where thou anointedst a pillar, where thou vowedst a vow unto me: now arise, get thee out from this land, and return unto the land of thy nativity. ^14And Rachel and Leah answered and said unto him, Is there yet any portion or inheritance for us in our father's house? ^15Are we not accounted by him as foreigners? for he hath sold us, and hath also quite devoured our money. ^16For all the riches which God hath taken away from our father, that is ours and our children's: now then, whatsoever God hath said unto thee, do.

^17Then Jacob rose up, and set his sons and his wives upon the camels; ^18and he carried away all his cattle, and all his substance which he had gathered, the cattle of his getting, which he had gathered in Paddan-aram, to go to Isaac his father unto the land of Canaan. ^19Now Laban was gone to shear his sheep: and Rachel stole the teraphim that were her father's. ^20And Jacob stole away unawares to Laban the Syrian, in that he told him not that he fled. ^21So he fled with all that he had; and he rose up, and passed over the River, and set his face toward the mountain of Gilead.

^22And it was told Laban on the third day that Jacob was fled. ^23And he took his brethren with him, and pursued after him seven days' journey; and he overtook him in the mountain of Gilead. ^24And God came to Laban the Syrian in a dream of the night, and said unto him, Take heed to thyself that thou speak not to Jacob either good or bad. ^25And Laban came up with Jacob. Now Jacob had pitched his tent in the mountain: and Laban with his brethren encamped in the mountain of Gilead. ^26And Laban said to Jacob, What hast thou done, that thou hast stolen away unawares to me, and carried away my daughters as captives of the sword? ^27Wherefore didst thou flee secretly, and steal away from me, and didst not tell me, that I might have sent thee away with mirth and with songs, with tabret and with harp; ^28and didst not suffer me to kiss my sons and my daughters? now hast thou done foolishly. ^29It is in the power of my hand to do you hurt: but the God of your father spake unto me yesternight, saying, Take heed to thyself that thou speak not to Jacob either good or bad. ^30And now, though thou wouldest needs be gone, because thou sore longedst after thy father's house, yet wherefore hast thou stolen my gods? ^31And Jacob answered and said to Laban, Because I was afraid: for I said, Lest thou shouldest take thy daughters from me by force. ^32With whomsoever thou findest thy gods, he shall not live: before our brethren discern thou what is thine with me, and take it to thee. For Jacob knew not that Rachel had stolen them.

^33And Laban went into Jacob's tent, and into Leah's tent, and into the tent of the two maid-servants; but he found them not. And he went out of Leah's tent, and entered into Rachel's tent. ^34Now Rachel had taken the teraphim, and put them in the camel's saddle, and sat upon them. And Laban felt about all the tent, but found them not. ^35And she said to her father, Let not my lord be angry that I cannot rise up before thee; for the manner of women is upon me. And he searched, but found not the teraphim.

^36And Jacob was wroth, and chode with Laban: and Jacob answered and said to Laban, What is my trespass? what is my sin, that thou hast hotly pursued after me? ^37Whereas thou hast felt about all my stuff, what hast thou found of all thy household stuff? Set it here before my brethren and thy brethren, that they may judge betwixt us two. ^38These twenty years have I been with thee; thy ewes and thy she-goats have not cast their young, and the rams of thy flocks have I not eaten. ^39That which was torn of beasts I brought not unto thee; I bare the loss of it; of my hand didst thou require it, whether stolen by day or stolen by night. ^40Thus I was; in the day the drought consumed me, and the frost by night; and my sleep fled from mine eyes. ^41These twenty years have I been in thy house; I served thee fourteen years for thy two daughters, and six years for thy flock: and thou hast changed my wages ten times. ^42Except the God of my father, the God of Abraham, and the Fear of Isaac, had been with me, surely now hadst thou sent me away empty. God hath seen mine affliction and the labor of my hands, and rebuked thee yesternight.

^43And Laban answered and said unto Jacob, The daughters are my daughters, and the children are my children, and the flocks are my flocks, and all that thou seest is mine: and what can I do this day unto these my daughters, or unto their children whom they have borne? ^44And now come, let us make a covenant, I and thou; and let it be for a witness between me and thee. ^45And Jacob took a stone, and set it up for a pillar. ^46And Jacob said unto his brethren, Gather stones; and they took stones, and made a heap: and they did eat there by the heap. ^47And Laban called it Jegar-saha-dutha: but Jacob called it Galeed. ^48And Laban said, This heap is witness between me and thee this day. Therefore was the name of it called Galeed: ^49and Mizpah, for he said, Jehovah watch between me and thee, when we are absent one from another. ^50If thou shalt afflict my daughters, and if thou shalt take wives besides my daughters, no man is with us; see, God is witness betwixt me and thee. ^51And Laban said to Jacob, Behold this heap, and behold the pillar, which I have set betwixt me and thee. ^52This heap be witness, and the pillar be witness, that I will not pass over this heap to thee, and that thou shalt not pass over this heap and this pillar unto me, for harm. ^53The God of Abraham, and the God of Nahor, the God of their father, judge betwixt us. And Jacob sware by the Fear of his father Isaac. ^54And Jacob offered a sacrifice in the mountain, and called his brethren to eat bread: and they did eat bread, and tarried all night in the mountain. ^55And early in the morning Laban rose up, and kissed his sons and his daughters, and blessed them: and Laban departed and returned unto his place.

Genesis 32

32

^1And Jacob went on his way, and the angels of God met him. ^2And Jacob said when he saw them, This is God's host: and he called the name of that place Mahanaim.

^3And Jacob sent messengers before him to Esau his brother unto the land of Seir, the field of Edom. ^4And he commanded them, saying, Thus shall ye say unto my lord Esau: Thus saith thy servant Jacob, I have sojourned with Laban, and stayed until now: ^5and I have oxen, and asses, and flocks, and men-servants, and maid-servants: and I have sent to tell my lord, that I may find favor in thy sight. ^6And the messengers returned to Jacob, saying, We came to thy brother Esau, and moreover he cometh to meet thee, and four hundred men with him. ^7Then Jacob was greatly afraid and was distressed: and he divided the people that were with him, and the flocks, and the herds, and the camels, into two companies; ^8and he said, If Esau come to the one company, and smite it, then the company which is left shall escape. ^9And Jacob said, O God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Isaac, O Jehovah, who saidst unto me, Return unto thy country, and to thy kindred, and I will do thee good: ^10I am not worthy of the least of all the lovingkindnesses, and of all the truth, which thou hast showed unto thy servant; for with my staff I passed over this Jordan; and now I am become two companies. ^11Deliver me, I pray thee, from the hand of my brother, from the hand of Esau: for I fear him, lest he come and smite me, the mother with the children. ^12And thou saidst, I will surely do thee good, and make thy seed as the sand of the sea, which cannot be numbered for multitude.

^13And he lodged there that night, and took of that which he had with him a present for Esau his brother: ^14two hundred she-goats and twenty he-goats, two hundred ewes and twenty rams, ^15thirty milch camels and their colts, forty cows and ten bulls, twenty she-asses and ten foals. ^16And he delivered them into the hand of his servants, every drove by itself, and said unto his servants, Pass over before me, and put a space betwixt drove and drove. ^17And he commanded the foremost, saying, When Esau my brother meeteth thee, and asketh thee, saying, Whose art thou? and whither goest thou? and whose are these before thee? ^18then thou shalt say They are thy servant Jacob's; it is a present sent unto my lord Esau: and, behold, he also is behind us. ^19And he commanded also the second, and the third, and all that followed the droves, saying, On this manner shall ye speak unto Esau, when ye find him; ^20and ye shall say, Moreover, behold, thy servant Jacob is behind us. For he said, I will appease him with the present that goeth before me, and afterward I will see his face; peradventure he will accept me. ^21So the present passed over before him: and he himself lodged that night in the company.

^22And he rose up that night, and took his two wives, and his two handmaids, and his eleven children, and passed over the ford of the Jabbok. ^23And he took them, and sent them over the stream, and sent over that which he had. ^24And Jacob was left alone; and there wrestled a man with him until the breaking of the day. ^25And when he saw that he prevailed not against him, he touched the hollow of his thigh; and the hollow of Jacob's thigh was strained, as he wrestled with him. ^26And he said, Let me go, for the day breaketh. And he said, I will not let thee go, except thou bless me. ^27And he said unto him, What is thy name? And he said, Jacob. ^28And he said, Thy name shall be called no more Jacob, but Israel: for thou hast striven with God and with men, and hast prevailed. ^29And Jacob asked him, and said, Tell me, I pray thee, thy name. And he said, Wherefore is it that thou dost ask after my name? And he blessed him there. ^30And Jacob called the name of the place Peniel: for, said he, I have seen God face to face, and my life is preserved. ^31And the sun rose upon him as he passed over Penuel, and he limped upon his thigh. ^32Therefore the children of Israel eat not the sinew of the hip which is upon the hollow of the thigh, unto this day: because he touched the hollow of Jacob's thigh in the sinew of the hip.

Genesis 33

33

^1And Jacob lifted up his eyes, and looked, and, behold, Esau was coming, and with him four hundred men. And he divided the children unto Leah, and unto Rachel, and unto the two handmaids. ^2And he put the handmaids and their children foremost, and Leah and her children after, and Rachel and Joseph hindermost. ^3And he himself passed over before them, and bowed himself to the ground seven times, until he came near to his brother. ^4And Esau ran to meet him, and embraced him, and fell on his neck, and kissed him: and they wept. ^5And he lifted up his eyes, and saw the women and the children; and said, Who are these with thee? And he said, The children whom God hath graciously given thy servant. ^6Then the handmaids came near, they and their children, and they bowed themselves. ^7And Leah also and her children came near, and bowed themselves: and after came Joseph near and Rachel, and they bowed themselves. ^8And he said, What meanest thou by all this company which I met? And he said, To find favor in the sight of my lord. ^9And Esau said, I have enough, my brother; let that which thou hast be thine. ^10And Jacob said, Nay, I pray thee, if now I have found favor in thy sight, then receive my present at my hand; forasmuch as I have seen thy face, as one seeth the face of God, and thou wast pleased with me. ^11Take, I pray thee, my gift that is brought to thee; because God hath dealt graciously with me, and because I have enough. And he urged him, and he took it. ^12And he said, Let us take our journey, and let us go, and I will go before thee. ^13And he said unto him, My lord knoweth that the children are tender, and that the flocks and herds with me have their young: and if they overdrive them one day, all the flocks will die. ^14Let my lord, I pray thee, pass over before his servant: and I will lead on gently, according to the pace of the cattle that are before me and according to the pace of the children, until I come unto my lord unto Seir. ^15And Esau said, Let me now leave with thee some of the folk that are with me. And he said, What needeth it? let me find favor in the sight of my lord. ^16So Esau returned that day on his way unto Seir. ^17And Jacob journeyed to Succoth, and built him a house, and made booths for his cattle: therefore the name of the place is called Succoth.

^18And Jacob came in peace to the city of Shechem, which is in the land of Canaan, when he came from Paddan-aram; and encamped before the city. ^19And he bought the parcel of ground, where he had spread his tent, at the hand of the children of Hamor, Shechem's father, for a hundred pieces of money. ^20And he erected there an altar, and called it El-elohe-israel.

Genesis 34

34

^1And Dinah the daughter of Leah, whom she bare unto Jacob, went out to see the daughters of the land. ^2And Shechem the son of Hamor the Hivite, the prince of the land, saw her; And he took her, and lay with her, and humbled her. ^3And his soul clave unto Dinah the daughter of Jacob, and he loved the damsel, and spake kindly unto the damsel. ^4And Shechem spake unto his father Hamor, saying, Get me this damsel to wife. ^5Now Jacob heard that he had defiled Dinah his daughter; and his sons were with his cattle in the field: and Jacob held his peace until they came. ^6And Hamor the father of Shechem went out unto Jacob to commune with him. ^7And the sons of Jacob came in from the field when they heard it: and the men were grieved, and they were very wroth, because he had wrought folly in Israel in lying with Jacob's daughter; which thing ought not to be done. ^8And Hamor communed with them, saying, The soul of my son Shechem longeth for your daughter: I pray you, give her unto him to wife. ^9And make ye marriages with us; give your daughters unto us, and take our daughters unto you. ^10And ye shall dwell with us: and the land shall be before you; dwell and trade ye therein, and get you possessions therein. ^11And Shechem said unto her father and unto her brethren, Let me find favor in your eyes, and what ye shall say unto me I will give. ^12Ask me never so much dowry and gift, and I will give according as ye shall say unto me: but give me the damsel to wife. ^13And the sons of Jacob answered Shechem and Hamor his father with guile, and spake, because he had defiled Dinah their sister, ^14and said unto them, We cannot do this thing, to give our sister to one that is uncircumcised; for that were a reproach unto us. ^15Only on this condition will we consent unto you: if ye will be as we are, that every male of you be circumcised; ^16then will we give our daughters unto you, and we will take your daughters to us, and we will dwell with you, and we will become one people. ^17But if ye will not hearken unto us, to be circumcised; then will we take our daughter, and we will be gone.

^18And their words pleased Hamor, and Shechem Hamor's son. ^19And the young man deferred not to do the thing, because he had delight in Jacob's daughter: and he was honored above all the house of his father. ^20And Hamor and Shechem his son came unto the gate of their city, and communed with the men of their city, saying, ^21These men are peaceable with us; therefore let them dwell in the land, and trade therein; for, behold, the land is large enough for them; let us take their daughters to us for wives, and let us give them our daughters. ^22Only on this condition will the men consent unto us to dwell with us, to become one people, if every male among us be circumcised, as they are circumcised. ^23Shall not their cattle and their substance and all their beasts be ours? only let us consent unto them, and they will dwell with us. ^24And unto Hamor and unto Shechem his son hearkened all that went out of the gate of his city; and every male was circumcised, all that went out of the gate of his city. ^25And it came to pass on the third day, when they were sore, that two of the sons of Jacob, Simeon and Levi, Dinah's brethren, took each man his sword, and came upon the city unawares, and slew all the males. ^26And they slew Hamor and Shechem his son with the edge of the sword, and took Dinah out of Shechem's house, and went forth. ^27The sons of Jacob came upon the slain, and plundered the city, because they had defiled their sister. ^28They took their flocks and their herds and their asses, and that which was in the city, and that which was in the field; ^29and all their wealth, and all their little ones and their wives, took they captive and made a prey, even all that was in the house. ^30And Jacob said to Simeon and Levi, Ye have troubled me, to make me odious to the inhabitants of the land, among the Canaanites and the Perizzites: and, I being few in number, they will gather themselves together against me and smite me; and I shall be destroyed, I and my house. ^31And they said, Should he deal with our sister as with a harlot?

Genesis 36

36

^1Now these are the generations of Esau (the same is Edom). ^2Esau took his wives of the daughters of Canaan: Adah the daughter of Elon the Hittite, and Oholibamah the daughter of Anah, the daughter of Zibeon the Hivite, ^3and Basemath Ishmael's daughter, sister of Nebaioth. ^4And Adah bare to Esau Eliphaz; and Basemath bare Reuel; ^5and Oholibamah bare Jeush, and Jalam, and Korah: these are the sons of Esau, that were born unto him in the land of Canaan. ^6And Esau took his wives, and his sons, and his daughters, and all the souls of his house, and his cattle, and all his beasts, and all his possessions, which he had gather in the land of Canaan; and went into a land away from his brother Jacob. ^7For their substance was too great for them to dwell together; and the land of their sojournings could not bear them because of their cattle. ^8And Esau dwelt in mount Seir: Esau is Edom.

^9And these are the generations of Esau the father of the Edomites in mount Seir: ^10these are the names of Esau's sons: Eliphaz the son of Adah the wife of Esau, Reuel the son of Basemath the wife of Esau. ^11And the sons of Eliphaz were Teman, Omar, Zepho, and Gatam, and Kenaz. ^12And Timna was concubine to Eliphaz Esau's son; and she bare to Eliphaz Amalek: these are the sons of Adah, Esau's wife. ^13And these are the sons of Reuel: Nahath, and Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah: these were the sons of Basemath, Esau's wife. ^14And these were the sons of Oholibamah the daughter of Anah, the daughter of Zibeon, Esau's wife: and she bare to Esau Jeush, and Jalam, and Korah.

^15These are the chiefs of the sons of Esau: the sons of Eliphaz the first-born of Esau: chief Teman, chief Omar, chief Zepho, chief Kenaz, ^16chief Korah, chief Gatam, chief Amalek: these are the chiefs that came of Eliphaz in the land of Edom; these are the sons of Adah. ^17And these are the sons of Reuel, Esau's son: chief Nahath, chief Zerah, chief Shammah, chief Mizzah: these are the chiefs that came of Reuel in the land of Edom; these are the sons of Basemath, Esau's wife. ^18And these are the sons of Oholibamah, Esau's wife: chief Jeush, chief Jalam, chief Korah: these are the chiefs that came of Oholibamah the daughter of Anah, Esau's wife. ^19These are the sons of Esau, and these are their chiefs: the same is Edom.

^20These are the sons of Seir the Horite, the inhabitants of the land: Lotan and Shobal and Zibeon and Anah, ^21and Dishon and Ezer and Dishan: these are the chiefs that came of the Horites, the children of Seir in the land of Edom. ^22And the children of Lotan were Hori and Heman. And Lotan's sister was Timna. ^23And these are the children of Shobal: Alvan and Manahath and Ebal, Shepho and Onam. ^24And these are the children of Zibeon: Aiah and Anah; this is Anah who found the hot springs in the wilderness, as he fed the asses of Zibeon his father. ^25And these are the children of Anah: Dishon and Oholibamah the daughter of Anah. ^26And these are the children of Dishon: Hemdan and Eshban and Ithran and Cheran. ^27These are the children of Ezer: Bilhan and Zaavan and Akan. ^28These are the children of Dishan: Uz and Aran. ^29These are the chiefs that came of the Horites: chief Lotan, chief Shobal, chief Zibeon, chief Anah, ^30chief Dishon, chief Ezer, chief Dishan: these are the chiefs that came of the Horites, according to their chiefs in the land of Seir.

^31And these are the kings that reigned in the land of Edom, before there reigned any king over the children of Israel. ^32And Bela the son of Beor reigned in Edom; and the name of his city was Dinhabah. ^33And Bela died, and Jobab the son of Zerah of Bozrah reigned in his stead. ^34And Jobab died, and Husham of the land of the Temanites reigned in his stead. ^35And Husham died, and Hadad the son of Bedad, who smote Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Avith. ^36And Hadad died, and Samlah of Masrekah reigned in his stead. ^37And Samlah died, and Shaul of Rehoboth by the River reigned in his stead. ^38And Shaul died, and Baal-hanan the son of Achbor reigned in his stead. ^39And Baal-hanan the son of Achbor died, and Hadar reigned in his stead: and the name of his city was Pau; and his wife's name was Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Me-zahab.

^40And these are the names of the chiefs that came of Esau, according to their families, after their places, by their names: chief Timna, chief Alvah, chief Jetheth, ^41chief Oholibamah, chief Elah, chief Pinon, ^42chief Kenaz, chief Teman, chief Mibzar, ^43chief Magdiel, chief Iram: these are the chiefs of Edom, according to their habitations in the land of their possession. This is Esau, the father of the Edomites.

Genesis 37

37

^1And Jacob dwelt in the land of his father's sojournings, in the land of Canaan. ^2These are the generations of Jacob. Joseph, being seventeen years old, was feeding the flock with his brethren; and he was a lad with the sons of Bilhah, and with the sons of Zilpah, his father's wives: and Joseph brought the evil report of them unto their father. ^3Now Israel loved Joseph more than all his children, because he was the son of his old age: and he made him a coat of many colors. ^4And his brethren saw that their father loved him more than all his brethren; and they hated him, and could not speak peaceably unto him.

^5And Joseph dreamed a dream, and he told it to his brethren: and they hated him yet the more. ^6And he said unto them, Hear, I pray you, this dream which I have dreamed: ^7for, behold, we were binding sheaves in the field, and, lo, my sheaf arose, and also stood upright; and, behold, your sheaves came round about, and made obeisance to my sheaf. ^8And his brethren said to him, Shalt thou indeed reign over us? Or shalt thou indeed have dominion over us? And they hated him yet the more for his dreams, and for his words. ^9And he dreamed yet another dream, and told it to his brethren, and said, Behold, I have dreamed yet a dream: and, behold, the sun and the moon and eleven stars made obeisance to me. ^10And he told it to his father, and to his brethren; and his father rebuked him, and said unto him, What is this dream that thou hast dreamed? Shall I and thy mother and thy brethren indeed come to bow down ourselves to thee to the earth? ^11And his brethren envied him; but his father kept the saying in mind.

^12And his brethren went to feed their father's flock in Shechem. ^13And Israel said unto Joseph, Are not thy brethren feeding the flock in Shechem? Come, and I will send thee unto them. And he said to him, Here am I. ^14And he said to him, Go now, see whether it is well with thy brethren, and well with the flock; and bring me word again. So he sent him out of the vale of Hebron, and he came to Shechem. ^15And a certain man found him, and, behold, he was wandering in the field: and the man asked him, saying, What seekest thou? ^16And he said, I am seeking my brethren: tell me, I pray thee, where they are feeding the flock. ^17And the man said, They are departed hence; for I heard them say, Let us go to Dothan. And Joseph went after his brethren, and found them in Dothan.

^18And they saw him afar off, and before he came near unto them, they conspired against him to slay him. ^19And they said one to another, Behold, this dreamer cometh. ^20Come now therefore, and let us slay him, and cast him into one of the pits, and we will say, And evil beast hath devoured him: and we shall see what will become of his dreams. ^21And Reuben heard it, and delivered him out of their hand, and said, Let us not take his life. ^22And Reuben said unto them, Shed no blood; cast him into this pit that is in the wilderness, but lay no hand upon him: that he might deliver him out of their hand, to restore him to his father. ^23And it came to pass, when Joseph was come unto his brethren, that they stripped Joseph of his coat, the coat of many colors that was on him; ^24and they took him, and cast him into the pit: and the pit was empty, there was no water in it.

^25And they sat down to eat bread: and they lifted up their eyes and looked, and, behold, a caravan of Ishmaelites was coming from Gilead, with their camels bearing spicery and balm and myrrh, going to carry it down to Egypt. ^26And Judah said unto his brethren, What profit is it if we slay our brother and conceal his blood? ^27Come, and let us sell him to the Ishmaelites, and let not our hand be upon him; for he is our brother, our flesh. And his brethren hearkened unto him. ^28And there passed by Midianites, merchantmen; and they drew and lifted up Joseph out of the pit, and sold Joseph to the Ishmaelites for twenty pieces of silver. And they brought Joseph into Egypt.

^29And Reuben returned unto the pit; and, behold, Joseph was not in the pit; and he rent his clothes. ^30And he returned unto his brethren, and said, The child is not; and I, whither shall I go? ^31And they took Joseph's coat, and killed a he-goat, and dipped the coat in the blood; ^32and they sent the coat of many colors, and they brought it to their father, and said, This have we found: know now whether it is thy son's coat or not. ^33And he knew it, and said, It is my son's coat: an evil beast hath devoured him; Joseph is without doubt torn in pieces. ^34And Jacob rent his garments, and put sackcloth upon his loins, and mourned for his son many days. ^35And all his sons and all his daughters rose up to comfort him; but he refused to be comforted; and he said, For I will go down to Sheol to my son mourning. And his father wept for him. ^36And the Midianites sold him into Egypt unto Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh's, the captain of the guard.

Genesis 38

38

^1And it came to pass at that time, that Judah went down from his brethren, and turned in to a certain Adullamite, whose name was Hirah. ^2And Judah saw there a daughter of a certain Canaanite whose name was Shua. And he took her, and went in unto her. ^3And she conceived, and bare a son; and he called his name Er. ^4And she conceived again, and bare a son; and she called his name Onan. ^5And she yet again bare a son, and called his name Shelah: and he was at Chezib, when she bare him. ^6And Judah took a wife for Er his first-born, and her name was Tamar. ^7And Er, Judah's first-born, was wicked in the sight of Jehovah. And Jehovah slew him. ^8And Judah said unto Onan, Go in unto thy brother's wife, and perform the duty of a husband's brother unto her, and raise up seed to thy brother. ^9And Onan knew that the seed would not be his; and it came to pass, when he went in unto his brother's wife, that he spilled it on the ground, lest he should give seed to his brother. ^10And the thing which he did was evil in the sight of Jehovah: and he slew him also. ^11Then said Judah to Tamar his daughter-in-law, Remain a widow in thy father's house, till Shelah my son be grown up; for he said, Lest he also die, like his brethren. And Tamar went and dwelt in her father's house.

^12And in process of time Shua's daughter, the wife of Judah, died; and Judah was comforted, and went up unto his sheep-shearers to Timnah, he and his friend Hirah the Adullamite. ^13And it was told Tamar, saying, Behold, thy father-in-law goeth up to Timnah to shear his sheep. ^14And she put off from her the garments of her widowhood, and covered herself with her veil, and wrapped herself, and sat in the gate of Enaim, which is by the way to Timnah; for she saw that Shelah was grown up, and she was not given unto him to wife. ^15When Judah saw her, he thought her to be a harlot; for she had covered her face. ^16And he turned unto her by the way, and said, Come, I pray thee, let me come in unto thee: for he knew not that she was his daughter-in-law. And she said, What wilt thou give me, that thou mayest come in unto me? ^17And he said, I will send thee a kid of the goats from the flock. And she said, Wilt thou give me a pledge, till thou send it? ^18And he said, What pledge shall I give thee? And she said, Thy signet and thy cord, and thy staff that is in thy hand. And he gave them to her, and came in unto her, and she conceived by him. ^19And she arose, and went away, and put off her veil from her, and put on the garments of her widowhood. ^20And Judah sent the kid of the goats by the hand of his friend the Adullamite, to receive the pledge from the woman's hand: but he found her not. ^21Then he asked the men of her place, saying, Where is the prostitute, that was at Enaim by the wayside? And they said, There hath been no prostitute here. ^22And he returned to Judah, and said, I have not found her; and also the men of the place said, There hath been no prostitute here. ^23And Judah said, Let her take it to her, lest we be put to shame: behold, I sent this kid, and thou hast not found her.

^24And it came to pass about three months after, that it was told Judah, saying, Tamar thy daughter-in-law hath played the harlot; and moreover, behold, she is with child by whoredom. And Judah said, Bring her forth, and let her be burnt. ^25When she was brought forth, she sent to her father-in-law, saying, By the man, whose these are, am I with child: and she said, Discern, I pray thee, whose are these, the signet, and the cords, and the staff. ^26And Judah acknowledged them, and said, She is more righteous than I; forasmuch as I gave her not to Shelah my son. And he knew her again no more. ^27And it came to pass in the time of her travail, that, behold, twins were in her womb. ^28And it came to pass, when she travailed, that one put out a hand: and the midwife took and bound upon his hand a scarlet thread, saying, This came out first. ^29And it came to pass, as he drew back his hand, that, behold, his brother came out: and she said, Wherefore hast thou made a breach for thyself? Therefore his name was called Perez. ^30And afterward came out his brother, that had the scarlet thread upon his hand: and his name was called Zerah.

Genesis 39

39

^1And Joseph was brought down to Egypt; and Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh's, the captain of the guard, an Egyptian, bought him of the hand of the Ishmaelites, that had brought him down thither. ^2And Jehovah was with Joseph, and he was a prosperous man; and he was in the house of his master the Egyptian. ^3And his master saw that Jehovah was with him, and that Jehovah made all that he did to prosper in his hand. ^4And Joseph found favor in his sight, and he ministered unto him: and he made him overseer over his house, and all that he had he put into his hand. ^5And it came to pass from the time that he made him overseer in his house, and over all that he had, that Jehovah blessed the Egyptian's house for Joseph's sake; and the blessing of Jehovah was upon all that he had, in the house and in the field. ^6And he left all that he had in Joseph's hand; and he knew not aught that was with him, save the bread which he did eat. And Joseph was comely, and well-favored. ^7And it came to pass after these things, that his master's wife cast her eyes upon Joseph; and she said, Lie with me. ^8But he refused, and said unto his master's wife, Behold, my master knoweth not what is with me in the house, and he hath put all that he hath into my hand: ^9he is not greater in this house than I; neither hath he kept back anything from me but thee, because thou art his wife: how then can I do this great wickedness, and sin against God? ^10And it came to pass, as she spake to Joseph day by day, that he hearkened not unto her, to lie by her, or to be with her. ^11And it came to pass about this time, that he went into the house to do his work; and there was none of the men of the house there within. ^12And she caught him by his garment, saying, Lie with me: and he left his garment in her hand, and fled, and got him out. ^13And it came to pass, when she saw that he had left his garment in her hand, and was fled forth, ^14that she called unto the men of her house, and spake unto them, saying, See, he hath brought in a Hebrew unto us to mock us: he came in unto me to lie with me, and I cried with a loud voice: ^15and it came to pass, when he heard that I lifted up my voice and cried, that he left his garment by me, and fled, and got him out. ^16And she laid up his garment by her, until his master came home. ^17And she spake unto him according to these words, saying, The Hebrew servant, whom thou hast brought unto us, came in unto me to mock me: ^18and it came to pass, as I lifted up my voice and cried, that he left his garment by me, and fled out.

^19And it came to pass, when his master heard the words of his wife, which she spake unto him, saying, After this manner did thy servant to me; that his wrath was kindled. ^20And Joseph's master took him, and put him into the prison, the place where the king's prisoners were bound: and he was there in the prison. ^21But Jehovah was with Joseph, and showed kindness unto him, and gave him favor in the sight of the keeper of the prison. ^22And the keeper of the prison committed to Joseph's hand all the prisoners that were in the prison; and whatsoever they did there, he was the doer of it. ^23The keeper of the prison looked not to anything that was under his hand, because Jehovah was with him; and that which he did, Jehovah made it prosper.

Genesis 40

40

^1And it came to pass after these things, that the butler of the king of Egypt and his baker offended their lord the king of Egypt. ^2And Pharaoh was wroth against his two officers, against the chief of the butlers, and against the chief of the bakers. ^3And he put them in ward in the house of the captain of the guard, into the prison, the place where Joseph was bound. ^4And the captain of the guard charged Joseph with them, and he ministered unto them: and they continued a season in ward. ^5And they dreamed a dream both of them, each man his dream, in one night, each man according to the interpretation of his dream, the butler and the baker of the king of Egypt, who were bound in the prison. ^6And Joseph came in unto them in the morning, and saw them, and, behold, they were sad. ^7And he asked Pharaoh's officers that were with him in ward in his master's house, saying, Wherefore look ye so sad to-day? ^8And they said unto him, We have dreamed a dream, and there is none that can interpret it. And Joseph said unto them, Do not interpretations belong to God? tell it me, I pray you.

^9And the chief butler told his dream to Joseph, and said to him, In my dream, behold, a vine was before me; ^10and in the vine were three branches: and it was as though it budded, and its blossoms shot forth; and the clusters thereof brought forth ripe grapes: ^11and Pharaoh's cup was in my hand; and I took the grapes, and pressed them into Pharaoh's cup, and I gave the cup into Pharaoh's hand. ^12And Joseph said unto him, This is the interpretation of it: the three branches are three days; ^13within yet three days shall Pharaoh lift up thy head, and restore thee unto thine office: and thou shalt give Pharaoh's cup into his hand, after the former manner when thou wast his butler. ^14But have me in thy remembrance when it shall be well with thee, and show kindness, I pray thee, unto me, and make mention of me unto Pharaoh, and bring me out of this house: ^15for indeed I was stolen away out of the land of the Hebrews: and here also have I done nothing that they should put me into the dungeon.

^16When the chief baker saw that the interpretation was good, he said unto Joseph, I also was in my dream, and, behold, three baskets of white bread were on my head: ^17and in the uppermost basket there was of all manner of baked food for Pharaoh; and the birds did eat them out of the basket upon my head. ^18And Joseph answered and said, This is the interpretation thereof: the three baskets are three days; ^19within yet three days shall Pharaoh lift up thy head from off thee, and shall hang thee on a tree; and the birds shall eat thy flesh from off thee. ^20And it came to pass the third day, which was Pharaoh's birthday, that he made a feast unto all his servants: and he lifted up the head of the chief butler and the head of the chief baker among his servants. ^21And he restored the chief butler unto his butlership again; and he gave the cup into Pharaoh's hand: ^22but he hanged the chief baker: as Joseph had interpreted to them. ^23Yet did not the chief butler remember Joseph, but forgat him.

Genesis 41

41

^1And it came to pass at the end of two full years, that Pharaoh dreamed: and, behold, he stood by the river. ^2And, behold, there came up out of the river seven kine, well-favored and fat-fleshed; and they fed in the reed-grass. ^3And, behold, seven other kine came up after them out of the river, ill-favored and lean-fleshed, and stood by the other kine upon the brink of the river. ^4And the ill-favored and lean-fleshed kine did eat up the seven well-favored and fat kine. So Pharaoh awoke. ^5And he slept and dreamed a second time: and, behold, seven ears of grain came up upon one stalk, rank and good. ^6And, behold, seven ears, thin and blasted with the east wind, sprung up after them. ^7And the thin ears swallowed up the seven rank and full ears. And Pharaoh awoke, and, behold, it was a dream. ^8And it came to pass in the morning that his spirit was troubled; and he sent and called for all the magicians of Egypt, and all the wise men thereof: and Pharaoh told them his dream; but there was none that could interpret them unto Pharaoh.

^9Then spake the chief butler unto Pharaoh, saying, I do remember my faults this day: ^10Pharaoh was wroth with his servants, and put me in ward in the house of the captain of the guard, me and the chief baker: ^11and we dreamed a dream in one night, I and he; we dreamed each man according to the interpretation of his dream. ^12And there was with us there a young man, a Hebrew, servant to the captain of the guard; and we told him, and he interpreted to us our dreams; to each man according to his dream he did interpret. ^13And it came to pass, as he interpreted to us, so it was; me he restored unto mine office, and him he hanged.

^14Then Pharaoh sent and called Joseph, and they brought him hastily out of the dungeon: and he shaved himself, and changed his raiment, and came in unto Pharaoh. ^15And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I have dreamed a dream, and there is none that can interpret it: and I have heard say of thee, that when thou hearest a dream thou canst interpret it. ^16And Joseph answered Pharaoh, saying, It is not in me: God will give Pharaoh an answer of peace. ^17And Pharaoh spake unto Joseph, In my dream, behold, I stood upon the brink of the river: ^18and, behold, there came up out of the river seven kine, fat-fleshed and well-favored: and they fed in the reed-grass: ^19and, behold, seven other kine came up after them, poor and very ill-favored and lean-fleshed, such as I never saw in all the land of Egypt for badness: ^20and the lean and ill-favored kine did eat up the first seven fat kine: ^21and when they had eaten them up, it could not be known that they had eaten them; but they were still ill-favored, as at the beginning. So I awoke. ^22And I saw in my dream, and, behold, seven ears came up upon one stalk, full and good: ^23and, behold, seven ears, withered, thin, and blasted with the east wind, sprung up after them: ^24and the thin ears swallowed up the seven good ears: and I told it unto the magicians; but there was none that could declare it to me.

^25And Joseph said unto Pharaoh, The dream of Pharaoh is one: what God is about to do he hath declared unto Pharaoh. ^26The seven good kine are seven years; and the seven good ears are seven years: the dream is one. ^27And the seven lean and ill-favored kine that came up after them are seven years, and also the seven empty ears blasted with the east wind; they shall be seven years of famine. ^28That is the thing which I spake unto Pharaoh: what God is about to do he hath showed unto Pharaoh. ^29Behold, there come seven years of great plenty throughout all the land of Egypt: ^30and there shall arise after them seven years of famine; and all the plenty shall be forgotten in the land of Egypt; and the famine shall consume the land; ^31and the plenty shall not be known in the land by reason of that famine which followeth; for it shall be very grievous. ^32And for that the dream was doubled unto Pharaoh, it is because the thing is established by God, and God will shortly bring it to pass. ^33Now therefore let Pharaoh look out a man discreet and wise, and set him over the land of Egypt. ^34Let Pharaoh do this, and let him appoint overseers over the land, and take up the fifth part of the land of Egypt in the seven plenteous years. ^35And let them gather all the food of these good years that come, and lay up grain under the hand of Pharaoh for food in the cities, and let them keep it. ^36And the food shall be for a store to the land against the seven years of famine, which shall be in the land of Egypt; that the land perish not through the famine.

^37And the thing was good in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of all his servants. ^38And Pharaoh said unto his servants, Can we find such a one as this, a man in whom the spirit of God is? ^39And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Forasmuch as God hath showed thee all of this, there is none so discreet and wise as thou: ^40thou shalt be over my house, and according unto thy word shall all my people be ruled: only in the throne will I be greater than thou. ^41And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, See, I have set thee over all the land of Egypt. ^42And Pharaoh took off his signet ring from his hand, and put it upon Joseph's hand, and arrayed him in vestures of fine linen, and put a gold chain about his neck; ^43and he made him to ride in the second chariot which he had; and they cried before him, Bow the knee: and he set him over all the land of Egypt. ^44And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, I am Pharaoh, and without thee shall no man lift up his hand or his foot in all the land of Egypt. ^45And Pharaoh called Joseph's name Zaphenath-paneah; and he gave him to wife Asenath, the daughter of Poti-phera priest of On. And Joseph went out over the land of Egypt.

^46And Joseph was thirty years old when he stood before Pharaoh king of Egypt. And Joseph went out from the presence of Pharaoh, and went throughout all the land of Egypt. ^47And in the seven plenteous years the earth brought forth by handfuls. ^48And he gathered up all the food of the seven years which were in the land of Egypt, and laid up the food in the cities: the food of the field, which was round about every city, laid he up in the same. ^49And Joseph laid up grain as the sand of the sea, very much, until he left off numbering; for it was without number. ^50And unto Joseph were born two sons before the year of famine came, whom Asenath, the daughter of Potiphera priest of On, bare unto him. ^51And Joseph called the name of the first-born Manasseh: For, said he, God hath made me forget all my toil, and all my father's house. ^52And the name of the second called he Ephraim: For God hath made me fruitful in the land of my affliction. ^53And the seven years of plenty, that was in the land of Egypt, came to an end. ^54And the seven years of famine began to come, according as Joseph had said: and there was famine in all lands; but in all the land of Egypt there was bread. ^55And when all the land of Egypt was famished, the people cried to Pharaoh for bread: and Pharaoh said unto all the Egyptians, Go unto Joseph; what he saith to you, do. ^56And the famine was over all the face of the earth: and Joseph opened all the store-houses, and sold unto the Egyptians; and the famine was sore in the land of Egypt. ^57And all countries came into Egypt to Joseph to buy grain, because the famine was sore in all the earth.

Genesis 42

42

^1Now Jacob saw that there was grain in Egypt, and Jacob said unto his sons, Why do ye look one upon another? ^2And he said, Behold, I have heard that there is grain in Egypt: get you down thither, and buy for us from thence; that we may live, and not die. ^3And Joseph's ten brethren went down to buy grain from Egypt. ^4But Benjamin, Joseph's brother, Jacob sent not with his brethren; for he said, Lest Peradventure harm befall him. ^5And the sons of Israel came to buy among those that came: for the famine was in the land of Canaan. ^6And Joseph was the governor over the land; he it was that sold to all the people of the land. And Joseph's brethren came, and bowed down themselves to him with their faces to the earth. ^7And Joseph saw his brethren, and he knew them, but made himself strange unto them, and spake roughly with them; and he said unto them. Whence come ye? And they said, From the land of Canaan to buy food. ^8And Joseph knew his brethren, but they knew not him. ^9And Joseph remembered the dreams which he dreamed of them, and said unto them, Ye are spies; to see the nakedness of the land ye are come. ^10And they said unto him, Nay, my lord, but to buy food are thy servants come. ^11We are all one man's sons; we are true men, thy servants are no spies. ^12And he said unto them, Nay, but to see the nakedness of the land ye are come. ^13And they said, We thy servants are twelve brethren, the sons of one man in the land of Canaan; and, behold, the youngest is this day with our father, and one is not. ^14And Joseph said unto them, That is it that I spake unto you, saying, Ye are spies: ^15hereby ye shall be proved: by the life of Pharaoh ye shall not go forth hence, except your youngest brother come hither. ^16Send one of you, and let him fetch your brother, and ye shall be bound, that your words may be proved, whether there be truth in you: or else by the life of Pharaoh surely ye are spies. ^17And he put them all together into ward three days.

^18And Joseph said unto them the third day, This do, and live: for I fear God: ^19if ye be true men, let one of your brethren be bound in your prison-house; but go ye, carry grain for the famine of your houses: ^20and bring your youngest brother unto me; so shall your words be verified, and ye shall not die. And they did so. ^21And they said one to another, We are verily guilty concerning our brother, in that we saw the distress of his soul, when he besought us, and we would not hear; therefore is this distress come upon us. ^22And Reuben answered them, saying, Spake I not unto you, saying, Do not sin against the child; and ye would not hear? therefore also, behold, his blood is required. ^23And they knew not that Joseph understood them; for there was an interpreter between them. ^24And he turned himself about from them, and wept; and he returned to them, and spake to them, and took Simeon from among them, and bound him before their eyes. ^25Then Joseph commanded to fill their vessels with grain, and to restore every man's money into his sack, and to give them provisions for the way: and thus was it done unto them.

^26And they laded their asses with their grain, and departed thence. ^27And as one of them opened his sack to give his ass provender in the lodging-place, he espied his money; and, behold, it was in the mouth of his sack. ^28And he said unto his brethren, My money is restored; and, lo, it is even in my sack: and their heart failed them, and they turned trembling one to another, saying, What is this that God hath done unto us? ^29And they came unto Jacob their father unto the land of Canaan, and told him all that had befallen them, saying, ^30The man, the lord of the land, spake roughly with us, and took us for spies of the country. ^31And we said unto him, We are true men; and we are no spies: ^32we are twelve brethren, sons of our father; one is not, and the youngest is this day with our father in the land of Canaan. ^33And the man, the lord of the land, said unto us, Hereby shall I know that ye are true men: leave one of your brethren with me, and take grain for the famine of your houses, and go your way; ^34and bring your youngest brother unto me: then shall I know that ye are no spies, but that ye are true men: so will I deliver you your brother, and ye shall traffic in the land.

^35And it came to pass as they emptied their sacks, that, behold, every man's bundle of money was in his sack: and when they and their father saw their bundles of money, they were afraid. ^36And Jacob their father said unto them, Me have ye bereaved of my children: Joseph is not, and Simeon is not, and ye will take Benjamin away: all these things are against me. ^37And Reuben spake unto his father, saying, Slay my two sons, if I bring him not to thee: deliver him into my hand, and I will bring him to thee again. ^38And he said, My son shall not go down with you; for his brother is dead, and he only is left: if harm befall him by the way in which ye go, then will ye bring down my gray hairs with sorrow to Sheol.

Genesis 43

43

^1And the famine was sore in the land. ^2And it came to pass, when they had eaten up the grain which they had brought out of Egypt, their father said unto them, Go again, buy us a little food. ^3And Judah spake unto him, saying, The man did solemnly protest unto us, saying, Ye shall not see my face, except your brother be with you. ^4If thou wilt send our brother with us, we will go down and buy thee food: ^5but if thou wilt not send him, we will not go down; for the man said unto us, Ye shall not see my face, except your brother be with you. ^6And Israel said, Wherefore dealt ye so ill with me, as to tell the man whether ye had yet a brother? ^7And they said, The man asked straitly concerning ourselves, and concerning our kindred, saying, Is your father yet alive? have ye another brother? and we told him according to the tenor of these words: could we in any wise know that he would say, Bring your brother down? ^8And Judah said unto Israel his father, Send the lad with me, and we will arise and go; that we may live, and not die, both we, and thou, and also our little ones. ^9I will be surety for him; of my hand shalt thou require him: if I bring him not unto thee, and set him before thee, then let me bear the blame for ever: ^10for except we had lingered, surely we had now returned a second time. ^11And their father Israel said unto them, If it be so now, do this: take of the choice fruits of the land in your vessels, and carry down the man a present, a little balm, and a little honey, spicery and myrrh, nuts, and almonds; ^12and take double money in your hand; and the money that was returned in the mouth of your sacks carry again in your hand; peradventure it was an oversight: ^13take also your brother, and arise, go again unto the man: ^14and God Almighty give you mercy before the man, that he may release unto you your other brother and Benjamin. And if I be bereaved of my children, I am bereaved. ^15And the men took that present, and they took double money in their hand, and Benjamin; and rose up, and went down to Egypt, and stood before Joseph. ^16And when Joseph saw Benjamin with them, he said to the steward of his house, Bring the men into the house, and slay, and make ready; for the men shall dine with me at noon. ^17And the man did as Joseph bade; and the man brought the men to Joseph's house. ^18And the men were afraid, because they were brought to Joseph's house; and they said, Because of the money that was returned in our sacks at the first time are we brought in; that he may seek occasion against us, and fall upon us, and take us for bondmen, and our asses. ^19And they came near to the steward of Joseph's house, and they spake unto him at the door of the house, ^20and said, Oh, my lord, we came indeed down at the first time to buy food: ^21and it came to pass, when we came to the lodging-place, that we opened our sacks, and, behold, every man's money was in the mouth of his sack, our money in full weight: and we have brought it again in our hand. ^22And other money have we brought down in our hand to buy food: we know not who put our money in our sacks. ^23And he said, Peace be to you, fear not: your God, and the God of your father, hath given you treasure in your sacks: I had your money. And he brought Simeon out unto them. ^24And the man brought the men into Joseph's house, and gave them water, and they washed their feet. And he gave their asses provender. ^25And they made ready the present against Joseph's coming at noon: for they heard that they should eat bread there.

^26And when Joseph came home, they brought him the present which was in their hand into the house, and bowed down themselves to him to the earth. ^27And he asked them of their welfare, and said, Is your father well, the old man of whom ye spake? Is he yet alive? ^28And they said, Thy servant our father is well, he is yet alive. And they bowed the head, and made obeisance. ^29And he lifted up his eyes, and saw Benjamin his brother, his mother's son, and said, Is this your youngest brother, of whom ye spake unto me? And he said, God be gracious unto thee, my son. ^30And Joseph made haste; for his heart yearned over his brother: and he sought where to weep; and he entered into his chamber, and wept there. ^31And he washed his face, and came out; and he refrained himself, and said, Set on bread. ^32And they set on for him by himself, and for them by themselves, and for the Egyptians, that did eat with him, by themselves: because the Egyptians might not eat bread with the Hebrews; for that is an abomination unto the Egyptians. ^33And they sat before him, the first-born according to his birthright, and the youngest according to his youth: and the men marvelled one with another. ^34And he took and sent messes unto them from before him: but Benjamin's mess was five times so much as any of theirs. And they drank, and were merry with him.

Genesis 44

44

^1And he commanded the steward of his house, saying, Fill the men's sacks with food, as much as they can carry, and put every man's money in his sack's mouth. ^2And put my cup, the silver cup, in the sack's mouth of the youngest, and his grain money. And he did according to the word that Joseph had spoken. ^3As soon as the morning was light, the men were sent away, they and their asses. ^4And when they were gone out of the city, and were not yet far off, Joseph said unto his steward, Up, follow after the men; and when thou dost overtake them, say unto them, Wherefore have ye rewarded evil for good? ^5Is not this that in which my lord drinketh, and whereby he indeed divineth? ye have done evil in so doing. ^6And he overtook them, and he spake unto them these words. ^7And they said unto him, Wherefore speaketh my lord such words as these? Far be it from thy servants that they should do such a thing. ^8Behold, the money, which we found in our sacks' mouths, we brought again unto thee out of the land of Canaan: how then should we steal out of thy lord's house silver or gold? ^9With whomsoever of thy servants it be found, let him die, and we also will be my lord's bondmen. ^10And he said, Now also let it be according unto your words: he with whom it is found shall be my bondman; and ye shall be blameless. ^11Then they hasted, and took down every man his sack to the ground, and opened every man his sack. ^12And he searched, and began at the eldest, and left off at the youngest: and the cup was found in Benjamin's sack. ^13Then they rent their clothes, and laded every man his ass, and returned to the city.

^14And Judah and his brethren came to Joseph's house; and he was yet there: and they fell before him on the ground. ^15And Joseph said unto them, What deed is this that ye have done? know ye not that such a man as I can indeed divine? ^16And Judah said, What shall we say unto my lord? what shall we speak? or how shall we clear ourselves? God hath found out the iniquity of thy servants: behold, we are my lord's bondmen, both we, and he also in whose hand the cup is found. ^17And he said, Far be it from me that I should do so: the man in whose hand the cup is found, he shall be my bondman; but as for you, get you up in peace unto your father.

^18Then Judah came near unto him, and said, Oh, my lord, let thy servant, I pray thee, speak a word in my lord's ears, and let not thine anger burn against thy servant; for thou art even as Pharaoh. ^19My lord asked his servants, saying, Have ye a father, or a brother? ^20And we said unto my lord, We have a father, an old man, and a child of his old age, a little one; and his brother is dead, and he alone is left of his mother; and his father loveth him. ^21And thou saidst unto thy servants, Bring him down unto me, that I may set mine eyes upon him. ^22And we said unto my lord, The lad cannot leave his father: for if he should leave his father, his father would die. ^23And thou saidst unto thy servants, Except your youngest brother come down with you, ye shall see my face no more. ^24And it came to pass when we came up unto thy servant my father, we told him the words of my lord. ^25And our father said, Go again, buy us a little food. ^26And we said, We cannot go down: if our youngest brother be with us, then will we go down: for we may not see the man's face, expect our youngest brother be with us. ^27And thy servant my father said unto us, Ye know that my wife bare me two sons: ^28and the one went out from me, and I said, Surely he is torn in pieces; and I have not seen him since: ^29and if ye take this one also from me, and harm befall him, ye will bring down my gray hairs with sorrow to Sheol. ^30Now therefore when I come to thy servant my father, and the lad is not with us; seeing that his life is bound up in the lad's life; ^31it will come to pass, when he seeth that the lad is not with us, that he will die: and thy servants will bring down the gray hairs of thy servant our father with sorrow to Sheol. ^32For thy servant became surety for the lad unto my father, saying, If I bring him not unto thee, then shall I bear the blame to my father for ever. ^33Now therefore, let thy servant, I pray thee, abide instead of the lad a bondman to my lord; and let the lad go up with his brethren. ^34For how shall I go up to my father, if the lad be not with me? lest I see the evil that shall come on my father.

Genesis 45

45

^1Then Joseph could not refrain himself before all them that stood before him; and he cried, Cause every man to go out from me. And there stood no man with him, while Joseph made himself known unto his brethren. ^2And he wept aloud: and the Egyptians heard, and the house of Pharaoh heard. ^3And Joseph said unto his brethren, I am Joseph; doth my father yet live? And his brethren could not answer him; for they were troubled at his presence. ^4And Joseph said unto his brethren, Come near to me, I pray you. And they came near. And he said, I am Joseph your brother, whom ye sold into Egypt. ^5And now be not grieved, nor angry with yourselves, that ye sold me hither: for God did send me before you to preserve life. ^6For these two years hath the famine been in the land: and there are yet five years, in which there shall be neither plowing nor harvest. ^7And God sent me before you to preserve you a remnant in the earth, and to save you alive by a great deliverance. ^8So now it was not you that sent me hither, but God: and he hath made me a father to Pharaoh, and lord of all his house, and ruler over all the land of Egypt. ^9Haste ye, and go up to my father, and say unto him, Thus saith thy son Joseph, God hath made me lord of all Egypt: come down unto me, tarry not; ^10and thou shalt dwell in the land of Goshen, and thou shalt be near unto me, thou, and thy children, and thy children's children, and thy flocks, and thy herds, and all that thou hast: ^11and there will I nourish thee; for there are yet five years of famine; lest thou come to poverty, thou, and thy household, and all that thou hast. ^12And, behold, your eyes see, and the eyes of my brother Benjamin, that it is my mouth that speaketh unto you. ^13And ye shall tell my father of all my glory in Egypt, and of all that ye have seen: and ye shall haste and bring down my father hither. ^14And he fell upon his brother Benjamin's neck, and wept; and Benjamin wept upon his neck. ^15And he kissed all his brethren, and wept upon them: and after that his brethren talked with him. ^16And the report thereof was heard in Pharaoh's house, saying, Joseph's brethren are come: and it pleased Pharaoh well, and his servants. ^17And Pharaoh said unto Joseph, Say unto thy brethren, This do ye: lade your beasts, and go, get you unto the land of Canaan; ^18and take your father and your households, and come unto me: and I will give you the good of the land of Egypt, and ye shall eat the fat of the land. ^19Now thou art commanded, this do ye: take you wagons out of the land of Egypt for your little ones, and for your wives, and bring your father, and come. ^20Also regard not your stuff; for the good of all the land of Egypt is yours.

^21And the sons of Israel did so: and Joseph gave them wagons, according to the commandment of Pharaoh, and gave them provision for the way. ^22To all of them he gave each man changes of raiment; but to Benjamin he gave three hundred pieces of silver, and five changes of raiment. ^23And to his father he sent after this manner: ten asses laden with the good things of Egypt, and ten she-asses laden with grain and bread and provision for his father by the way. ^24So he sent his brethren away, and they departed: and he said unto them, See that ye fall not out by the way. ^25And they went up out of Egypt, and came into the land of Canaan unto Jacob their father. ^26And they told him, saying, Joseph is yet alive, and he is ruler over all the land of Egypt. And his heart fainted, for he believed them not. ^27And they told him all the words of Joseph, which he had said unto them: and when he saw the wagons which Joseph had sent to carry him, the spirit of Jacob their father revived: ^28and Israel said, It is enough; Joseph my son is yet alive: I will go and see him before I die.

Genesis 46

46

^1And Israel took his journey with all that he had, and came to Beer-sheba, and offered sacrifices unto the God of his father Isaac. ^2And God spake unto Israel in the visions of the night, and said, Jacob, Jacob. And he said, Here am I. ^3And he said, I am God, the God of thy father: fear not to go down into Egypt; for I will there make of thee a great nation: ^4I will go down with thee into Egypt; and I will also surely bring thee up again: and Joseph shall put his hand upon thine eyes. ^5And Jacob rose up from Beer-sheba: and the sons of Israel carried Jacob their father, and their little ones, and their wives, in the wagons which Pharaoh had sent to carry him. ^6And they took their cattle, and their goods, which they had gotten in the land of Canaan, and came into Egypt, Jacob, and all his seed with him: ^7his sons, and his sons' sons with him, his daughters, and his sons's daughters, and all his seed brought he with him into Egypt.

^8And these are the names of the children of Israel, who came into Egypt, Jacob and his sons: Reuben, Jacob's first-born. ^9And the sons of Reuben: Hanoch, and Pallu, and Hezron, and Carmi. ^10And the sons of Simeon: Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul the son of a Canaanitish woman. ^11And the sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. ^12And the sons of Judah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah, and Perez, and Zerah; but Er and Onan died in the land of Canaan. And the sons of Perez were Hezron and Hamul. ^13And the sons of Issachar: Tola, and Puvah, and Iob, and Shimron. ^14And the sons of Zebulun: Sered, and Elon, and Jahleel. ^15These are the sons of Leah, whom she bare unto Jacob in Paddan-aram, with his daughter Dinah: all the souls of his sons and his daughters were thirty and three. ^16And the sons of Gad: Ziphion, and Haggi, Shuni, and Ezbon, Eri, and Arodi, and Areli. ^17And the sons of Asher: Imnah, and Ishvah, and Ishvi, and Beriah, and Serah their sister; and the sons of Beriah: Heber, and Malchiel. ^18These are the sons of Zilpah, whom Laban gave to Leah his daughter; and these she bare unto Jacob, even sixteen souls. ^19The sons of Rachel Jacob's wife: Joseph and Benjamin. ^20And unto Joseph in the land of Egypt were born Manasseh and Ephraim, whom Asenath, the daughter of Poti-phera priest of On, bare unto him. ^21And the sons of Benjamin: Bela, and Becher, and Ashbel, Gera, and Naaman, Ehi, and Rosh, Muppim, and Huppim, and Ard. ^22These are the sons of Rachel, who were born to Jacob: all the souls were fourteen. ^23And the sons of Dan: Hushim. ^24And the sons of Naphtali: Jahzeel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shillem. ^25These are the sons of Bilhah, whom Laban gave unto Rachel his daughter, and these she bare unto Jacob: all the souls were seven. ^26All the souls that came with Jacob into Egypt, that came out of his loins, besides Jacob's sons' wives, all the souls were threescore and six; ^27and the sons of Joseph, who were born to him in Egypt, were two souls: all the souls of the house of Jacob, that came into Egypt, were threescore and ten.

^28And he sent Judah before him unto Joseph, to show the way before him unto Goshen; and they came into the land of Goshen. ^29And Joseph made ready his chariot, and went up to meet Israel his father, to Goshen; and he presented himself unto him, and fell on his neck, and wept on his neck a good while. ^30And Israel said unto Joseph, Now let me die, since I have seen thy face, that thou art yet alive. ^31And Joseph said unto his brethren, and unto his father's house, I will go up, and tell Pharaoh, and will say unto him, My brethren, and my father's house, who were in the land of Canaan, are come unto me; ^32and the men are shepherds, for they have been keepers of cattle; and they have brought their flocks, and their herds, and all that they have. ^33And it shall come to pass, when Pharaoh shall call you, and shall say, What is your occupation? ^34that ye shall say, Thy servants have been keepers of cattle from our youth even until now, both we, and our fathers: that ye may dwell in the land of Goshen; for every shepherd is an abomination unto the Egyptians.

Genesis 47

47

^1Then Joseph went in and told Pharaoh, and said, My father and my brethren, and their flocks, and their herds, and all that they have, are come out of the land of Canaan; and, behold, they are in the land of Goshen. ^2And from among his brethren he took five men, and presented them unto Pharaoh. ^3And Pharaoh said unto his brethren, What is your occupation? And they said unto Pharaoh, Thy servants are shepherds, both we, and our fathers. ^4And they said unto Pharaoh, To sojourn in the land are we come; for there is no pasture for thy servants' flocks; for the famine is sore in the land of Canaan: now therefore, we pray thee, let thy servants dwell in the land of Goshen. ^5And Pharaoh spake unto Joseph, saying, Thy father and thy brethren are come unto thee: ^6the land of Egypt is before thee; in the best of the land make thy father and thy brethren to dwell; in the land of Goshen let them dwell: and if thou knowest any able men among them, then make them rulers over my cattle. ^7And Joseph brought in Jacob his father, and set him before Pharaoh: and Jacob blessed Pharaoh. ^8And Pharaoh said unto Jacob, How many are the days of the years of thy life? ^9And Jacob said unto Pharaoh, The days of the years of my pilgrimage are a hundred and thirty years: few and evil have been the days of the years of my life, and they have not attained unto the days of the years of the life of my fathers in the days of their pilgrimage. ^10And Jacob blessed Pharaoh, and went out from the presence of Pharaoh. ^11And Joseph placed his father and his brethren, and gave them a possession in the land of Egypt, in the best of the land, in the land of Rameses, as Pharaoh had commanded. ^12And Joseph nourished his father, and his brethren, and all his father's household, with bread, according to their families.

^13And there was no bread in all the land; for the famine was very sore, so that the land of Egypt and the land of Canaan fainted by reason of the famine. ^14And Joseph gathered up all the money that was found in the land of Egypt, and in the land of Canaan, for the grain which they bought: and Joseph brought the money into Pharaoh's house. ^15And when the money was all spent in the land of Egypt, and in the land of Canaan, all the Egyptians came unto Joseph, and said, Give us bread: for why should we die in thy presence? for our money faileth. ^16And Joseph said, Give your cattle; and I will give you for your cattle, if money fail. ^17And they brought their cattle unto Joseph; and Joseph gave them bread in exchange for the horses, and for the flocks, and for the herds, and for the asses: and he fed them with bread in exchange for all their cattle for that year. ^18And when that year was ended, they came unto him the second year, and said unto him, We will not hide from my lord, how that our money is all spent; and the herds of cattle are my lord's; there is nought left in the sight of my lord, but our bodies, and our lands: ^19wherefore should we die before thine eyes, both we and our land? buy us and our land for bread, and we and our land will be servants unto Pharaoh: and give us seed, that we may live, and not die, and that the land be not desolate.

^20So Joseph bought all the land of Egypt for Pharaoh; for the Egyptians sold every man his field, because the famine was sore upon them: and the land became Pharaoh's. ^21And as for the people, he removed them to the cities from one end of the border of Egypt even to the other end thereof. ^22Only the land of the priests bought he not: for the priests had a portion from Pharaoh, and did eat their portion which Pharaoh gave them; wherefore they sold not their land. ^23Then Joseph said unto the people, Behold, I have bought you this day and your land for Pharaoh: lo, here is seed for you, and ye shall sow the land. ^24And it shall come to pass at the ingatherings, that ye shall give a fifth unto Pharaoh, and four parts shall be your own, for seed of the field, and for your food, and for them of your households, and for food for your little ones. ^25And they said, Thou hast saved our lives: let us find favor in the sight of my lord, and we will be Pharaoh's servants. ^26And Joseph made it a statute concerning the land of Egypt unto this day, that Pharaoh should have the fifth; only the land of the priests alone became not Pharaoh's.

^27And Israel dwelt in the land of Egypt, in the land of Goshen; and they gat them possessions therein, and were fruitful, and multiplied exceedingly. ^28And Jacob lived in the land of Egypt seventeen years: so the days of Jacob, the years of his life, were a hundred forty and seven years. ^29And the time drew near that Israel must die: and he called his son Joseph, and said unto him, If now I have found favor in thy sight, put, I pray thee, thy hand under my thigh, and deal kindly and truly with me: bury me not, I pray thee, in Egypt; ^30but when I sleep with my fathers, thou shalt carry me out of Egypt, and bury me in their burying-place. And he said, I will do as thou hast said. ^31And he said, Swear unto me: and he sware unto him. And Israel bowed himself upon the bed's head.

Genesis 48

48

^1And it came to pass after these things, that one said to Joseph, Behold, thy father is sick: and he took with him his two sons, Manasseh and Ephraim. ^2And one told Jacob, and said, Behold, thy son Joseph cometh unto thee: and Israel strengthened himself, and sat upon the bed. ^3And Jacob said unto Joseph, God Almighty appeared unto me at Luz in the land of Canaan, and blessed me, ^4and said unto me, Behold, I will make thee fruitful, and multiply thee, and I will make of thee a company of peoples, and will give this land to thy seed after thee for an everlasting possession. ^5And now thy two sons, who were born unto thee in the land of Egypt before I came unto thee into Egypt, are mine; Ephraim and Manasseh, even as Reuben and Simeon, shall be mine. ^6And thy issue, that thou begettest after them, shall be thine; they shall be called after the name of their brethren in their inheritance. ^7And as for me, when I came from Paddan, Rachel died by me in the land of Canaan in the way, when there was still some distance to come unto Ephrath: and I buried her there in the way to Ephrath (the same is Beth-lehem).

^8And Israel beheld Joseph's sons, and said, Who are these? ^9And Joseph said unto his father, They are my sons, whom God hath given me here. And he said, Bring them, I pray thee, unto me, and I will bless them. ^10Now the eyes of Israel were dim for age, so that he could not see. And he brought them near unto him; and he kissed them, and embraced them. ^11And Israel said unto Joseph, I had not thought to see thy face: and, lo, God hath let me see thy seed also. ^12And Joseph brought them out from between his knees; and he bowed himself with his face to the earth. ^13And Joseph took them both, Ephraim in his right hand toward Israel's left hand, and Manasseh in his left hand toward Israel's right hand, and brought them near unto him. ^14And Israel stretched out his right hand, and laid it upon Ephraim's head, who was the younger, and his left hand upon Manasseh's head, guiding his hands wittingly; for Manasseh was the first-born. ^15And he blessed Joseph, and said, The God before whom my fathers Abraham and Isaac did walk, the God who hath fed me all my life long unto this day, ^16the angel who hath redeemed me from all evil, bless the lads; and let my name be named on them, and the name of my fathers Abraham and Isaac; and let them grow into a multitude in the midst of the earth. ^17And when Joseph saw that his father laid his right hand upon the head of Ephraim, it displeased him: and he held up his father's hand, to remove it from Ephraim's head unto Manasseh's head. ^18And Joseph said unto his father, Not so, my father; for this is the first-born; put thy right hand upon his head. ^19And his father refused, and said, I know it, my son, I know it. He also shall become a people, and he also shall be great: howbeit his younger brother shall be greater than he, and his seed shall become a multitude of nations. ^20And he blessed them that day, saying, In thee will Israel bless, saying, God make thee as Ephraim and as Manasseh: and he set Ephraim before Manasseh. ^21And Israel said unto Joseph, Behold, I die: but God will be with you, and bring you again unto the land of your fathers. ^22Moreover I have given to thee one portion above thy brethren, which I took out of the hand of the Amorite with my sword and with my bow.

Genesis 50

50

^1And Joseph fell upon his father's face, and wept upon him, and kissed him. ^2And Joseph commanded his servants the physicians to embalm his father: and the physicians embalmed Israel. ^3And forty days were fulfilled for him; for so are fulfilled the days of embalming: and the Egyptians wept for him three-score and ten days.

^4And when the days of weeping for him were past, Joseph spake unto the house of Pharaoh, saying, If now I have found favor in your eyes, speak, I pray you, in the ears of Pharaoh, saying, ^5My father made me swear, saying, Lo, I die: in my grave which I have digged for me in the land of Canaan, there shalt thou bury me. Now therefore let me go up, I pray thee, and bury my father, and I will come again. ^6And Pharaoh said, Go up, and bury thy father, according as he made thee swear. ^7And Joseph went up to bury his father; and with him went up all the servants of Pharaoh, the elders of his house, and all the elders of the land of Egypt, ^8and all the house of Joseph, and his brethren, and his father's house: only their little ones, and their flocks, and their herds, they left in the land of Goshen. ^9And there went up with him both chariots and horsemen: and it was a very great company. ^10And they came to the threshing-floor of Atad, which is beyond the Jordan, and there they lamented with a very great and sore lamentation: and he made a mourning for his father seven days. ^11And when the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, saw the mourning in the floor of Atad, they said, This is a grievous mourning to the Egyptians: wherefore the name of it was called Abel-mizraim, which is beyond the Jordan. ^12And his sons did unto him according as he commanded them: ^13for his sons carried him into the land of Canaan, and buried him in the cave of the field of Machpelah, which Abraham bought with the field, for a possession of a burying-place, of Ephron the Hittite, before Mamre. ^14And Joseph returned into Egypt, he, and his brethren, and all that went up with him to bury his father, after he had buried his father.

^15And when Joseph's brethren saw that their father was dead, they said, It may be that Joseph will hate us, and will fully requite us all the evil which we did unto him. ^16And they sent a message unto Joseph, saying, Thy father did command before he died, saying, ^17So shall ye say unto Joseph, Forgive, I pray thee now, the transgression of thy brethren, and their sin, for that they did unto thee evil. And now, we pray thee, forgive the transgression of the servants of the God of thy father. And Joseph wept when they spake unto him. ^18And his brethren also went and fell down before his face; and they said, Behold, we are thy servants. ^19And Joseph said unto them, Fear not: for am I in the place of God? ^20And as for you, ye meant evil against me; but God meant it for good, to bring to pass, as it is this day, to save much people alive. ^21Now therefore fear ye not: I will nourish you, and your little ones. And he comforted them, and spake kindly unto them.

^22And Joseph dwelt in Egypt, he, and his father's house: and Joseph lived a hundred and ten years. ^23And Joseph saw Ephraim's children of the third generation: the children also of Machir the son of Manasseh were born upon Joseph's knees. ^24And Joseph said unto his brethren, I die; but God will surely visit you, and bring you up out of this land unto the land which he sware to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. ^25And Joseph took an oath of the children of Israel, saying, God will surely visit you, and ye shall carry up my bones from hence. ^26So Joseph died, being a hundred and ten years old: and they embalmed him, and he was put in a coffin in Egypt.

Habakkuk 2

2

^1I will stand upon my watch, and set me upon the tower, and will look forth to see what he will speak with me, and what I shall answer concerning my complaint. ^2And Jehovah answered me, and said, Write the vision, and make it plain upon tablets, that he may run that readeth it. ^3For the vision is yet for the appointed time, and it hasteth toward the end, and shall not lie: though it tarry, wait for it; because it will surely come, it will not delay. ^4Behold, his soul is puffed up, it is not upright in him; but the righteous shall live by his faith. ^5Yea, moreover, wine is treacherous, a haughty man, that keepeth not at home; who enlargeth his desire as Sheol, and he is as death, and cannot be satisfied, but gathereth unto him all nations, and heapeth unto him all peoples. ^6Shall not all these take up a parable against him, and a taunting proverb against him, and say, Woe to him that increaseth that which is not his! how long? and that ladeth himself with pledges! ^7Shall they not rise up suddenly that shall bite thee, and awake that shall vex thee, and thou shalt be for booty unto them? ^8Because thou hast plundered many nations, all the remnant of the peoples shall plunder thee, because of men's blood, and for the violence done to the land, to the city and to all that dwell therein. ^9Woe to him that getteth an evil gain for his house, that he may set his nest on high, that he may be delivered from the hand of evil! ^10Thou hast devised shame to thy house, by cutting off many peoples, and hast sinned against thy soul. ^11For the stone shall cry out of the wall, and the beam out of the timber shall answer it. ^12Woe to him that buildeth a town with blood, and establisheth a city by iniquity! ^13Behold, is it not of Jehovah of hosts that the peoples labor for the fire, and the nations weary themselves for vanity? ^14For the earth shall be filled with the knowledge of the glory of Jehovah, as the waters cover the sea. ^15Woe unto him that giveth his neighbor drink, to thee that addest thy venom, and makest him drunken also, that thou mayest look on their nakedness! ^16Thou art filled with shame, and not glory: drink thou also, and be as one uncircumcised; the cup of Jehovah's right hand shall come round unto thee, and foul shame shall be upon thy glory. ^17For the violence done to Lebanon shall cover thee, and the destruction of the beasts, which made them afraid; because of men's blood, and for the violence done to the land, to the city and to all that dwell therein. ^18What profiteth the graven image, that the maker thereof hath graven it; the molten image, even the teacher of lies, that he that fashioneth its form trusteth therein, to make dumb idols? ^19Woe unto him that saith to the wood, Awake; to the dumb stone, Arise! Shall this teach? Behold, it is overlaid with gold and silver, and there is no breath at all in the midst of it. ^20But Jehovah is in his holy temple: let all the earth keep silence before him.

Haggai 2

2

^1In the seventh month, in the one and twentieth day of the month, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet, saying, ^2Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying, ^3Who is left among you that saw this house in its former glory? and how do ye see it now? is it not in your eyes as nothing? ^4Yet now be strong, O Zerubbabel, saith Jehovah; and be strong, O Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest; and be strong, all ye people of the land, saith Jehovah, and work: for I am with you, saith Jehovah of hosts, ^5according to the word that I covenanted with you when ye came out of Egypt, and my Spirit abode among you: fear ye not. ^6For thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, and the earth, and the sea, and the dry land; ^7and I will shake all nations; and the precious things of all nations shall come; and I will fill this house with glory, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^8The silver is mine, and the gold is mine, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^9The latter glory of this house shall be greater than the former, saith Jehovah of hosts; and in this place will I give peace, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^10In the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of Jehovah by Haggai the prophet, saying, ^11Thus saith Jehovah of hosts: Ask now the priests concerning the law, saying, ^12If one bear holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt do touch bread, or pottage, or wine, or oil, or any food, shall it become holy? And the priests answered and said, No. ^13Then said Haggai, If one that is unclean by reason of a dead body touch any of these, shall it be unclean? And the priests answered and said, It shall be unclean. ^14Then answered Haggai and said, So is this people, and so is this nation before me, saith Jehovah; and so is every work of their hands; and that which they offer there is unclean. ^15And now, I pray you, consider from this day and backward, before a stone was laid upon a stone in the temple of Jehovah. ^16Through all that time, when one came to a heap of twenty measures, there were but ten; when one came to the winevat to draw out fifty vessels, there were but twenty. ^17I smote you with blasting and with mildew and with hail in all the work of your hands; yet ye turned not to me, saith Jehovah. ^18Consider, I pray you, from this day and backward, from the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, since the day that the foundation of Jehovah's temple was laid, consider it. ^19Is the seed yet in the barn? yea, the vine, and the fig-tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive-tree have not brought forth; from this day will I bless you. ^20And the word of Jehovah came the second time unto Haggai in the four and twentieth day of the month, saying, ^21Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, I will shake the heavens and the earth; ^22and I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms; and I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the nations; and I will overthrow the chariots, and those that ride in them; and the horses and their riders shall come down, every one by the sword of his brother. ^23In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, will I take thee, O Zerubbabel, my servant, the son of Shealtiel, saith Jehovah, and will make thee as a signet; for I have chosen thee, saith Jehovah of hosts.

Hebrews 2

2

^1Therefore we ought to give the more earnest heed to the things that were heard, lest haply we drift away from them. ^2For if the word spoken through angels proved stedfast, and every transgression and disobedience received a just recompense of reward; ^3how shall we escape, if we neglect so great a salvation? which having at the first been spoken through the Lord, was confirmed unto us by them that heard; ^4God also bearing witness with them, both by signs and wonders, and by manifold powers, and by gifts of the Holy Spirit, according to his own will. ^5For not unto angels did he subject the world to come, whereof we speak. ^6But one hath somewhere testified, saying,

What is man, that thou art mindful of him?

Or the son of man, that thou visitest him?

^7Thou madest him a little lower than the angels;

Thou crownedst him with glory and honor,

And didst set him over the works of thy hands:

^8Thou didst put all things in subjection under his feet.

For in that he subjected all things unto him, he left nothing that is not subject to him. But now we see not yet all things subjected to him. ^9But we behold him who hath been made a little lower than the angels, even Jesus, because of the suffering of death crowned with glory and honor, that by the grace of God he should taste of death for every man. ^10For it became him, for whom are all things, and through whom are all things, in bringing many sons unto glory, to make the author of their salvation perfect through sufferings. ^11For both he that sanctifieth and they that are sanctified are all of one: for which cause he is not ashamed to call them brethren, ^12saying,

I will declare thy name unto my brethren,

In the midst of the congregation will I sing thy praise.

^13And again, I will put my trust in him. And again, Behold, I and the children whom God hath given me. ^14Since then the children are sharers in flesh and blood, he also himself in like manner partook of the same; that through death he might bring to nought him that had the power of death, that is, the devil; ^15and might deliver all them who through fear of death were all their lifetime subject to bondage. ^16For verily not to angels doth he give help, but he giveth help to the seed of Abraham. ^17Wherefore it behooved him in all things to be made like unto his brethren, that he might become a merciful and faithful high priest in things pertaining to God, to make propitiation for the sins of the people. ^18For in that he himself hath suffered being tempted, he is able to succor them that are tempted.

Hebrews 4

4

^1Let us fear therefore, lest haply, a promise being left of entering into his rest, any one of you should seem to have come short of it. ^2For indeed we have had good tidings preached unto us, even as also they: but the word of hearing did not profit them, because it was not united by faith with them that heard. ^3For we who have believed do enter into that rest; even as he hath said,

As I sware in my wrath,

They shall not enter into my rest:

although the works were finished from the foundation of the world. ^4For he hath said somewhere of the seventh day on this wise, And God rested on the seventh day from all his works; ^5and in this place again,

They shall not enter into my rest.

^6Seeing therefore it remaineth that some should enter thereinto, and they to whom the good tidings were before preached failed to enter in because of disobedience, ^7he again defineth a certain day, To-day, saying in David so long a time afterward (even as hath been said before),

To-day if ye shall hear his voice,

Harden not your hearts.

^8For if Joshua had given them rest, he would not have spoken afterward of another day. ^9There remaineth therefore a sabbath rest for the people of God. ^10For he that is entered into his rest hath himself also rested from his works, as God did from his. ^11Let us therefore give diligence to enter into that rest, that no man fall after the same example of disobedience. ^12For the word of God is living, and active, and sharper than any two-edged sword, and piercing even to the dividing of soul and spirit, of both joints and marrow, and quick to discern the thoughts and intents of the heart. ^13And there is no creature that is not manifest in his sight: but all things are naked and laid open before the eyes of him with whom we have to do. ^14Having then a great high priest, who hath passed through the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold fast our confession. ^15For we have not a high priest that cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities; but one that hath been in all points tempted like as we are, yet without sin. ^16Let us therefore draw near with boldness unto the throne of grace, that we may receive mercy, and may find grace to help us in time of need.

Hebrews 5

5

^1For every high priest, being taken from among men, is appointed for men in things pertaining to God, that he may offer both gifts and sacrifices for sins: ^2who can bear gently with the ignorant and erring, for that he himself also is compassed with infirmity; ^3and by reason thereof is bound, as for the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins. ^4And no man taketh the honor unto himself, but when he is called of God, even as was Aaron. ^5So Christ also glorified not himself to be made a high priest, but he that spake unto him,

Thou art my Son,

This day have I begotten thee:

^6as he saith also in another place,

Thou art a priest for ever

After the order of Melchizedek.

^7Who in the days of his flesh, having offered up prayers and supplications with strong crying and tears unto him that was able to save him from death, and having been heard for his godly fear, ^8though he was a Son, yet learned obedience by the things which he suffered; ^9and having been made perfect, he became unto all them that obey him the author of eternal salvation; ^10named of God a high priest after the order of Melchizedek. ^11Of whom we have many things to say, and hard of interpretation, seeing ye are become dull of hearing. ^12For when by reason of the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have need again that some one teach you the rudiments of the first principles of the oracles of God; and are become such as have need of milk, and not of solid food. ^13For every one that partaketh of milk is without experience of the word of righteousness; for he is a babe. ^14But solid food is for fullgrown men, even those who by reason of use have their senses exercised to discern good and evil.

Hebrews 6

6

^1Wherefore leaving the doctrine of the first principles of Christ, let us press on unto perfection; not laying again a foundation of repentance from dead works, and of faith toward God, ^2of the teaching of baptisms, and of laying on of hands, and of resurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment. ^3And this will we do, if God permit. ^4For as touching those who were once enlightened and tasted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Spirit, ^5and tasted the good word of God, and the powers of the age to come, ^6and then fell away, it is impossible to renew them again unto repentance; seeing they crucify to themselves the Son of God afresh, and put him to an open shame. ^7For the land which hath drunk the rain that cometh oft upon it, and bringeth forth herbs meet for them for whose sake it is also tilled, receiveth blessing from God: ^8but if it beareth thorns and thistles, it is rejected and nigh unto a curse; whose end is to be burned. ^9But, beloved, we are persuaded better things of you, and things that accompany salvation, though we thus speak: ^10for God is not unrighteous to forget your work and the love which ye showed toward his name, in that ye ministered unto the saints, and still do minister. ^11And we desire that each one of you may show the same diligence unto the fulness of hope even to the end: ^12that ye be not sluggish, but imitators of them who through faith and patience inherit the promises. ^13For when God made promise to Abraham, since he could swear by none greater, he sware by himself, ^14saying, Surely blessing I will bless thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee. ^15And thus, having patiently endured, he obtained the promise. ^16For men swear by the greater: and in every dispute of theirs the oath is final for confirmation. ^17Wherein God, being minded to show more abundantly unto the heirs of the promise the immutability of his counsel, interposed with an oath; ^18that by two immutable things, in which it is impossible for God to lie, we may have a strong encouragement, who have fled for refuge to lay hold of the hope set before us: ^19which we have as an anchor of the soul, a hope both sure and stedfast and entering into that which is within the veil; ^20whither as a forerunner Jesus entered for us, having become a high priest for ever after the order of Melchizedek.

Hebrews 7

7

^1For this Melchizedek, king of Salem, priest of God Most High, who met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings and blessed him, ^2to whom also Abraham divided a tenth part of all (being first, by interpretation, King of righteousness, and then also King of Salem, which is King of peace; ^3without father, without mother, without genealogy, having neither beginning of days nor end of life, but made like unto the Son of God), abideth a priest continually. ^4Now consider how great this man was, unto whom Abraham, the patriarch, gave a tenth out of the chief spoils. ^5And they indeed of the sons of Levi that receive the priest's office have commandment to take tithes of the people according to the law, that is, of their brethren, though these have come out of the loins of Abraham: ^6but he whose genealogy is not counted from them hath taken tithes of Abraham, and hath blessed him that hath the promises. ^7But without any dispute the less is blessed of the better. ^8And here men that die receive tithes; but there one, of whom it is witnessed that he liveth. ^9And, so to say, through Abraham even Levi, who receiveth tithes, hath paid tithes; ^10for he was yet in the loins of his father, when Melchizedek met him. ^11Now if there was perfection through the Levitical priesthood (for under it hath the people received the law), what further need was there that another priest should arise after the order of Melchizedek, and not be reckoned after the order of Aaron? ^12For the priesthood being changed, there is made of necessity a change also of the law. ^13For he of whom these things are said belongeth to another tribe, from which no man hath given attendance at the altar. ^14For it is evident that our Lord hath sprung out of Judah; as to which tribe Moses spake nothing concerning priests. ^15And what we say is yet more abundantly evident, if after the likeness of Melchizedek there ariseth another priest, ^16who hath been made, not after the law of a carnal commandment, but after the power of an endless life: ^17for it is witnessed of him,

Thou art a priest for ever

After the order of Melchizedek.

^18For there is a disannulling of a foregoing commandment because of its weakness and unprofitableness ^19(for the law made nothing perfect), and a bringing in thereupon of a better hope, through which we draw nigh unto God. ^20And inasmuch as it is not without the taking of an oath ^21(for they indeed have been made priests without an oath; but he with an oath by him that saith of him,

The Lord sware and will not repent himself,

Thou art a priest for ever);

^22by so much also hath Jesus become the surety of a better covenant. ^23And they indeed have been made priests many in number, because that by death they are hindered from continuing: ^24but he, because he abideth for ever, hath his priesthood unchangeable. ^25Wherefore also he is able to save to the uttermost them that draw near unto God through him, seeing he ever liveth to make intercession for them. ^26For such a high priest became us, holy, guileless, undefiled, separated from sinners, and made higher than the heavens; ^27who needeth not daily, like those high priests, to offer up sacrifices, first for his own sins, and then for the sins of the people: for this he did once for all, when he offered up himself. ^28For the law appointeth men high priests, having infirmity; but the word of the oath, which was after the law, appointeth a Son, perfected for evermore.